<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-07-04T22:21:54Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4233</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4233" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4233#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4233" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">John Wright joins UT Austin</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">I’m delighted to announce that quantum computing theorist John Wright will be joining the computer science faculty at UT Austin in Fall 2020, after he finishes a one-year postdoc at Caltech. John made an appearance on this blog a few months ago, when I wrote about the new breakthrough by him and Anand Natarajan: namely, […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter"><img alt="" class="wp-image-4244" src="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2019/07/image-1.png"/></figure></div>



<p>I’m delighted to announce that quantum computing theorist <a href="http://www.mit.edu/~jswright/">John Wright</a> will be joining the computer science faculty at UT Austin in Fall 2020, after he finishes a one-year postdoc at Caltech. </p>



<p>John made an appearance on this blog a few months ago, when I <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4172">wrote about</a> the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.05870">new breakthrough</a> by him and <a href="http://www.its.caltech.edu/~anataraj/">Anand Natarajan</a>: namely, that MIP* (multi-prover interactive proofs with entangled provers) contains NEEXP (nondeterministic double-exponential time).  Previously, MIP* had only been known to contain NEXP (nondeterministic <em>single</em> exponential time).  So, this is an exponential expansion in the power of entangled provers over what was previously known and believed, and the first proof that entanglement actually <em>increases</em> the power of multi-prover protocols, rather than decreasing it (as it could’ve done a priori).  Even more strikingly, there seems to be no natural stopping point: MIP* might soon swallow up arbitrary towers of exponentials or even the halting problem (!).  For more, see for example <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/computer-scientists-expand-the-frontier-of-verifiable-knowledge-20190523/">this <em>Quanta</em> article</a>, or <a href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/2019/04/14/randomness-and-interaction-entanglement-ups-the-game/">this post by Thomas Vidick</a>, or <a href="http://www.henryyuen.net/post/alice-and-bob-visit/">this short story [sic] by Henry Yuen</a>.</p>



<p>John grew up in Texas, so he’s no stranger to BBQ brisket or scorching weather.  He did his undergrad in computer science at UT Austin—my colleagues remember him as a star—and then completed his PhD with Ryan O’Donnell at Carnegie Mellon, followed by a postdoc at MIT.  Besides the work on MIP*, John is also well-known for his <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1508.01907">2015 work with O’Donnell</a> pinning down the sample complexity of quantum state tomography.  Their important result, a version of which was independently obtained by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1508.01797">Haah et al.</a>, says that if you want to learn an unknown d-dimensional quantum mixed state ρ to a reasonable precision, then ~d<sup>2</sup> copies of ρ are both necessary and sufficient.  This solved a problem that had personally interested me, and already plays a role in, e.g., my work on <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.01053">shadow tomography</a> and <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/papers/dpgentle.pdf">gentle measurements</a>.</p>



<p>Our little <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~qic/">quantum information center</a> at UT Austin is growing rapidly.  <a href="http://sites.utexas.edu/shyamshankar/">Shyam Shankar</a>, a superconducting qubits guy who previously worked in Rob Schoelkopf’s lab at Yale, will also be joining UT’s Electrical and Computer Engineering department this fall.  I’ll have two new postdocs—<a href="https://twitter.com/a_rocchetto?lang=en">Andrea Rocchetto</a> and <a href="http://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~yosiat/">Yosi Atia</a>—as well as new PhD students.  We’ll continue recruiting this coming year, with potential opportunities for students, postdocs, faculty, and research scientists across the CS, physics, and ECE departments as well as the Texas Advanced Computing Center (TACC).  I hope you’ll consider applying to join us.</p>



<p>With no evaluative judgment attached, I can honestly say that this is an unprecedented time for quantum computing as a field.  Where once faculty applicants struggled to make a case for quantum computing (physics departments: “but isn’t this really CS?” / CS departments: “isn’t it really physics?” / everyone: “couldn’t this whole QC thing, like, all blow over in a year?”), today departments are vying with each other and with industry players and startups to recruit talented people.  In such an environment, we’re fortunate to be doing as well as we are.  We hope to continue to expand.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, this was an <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/24/technology/computer-science-courses-college.html">unprecedented year for CS hiring at UT Austin</a> more generally.  John Wright is one of at least four new faculty (probably more) who will be joining us.  It’s a good time to be in CS.</p>



<p>A huge welcome to John, and hook ’em Hadamards!</p>



<p>(And for US readers: have a great 4<sup>th</sup>!  Though how could any fireworks match the proof of the Sensitivity Conjecture?)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:08:54Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-04T01:08:54Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T14:56:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.02056</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.02056" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Variance Reduction for Matrix Games</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Carmon:Yair.html">Yair Carmon</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jin:Yujia.html">Yujia Jin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sidford:Aaron.html">Aaron Sidford</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tian:Kevin.html">Kevin Tian</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.02056">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a randomized primal-dual algorithm that solves the problem
$\min_{x} \max_{y} y^\top A x$ to additive error $\epsilon$ in time
$\mathrm{nnz}(A) + \sqrt{\mathrm{nnz}(A)n}/\epsilon$, for matrix $A$ with
larger dimension $n$ and $\mathrm{nnz}(A)$ nonzero entries. This improves on
Nemirovski's mirror-prox method by a factor of $\sqrt{\mathrm{nnz}(A)/n}$ and
is faster than stochastic gradient methods in the accurate and/or sparse regime
$\epsilon \le \sqrt{n/\mathrm{nnz}(A)}$. Our results hold for $x,y$ in the
simplex (matrix games, linear programming) and for $x$ in an $\ell_2$ ball and
$y$ in the simplex (perceptron / SVM, minimum enclosing ball). Our algorithm
combines the mirror-prox method and a novel variance-reduced gradient estimator
based on "sampling from the difference" between the current iterate and a
reference point.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:29:52Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.02053</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.02053" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Evaluation of a Flow-Based Hypergraph Bipartitioning Algorithm</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gottesb=uuml=ren:Lars.html">Lars Gottesbüren</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hamann:Michael.html">Michael Hamann</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wagner:Dorothea.html">Dorothea Wagner</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.02053">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we propose HyperFlowCutter, an algorithm for balanced
hypergraph bipartitioning. It is based on minimum S-T hyperedge cuts and
maximum flows. It computes a sequence of bipartitions that optimize cut size
and balance in the Pareto sense, being able to trade one for the other.
HyperFlowCutter builds on the FlowCutter algorithm for partitioning graphs. We
propose additional features, such as handling disconnected hypergraphs, novel
methods for obtaining starting S,T pairs as well as an approach to refine a
given partition with HyperFlowCutter. Our main contribution is ReBaHFC, a new
algorithm which obtains an initial partition with the fast multilevel
hypergraph partitioner PaToH and then improves it using HyperFlowCutter as a
refinement algorithm. ReBaHFC is able to significantly improve the solution
quality of PaToH at little additional running time. The solution quality is
only marginally worse than that of the best-performing hypergraph partitioners
KaHyPar and hMETIS, while being one order of magnitude faster. Thus ReBaHFC
offers a new time-quality trade-off in the current spectrum of hypergraph
partitioners. For the special case of perfectly balanced bipartitioning, only
the much slower plain HyperFlowCutter yields slightly better solutions than
ReBaHFC, while only PaToH is faster than ReBaHFC.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:39:45Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01980</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01980" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Triangles and Girth in Disk Graphs and Transmission Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kaplan:Haim.html">Haim Kaplan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Klost:Katharina.html">Katharina Klost</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mulzer:Wolfgang.html">Wolfgang Mulzer</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Roditty:Liam.html">Liam Roditty</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Seiferth:Paul.html">Paul Seiferth</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sharir:Micha.html">Micha Sharir</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01980">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Let $S \subset \mathbb{R}^2$ be a set of $n$ sites, where each $s \in S$ has
an associated radius $r_s &gt; 0$. The disk graph $D(S)$ is the undirected graph
with vertex set $S$ and an undirected edge between two sites $s, t \in S$ if
and only if $|st| \leq r_s + r_t$, i.e., if the disks with centers $s$ and $t$
and respective radii $r_s$ and $r_t$ intersect. Disk graphs are used to model
sensor networks. Similarly, the transmission graph $T(S)$ is the directed graph
with vertex set $S$ and a directed edge from a site $s$ to a site $t$ if and
only if $|st| \leq r_s$, i.e., if $t$ lies in the disk with center $s$ and
radius $r_s$.
</p>
<p>We provide algorithms for detecting (directed) triangles and, more generally,
computing the length of a shortest cycle (the girth) in $D(S)$ and in $T(S)$.
These problems are notoriously hard in general, but better solutions exist for
special graph classes such as planar graphs. We obtain similarly efficient
results for disk graphs and for transmission graphs. More precisely, we show
that a shortest (Euclidean) triangle in $D(S)$ and in $T(S)$ can be found in
$O(n \log n)$ expected time, and that the (weighted) girth of $D(S)$ can be
found in $O(n \log n)$ expected time. For this, we develop new tools for
batched range searching that may be of independent interest.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:48:04Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01815</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01815" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Circular Pattern Matching with $k$ Mismatches</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Charalampopoulos:Panagiotis.html">Panagiotis Charalampopoulos</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kociumaka:Tomasz.html">Tomasz Kociumaka</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pissis:Solon_P=.html">Solon P. Pissis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Radoszewski:Jakub.html">Jakub Radoszewski</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rytter:Wojciech.html">Wojciech Rytter</a>, Juliusz Straszyński, Tomasz Waleń, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zuba:Wiktor.html">Wiktor Zuba</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01815">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The $k$-mismatch problem consists in computing the Hamming distance between a
pattern $P$ of length $m$ and every length-$m$ substring of a text $T$ of
length $n$, if this distance is no more than $k$. In many real-world
applications, any cyclic shift of $P$ is a relevant pattern, and thus one is
interested in computing the minimal distance of every length-$m$ substring of
$T$ and any cyclic shift of $P$. This is the circular pattern matching with $k$
mismatches ($k$-CPM) problem. A multitude of papers have been devoted to
solving this problem but, to the best of our knowledge, only average-case upper
bounds are known. In this paper, we present the first non-trivial worst-case
upper bounds for the $k$-CPM problem. Specifically, we show an $O(nk)$-time
algorithm and an $O(n+\frac{n}{m}\,{\small k^5})$-time algorithm. The latter
algorithm applies in an extended way a technique that was very recently
developed for the $k$-mismatch problem [Bringmann et al., SODA 2019].
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:25:22Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01773</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01773" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Accelerating Deconvolution on Unmodified CNN Accelerators for Generative Adversarial Networks -- A Software Approach</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tu:Kaijie.html">Kaijie Tu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01773">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) are the emerging machine learning
technology that can learn to automatically create labeled datasets in massive
application domains such as speech, image, video and texts. A GAN typically
includes a generative model that is taught to generate any distribution of
data, and a discriminator trained to distinguish the synthetic data from
real-world data. Both convolutional and deconvolutional layers are the major
source of performance overhead for GANs and directly impacts the efficiency of
GAN-based systems. There are many prior works investigating specialized
hardware architectures that can accelerate convolution and deconvolution
simultaneously, but they entail intensive hardware modifications to the
existing CNN accelerators or processors that focus on convolution acceleration.
In contrast, this work proposes a novel deconvolution layer implementation with
a software approach and enables fast and efficient generative network inference
on the legacy Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) accelerators. Our proposed
method reorganizes the computation of deconvolutional layer and allows the CNN
accelerators to treat it as the standard convolutional layer after we split the
original deconvolutional filters into multiple small filters. The proposed data
flow is implemented on representative CNN accelerators including dot-production
array and regular 2D PE array architectures. Compared to the prior baseline
acceleration scheme, the implemented acceleration scheme achieves 2.4X - 4.3X
performance speedup and reduces the energy consumption by 27.7% - 54.5% on a
set of realistic benchmarks.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:25:18Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01766</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01766" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Algorithms for Competitive Division of Chores</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Br=acirc=nzei:Simina.html">Simina Brânzei</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sandomirskiy:Fedor.html">Fedor Sandomirskiy</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01766">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the problem of allocating divisible bads (chores) among multiple
agents with additive utilities, when money transfers are not allowed. The
competitive rule is known to be the best mechanism for goods with additive
utilities and was recently extended to chores by Bogomolnaia et al (2017). For
both goods and chores, the rule produces Pareto optimal and envy-free
allocations. In the case of goods, the outcome of the competitive rule can be
easily computed. Competitive allocations solve the Eisenberg-Gale convex
program; hence the outcome is unique and can be approximately found by standard
gradient methods. An exact algorithm that runs in polynomial time in the number
of agents and goods was given by Orlin.
</p>
<p>In the case of chores, the competitive rule does not solve any convex
optimization problem; instead, competitive allocations correspond to local
minima, local maxima, and saddle points of the Nash Social Welfare on the
Pareto frontier of the set of feasible utilities. The rule becomes multivalued
and none of the standard methods can be applied to compute its outcome.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we show that all the outcomes of the competitive rule for
chores can be computed in strongly polynomial time if either the number of
agents or the number of chores is fixed. The approach is based on a combination
of three ideas: all consumption graphs of Pareto optimal allocations can be
listed in polynomial time; for a given consumption graph, a candidate for a
competitive allocation can be constructed via explicit formula; and a given
allocation can be checked for being competitive using a maximum flow
computation as in Devanur et al (2002).
</p>
<p>Our algorithm immediately gives an approximately-fair allocation of
indivisible chores by the rounding technique of Barman and Krishnamurthy
(2018).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:23:34Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01745</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01745" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Generalized Assignment via Submodular Optimization with Reserved Capacity</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kulik:Ariel.html">Ariel Kulik</a>, Kanthi Sarpatwar, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schieber:Baruch.html">Baruch Schieber</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Shachnai:Hadas.html">Hadas Shachnai</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01745">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study a variant of the \emph{generalized assignment problem} ({\sf GAP})
with group constraints. An instance of {\sf Group GAP} is a set $I$ of items,
partitioned into $L$ groups, and a set of $m$ uniform (unit-sized) bins. Each
item $i \in I$ has a size $s_i &gt;0$, and a profit $p_{i,j} \geq 0$ if packed in
bin $j$. A group of items is \emph{satisfied} if all of its items are packed.
The goal is to find a feasible packing of a subset of the items in the bins
such that the total profit from satisfied groups is maximized. We point to
central applications of {\sf Group GAP} in Video-on-Demand services, mobile
Device-to-Device network caching and base station cooperation in 5G networks.
</p>
<p>Our main result is a $\frac{1}{6}$-approximation algorithm for {\sf Group
GAP} instances where the total size of each group is at most $\frac{m}{2}$. At
the heart of our algorithm lies an interesting derivation of a submodular
function from the classic LP formulation of {\sf GAP}, which facilitates the
construction of a high profit solution utilizing at most half the total bin
capacity, while the other half is \emph{reserved} for later use. In particular,
we give an algorithm for submodular maximization subject to a knapsack
constraint, which finds a solution of profit at least $\frac{1}{3}$ of the
optimum, using at most half the knapsack capacity, under mild restrictions on
element sizes. Our novel approach of submodular optimization subject to a
knapsack \emph{with reserved capacity} constraint may find applications in
solving other group assignment problems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:23:46Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01700</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01700" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Shortest Reconfiguration of Perfect Matchings via Alternating Cycles</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Ito:Takehiro.html">Takehiro Ito</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kakimura:Naonori.html">Naonori Kakimura</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kamiyama:Naoyuki.html">Naoyuki Kamiyama</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kobayashi:Yusuke.html">Yusuke Kobayashi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Okamoto:Yoshio.html">Yoshio Okamoto</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01700">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Motivated by adjacency in perfect matching polytopes, we study the shortest
reconfiguration problem of perfect matchings via alternating cycles. Namely, we
want to find a shortest sequence of perfect matchings which transforms one
given perfect matching to another given perfect matching such that the
symmetric difference of each pair of consecutive perfect matchings is a single
cycle. The problem is equivalent to the combinatorial shortest path problem in
perfect matching polytopes. We prove that the problem is NP-hard even when a
given graph is planar or bipartite, but it can be solved in polynomial time
when the graph is outerplanar.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:27Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01683</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01683" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>SkeletonNet: Shape Pixel to Skeleton Pixel</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Sabari Nathan, Priya Kansal <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01683">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Deep Learning for Geometric Shape Understating has organized a challenge for
extracting different kinds of skeletons from the images of different objects.
This competition is organized in association with CVPR 2019. There are three
different tracks of this competition. The present manuscript describes the
method used to train the model for the dataset provided in the first track. The
first track aims to extract skeleton pixels from the shape pixels of 89
different objects. For the purpose of extracting the skeleton, a U-net model
which is comprised of an encoder-decoder structure has been used. In our
proposed architecture, unlike the plain decoder in the traditional Unet, we
have designed the decoder in the format of HED architecture, wherein we have
introduced 4 side layers and fused them to one dilation convolutional layer to
connect the broken links of the skeleton. Our proposed architecture achieved
the F1 score of 0.77 on test data.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:43:04Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01631</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01631" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Cache-Friendly Search Trees; or, In Which Everything Beats std::set</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Jeffrey Barratt, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Brian.html">Brian Zhang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01631">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>While a lot of work in theoretical computer science has gone into optimizing
the runtime and space usage of data structures, such work very often neglects a
very important component of modern computers: the cache. In doing so, very
often, data structures are developed that achieve theoretically-good runtimes
but are slow in practice due to a large number of cache misses. In 1999, Frigo
et al. introduced the notion of a cache-oblivious algorithm: an algorithm that
uses the cache to its advantage, regardless of the size or structure of said
cache. Since then, various authors have designed cache-oblivious algorithms and
data structures for problems from matrix multiplication to array sorting. We
focus in this work on cache-oblivious search trees; i.e. implementing an
ordered dictionary in a cache-friendly manner. We will start by presenting an
overview of cache-oblivious data structures, especially cache-oblivious search
trees. We then give practical results using these cache-oblivious structures on
modern-day machinery, comparing them to the standard std::set and other
cache-friendly dictionaries such as B-trees.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:39:38Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01630</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01630" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Computing k-Modal Embeddings of Planar Digraphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Juan Jose Besa, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lozzo:Giordano_Da.html">Giordano Da Lozzo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Goodrich:Michael_T=.html">Michael T. Goodrich</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01630">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a planar digraph $G$ and a positive even integer $k$, an embedding of
$G$ in the plane is k-modal, if every vertex of $G$ is incident to at most $k$
pairs of consecutive edges with opposite orientations, i.e., the incoming and
the outgoing edges at each vertex are grouped by the embedding into at most k
sets of consecutive edges with the same orientation. In this paper, we study
the $k$-Modality problem, which asks for the existence of a $k$-modal embedding
of a planar digraph. This combinatorial problem is at the very core of a
variety of constrained embedding questions for planar digraphs and flat
clustered networks.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01624</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01624" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Efficient Circuit Simulation in MapReduce</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Frei:Fabian.html">Fabian Frei</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wada:Koichi.html">Koichi Wada</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01624">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The MapReduce framework has firmly established itself as one of the most
widely used parallel computing platforms for processing big data on tera- and
peta-byte scale. Approaching it from a theoretical standpoint has proved to be
notoriously difficult, however. In continuation of Goodrich et al.'s early
efforts, explicitly espousing the goal of putting the MapReduce framework on
footing equal to that of long-established models such as the PRAM, we
investigate the obvious complexity question of how the computational power of
MapReduce algorithms compares to that of combinational Boolean circuits
commonly used for parallel computations. Relying on the standard MapReduce
model introduced by Karloff et al. a decade ago, we develop an intricate
simulation technique to show that any problem in NC (i.e., a problem solved by
a logspace-uniform family of Boolean circuits of polynomial size and a depth
polylogarithmic in the input size) can be solved by a MapReduce computation in
O(T(n)/ log n) rounds, where n is the input size and T(n) is the depth of the
witnessing circuit family. Thus, we are able to closely relate the standard,
uniform NC hierarchy modeling parallel computations to the deterministic
MapReduce hierarchy DMRC by proving that NC^(i+1) is contained in DMRC^i for
all natural i, including 0. Besides the theoretical significance, this result
that has important applied aspects as well. In particular, we show for all
problems in NC^1---many practically relevant ones, such as integer
multiplication and division and the parity function, being among these---how to
solve them in a constant number of deterministic MapReduce rounds.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:22:52Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01619</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01619" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Learning from satisfying assignments under continuous distributions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Canonne:Cl=eacute=ment_L=.html">Clément L. Canonne</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/De:Anindya.html">Anindya De</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Servedio:Rocco_A=.html">Rocco A. Servedio</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01619">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>What kinds of functions are learnable from their satisfying assignments?
Motivated by this simple question, we extend the framework of De, Diakonikolas,
and Servedio [DDS15], which studied the learnability of probability
distributions over $\{0,1\}^n$ defined by the set of satisfying assignments to
"low-complexity" Boolean functions, to Boolean-valued functions defined over
continuous domains. In our learning scenario there is a known "background
distribution" $\mathcal{D}$ over $\mathbb{R}^n$ (such as a known normal
distribution or a known log-concave distribution) and the learner is given
i.i.d. samples drawn from a target distribution $\mathcal{D}_f$, where
$\mathcal{D}_f$ is $\mathcal{D}$ restricted to the satisfying assignments of an
unknown low-complexity Boolean-valued function $f$. The problem is to learn an
approximation $\mathcal{D}'$ of the target distribution $\mathcal{D}_f$ which
has small error as measured in total variation distance.
</p>
<p>We give a range of efficient algorithms and hardness results for this
problem, focusing on the case when $f$ is a low-degree polynomial threshold
function (PTF). When the background distribution $\mathcal{D}$ is log-concave,
we show that this learning problem is efficiently solvable for degree-1 PTFs
(i.e.,~linear threshold functions) but not for degree-2 PTFs. In contrast, when
$\mathcal{D}$ is a normal distribution, we show that this learning problem is
efficiently solvable for degree-2 PTFs but not for degree-4 PTFs. Our hardness
results rely on standard assumptions about secure signature schemes.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01617</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01617" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Short Proof of the Toughness of Delaunay Triangulations</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Biniaz:Ahmad.html">Ahmad Biniaz</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01617">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a self-contained short proof of the seminal result of Dillencourt
(SoCG 1987 and DCG 1990) that Delaunay triangulations, of planar point sets in
general position, are 1-tough. An important implication of this result is that
Delaunay triangulations have perfect matchings.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T02:01:24Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01600</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01600" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximate Similarity Search Under Edit Distance Using Locality-Sensitive Hashing</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562198400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/McCauley:Samuel.html">Samuel McCauley</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01600">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Edit distance similarity search, also called approximate pattern matching, is
a fundamental problem with widespread applications. The goal of the problem is
to preprocess n strings of length d to quickly answer queries q of the form: if
there is a database string within edit distance r of q, return a database
string within edit distance cr of q. A data structure solving this problem is
analyzed using two criteria: the amount of extra space used in preprocessing,
and the expected time to answer a query.
</p>
<p>Previous approaches to this problem have either used trie-based methods,
which give exact solutions at the cost of expensive queries, or embeddings,
which only work for large (superconstant) values of c.
</p>
<p>In this work we achieve the first bounds for any approximation factor c, via
a simple and easy-to-implement hash function. This gives a running time of
$\tilde{O}(d3^rn^{1/c})$, with space $\tilde{O}(3^r n^{1 + 1/c} + dn)$. We show
how to apply these ideas to the closely-related Approximate Nearest Neighbor
problem for edit distance, obtaining similar time bounds.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-04T01:42:57Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/07/03/postdoc-at-national-university-of-singapore-apply-by-november-30-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/07/03/postdoc-at-national-university-of-singapore-apply-by-november-30-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at National University of Singapore (apply by November 30, 2019)</title>
    <summary>Multiple post-doctoral research positions available in the project on “Provably Verified and Explainable Probabilistic Reasoning,” led by the Principle Investigator, Kuldeep S. Meel. The project broadly aims to develop of formal methods for AI techniques and employ advances in AI techniques for the development of formal methods. Website: https://meelgroup.github.io/files/postdoc.html Email: meel+postdoc@comp.nus.edu.sg</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Multiple post-doctoral research positions available in the project on “Provably Verified and Explainable Probabilistic Reasoning,” led by the Principle Investigator, Kuldeep S. Meel.</p>
<p>The project broadly aims to develop of formal methods for AI techniques and employ advances in AI techniques for the development of formal methods.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://meelgroup.github.io/files/postdoc.html">https://meelgroup.github.io/files/postdoc.html</a><br/>
Email: meel+postdoc@comp.nus.edu.sg</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-03T19:39:18Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-03T19:39:18Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T22:20:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16070</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/07/03/mathematics-of-gerrymandering/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Mathematics of Gerrymandering</title>
    <summary>Can theory help? source; art by Bill Hennessy John Roberts is the Chief Justice of the United States. Today I will discuss the recent Supreme Court decision on gerrymandering. The 5-4 decision in Rucho v. Common Cause takes the courts out of deciding if redistricting was done fairly. Roberts, penning the majority argument, felt that […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Can theory help?</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/07/03/mathematics-of-gerrymandering/unknown-124/" rel="attachment wp-att-16073"><img alt="" class="alignright size-full wp-image-16073" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/unknown.jpeg?w=600"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2"><a href="https://nonperele.com/john-biskupic-how-john-roberts-controls-the-us-supreme-court/">source</a>; art by Bill Hennessy</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
John Roberts is the Chief Justice of the United States.</p>
<p>
Today I will discuss the recent Supreme Court <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/rucho-v-common-cause-2/">decision</a> on gerrymandering.</p>
<p>
The 5-4 decision in Rucho v. Common Cause takes the courts out of deciding if redistricting was done fairly. Roberts, penning the majority argument, felt that it was hard, if not impossible, for courts to determine whether districts were reasonably drawn. That is, whether partisan motives dominated when they were created.</p>
<p>
I will explain what <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerrymandering">gerrymandering</a> is, and how computational methods may play a role. I must add a takeaway: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <i>The current view of computational methods to avoid gerrymandering may be based on incorrect assumptions.</i> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>More on this later.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> How It Works </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
You probably know that gerrymandering is used, negatively, to describe creating voting districts that do not reflect the voters will. The term was coined as part of an attack on the then Governor of Massachusetts in 1812. The shape of one particularly contrived district looked like a salamander. Since his name was Elbridge Gerry, it became a <i>gerrymander</i>. He was a Democratic-Republican and was not re-elected. </p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/07/03/mathematics-of-gerrymandering/gerry/" rel="attachment wp-att-16071"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-16071" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/gerry.png?w=600"/></a></p>
<p>
Here is a figure from our friends at Wikipedia that presents examples of gerrymandering. </p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/07/03/mathematics-of-gerrymandering/divide/" rel="attachment wp-att-16072"><img alt="" class="aligncenter  wp-image-16072" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/divide.png?w=270" width="270"/></a></p>
<p>
By redistricting in the above, one can achieve anything from districts all won by the majority, to most won by the majority. These examples, show how the party who controls the districts can control the outcome.</p>
<p>
Well that is an overstatement. They can control the believed leanings of the voters in the districts. In the above example, they can control how yellow a district is. Real life is complicated by other factors: </p>
<ol>
<li>
A candidate may win because they are just more popular. That is a green candidate could still win in a yellow district. <p/>
</li><li>
A candidate may win because of random fluctuations. If the voter margin is small enough, random fluctuations could change the “expected” outcome.
</li></ol>
<p>
The latter is a danger for gerrymanderers. This <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/blog/what-is-extreme-gerrymandering">site</a> on gerrymandering says: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> The trick is not to spread your voters out so much that districts become vulnerable to flipping to the other party in the normal give and take of electoral politics. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> How We Model It </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Since Roberts is not our intended audience we will use mathematical definitions. I am sure Roberts and the rest of the Supreme Court justices are smart, but we have our own methods. We do not use legal jargon such as “prima facie” and suspect they do not use math jargon like “prime” numbers.</p>
<p>
So let the yellow party have <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> fraction of the voters. Suppose the voters have to be divided into <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/> districts of the same size. A division is just a vector <img alt="{y=(y_{1},\dots,y_{d})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%3D%28y_%7B1%7D%2C%5Cdots%2Cy_%7Bd%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y=(y_{1},\dots,y_{d})}"/> so that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  y_{1} + \cdots + y_{d} = 1, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++y_%7B1%7D+%2B+%5Ccdots+%2B+y_%7Bd%7D+%3D+1%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  y_{1} + \cdots + y_{d} = 1, "/></p>
<p>and each <img alt="{y_{i}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By_%7Bi%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y_{i}}"/> is non-negative. For such a vector <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/> the number that yellow <i>wins</i> is the number of indices <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k}"/> so that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  y_{k} \ge \frac{1}{2d}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++y_%7Bk%7D+%5Cge+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2d%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  y_{k} \ge \frac{1}{2d}. "/></p>
<p>Note, we assume that <img alt="{1/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1/2}"/> of the voters makes a district a win. We can change this to strictly larger than <img alt="{1/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1/2}"/>, but will leave it for now.</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Definition 1</b> <em> Define <img alt="{{\rm MaxWin}(d, \alpha)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7B%5Crm+MaxWin%7D%28d%2C+%5Calpha%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{{\rm MaxWin}(d, \alpha)}"/> to the maximum over all <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/> of the number of wins; and define <img alt="{{\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7B%5Crm+MinWin%7D%28d%2C+%5Calpha%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{{\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha)}"/> to be the minimum number of wins. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Note, we do not care who is doing the redistricting. Nor do we care about the geometry. For example 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  {\rm MaxWin}(5, 0.60) = 5 \text{ and } {\rm MinWin}(5, 0.60) = 1. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%7B%5Crm+MaxWin%7D%285%2C+0.60%29+%3D+5+%5Ctext%7B+and+%7D+%7B%5Crm+MinWin%7D%285%2C+0.60%29+%3D+1.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  {\rm MaxWin}(5, 0.60) = 5 \text{ and } {\rm MinWin}(5, 0.60) = 1. "/></p>
<p>What can we say about these functions? Here are some simple observations.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> If <img alt="{\alpha \ge 0.5}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha+%5Cge+0.5%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha \ge 0.5}"/>, then <img alt="{{\rm MaxWin}(d, \alpha) = d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7B%5Crm+MaxWin%7D%28d%2C+%5Calpha%29+%3D+d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{{\rm MaxWin}(d, \alpha) = d}"/>. Just place <img alt="{\alpha }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha }"/> fraction of the voters in each district.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> If <img alt="{\alpha &gt; 0.5}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha+%3E+0.5%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha &gt; 0.5}"/>, then <img alt="{{\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha) \ge 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7B%5Crm+MinWin%7D%28d%2C+%5Calpha%29+%5Cge+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{{\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha) \ge 1}"/>. No matter how the districts are drawn there must be at least one where yellow has a majority. </p>
<p>
An advantage of these functions is that now we can discuss growth rates, not just present examples. A strength of theory is that we have replaced statements like “this algorithm is fast” by formulas for their running time. Another advantage is that these functions are <i>independent of geometry</i>. Previously I thought the dominating issue was how regions looked. Now I believe the issue is how close one gets to the best and worst case: <img alt="{\rm MaxWin}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Crm+MaxWin%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\rm MaxWin}"/> and <img alt="{\rm MinWin}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Crm+MinWin%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\rm MinWin}"/>. </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Lemma 2</b> <em> Suppose that <img alt="{\alpha &gt; 1/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha+%3E+1%2F2%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha &gt; 1/2}"/>. Then 	</em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  {\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha) = d-\lfloor 2(1-\alpha) d \rfloor " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%7B%5Crm+MinWin%7D%28d%2C+%5Calpha%29+%3D+d-%5Clfloor+2%281-%5Calpha%29+d+%5Crfloor+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  {\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha) = d-\lfloor 2(1-\alpha) d \rfloor "/></p>
</em><p><em/>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
<em>Proof:</em>  Let <img alt="{\beta = 1-\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta+%3D+1-%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\beta = 1-\alpha}"/>. Let’s create the arrangement that makes green win as many districts as possible. If <img alt="{g}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bg%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{g}"/> regions are mostly green then that takes <img alt="{\frac{g}{2d}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bg%7D%7B2d%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\frac{g}{2d}}"/> of the <img alt="{\beta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\beta}"/> green voters. This implies that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \frac{g}{2d} \le \beta. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cfrac%7Bg%7D%7B2d%7D+%5Cle+%5Cbeta.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \frac{g}{2d} \le \beta. "/></p>
<p>So it follows 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  g \le 2\beta d. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++g+%5Cle+2%5Cbeta+d.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  g \le 2\beta d. "/></p>
<p>This proves that <img alt="{g}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bg%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{g}"/> is equal to <img alt="{\lfloor 2\beta d \rfloor}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clfloor+2%5Cbeta+d+%5Crfloor%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\lfloor 2\beta d \rfloor}"/>. <img alt="\Box" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5CBox&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\Box"/></p>
<p>
It may help to set <img alt="{\alpha = 1/2 + \epsilon}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha+%3D+1%2F2+%2B+%5Cepsilon%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha = 1/2 + \epsilon}"/> where <img alt="{\epsilon&gt;0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon%3E0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon&gt;0}"/>. Let’s agree to ignore the rounding off and delete the floor and ceiling functions. Then 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  {\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha) = d-2(1-\alpha) d " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%7B%5Crm+MinWin%7D%28d%2C+%5Calpha%29+%3D+d-2%281-%5Calpha%29+d+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  {\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha) = d-2(1-\alpha) d "/></p>
<p>and so 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  {\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha) = 2\epsilon d. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%7B%5Crm+MinWin%7D%28d%2C+%5Calpha%29+%3D+2%5Cepsilon+d.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  {\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha) = 2\epsilon d. "/></p>
<p>Thus for <img alt="{\epsilon = 1/10}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon+%3D+1%2F10%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon = 1/10}"/> we get that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  {\rm MaxWin}(d, \alpha) = d \text{ and } {\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha) = 0.2d. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%7B%5Crm+MaxWin%7D%28d%2C+%5Calpha%29+%3D+d+%5Ctext%7B+and+%7D+%7B%5Crm+MinWin%7D%28d%2C+%5Calpha%29+%3D+0.2d.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  {\rm MaxWin}(d, \alpha) = d \text{ and } {\rm MinWin}(d, \alpha) = 0.2d. "/></p>
<p>This says that independent of any geometry if yellow has a ten percent majority, then best case if they set the districts they could win all, and if green sets the districts the worst they can get is twenty percent of the districts.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> How Algorithms Can Help </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
There is long-term and continuing interest in algorithms that automate redistricting. The hope is that automated systems will be able to create districts that are fair. A trouble with this research is that there is no universal notion of what makes districts fair. The mantra is: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <i>A redistricting is fair if and only if the districts collectively satisfy some geometric criterion</i>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>An explicit statement of such a criterion, from a <a href="https://bdistricting.com/about.html">site</a> on such algorithms, is: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <i>The best district map is the one where people have the lowest average distance to the center of their district</i>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Of course the name “gerrymandering” came from how districts looked. Somehow this enshrined the notion that districts must look right. I feel this could be wrong.</p>
<p>
Here is a quote from a recent <a href="http://district.cs.brown.edu">paper</a> on an algorithm for redistricting. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> We propose a method for redistricting, decomposing a geographical area into subareas, called districts, so that the populations of the districts are as close as possible and the districts are compact and contiguous. Each district is the intersection of a polygon with the geographical area. The polygons are convex and the average number of sides per polygon is less than six. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>The authors are Philip Klein and Neal Young, who are well known researchers on various aspects of algorithms. They do interesting work, their paper is interesting, but the assumption that geometry is the key I do not get.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> How To Do Better? </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I think that we need to go beyond geometry to understand and avoid gerrymandering. The connection between geometry and fairness is driven—I believe—by tradition. Voters in the same district probably want to be near each other. In the past being near each other was probably important, since travel was so difficult. Perhaps today location is less of an issue then it was before cars, phones, cell phones, internet access, and email. Perhaps districts can be fair and yet do not look good. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
An analogy to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair_cake-cutting">cake cutting</a> may occur to you. Recall in the cake cutting problem success is <i>not</i> measured in how the pieces of the cake look. It is only measured by whether the parties cutting the cake are happy. Is there some way to push this analogy? I just came across a <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1710.08781.pdf">paper</a> using the cake cutting method: <i>A Partisan Districting Protocol With Provably Nonpartisan Outcomes</i> by Wesley Pegden, Ariel Procaccia, and Dingli Yu. More in the future.</p>
<p>
Can algorithmic methods help? Is geometry the fundamental issue? </p>
<p/><p><br/>
[sourced photo, other word edits]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-03T13:51:13Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-03T13:51:13Z</published>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="cake-cutting"/>
    <category term="districts"/>
    <category term="fair"/>
    <category term="geometry"/>
    <category term="gerrymander"/>
    <category term="gerrymandering"/>
    <category term="reasonable"/>
    <category term="voters"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T22:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1136</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1136" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for June 2019</title>
    <summary>We’ve got four papers this month. A mix of distribution testing, matrix problems, and a different paper on the power of sampling. On the Complexity of Estimating the Effective Support Size, by Oded Goldreich (ECCC). In distribution testing, a classic problem is that of approximating the support size. By a (now) classic result of Valiant-Valiant, […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We’ve got four papers this month. A mix of distribution testing, matrix problems, and a different paper on the power of sampling.</p>



<p><strong>On the Complexity of Estimating the Effective Support Size</strong>, by Oded Goldreich (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/088/">ECCC</a>). In distribution testing, a classic problem is that of approximating the support size. By a (now) classic result of <a href="http://theory.stanford.edu/~valiant/papers/VV_stoc11.pdf">Valiant-Valiant</a>, the complexity of this problem is \(\Theta(n/\log n)\). This paper raises the question of approximating the “effective” support, and that too with more than just samples from the distribution. The \(\epsilon\)-support of discrete distribution \(\mathcal{D}\) is the smallest support among any distribution \(\mathcal{D}’\) such that \(\|\mathcal{D} – \mathcal{D}’\|_1 \leq \epsilon\) (or TV-distance). Denote this as \(supp_\epsilon(\mathcal{D})\). One can also consider a bicriteria version. Given approximation parameter \(f\) and thresholds \(\epsilon_1 &lt; \epsilon_2\), we need to provide a number in the range \([supp_{\epsilon_2}(\mathcal{D}), f\cdot supp_{\epsilon_1}(\mathcal{D})]\). The primary model studied allows for random samples and evaluation queries (where one gets the probability of any known element of the domain). In this model, for arbitrary \(\epsilon_1, \epsilon_2\), there is a continuum of algorithms, trading off query complexity with approximation. At one end, for \(f = O(\log n)\), the query complexity is \(\widetilde{O}(1/\epsilon_1)\). At the other end, for \(f=1\), the query complexity is \(O(\log^* n)\). (Here, \(n = supp_{\epsilon_1}(\mathcal{D})\).) There are lower bounds showing the necessity of evaluation queries for subpolynomial query complexities.</p>



<p><strong>Communication and Memory Efficient Testing of Discrete Distributions</strong>, by Ilias Diakonikolas, Themis Gouleakis, Daniel M. Kane, and Sankeerth Rao (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.04709">arXiv</a>). This paper adds additional computational constraints to the distribution testing problem. In the streaming setting, the algorithm is only allowed a single pass over the random samples. It has \(m\) bits of storage, much smaller than \(n\), the distribution size. The aim is to minimize the number of samples required for uniformity (and closeness) testing. For uniformity testing in the streaming setting, the paper gives an algorithm that uses \(\widetilde{O}(m + n/m)\) samples. The standard collision algorithm requires \(\Theta(\sqrt{n})\) storage (to store the samples), while this result gives a non-trivial bound for \(m \ll \sqrt{n}\). There are lower bounds showing that these bounds are basically tight. In the distributed distribution testing problem, there are a number of processors, each holding \(\ell\) samples. A referee asks a question to the processor, whose answers are broadcast to everyone. The aim is to minimize communication cost. For uniformity testing in this setting, there is a protocol using \(O(\sqrt{n\log n/\ell})\) bits of communication. As a sanity check, note that for \(\ell = \sqrt{n}\), one processor could simply run the collision algorithm locally to report the result. </p>



<p><strong>Querying a Matrix through Matrix-Vector Products</strong> by Xiaoming Sun, David P. Woodruff, Guang Yang, and Jialin Zhang (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.05736.pdf">arXiv</a>). Consider \(n \times d\) matrix \(M\) over some field \(\mathbb{F}\). One gets access to this matrix through matrix-vector products, and wishes to test some matrix property. This is a natural model in many settings, and generalizes the classic setting of query access. A subtle point is that one can only right multiply with “query” vectors, and there are problems where left multiplication can change the complexity. (A nice example in the paper is testing if a square matrix is symmetric. With both left and right multiplications, this is easy, since we can directly access rows and columns. By only accessing columns, this is non-trivial.) This paper studies a number of problems, broadly classified as linear algebra problems, statistics problems, and graph problems. Some highlights are: testing symmetry can be done in \(O(1)\) queries, and the maximum eigenvalue can be approximated in \(O(\log n)\) queries adaptively (but there is an \(\Omega(n)\) non-adaptive lower bound). For graph problems, here’s an interesting discovery. If \(M\) is the adjacency matrix, connectivity requires \(\Omega(n/\log n)\) queries. But if \(M\) is the signed edge-vertex matrix, then this can be done in \(poly(\log n)\) queries. This paper provides a number of interesting directions and problems to study.</p>



<p><strong>The Adversarial Robustness of Sampling</strong> by Omri Ben-Eliezer and Eylon Yogev (arXiv). This isn’t a property testing paper, but how can one ignore a paper on understanding the power of sampling? It’s convenient to think of the following setting. An algorithm gets a stream of \(n\) numbers, and has to answer some questions about the stream (say, the median or other quantiles). The simplest strategy is to take a small random sample of the stream. But what if an adversary was generating the stream, depending on the current sample? Under what circumstances is the sample still “representative” of the stream? The specific results of this paper require getting into set systems and VC dimension, which I’ll leave for the sake of simplicity. Let’s go back to the median question. To get an approximate median, a constant number of samples suffice. A consequence of the main result is that if one takes \(O(\log n)\) samples, then this is robust to adversarial streams. On the other hand, lower bounds show that constant sized samples can be fooled by an adversary. The paper is a really interesting read, and is a nice take on “standard facts” that we take for granted.</p>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-03T00:54:36Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-03T00:54:36Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Seshadhri</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T23:30:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01495</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01495" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Isomorphism Problem for $S_d$-graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Deniz Ağaoğlu <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01495">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>An $H$-graph is the intersection graph of connected subgraphs of a suitable
subdivision of a fixed graph $H$. We focus on $S_d$-graphs as a special case. A
graph $G$ is an $S_d$-graph when it is the intersection graph of connected
subgraphs of a subdivision of a fixed star $S_d$. It is useful to mention that,
for an $S_d$-graph $G$ with some proper maximal clique $C \in G$, each
connected component of $G-C$ is an interval graph and the partial order on the
connected components of $G-C$ has a chain cover of size $\leq d$. Considering
the recognition algorithm given by Chaplick et al., we give an FPT-time
algorithm to solve the isomorphism problem for $S_d$-graphs with bounded clique
size. Then, we give a polynomial time reduction to $S_d$-graph isomorphism from
the isomorphism problem for posets of width $d$. Finally, we show that the
graph isomorphism problem for $S_d$-graphs can be solved in FPT-time with
parameter $d$, even when the clique size is unbounded.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T23:22:53Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01258</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01258" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A hybrid algorithm framework for small quantum computers with application to finding Hamiltonian cycles</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Ge:Yimin.html">Yimin Ge</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dunjko:Vedran.html">Vedran Dunjko</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01258">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Recent works have shown that quantum computers can polynomially speed up
certain SAT-solving algorithms even when the number of available qubits is
significantly smaller than the number of variables. Here we generalise this
approach. We present a framework for hybrid quantum-classical algorithms which
utilise quantum computers significantly smaller than the problem size. Given an
arbitrarily small ratio of the quantum computer to the instance size, we
achieve polynomial speedups for classical divide-and-conquer algorithms,
provided that certain criteria on the time- and space-efficiency are met. We
demonstrate how this approach can be used to enhance Eppstein's algorithm for
the cubic Hamiltonian cycle problem, and achieve a polynomial speedup for any
ratio of the number of qubits to the size of the graph.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01243</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01243" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Geometric Crossing-Minimization -- A Scalable Randomized Approach</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Radermacher:Marcel.html">Marcel Radermacher</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rutter:Ignaz.html">Ignaz Rutter</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01243">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the minimization of edge-crossings in geometric drawings of
graphs $G=(V, E)$, i.e., in drawings where each edge is depicted as a line
segment. The respective decision problem is NP-hard [Bienstock, '91]. In
contrast to theory and the topological setting, the geometric setting did not
receive a lot of attention in practice. Prior work [Radermacher et al.,
ALENEX'18] is limited to the crossing-minimization in geometric graphs with
less than $200$ edges. The described heuristics base on the primitive operation
of moving a single vertex $v$ to its crossing-minimal position, i.e., the
position in $\mathbb{R}^2$ that minimizes the number of crossings on edges
incident to $v$.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we introduce a technique to speed-up the computation by a
factor of $20$. This is necessary but not sufficient to cope with graphs with a
few thousand edges. In order to handle larger graphs, we drop the condition
that each vertex $v$ has to be moved to its crossing-minimal position and
compute a position that is only optimal with respect to a small random subset
of the edges. In our theoretical contribution, we consider drawings that
contain for each edge $uv \in E$ and each position $p \in \mathbb{R}^2$ for $v$
$o(|E|)$ crossings. In this case, we prove that with a random subset of the
edges of size $\Theta(k \log k)$ the co-crossing number of a degree-$k$ vertex
$v$, i.e., the number of edge pairs $uv \in E, e \in E$ that do not cross, can
be approximated by an arbitrary but fixed factor $\delta$ with high
probability. In our experimental evaluation, we show that the randomized
approach reduces the number of crossings in graphs with up to $13\,000$ edges
considerably. The evaluation suggests that depending on the degree-distribution
different strategies result in the fewest number of crossings.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01241</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01241" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the VC-dimension of convex sets and half-spaces</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grelier:Nicolas.html">Nicolas Grelier</a>, Saeed Gh. Ilchi, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Miltzow:Tillmann.html">Tillmann Miltzow</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Smorodinsky:Shakhar.html">Shakhar Smorodinsky</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01241">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A family $S$ of convex sets in the plane defines a hypergraph $H = (S,E)$ as
follows. Every subfamily $S'\subset S$ defines a hyperedge of $H$ if and only
if there exists a halfspace $h$ that fully contains $S'$, and no other set of
$S$ is fully contained in $h$. In this case, we say that $h$ realizes $S'$. We
say a set $S$ is shattered, if all its subsets are realized. The VC-dimension
of a hypergraph $H$ is the size of the largest shattered set. We show that the
VC-dimension for \emph{pairwise disjoint} convex sets in the plane is bounded
by $3$, and this is tight. In contrast, we show the VC-dimension of convex sets
in the plane (not necessarily disjoint) is unbounded. We also show that the
VC-dimension is unbounded for pairwise disjoint convex sets in $\mathbb{R}^d$,
for $d\geq 3$. We focus on, possibly intersecting, segments in the plane and
determine that the VC-dimension is always at most $5$. And this is tight, as we
construct a set of five segments that can be shattered. We give two exemplary
applications. One for a geometric set cover problem and one for a range-query
data structure problem, to motivate our findings.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01228</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01228" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Constant-Factor Approximation Algorithm for Vertex Guarding a WV-Polygon</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Stav Ashur, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Filtser:Omrit.html">Omrit Filtser</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Katz:Matthew_J=.html">Matthew J. Katz</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01228">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The problem of vertex guarding a simple polygon was first studied by Subir K.
Ghosh (1987), who presented a polynomial-time $O(\log n)$-approximation
algorithm for placing as few guards as possible at vertices of a simple $n$-gon
$P$, such that every point in $P$ is visible to at least one of the guards.
Ghosh also conjectured that this problem admits a polynomial-time algorithm
with constant approximation ratio. Due to the centrality of guarding problems
in the field of computational geometry, much effort has been invested
throughout the years in trying to resolve this conjecture. Despite some
progress (surveyed below), the conjecture remains unresolved to date. In this
paper, we confirm the conjecture for the important case of weakly visible
polygons, by presenting a $(2+\varepsilon)$-approximation algorithm for
guarding such a polygon using vertex guards. A simple polygon $P$ is weakly
visible if it has an edge $e$, such that every point in $P$ is visible from
some point on $e$. We also present a $(2+\varepsilon)$-approximation algorithm
for guarding a weakly visible polygon $P$, where guards may be placed anywhere
on $P$'s boundary (except in the interior of the edge $e$). Finally, we present
a $3c$-approximation algorithm for vertex guarding a polygon $P$ that is weakly
visible from a chord, given a subset $G$ of $P$'s vertices that guards $P$'s
boundary whose size is bounded by $c$ times the size of a minimum such subset.
</p>
<p>Our algorithms are based on an in-depth analysis of the geometric properties
of the regions that remain unguarded after placing guards at the vertices to
guard the polygon's boundary. It is plausible that our results will enable
Bhattacharya et al. to complete their grand attempt to prove the original
conjecture, as their approach is based on partitioning the underlying simple
polygon into a hierarchy of weakly visible polygons.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T23:27:49Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01218</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01218" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Representing fitness landscapes by valued constraints to understand the complexity of local search</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kaznatcheev:Artem.html">Artem Kaznatcheev</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cohen:David_A=.html">David A. Cohen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jeavons:Peter_G=.html">Peter G. Jeavons</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01218">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Local search is widely used to solve combinatorial optimisation problems and
to model biological evolution, but the performance of local search algorithms
on different kinds of fitness landscapes is poorly understood. Here we
introduce a natural approach to modelling fitness landscapes using valued
constraints. This allows us to investigate minimal representations (normal
forms) and to consider the effects of the structure of the constraint graph on
the tractability of local search. First, we show that for fitness landscapes
representable by binary Boolean valued constraints there is a minimal necessary
constraint graph that can be easily computed. Second, we consider landscapes as
equivalent if they allow the same (improving) local search moves; we show that
a minimal normal form still exists, but is NP-hard to compute. Next we consider
the complexity of local search on fitness landscapes modelled by valued
constraints with restricted forms of constraint graph. In the binary Boolean
case, we prove that a tree-structured constraint graph gives a tight quadratic
bound on the number of improving moves made by any local search; hence, any
landscape that can be represented by such a model will be tractable for local
search. We build two families of examples to show that both the conditions in
our tractability result are essential. With domain size three, even just a path
of binary constraints can model a landscape with an exponentially long sequence
of improving moves. With a treewidth two constraint graph, even with a maximum
degree of three, binary Boolean constraints can model a landscape with an
exponentially long sequence of improving moves.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01129</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01129" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>New Results for the Complexity of Resilience for Binary Conjunctive Queries with Self-Joins</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Freire:Cibele.html">Cibele Freire</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gatterbauer:Wolfgang.html">Wolfgang Gatterbauer</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Immerman:Neil.html">Neil Immerman</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Meliou:Alexandra.html">Alexandra Meliou</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01129">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The resilience of a Boolean query is the minimum number of tuples that need
to be deleted from the input tables in order to make the query false. A
solution to this problem immediately translates into a solution for the more
widely known problem of deletion propagation with source-side effects. In this
paper, we give several novel results on the hardness of the resilience problem
for $\textit{binary conjunctive queries with self-joins}$ (i.e. conjunctive
queries with relations of maximal arity 2) with one repeated relation. Unlike
in the self-join free case, the concept of triad is not enough to fully
characterize the complexity of resilience. We identify new structural
properties, namely chains, confluences and permutations, which lead to various
$NP$-hardness results. We also give novel involved reductions to network flow
to show certain cases are in $P$. Overall, we give a dichotomy result for the
restricted setting when one relation is repeated at most 2 times, and we cover
many of the cases for 3. Although restricted, our results provide important
insights into the problem of self-joins that we hope can help solve the general
case of all conjunctive queries with self-joins in the future.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T23:21:21Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01117</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01117" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Exploring Feasible Design Spaces for Heterogeneous Constraints</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mirzendehdel:Amir_M=.html">Amir M. Mirzendehdel</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Behandish:Morad.html">Morad Behandish</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nelaturi:Saigopal.html">Saigopal Nelaturi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01117">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We demonstrate an approach of exploring design spaces to simultaneously
satisfy kinematics- and physics-based requirements. We present a classification
of constraints and solvers to enable postponing optimization as far down the
design workflow as possible. The solvers are organized into two broad classes
of design space 'pruning' and 'exploration' by considering the types of
constraints they can satisfy. We show that pointwise constraints define
feasible design subspaces that can be represented and computed as first-class
entities by their maximal feasible elements. The design space is pruned upfront
by intersecting maximal elements, without premature optimization. To solve for
other constraints, we apply topology optimization (TO), starting from the
pruned feasible space. The optimization is steered by a topological sensitivity
field (TSF) that measures the global changes in violation of constraints with
respect to local topological punctures. The TSF for global objective functions
is augmented with TSF for global constraints, and penalized/filtered to
incorporate local constraints, including set constraints converted to
differentiable (in)equality constraints. We demonstrate application of the
proposed workflow to nontrivial examples in design and manufacturing. Among
other examples, we show how to explore pruned design spaces via TO to
simultaneously satisfy physics-based constraints (e.g., minimize compliance and
mass) as well as kinematics-based constraints (e.g., maximize accessibility for
machining).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T23:26:24Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01076</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01076" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Polynomial Complexity of Vector Addition Systems with States</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zuleger:Florian.html">Florian Zuleger</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01076">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Vector addition systems are an important model in theoretical computer
science and have been used in a variety of areas. In this paper, we consider
vector addition systems with states over a parameterized initial configuration.
For these systems, we are interested in the standard notion of computational
complexity, i.e., we want to understand the length of the longest trace for a
fixed vector addition system with states depending on the size of the initial
configuration. We show that the asymptotic complexity of a given vector
addition system with states is either $\Theta(N^k)$ for some computable integer
$k$, where $N$ is the size of the initial configuration, or at least
exponential. We further show that $k$ can be computed in polynomial time in the
size of the considered vector addition system. Finally, we show that $1 \le k
\le 2^n$, where $n$ is the dimension of the considered vector addition system.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T23:22:31Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01032</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01032" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On Slicing Sorted Integer Sequences</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pibiri:Giulio_Ermanno.html">Giulio Ermanno Pibiri</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01032">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Representing sorted integer sequences in small space is a central problem for
large-scale retrieval systems such as Web search engines. Efficient query
resolution, e.g., intersection or random access, is achieved by carefully
partitioning the sequences. In this work we describe and compare two different
partitioning paradigms: partitioning by cardinality and partitioning by
universe. Although the ideas behind such paradigms have been known in the
coding and algorithmic community since many years, inverted index compression
has extensively adopted the former paradigm, whereas the latter has received
only little attention. As a result, an experimental comparison between these
two is missing for the setting of inverted index compression. We also propose
and implement a solution that recursively slices the universe of representation
of a sequence to achieve compact storage and attain to fast query execution.
Albeit larger than some state-of-the-art representations, this slicing approach
substantially improves the performance of list intersections and unions while
operating in compressed space, thus offering an excellent space/time trade-off
for the problem.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T23:25:22Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01018</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01018" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Information Kernels</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Epstein:Samuel.html">Samuel Epstein</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01018">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a set X of finite strings, one interesting question to ask is whether
there exists a member of X which is simple conditional to all other members of
X. Conditional simplicity is measured by low conditional Kolmogorov complexity.
We prove the affirmative to this question for sets that have low mutual
information with the halting sequence. There are two results with respect to
this question. One is dependent on the maximum conditional complexity between
two elements of X, the other is dependent on the maximum expected value of the
conditional complexity of a member of X relative to each member of X.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T23:20:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01006</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01006" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Enumeration of Preferred Extensions in Almost Oriented Digraphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gaspers:Serge.html">Serge Gaspers</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Ray.html">Ray Li</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01006">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we present enumeration algorithms to list all preferred
extensions of an argumentation framework. This task is equivalent to
enumerating all maximal semikernels of a directed graph. For directed graphs on
$n$ vertices, all preferred extensions can be enumerated in $O^*(3^{n/3})$ time
and there are directed graphs with $\Omega(3^{n/3})$ preferred extensions. We
give faster enumeration algorithms for directed graphs with at most
$0.8004\cdot n$ vertices occurring in $2$-cycles. In particular, for oriented
graphs (digraphs with no 2-cycles) one of our algorithms runs in time
$O(1.2321^n)$, and we show that there are oriented graphs with $\Omega(3^{n/6})
&gt; \Omega(1.2009^n)$ preferred extensions.
</p>
<p>A combination of three algorithms leads to the fastest enumeration times for
various proportions of the number of vertices in $2$-cycles. The most
innovative one is a new 2-stage sampling algorithm, combined with a new
parameterized enumeration algorithm, analyzed with a combination of the recent
monotone local search technique (STOC 2016) and an extension thereof (ICALP
2017).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T23:23:02Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01005</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01005" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Algorithms and data structures for matrix-free finite element operators with MPI-parallel sparse multi-vectors</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Davydov:Denis.html">Denis Davydov</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kronbichler:Martin.html">Martin Kronbichler</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01005">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Traditional solution approaches for problems in quantum mechanics scale as
$\mathcal O(M^3)$, where $M$ is the number of electrons. Various methods have
been proposed to address this issue and obtain linear scaling $\mathcal O(M)$.
One promising formulation is the direct minimization of energy. Such methods
take advantage of physical localization of the solution, namely that the
solution can be sought in terms of non-orthogonal orbitals with local support.
In this work a numerically efficient implementation of sparse parallel vectors
within the open-source finite element library deal.II is proposed. The main
algorithmic ingredient is the matrix-free evaluation of the Hamiltonian
operator by cell-wise quadrature. Based on an a-priori chosen support for each
vector we develop algorithms and data structures to perform (i) matrix-free
sparse matrix multivector products (SpMM), (ii) the projection of an operator
onto a sparse sub-space (inner products), and (iii) post-multiplication of a
sparse multivector with a square matrix. The node-level performance is analyzed
using a roofline model. Our matrix-free implementation of finite element
operators with sparse multivectors achieves the performance of 157 GFlop/s on
Intel Cascade Lake architecture. Strong and weak scaling results are reported
for a typical benchmark problem using quadratic and quartic finite element
bases.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T23:22:53Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01004</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1907.01004" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Symmetry Detection and Classification in Drawings of Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1562112000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Luca:Felice_De.html">Felice De Luca</a>, Md Iqbal Hossain, Stephen Kobourov <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1907.01004">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Symmetry is a key feature observed in nature (from flowers and leaves, to
butterflies and birds) and in man-made objects (from paintings and sculptures,
to manufactured objects and architectural design). Rotational, translational,
and especially reflectional symmetries, are also important in drawings of
graphs. Detecting and classifying symmetries can be very useful in algorithms
that aim to create symmetric graph drawings and in this paper we present a
machine learning approach for these tasks. Specifically, we show that deep
neural networks can be used to detect reflectional symmetries with 92%
accuracy. We also build a multi-class classifier to distinguish between
reflectional horizontal, reflectional vertical, rotational, and translational
symmetries. Finally, we make available a collection of images of graph drawings
with specific symmetric features that can be used in machine learning systems
for training, testing and validation purposes. Our datasets, best trained ML
models, source code are available online.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-03T23:26:38Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-07-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8952301722851173857</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/8952301722851173857/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/07/local-kid-makes-history.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8952301722851173857" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8952301722851173857" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/07/local-kid-makes-history.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Local Kid Makes History</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;">
</div>
<a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-OpUgtDyqMf0/XRuOhVHWTFI/AAAAAAABplw/Tz0jTV3EQCo9w0aZ1bsI9xsJiec3OfytgCLcBGAs/s1600/Huang.jpg" style="clear: right; float: right; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 1em;"><img border="0" height="200" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-OpUgtDyqMf0/XRuOhVHWTFI/AAAAAAABplw/Tz0jTV3EQCo9w0aZ1bsI9xsJiec3OfytgCLcBGAs/s200/Huang.jpg" width="163"/></a>The <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4229">blogosphere</a> is <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/07/02/amazing-hao-huang-proved-the-sensitivity-conjecture/">blowing</a> <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/07/02/sensitivity-conjecture-proved/">up</a> over Hao Huang's just <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.00847">posted proof</a> of the sensitivity conjecture, what was one of the more <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2017/12/razors-edge.html">frustrating open questions</a> in complexity.<br/>
<br/>
Huang, an assistant professor in the math department at Emory, settled an open question about the hypercube. The hypercube is a graph on N=2<sup>n</sup> vertices where each vertex corresponds to an n-bit string and their are edges between vertices corresponding to strings that differ in a single bit. Think of the set of the strings of odd parity, N/2 vertices with no edges between them. Add any other vertex and it would have n neighbors. Huang showed that no matter how you placed those N/2+1 vertices in the hypercube, some vertex will have at least n<sup>1/2</sup> neighbors. By an <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0097-3165(92)90060-8">old result</a> of Gotsman and Linial, Huang's theorem implies the sensitivity conjecture.<br/>
<br/>
I won't go through the shockingly simple proof, the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.00847">paper</a> is well written, or you can read the blogs I linked to above or even just Ryan O'Donnell's <a href="https://twitter.com/BooleanAnalysis/status/1145837576487612416">tweet</a>.<br/>
<br/>
I have nothing more to say than wow, just wow.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-02T17:05:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-02T17:05:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T20:00:18Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7530</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/07/02/sensitivity-conjecture-proved/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Sensitivity conjecture proved!</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div class="wp-block-jetpack-markdown"><p>In a recent breakthrough, <a href="http://www.mathcs.emory.edu/~hhuan30/">Hao Huang</a> gave a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.00847">6 page paper</a> proving the longstanding sensitivity conjecture. (Hat tip, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4229">Scott Aaronson</a> and <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/07/02/amazing-hao-huang-proved-the-sensitivity-conjecture/">Gil Kalai</a>. See this <a href="https://cstheory.stackexchange.com/questions/27714/sensitivity-block-sensitivity-conjecture-implications">stackexchange post</a> and <a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2016/062/">this paper of Avishai</a> for some links to the literature on this.)</p>
<p>The proof is beautiful and simple. I will write a few words here, but it is probably easier for you to just read the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.00847">paper</a>. The sensitivity conjecture <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0097316592900608">was known</a> to follow from the following statement: let <img alt="G_n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G_n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="G_n"/> be the <em>Boolean Cube</em> which is the degree <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="n"/> graph on <img alt="N=2^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%3D2%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N=2^n"/> vertices identified with <img alt="\{0,1\}^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%7B0%2C1%5C%7D%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\{0,1\}^n"/> such that for every <img alt="x,y\in \{0,1\}^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x%2Cy%5Cin+%5C%7B0%2C1%5C%7D%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x,y\in \{0,1\}^n"/>, <img alt="x \sim y" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x+%5Csim+y&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x \sim y"/> if their Hamming distance is one. Then, the maximum degree of every subgraph <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="H"/> of <img alt="G_n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G_n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="G_n"/> of size <img alt="&gt;N/2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%3EN%2F2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="&gt;N/2"/> is at least <img alt="\sqrt{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Csqrt%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\sqrt{n}"/>.</p>
<p>Hao proves the above statement by showing that there is a <em>signing</em> of the <img alt="N\times N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%5Ctimes+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N\times N"/> adjacency matrix of <img alt="G_n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G_n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="G_n"/> that turns it into a matrix with <img alt="N/2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%2F2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N/2"/> eigenvalues equaling <img alt="+\sqrt{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%2B%5Csqrt%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="+\sqrt{n}"/> and <img alt="N/2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%2F2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N/2"/> eigenvalues equaling <img alt="-\sqrt{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=-%5Csqrt%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="-\sqrt{n}"/>. That is, he shows (using a simple but clever inductive argument, see the 5 line proof of his Lemma 2.2) that there is an <img alt="N\times N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%5Ctimes+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N\times N"/> matrix <img alt="A" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="A"/> with entries in <img alt="\{ 0, \pm 1 \}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%7B+0%2C+%5Cpm+1+%5C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\{ 0, \pm 1 \}"/> whose nonzero entries correspond to the edges of the Boolean cube, and such that all the <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N"/> eigenvalues of <img alt="A" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="A"/> are <img alt="\pm \sqrt{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cpm+%5Csqrt%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\pm \sqrt{n}"/> and they sum up to zero. (Note that this makes sense since <img alt="A" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="A"/> should have the same <em>Frobenius norm</em> as  the adjacency matrix of <img alt="G_n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G_n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="G_n"/>. The Frobenius norm squared is both the sum of squares of entries, which is <img alt="N\cdot n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%5Ccdot+n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N\cdot n"/> for <img alt="G_n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G_n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="G_n"/> which is a degree <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="n"/> graph, and also equal to the sum of squares of the eigenvalues, which is <img alt="N\cdot n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%5Ccdot+n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N\cdot n"/> if all eigenvalues are <img alt="\pm \sqrt{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cpm+%5Csqrt%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\pm \sqrt{n}"/>.)</p>
<p>Once you have such a signing, the result follows from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Min-max_theorem#Cauchy_interlacing_theorem">Cauchy’s Interlace Theorem</a> that says that for every <img alt="N\times N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%5Ctimes+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N\times N"/> matrix <img alt="A" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="A"/> and any <img alt="M\times M" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=M%5Ctimes+M&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="M\times M"/> matrix <img alt="B" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=B&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="B"/> that is a principle sub-matrix of <img alt="A" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="A"/>,</p>
<p><img alt="\lambda_{1+N-M}(A) \leq \lambda_1(B) \leq \lambda_1(A)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_%7B1%2BN-M%7D%28A%29+%5Cleq+%5Clambda_1%28B%29+%5Cleq+%5Clambda_1%28A%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\lambda_{1+N-M}(A) \leq \lambda_1(B) \leq \lambda_1(A)"/></p>
<p>where <img alt="\lambda_1(A) \geq \lambda_2(A) \cdots \geq \lambda_N(A)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_1%28A%29+%5Cgeq+%5Clambda_2%28A%29+%5Ccdots+%5Cgeq+%5Clambda_N%28A%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\lambda_1(A) \geq \lambda_2(A) \cdots \geq \lambda_N(A)"/> are the eigenvalues of <img alt="A" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="A"/> and <img alt="\lambda_1(B)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_1%28B%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\lambda_1(B)"/> is the maximum eigenvalue of <img alt="B" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=B&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="B"/>. A corollary of this (which is the only fact we need) is that if <img alt="A" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="A"/> has its top eigenvalue <img alt="\lambda_1(A)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_1%28A%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\lambda_1(A)"/> with multiplicity <img alt="K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="K"/> (i.e., <img alt="\lambda_1(A)=\lambda_K(A)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_1%28A%29%3D%5Clambda_K%28A%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\lambda_1(A)=\lambda_K(A)"/>), then every principle sub-matrix <img alt="B" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=B&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="B"/> of order larger than <img alt="N-K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N-K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N-K"/> will satisfy <img alt="\lambda_1(B) = \lambda_1(A)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_1%28B%29+%3D+%5Clambda_1%28A%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\lambda_1(B) = \lambda_1(A)"/>. (In fact, we only need <img alt="\lambda_1(B) \geq \lambda_1(A)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_1%28B%29+%5Cgeq+%5Clambda_1%28A%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\lambda_1(B) \geq \lambda_1(A)"/>.)</p>
<p>Indeed, suppose that <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="H"/> is a subgraph of the Boolean cube of size <img alt="M&gt;N/2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=M%3EN%2F2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="M&gt;N/2"/>. Then the principle submatrix <img alt="B" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=B&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="B"/> of <img alt="A" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="A"/> corresponding to the vertices of <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="H"/> satisfies <img alt="\lambda_1(B) \geq \lambda_{1+N-M}(A) = \sqrt{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_1%28B%29+%5Cgeq+%5Clambda_%7B1%2BN-M%7D%28A%29+%3D+%5Csqrt%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\lambda_1(B) \geq \lambda_{1+N-M}(A) = \sqrt{n}"/> (since <img alt="M&gt;N/2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=M%3EN%2F2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="M&gt;N/2"/> and the first <img alt="N/2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%2F2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="N/2"/> eigenvalues of <img alt="A" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="A"/> are <img alt="+\sqrt{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%2B%5Csqrt%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="+\sqrt{n}"/>).
But it’s easy to show that for every matrix <img alt="B" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=B&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="B"/> the maximum eigenvalue of <img alt="B" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=B&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="B"/> is upper bounded by the maximum <img alt="\ell_1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cell_1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\ell_1"/> norm of its rows, which in our case is the maximum degree of the graph <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="H"/>.</p>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-02T16:18:34Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-02T16:18:34Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T22:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3401</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/07/02/papafest-september-6-8-columbia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PapaFest (September 6-8 @ Columbia)</title>
    <summary>Announcing a conference celebrating Christos Papadimitriou, September 6-8, 2019, at Columbia University.  Registration is free.  Confirmed invited speakers include: Sanjeev Arora, Michael Collins, Michael I. Jordan, Anna Karlin,  Jon Kleinberg, Elias Koutsoupias, Adi Livnat, Noam Nisan, Prabhakar Raghavan, Scott Shenker, Eva Tardos, John Tsitsiklis, Leslie Valiant, Umesh Vazirani, and Santosh Vempala. More details here. Advertisements</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Announcing a conference celebrating Christos Papadimitriou, September 6-8, 2019, at Columbia University.  Registration is free.  Confirmed invited speakers include: Sanjeev Arora, Michael Collins, Michael I. Jordan, Anna Karlin,  Jon Kleinberg, Elias Koutsoupias, Adi Livnat, Noam Nisan, Prabhakar Raghavan, Scott Shenker, Eva Tardos, John Tsitsiklis, Leslie Valiant, Umesh Vazirani, and Santosh Vempala.</p>
<p>More details <a href="http://papafest.cs.columbia.edu/">here.</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-02T12:47:57Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-02T12:47:57Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>timroughgarden</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T22:20:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/07/02/the-autumn-school-on-machine-learning/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/07/02/the-autumn-school-on-machine-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Autumn school on Machine Learning</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">October 3-11, 2019 Tbilisi, Georgia https://cte.ibsu.edu.ge/autumn/ Registration deadline: October 3, 2019 The school will be organized by the International Black Sea University with the support of Shota Rustaveli National Science Foundation of Georgia (SRNSFG). The intended audience of the autumn school includes BSc, MSc and PhD students, researchers as well as industry professionals from the … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/07/02/the-autumn-school-on-machine-learning/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">The Autumn school on Machine Learning</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-02T09:09:23Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-02T09:09:23Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T22:21:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-6337479962158243575</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/6337479962158243575/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=6337479962158243575" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/6337479962158243575" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/6337479962158243575" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2019/07/phd-position-at-tu-wirn-formal-methods.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PhD position at TU Wirn: Formal methods applied to the specification and monitoring of large-scale, spatially-distributed, stochastic systems</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div class="_5pbx userContent _3576" id="js_3b"><i>Interesting PhD position at TU Wien with <a class="profileLink" href="http://www.eziobartocci.com/" title="Ezio Bartocci">Ezio Bartocci</a> and <a href="https://lauranenzi.github.io/">Laura Nenzi</a>. Spread the news! </i><br/><br/> The <a href="http://ti.tuwien.ac.at/">Institute of Computer Engineering</a> at the Technische Universität Wien (TU Wien) is seeking a candidate for a  research assistant position (PhD student, 4 years). The position is  available from September (a starting date until Fall 2019 is intended)  and the successful candidate will be a PhD student of the <a href="https://logic-cs.at/phd/">LogiCS Doctoral Program</a> and she/he will be supervised by Prof. Ezio Bartocci &lt;<a href="https://l.facebook.com/l.php?u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.eziobartocci.com%2F%3Ffbclid%3DIwAR0DbRlQ3WbZCS1HzoZXYIRYXBsRDz2tCxE2G_6APz6K76RRDmLVMIkgBOg&amp;h=AT3xOIDKhxhBw2_daqAKot9Y3qtCNlITUpSxTEttEVYsbYoofL5LKQ7MD72mx8Nf3f0zPGNE5AY-FvqTQsTVZMllhO6DR94ug3vsjG3H84L4h8RDLdPWJxht8otBFNix1De-G1NEeihv6M6l-3cp" rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank">http://www.eziobartocci.com/</a>&gt; and co-supervised by Dr. Laura Nenzi &lt;<a href="https://l.facebook.com/l.php?u=https%3A%2F%2Flauranenzi.github.io%2F%3Ffbclid%3DIwAR0O-FIXoCWcyMBVUqn5K-Ejd0vxQQJFYQ7ni1qBAdy9Ez01d6CDolZcb6U&amp;h=AT1RfdebNNlmUThAy2WWm6AclixjQ6sGfMnjrc5C-e4EbEglPtsVHAvYqJHIPfOZfHtYPGxz__so98GKEhDQZkGKQWB2z2fBom5MdlaCvrImUyjEZ5wotHeR5-w6sF4BkAIL-PGzihR9ZVsmSasc" rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank">https://lauranenzi.github.io/</a>&gt;<br/> The successful applicant will carry out his/her PhD in the research  area of formal methods applied to the specification and monitoring of  large-scale, spatially-distributed, stochastic systems.<br/> The position in funded by the ÖAW and the FWF &lt;<a href="https://l.facebook.com/l.php?u=https%3A%2F%2Fm.fwf.ac.at%2Fen%2Fresearch-funding%2Fpersonnel-costs%2F%3Ffbclid%3DIwAR10rZDtpakXdwSo_WXE4A9GuFDbfkJoVYoCTgpZuBDmCMPVOmC8ZAo7Cyg&amp;h=AT13vFq0Svw4kLAe0VMNoonNMZyo8o6gdfK_-O0_LFJNhJavAH7Zt2YCyKMEKHuymeDiRrW6PggMAbBH0FyhcksLJJ0py3YWXi5vgwUwD0r_i3SFPvATFXhyZukxJL770ABLvhkdvgFQyiFvm5I8" rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank">https://m.fwf.ac.at/en/research-funding/personnel-costs/</a>&gt;  for the recently acquired YIRG grant: “High-dimensional statistical  learning: new methods to advance economic and sustainability policies”,  an interdisciplinary project to be led for the TU part by PhD Laura  Nenzi.<br/> TASK DESCRIPTION (leader Laura Nenzi):   <br/> Formal  methods provide precise formal specification languages that can be  easily interpreted by humans and verification algorithms that can check  in an automatic way the value of satisfaction of interesting properties.  One of the main problems of such techniques is the curse of  dimensionality. A possibility to treat the problem is to use approximate  methods such as statistical model checking. However, even these  methodologies can be unfeasible for very-large-scale stochastic systems.  A new research line consists of exploiting machine learning techniques  and Bayesian inference to identify relevant data and decrease the  computational cost, permitting the application of such powerful formal  analysis on very complex systems. An important aspect that will be  covered in the study is the spatial configuration of such systems, a key  feature in several real case studies that are considering in the  project. The methodology will be principally applied to tackle questions  related to sustainable urban mobility and thus responsible consumption.<br/> APPLICATION<br/> Please apply your application following  the instructions in the DK LogiCS admission portal. <a href="https://l.facebook.com/l.php?u=https%3A%2F%2Flogic-cs.at%2Fphd%2Fadmission%2F%3Ffbclid%3DIwAR3oZZ1EmwtB7RHLErRrlbfY-HBeprkDbr8y-WyttxBelPGVrFY46hZuy3o&amp;h=AT2erabItYmdcemt5VHuXftBV82JOmliZPV-SIiYfhedKPgLyH9PR_pf1dJ3EHa-SQgsBTWJqgjsgzUJPauzRI4h_2t1t8Ci_NW6DannlCzLkriOSguTjs3IfU4p0eBWTTEvJmljKFMYpbZ36tKn" rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank">https://logic-cs.at/phd/admission/</a> &lt;<a href="https://logic-cs.at/phd/admission/?fbclid=IwAR1rL9Zavpr2JH9oOonuC0OZ0wPUsoFxWi0usVFZPXQJzSJeSQr97rk490c" rel="noopener nofollow" target="_blank">https://logic-cs.at/phd/admission/</a>&gt;,  by indicating in the application form: Prof. Ezio Bartocci and Dr.  Laura Nenzi as supervisors. While it is not necessary to have the Master  degree at the moment of the application, it is instead mandatory to  complete it before starting the PhD.<br/> CONTACT DETAILS<br/> For  further information and inquiries about this post please contact Laura  Nenzi, e-mail: laura.nenzi@gmail.com  .</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-02T08:47:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-02T08:47:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2019-07-02T12:00:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/07/02/papafest-for-christos-70th-birthday/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/07/02/papafest-for-christos-70th-birthday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PapaFest for Christos’ 70th birthday</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">September 6-8, 2019 Columbia University http://papafest.cs.columbia.edu/ We are happy to invite you to Columbia University to celebrate Christos Papadimitriou’s contributions to science on the occasion of his 70th birthday, through a mix of talks, panels, and fun activities. One of world’s leading computer scientists, Christos is best known for his work in computational complexity, helping … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/07/02/papafest-for-christos-70th-birthday/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">PapaFest for Christos’ 70th birthday</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-07-02T08:32:49Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-02T08:32:49Z</published>
    <category term="other"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T22:21:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4229</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4229" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4229#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4229" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Sensitivity Conjecture resolved</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">The Sensitivity Conjecture, which I blogged about here, says that, for every Boolean function f:{0,1}n→{0,1}, the sensitivity of f—that is, the maximum, over all 2n input strings x∈{0,1}n, of the number of input bits such that flipping them changes the value of f—is at most polynomially smaller than a bunch of other complexity measures of […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Sensitivity Conjecture, which I blogged about <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=453">here</a>, says that, for every Boolean function f:{0,1}<sup>n</sup>→{0,1}, the <em>sensitivity</em> of f—that is, the maximum, over all 2<sup>n</sup> input strings x∈{0,1}<sup>n</sup>, of the number of input bits such that flipping them changes the value of f—is at most polynomially smaller than a bunch of other complexity measures of f, including f’s block sensitivity, degree as a real polynomial, and classical and quantum query complexities.  (For more, see for example <a href="http://www.cs.columbia.edu/~rocco/Teaching/S12/Readings/BdW.pdf">this survey</a> by Buhrman and de Wolf.  Or for quick definitions of the relevant concepts, <a href="https://cstheory.stackexchange.com/questions/19902/boolean-functions-where-sensitivity-equals-block-sensitivity">see here</a>.)</p>



<p>Ever since it was posed by Nisan and Szegedy in 1989, this conjecture has stood as one of the most frustrating and embarrassing open problems in all of combinatorics and theoretical computer science.  It seemed so easy, and so similar to other statements that had 5-line proofs.  But a lot of the best people in the field sank months into trying to prove it.  For whatever it’s worth, I also sank … well, at least weeks into it.</p>



<p>Now <a href="http://www.mathcs.emory.edu/~hhuan30/">Hao Huang</a>, a mathematician at Emory University, has posted a <a href="http://www.mathcs.emory.edu/~hhuan30/papers/sensitivity_1.pdf">6-page preprint</a> on his homepage that finally proves the Sensitivity Conjecture, in the form s(f)≥√deg(f).  (I thank Ryan O’Donnell for tipping me off to this.)  Within the preprint, the proof itself is about a page and a half.</p>



<p>Whenever there’s an announcement like this, ~99% of the time either the proof is wrong, or at any rate it’s way too complicated for outsiders to evaluate it quickly.  This is one of the remaining 1% of cases.  I’m rather confident that the proof is right.  Why?  Because I read and understood it.  It took me about half an hour.  If you’re comfortable with concepts like <em>induced subgraph</em> and <em>eigenvalue</em>, you can do the same.</p>



<p>From pioneering work by Gotsman and Linial in 1992, it was known that to prove the Sensitivity Conjecture, it suffices to prove the following even simpler combinatorial conjecture:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Let S be any subset of the n-dimensional Boolean hypercube, {0,1}<sup>n</sup>, which has size 2<sup>n-1</sup>+1.  Then there must be a point in S with at least ~n<sup>c</sup> neighbors in S.</p></blockquote>



<p>Here c&gt;0 is some constant (say 1/2), and two points in S are “neighbors” if and only they differ in a single coordinate.  Note that if S had size 2<sup>n-1</sup>, then the above statement would be false—as witnessed, for example, by the set of all n-bit strings with an even number of 1’s.</p>



<p>Huang proceeds by proving the Gotsman-Linial Conjecture.  And the way he proves Gotsman-Linial is … well, at this point maybe I should just let you <a href="http://www.mathcs.emory.edu/~hhuan30/papers/sensitivity_1.pdf">read the damn preprint</a> yourself.  I can’t say it more simply than he does.</p>



<p>If I had to try anyway, I’d say: Huang constructs a 2<sup>n</sup>×2<sup>n</sup> matrix, called A<sub>n</sub>, that has 0’s where there are no edges between the corresponding vertices of the Boolean hypercube, and either 1’s or -1’s where there <em>are</em> edges—with a simple, weird pattern of 1’s and -1’s that magically makes everything work.  He then lets H be an induced subgraph of the Boolean hypercube of size 2<sup>n-1</sup>+1.  He lower-bounds the maximum degree of H by the largest eigenvalue of the corresponding (2<sup>n-1</sup>+1)×(2<sup>n-1</sup>+1) submatrix of A<sub>n</sub>.  Finally, he lower-bounds that largest eigenvalue by … no, I don’t want to spoil it!  Read it yourself!</p>



<p>Paul Erdös famously spoke of a book, maintained by God, in which was written the simplest, most beautiful proof of each theorem.  The highest compliment Erdös could give a proof was that it “came straight from the book.”  In this case, I find it hard to imagine that even God knows how to prove the Sensitivity Conjecture in any simpler way than this.</p>



<p>Indeed, the question is: how could such an elementary 1.5-page argument have been overlooked for 30 years?  I don’t have a compelling answer to that, besides noting that “short” and “elementary” often have little to do with “obvious.”  Once you start looking at the spectral properties of this matrix A<sub>n</sub>, the pieces snap together in precisely the right way—but how would you know to look at that?</p>



<p>By coincidence, earlier today I finished reading my first PG Wodehouse novel (<em><a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/10554/10554-h/10554-h.htm">Right Ho, Jeeves!</a></em>), on the gushing recommendation of a friend.  I don’t know how I’d missed Wodehouse for 38 years.  His defining talent is his ability to tie together five or six plot threads in a way that feels perfect and inevitable even though you didn’t see it coming.  This produces a form of pleasure that’s nearly indistinguishable from the pleasure one feels in reading a “proof from the book.”  So my pleasure centers are pretty overloaded today—but in such depressing times for the world, I’ll take pleasure wherever I can get it.</p>



<p>Huge congratulations to Hao!</p>



<p><strong>Added thought:</strong> What this really is, is one of the purest illustrations I’ve seen in my career of the power and glory of the P≠NP phenomenon.  We talk all the time about how proofs are easier to verify than to find.  In practice, though, it can be far from obvious that that’s true.  Consider your typical STOC/FOCS paper: writing it probably took the authors several months, while fully understanding the thing from scratch would probably take … <em>also</em> several months!  If there’s a gap, it’s only by a factor of 4 or 5 or something.  Whereas in this case, I don’t know how long Huang spent searching for the proof, but the combined search efforts of the community add up to years or decades.  The ratio of the difficulty of finding to the difficulty of completely grasping is in the hundreds of thousands or millions.</p>



<p><strong>Another added thought:</strong> Because Hao actually proves a stronger statement than the original Sensitivity Conjecture, it has additional implications, a few of which Hao mentions in his preprint.  Here’s one he didn’t mention: any randomized algorithm to guess the parity of an n-bit string, which succeeds with probability at least 2/3 on the majority of strings, must make at least ~√n queries to the string, while any such quantum algorithm must make at least ~n<sup>1/4</sup> queries.  For more, see the paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1312.0036.pdf">Weak Parity</a> by me, Ambainis, Balodis, and Bavarian (Section 6).</p>



<p><strong>Important Update:</strong> Hao Huang himself has graciously <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4229#comment-1813116">visited the comment section</a> to satisfy readers’ curiosity by providing a detailed timeline of his work on the Sensitivity Conjecture.  (tl;dr: he was introduced to the problem by Mike Saks in 2012, and had been attacking it on and off since then, until he finally had the key insight this past month while writing a grant proposal.  Who knew that grant proposals could ever be useful for anything?!?)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-02T05:15:43Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-02T05:15:43Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-07-04T14:56:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
