<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-08-28T15:21:46Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-08-28-what-is-a-cryptographic-hash-function/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-08-28-what-is-a-cryptographic-hash-function/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What is a Cryptographic Hash Function?</title>
    <summary>If you ever tried to understand Bitcoin, you’ve probably banged your head against the wall trying to understand what is a cryptographic hash function? The goal of this post is to: Give you a very simple mental model for how hash functions work, called the random oracle model Give you...</summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T17:05:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-28T17:05:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-08-27T23:27:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/?p=276</id>
    <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2020/08/lattice-blog-reduction-part-iii-self-dual-bkz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Lattice Blog Reduction – Part III: Self-Dual BKZ</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is the third and last entry in a series of posts about lattice block reduction. See here and here for the first and second part, resp. In this post I will assume you have read the other parts. In … <a href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2020/08/lattice-blog-reduction-part-iii-self-dual-bkz/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This is the third and last entry in a series of posts about lattice block reduction. See <a class="uri" href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2020/04/lattice-blog-reduction-part-i-bkz/">here</a> and <a class="uri" href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2020/05/lattice-blog-reduction-part-ii-slide-reduction/">here</a> for the first and second part, resp. In this post I will assume you have read the other parts.</p>
<p>In the first two parts we looked at BKZ and Slide reduction, the former being the oldest and most useful in practice, while the latter achieves the best provable bounds and has the cleaner analysis. While BKZ is a natural generalization of LLL, we have seen that the analysis of LLL does not generalize well to BKZ. One can view Slide reduction as a different generalization of LLL with the goal of also naturally generalizing its analysis. As we mentioned in the first part, there is another analysis technique based on dynamical systems, introduced in [HPS11]. Unfortunately, as applied to BKZ, there are some cumbersome technicalities and the resulting bounds on the output quality are not as tight as we would like them to be (i.e. as for Slide reduction). One can view the algorithm we are considering today – SDBKZ [MW16] – as a generalization of LLL that lends itself much easier to this dynamical systems analysis: it is simpler, cleaner and yields better results. Since part of the goal of today’s post is to demonstrate this very useful analysis technique, SDBKZ is a natural candidate.</p>
<h1 id="sec:sdbkz">SDBKZ</h1>
<p>Recall the two tools we’ve been relying on in the first two algorithms, SVP and DSVP reduction of projected subblocks:</p>



<div class="wp-block-group"><div class="wp-block-group__inner-container">
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-156" src="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/svp.png"/>Effect of a call to the DSVP oracle. GSO log norms of the input in black, of the output in blue. Note that the sum of the GSO log norms is a constant, so increasing the length of the last vector, decreases the (average of the) remaining vectors.</figure></div>
</div></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-262" src="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/dsvp.png"/>Effect of a call to the DSVP oracle. GSO log norms  of the input in black, of the output in blue. Note that the sum of the GSO log norms is a constant, so increasing the length of the last vector, decreases the (average of the) remaining vectors.</figure></div>



<p>We will use both of them again today. Like BKZ, a tour of SDBKZ starts by calling the SVP oracle on successive blocks of our basis. However, when we reach the end of the basis, we will not decrease the size of the window, since this is actually quite inconvenient for the analysis. Instead, we will keep the size of the window constant but switch to DSVP reduction, i.e. at the end of the BKZ tour we DSVP reduce the last block. This will locally maximize the last GSO vector in the basis, just as the first SVP call locally minimized the first vector of the basis. Then we will move the window successively backwards, mirroring a BKZ tour, but using DSVP reduction, until we reach the beginning of the basis again. At this point, we switch back to SVP reduction and move the window forward, etc. So SDBKZ runs in forward and backward tours.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-283" src="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/sdbkz-1024x825.png"/>SDBKZ in one picture: apply the SVP oracle to the projected blocks from start to finish and when you reach the end, apply the DSVP oracle to from finish to start. Repeat.</figure>



<p>A nice observation here is that the backward tour can be viewed equivalently as: 1) compute the reversed dual basis (i.e. the dual basis with reversed columns), 2) run a forward tour, 3) compute the primal basis again. The first of these two steps is self-inverse: computing the reversed dual basis of the reversed dual basis yields the original primal basis. This means step 3) is actually the same as step 1). So in effect, one can view SDBKZ as simply repeating the following two steps: 1) run a forward tour, 2) compute the reversed dual basis. So it doesn’t matter if we use the primal or the dual basis as input, the operations of the algorithm are the same. This is why it is called <em>Self-Dual</em> BKZ.</p>
<p>There is one caveat with this algorithm: it is not clear, when one should terminate. In BKZ and Slide reduction one can formulate clear criteria, when the algorithm makes no more progress anymore. In SDBKZ this is not the case, but the analysis will show that we can bound the number of required tours ahead of time.</p>
<h4 id="the-analysis">The Analysis</h4>
<p>We will start by analyzing the effect of a forward tour. Let <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}\)</span> be our input basis. The first call to the SVP oracle in a forward tour replaces <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{b}}_1\)</span> with the shortest vector in <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}_{[1,k]}\)</span>. This means that the new basis <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}’\)</span> satifies <span class="math inline">\(\| {\mathbf{b}}_1′ \| \leq \sqrt{\gamma_k} (\prod_{i=1}^k \|{\mathbf{b}}_i^* \|)^{1/k}\)</span> by Minkowski’s bound. Equivalently, this can be written as <span class="math display">\[\log \| {\mathbf{b}}_1′ \|
  \leq \log \sqrt{\gamma_k} + \frac1k (\sum_{i=1}^k \log \|{\mathbf{b}}_i^* \|).\]</span> So if we consider the <span class="math inline">\(\log \|{\mathbf{b}}_i^*\|\)</span> as variables, it seems like linear algebra could be useful here. So far, so good. The second step is more tricky though. We know that the next basis <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}”\)</span>, i.e. after the call to the SVP oracle on <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}’_{[2,k+1]}\)</span>, satisfies <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{b}}_1” = {\mathbf{b}}_1’\)</span> and <span class="math inline">\(\| ({\mathbf{b}}_2”)^* \| \leq \sqrt{\gamma_k} (\prod_{i=2}^{k+1} \|({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \|)^{1/k}\)</span>. Unfortunately, we have no control over <span class="math inline">\(\|({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \|\)</span> for <span class="math inline">\(i \in {2,\dots,k} \)</span>, since we do not know how the SVP oracle in the first call changed these vector. However, we do know that the lattice <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}_{[1,k+1]}\)</span> did not change in that call. So we can write <span class="math display">\[\prod_{i=2}^{k+1} \|({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \| = \frac{\prod_{i=1}^{k+1} \|{\mathbf{b}}_i^* \|}{\| {\mathbf{b}}’_1 \|}\]</span> and thus we obtain <span class="math display">\[\log \| ({\mathbf{b}}_2′)^* \|
  \leq \log \sqrt{\gamma_k} + \frac1k (\sum_{i=1}^{k+1} \log \|{\mathbf{b}}_i^* \| – \log \|{\mathbf{b}}’_1 \|).\]</span> Again, this looks fairly “linear algebraicy”, so it could be useful. But there is another issue now: in order to get an inequality purely in the input basis <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}\)</span>, we would like to use our inequality for <span class="math inline">\(\log \|{\mathbf{b}}_1′ \|\)</span> in the one for <span class="math inline">\(\log \| ({\mathbf{b}}_2′)^* \|\)</span>. But the coefficient of <span class="math inline">\(\log \|{\mathbf{b}}_1′ \|\)</span> is negative, so we would need a lower bound for <span class="math inline">\(\log \|{\mathbf{b}}_1′ \|\)</span>. Furthermore, we would like to use upper bounds for our variables later, since the analysis of a tour will result in upper bounds and we would like to apply it iteratively. For this, negative coefficients are a problem. So, we need one more modification: we will use a change of variable to fix this. Instead of considering the variables <span class="math inline">\(\log \| {\mathbf{b}}_i^* \|\)</span>, we let the input variables to our forward tour be <span class="math inline">\(x_i = \sum_{j &lt; k+i} \log \|{\mathbf{b}}^*_i \|\)</span> and the output variables <span class="math inline">\(y_i = \sum_{j \leq i} \log \|({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \|\)</span> for <span class="math inline">\(i \in [1,\dots,n-k]\)</span>. Clearly, we can now write our upper bound on <span class="math inline">\(\log \|({\mathbf{b}}’_1)^*\|\)</span> as <span class="math display">\[y_1 \leq \log \sqrt{\gamma_k} + \frac{x_1}{k}.\]</span> More generally, we have <span class="math display">\[\|({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \| \leq \sqrt{\gamma_k} \left(\frac{\prod_{j=1}^{i+k-1} \|{\mathbf{b}}_j^* \|}{\prod_{j=1}^{i-1} \|({\mathbf{b}}’_j)^* \|} \right)^{\frac1k}\]</span> which means for our variables <span class="math inline">\(x_i\)</span> and <span class="math inline">\(y_i\)</span> that <span class="math display">\[y_i = y_{i-1} + \log \| ({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \|
  \leq y_{i-1} + \log \sqrt{\gamma_k} + \frac{x_i – y_{i-1}}{k}
  = (1-\frac1k) y_{i-1} + \frac1k x_i + \log \sqrt{\gamma_k}.\]</span></p>
<p>Note that we can write each <span class="math inline">\(y_i\)</span> in terms of <span class="math inline">\(x_i\)</span> and the previous <span class="math inline">\(y_i\)</span> with only positive coefficients. So now we can apply induction to write each <span class="math inline">\(y_i\)</span> only in terms of the <span class="math inline">\(x_i\)</span>’s, which shows that <span class="math display">\[y_i = \frac1k \sum_{j=1}^i \omega^{i-j} x_j + (1-\omega)^i k \alpha\]</span> where we simplified notation a little by defining <span class="math inline">\(\alpha = \log \sqrt{\gamma_k}\)</span> and <span class="math inline">\(\omega = 1-\frac1k\)</span>. By collecting the <span class="math inline">\(x_i\)</span>’s and <span class="math inline">\(y_i\)</span>’s in a vector each, we have the vectorial inequality <span class="math display">\[{\mathbf{y}} \leq {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}} + {\mathbf{b}}\]</span> where <span class="math display">\[{\mathbf{b}} = \alpha k \left[
\begin{array}{c}
1 – \omega \\ 
\vdots \\
1 – \omega^{n-k} 
\end{array}\right]
\qquad\qquad
{\mathbf{A}} = \frac1k 
\left[
\begin{array}{cccc}
  1 &amp; &amp; &amp; \\
  \omega &amp; 1 &amp; &amp; \\
   \vdots &amp; \ddots &amp; \ddots &amp; \\
   \omega^{n-k-1} &amp; \cdots &amp; \omega &amp; 1
\end{array}
\right].\]</span></p>
<p>Now recall that after a forward tour, SDBKZ computes the reversed dual basis. Given the close relationship between the primal and the dual basis and their GSO, one can show that simply reversing the vector <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{y}}\)</span> will yield the right variables <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}’_i\)</span> to start the next “forward tour” (which is actually a backward tour, but on the dual). I.e. after reversing <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{y}}\)</span>, the variables represent the logarithm of the corresponding subdeterminants of the dual basis. (For this we assume for convenience and w.l.o.g. that the lattice has determinant 1; otherwise, there would be a scaling factor involved in this transformation.)</p>
<p>In summary, the effect on the vector <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}\)</span> of executing once the two steps, 1) forward tour and 2) computing the reversed dual basis, can be described as <span class="math display">\[{\mathbf{x}}’ \leq {\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}} + {\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{b}}\]</span> where <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{R}}\)</span> is the reversed identity matrix (i.e. the identity matrix with reversed columns). Iterating the two steps simply means we will be iterating the vectorial inequality above. So analyzing the affine dynamical system <span class="math display">\[{\mathbf{x}} \mapsto {\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}} + {\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{b}}\]</span> will allow us to deduce information about the basis after a certain number of iterations.</p>
<h4 id="small-digression-affine-dynamical-systems">Small Digression: Affine Dynamical Systems</h4>
<p>Consider some dynamical system <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}} \mapsto {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}} + {\mathbf{b}} \)</span> and assume it has exactly one fixed point, i.e. <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}^*\)</span> such that <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}}^* + {\mathbf{b}} = {\mathbf{x}}^* \)</span>. We can write any input <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}’\)</span> as <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}’ = {\mathbf{x}}^* + {\mathbf{e}}\)</span> for some “error vector” <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{e}}\)</span>. When applying the system to it, we get <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}’ \mapsto {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}}’ + {\mathbf{b}} = {\mathbf{x}}^* + {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{e}}\)</span>. So the error vector <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{e}}\)</span> is mapped to <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{e}}\)</span>. Applying this <span class="math inline">\(t\)</span> times maps <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{e}}\)</span> to <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{A}}^t {\mathbf{e}}\)</span>, which means after <span class="math inline">\(t\)</span> iterations the error vector has norm <span class="math inline">\(\|{\mathbf{A}}^t {\mathbf{e}} \|_{p} \leq \|{\mathbf{A}}^t \|_{p} \| {\mathbf{e}} \|_{p} \)</span> (where <span class="math inline">\(\| \cdot \|_{p}\)</span> is the matrix norm induced by the vector <span class="math inline">\(p\)</span>-norm). If we can show that <span class="math inline">\(\|{\mathbf{A}} \|_p \leq 1 – \epsilon\)</span>, then <span class="math inline">\(\|{\mathbf{A}}^t \|_p \leq \|A \|^t \leq (1-\epsilon)^t \leq e^{-\epsilon t}\)</span>, so the error vector will decay exponentially in <span class="math inline">\(t\)</span> with base <span class="math inline">\(e^{-\epsilon}\)</span> and the algorithm converges to the fixed point <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}^*\)</span>.</p>
<p>Back to our concrete system above. As we just saw, we can analyze its output quality by computing its fixed point and its running time by computing <span class="math inline">\(\|{\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{A}} \|_p\)</span> for some induced matrix <span class="math inline">\(p\)</span>-norm. Since this has been a lenghty post already, I hope you’ll trust me that our system above has a fixed point <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}^*\)</span>, which can be written out explicitely in closed form. As a teaser, its first coordinate is <span class="math display">\[x^*_1 = \frac{(n-k)k}{k-1} \alpha.\]</span> This means that if the algorithm converges, it will converge to a basis such that <span class="math inline">\(\sum_{j \leq k}\log \| {\mathbf{b}}_j^*\| \leq \frac{(n-k)k}{k-1} \log \sqrt{\gamma_k}\)</span>. Applying Minkowski’s Theorem to the first block <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}_{[1,k]}\)</span> now shows that the shortest vector in this block satisfies <span class="math inline">\(\lambda_1({\mathbf{B}}_{[1,k]}) \leq \sqrt{\gamma_k}^{\frac{n-1}{k-1}}\)</span>. Note that the next forward tour will find a vector of such length. Recall that we assumed that our lattice has determinant 1, so this is exactly the Hermite factor achieved by Slide reduction, but for arbitrary block size (we do not need to assume that <span class="math inline">\(k\)</span> divides <span class="math inline">\(n\)</span>) and better than what we can achieve for BKZ (even using the same technique). Moreover, the fixed point actually gives us more information: the other coordinates (that I have ommited here) allow us control over all but <span class="math inline">\(k\)</span> GSO vectors and by terminating the algorithm at different positions, it allows us to choose which vectors we want control over.</p>
<p>It remains to show that the algorithm actually converges and figure out how fast. It is fairly straight-forward to show that <span class="math display">\[\|{\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{A}}\|_{\infty} = \|{\mathbf{A}}\|_{\infty} = 1 – \omega^{n-k} \approx e^{-\frac{n-k}{k}}.\]</span> (Consider the last row of <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{A}}\)</span>.) This is always smaller than 1, so the algorithm does indeed converge. For <span class="math inline">\(k = \Omega(n)\)</span> this is bounded far enough from 1 such that the system will converge to the fixed point up to an arbitrary constant in a number of SVP calls that is polynomial in <span class="math inline">\(n\)</span>. Using another change of variable [N16] or considering the relative error instead of the absolute error [MW15], one can show that this also holds for smaller <span class="math inline">\(k\)</span>.</p>
<p>As mentioned before, this type of analysis was introduced in [HPS11] and has inspired new ideas even in the heuristic analysis of BKZ. In particular, one can predict the behavior of BKZ by simply running such a dynamical system on typical inputs (and making some heuristic assumptions). This idea has been and is being used extensively in cryptanalysis and in optimizing parameters of state-of-the-art algorithms.</p>
<p>Finally, a few last words on SDBKZ: we have seen that it achieves a good Hermite factor, but what can we say about the approximation factor? I actually do not know if the algorithm achieves a good approximation factor and also do not see a good way to analyze it. However, there is a reduction [L86] from achieving approximation factor <span class="math inline">\(\alpha\)</span> to achieving Hermite factor <span class="math inline">\(\sqrt{\alpha}\)</span>. So SDBKZ can be used to achieve approximation factor <span class="math inline">\(\gamma_k^{\frac{n-1}{k-1}}\)</span>. This is a little unsatisfactory in two ways: 1) the reduction results in a different algorithm, and 2) the bound is a little worse than the factor achieved by slide reduction, which is <span class="math inline">\(\gamma_k^{\frac{n-k}{k-1}}\)</span>. On a positive note, a recent work [ALNS20] has shown that, due to the strong bound on the Hermite factor, SDBKZ can be used to generalize Slide reduction to arbitrary block size <span class="math inline">\(k\)</span> in a way to achieve the approximation factor <span class="math inline">\(\gamma_k^{\frac{n-k}{k-1}}\)</span>. Another recent work [ABFKSW20] exploited the fact that SDBKZ allows to heuristically predict large parts of the basis to achieve better bounds on the running time of the SVP oracle.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Lov<span>á</span>sz. An Algorithmic Theory of Numbers, Graphs and Convexity. 1986</p></li>
<li><p>Hanrot, Pujol, Stehlé. Analyzing blockwise lattice algorithms using dynamical systems. CRYPTO 2011</p></li>
<li><p>Micciancio, Walter. Practical, predictable lattice basis reduction – Full Version. <a class="uri" href="http://eprint.iacr.org/2015/1123">http://eprint.iacr.org/2015/1123</a></p></li>
<li><p>Micciancio, Walter. Practical, predictable lattice basis reduction. EUROCRYPT 2016</p></li>
<li><p>Neumaier. Bounding basis reduction properties. Designs, Codes and Cryptography 2016</p></li>
<li><p>Aggarwal, Li, Nguyen, Stephens-Davidowitz. Slide Reduction, Revisited—Filling the Gaps in SVP Approximation. CRYPTO 2020</p></li>
<li><p>Albrecht, Bai, Fouque, Kirchner, Stehlé, Wen. Faster Enumeration-based Lattice Reduction: Root Hermite Factor <span class="math inline">\(k^{(1/(2k))}\)</span> in Time <span class="math inline">\(k^{(k/8 + o(k))}\)</span>. CRYPTO 2020</p></li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-28T11:56:55Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-28T11:56:55Z</published>
    <category term="General"/>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Walter</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu</id>
      <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>What's New at the Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing.</subtitle>
      <title>Calvin Café: The Simons Institute Blog</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T12:21:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12259</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12259" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The k-interchange-constrained diameter of a transit network: A connectedness indicator that accounts for travel convenience</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598572800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dehouche:Nassim.html">Nassim Dehouche</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12259">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study two variants of the shortest path problem. Given an integer k, the
k-color-constrained and the k-interchange-constrained shortest path problems,
respectively seek a shortest path that uses no more than k colors and one that
makes no more than k - 1 alternations of colors. We show that the former
problem is NP-hard, when the latter is tractable. The study of these problems
is motivated by some limitations in the use of diameter-based metrics to
evaluate the topological structure of transit networks. We notably show that
indicators such as the diameter or directness of a transit network fail to
adequately account for travel convenience in measuring the connectivity of a
network and propose a new network indicator, based on solving the
k-interchange-constrained shortest path problem, that aims at alleviating these
limitations.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12237</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12237" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Spectral Planting and the Hardness of Refuting Cuts, Colorability, and Communities in Random Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598572800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bandeira:Afonso_S=.html">Afonso S. Bandeira</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Banks:Jess.html">Jess Banks</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kunisky:Dmitriy.html">Dmitriy Kunisky</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Moore:Cristopher.html">Cristopher Moore</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wein:Alexander_S=.html">Alexander S. Wein</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12237">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the problem of efficiently refuting the k-colorability of a graph,
or equivalently certifying a lower bound on its chromatic number. We give
formal evidence of average-case computational hardness for this problem in
sparse random regular graphs, showing optimality of a simple spectral
certificate. This evidence takes the form of a computationally-quiet planting:
we construct a distribution of d-regular graphs that has significantly smaller
chromatic number than a typical regular graph drawn uniformly at random, while
providing evidence that these two distributions are indistinguishable by a
large class of algorithms. We generalize our results to the more general
problem of certifying an upper bound on the maximum k-cut.
</p>
<p>This quiet planting is achieved by minimizing the effect of the planted
structure (e.g. colorings or cuts) on the graph spectrum. Specifically, the
planted structure corresponds exactly to eigenvectors of the adjacency matrix.
This avoids the pushout effect of random matrix theory, and delays the point at
which the planting becomes visible in the spectrum or local statistics. To
illustrate this further, we give similar results for a Gaussian analogue of
this problem: a quiet version of the spiked model, where we plant an eigenspace
rather than adding a generic low-rank perturbation.
</p>
<p>Our evidence for computational hardness of distinguishing two distributions
is based on three different heuristics: stability of belief propagation, the
local statistics hierarchy, and the low-degree likelihood ratio. Of independent
interest, our results include general-purpose bounds on the low-degree
likelihood ratio for multi-spiked matrix models, and an improved low-degree
analysis of the stochastic block model.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12170</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12170" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Complexity Aspects of Fundamental Questions in Polynomial Optimization</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598572800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Jeffrey.html">Jeffrey Zhang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12170">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this thesis, we settle the computational complexity of some fundamental
questions in polynomial optimization. These include the questions of (i)
finding a local minimum, (ii) testing local minimality of a point, and (iii)
deciding attainment of the optimal value. Our results characterize the
complexity of these three questions for all degrees of the defining polynomials
left open by prior literature.
</p>
<p>Regarding (i) and (ii), we show that unless P=NP, there cannot be a
polynomial-time algorithm that finds a point within Euclidean distance $c^n$
(for any constant $c$) of a local minimum of an $n$-variate quadratic program.
By contrast, we show that a local minimum of a cubic polynomial can be found
efficiently by semidefinite programming (SDP). We prove that second-order
points of cubic polynomials admit an efficient semidefinite representation,
even though their critical points are NP-hard to find. We also give an
efficiently-checkable necessary and sufficient condition for local minimality
of a point for a cubic polynomial.
</p>
<p>Regarding (iii), we prove that testing whether a quadratically constrained
quadratic program with a finite optimal value has an optimal solution is
NP-hard. We also show that testing coercivity of the objective function,
compactness of the feasible set, and the Archimedean property associated with
the description of the feasible set are all NP-hard. We also give a new
characterization of coercive polynomials that lends itself to a hierarchy of
SDPs.
</p>
<p>In our final chapter, we present an SDP relaxation for finding approximate
Nash equilibria in bimatrix games. We show that for a symmetric game, a
$1/3$-Nash equilibrium can be efficiently recovered from any rank-2 solution to
this relaxation. We also propose SDP relaxations for NP-hard problems related
to Nash equilibria, such as that of finding the highest achievable welfare
under any Nash equilibrium.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12110</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12110" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Interior-point methods for unconstrained geometric programming and scaling problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598572800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/B=uuml=rgisser:Peter.html">Peter Bürgisser</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Yinan.html">Yinan Li</a>, Harold Nieuwboer, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Walter:Michael.html">Michael Walter</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12110">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We provide a condition-based analysis of two interior-point methods for
unconstrained geometric programs, a class of convex programs that arise
naturally in applications including matrix scaling, matrix balancing, and
entropy maximization. Our condition numbers are natural geometric quantities
associated with the Newton polytope of the geometric program, and lead to
diameter bounds on approximate minimizers. We also provide effective bounds on
the condition numbers both in general and under combinatorial assumptions on
the Newton polytope. In this way, we generalize the iteration complexity of
recent interior-point methods for matrix scaling and matrix balancing.
Recently, there has been much work on algorithms for certain optimization
problems on Lie groups, known as capacity and scaling problems. For commutative
groups, these problems reduce to unconstrained geometric programs, which serves
as a particular source of motivation for our work.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12075</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12075" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the Approximability of the Traveling Salesman Problem with Line Neighborhoods</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598572800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Antoniadis:Antonios.html">Antonios Antoniadis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kisfaludi=Bak:S=aacute=ndor.html">Sándor Kisfaludi-Bak</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Laekhanukit:Bundit.html">Bundit Laekhanukit</a>, Daniel Vaz <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12075">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the variant of the Euclidean Traveling Salesman problem where
instead of a set of points, we are given a set of lines as input, and the goal
is to find the shortest tour that visits each line. The best known upper and
lower bounds for the problem in $\mathbb{R}^d$, with $d\ge 3$, are
$\mathrm{NP}$-hardness and an $O(\log^3 n)$-approximation algorithm which is
based on a reduction to the group Steiner tree problem.
</p>
<p>We show that TSP with lines in $\mathbb{R}^d$ is APX-hard for any $d\ge 3$.
More generally, this implies that TSP with $k$-dimensional flats does not admit
a PTAS for any $1\le k \leq d-2$ unless $\mathrm{P}=\mathrm{NP}$, which gives a
complete classification of the approximability of these problems, as there are
known PTASes for $k=0$ (i.e., points) and $k=d-1$ (hyperplanes). We are able to
give a stronger inapproximability factor for $d=O(\log n)$ by showing that TSP
with lines does not admit a $(2-\epsilon)$-approximation in $d$ dimensions
under the unique games conjecture. On the positive side, we leverage recent
results on restricted variants of the group Steiner tree problem in order to
give an $O(\log^2 n)$-approximation algorithm for the problem, albeit with a
running time of $n^{O(\log\log n)}$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12063</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12063" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Balanced dynamic multiple travelling salesmen: algorithms and continuous approximations</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598572800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Garn:Wolfgang.html">Wolfgang Garn</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12063">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Dynamic routing occurs when customers are not known in advance, e.g. for
real-time routing. Two heuristics are proposed that solve the balanced dynamic
multiple travelling salesmen problem (BD-mTSP). These heuristics represent
operational (tactical) tools for dynamic (online, real-time) routing. Several
types and scopes of dynamics are proposed. Particular attention is given to
sequential dynamics. The balanced dynamic closest vehicle heuristic (BD-CVH)
and the balanced dynamic assignment vehicle heuristic (BD-AVH) are applied to
this type of dynamics. The algorithms are tested for instances in the Euclidean
plane. Continuous approximation models for the BD-mTSP's are derived and serve
as strategic tools for dynamic routing. The models express route lengths using
vehicles, customers and dynamic scopes without the need of running an
algorithm. A machine learning approach was used to obtain regression models.
The mean-average-percentage error of two of these models is below 3%.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11964</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11964" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the High Accuracy Limitation of Adaptive Property Estimation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598572800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Han:Yanjun.html">Yanjun Han</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.11964">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Recent years have witnessed the success of adaptive (or unified) approaches
in estimating symmetric properties of discrete distributions, where one first
obtains a distribution estimator independent of the target property, and then
plugs the estimator into the target property as the final estimator. Several
such approaches have been proposed and proved to be adaptively optimal, i.e.
they achieve the optimal sample complexity for a large class of properties
within a low accuracy, especially for a large estimation error $\varepsilon\gg
n^{-1/3}$ where $n$ is the sample size.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we characterize the high accuracy limitation, or the penalty
for adaptation, for all such approaches. Specifically, we show that under a
mild assumption that the distribution estimator is close to the true sorted
distribution in expectation, any adaptive approach cannot achieve the optimal
sample complexity for every $1$-Lipschitz property within accuracy $\varepsilon
\ll n^{-1/3}$. In particular, this result disproves a conjecture in [Acharya et
al. 2017] that the profile maximum likelihood (PML) plug-in approach is optimal
in property estimation for all ranges of $\varepsilon$, and confirms a
conjecture in [Han and Shiragur, 2020] that their competitive analysis of the
PML is tight.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11943</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11943" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Network satisfaction for symmetric relation algebras with a flexible atom</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598572800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bodirsky:Manuel.html">Manuel Bodirsky</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kn=auml=uer:Simon.html">Simon Knäuer</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.11943">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Robin Hirsch posed in 1996 the Really Big Complexity Problem: classify the
computational complexity of the network satisfaction problem for all finite
relation algebras $\bf A$. We provide a complete classification for the case
that $\bf A$ is symmetric and has a flexible atom; the problem is in this case
NP-complete or in P. If a finite integral relation algebra has a flexible atom,
then it has a normal representation $\mathfrak{B}$. We can then study the
computational complexity of the network satisfaction problem of ${\bf A}$ using
the universal-algebraic approach, via an analysis of the polymorphisms of
$\mathfrak{B}$. We also use a Ramsey-type result of Ne\v{s}et\v{r}il and R\"odl
and a complexity dichotomy result of Bulatov for conservative finite-domain
constraint satisfaction problems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11786</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11786" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Simple Reductions from Formula-SAT to Pattern Matching on Labeled Graphs and Subtree Isomorphism</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598572800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gibney:Daniel.html">Daniel Gibney</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hoppenworth:Gary.html">Gary Hoppenworth</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Thankachan:Sharma_V=.html">Sharma V. Thankachan</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.11786">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The CNF formula satisfiability problem (CNF-SAT) has been reduced to many
fundamental problems in P to prove tight lower bounds under the Strong
Exponential Time Hypothesis (SETH). Recently, the works of Abboud, Hansen,
Vassilevska W. and Williams (STOC 16), and later, Abboud and Bringmann (ICALP
18) have proposed basing lower bounds on the hardness of general boolean
formula satisfiability (Formula-SAT). Reductions from Formula-SAT have two
advantages over the usual reductions from CNF-SAT: (1) conjectures on the
hardness of Formula-SAT are arguably much more plausible than those of CNF-SAT,
and (2) these reductions give consequences even for logarithmic improvements in
a problems upper bounds.
</p>
<p>Here we give tight reductions from Formula-SAT to two more problems: pattern
matching on labeled graphs (PMLG) and subtree isomorphism. Previous reductions
from Formula-SAT were to sequence alignment problems such as Edit Distance,
LCS, and Frechet Distance and required some technical work. This paper uses
ideas similar to those used previously, but in a decidedly simpler setting,
helping to illustrate the most salient features of the underlying techniques.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.09870</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.09870" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>FastORB-SLAM: a Fast ORB-SLAM Method with Coarse-to-Fine Descriptor Independent Keypoint Matching</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598572800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fu:Qiang.html">Qiang Fu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yu:Hongshan.html">Hongshan Yu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wang:Xiaolong.html">Xiaolong Wang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yang:Zhengeng.html">Zhengeng Yang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Hong.html">Hong Zhang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mian:Ajmal.html">Ajmal Mian</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.09870">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Indirect methods for visual SLAM are gaining popularity due to their
robustness to varying environments. ORB-SLAM2 is a benchmark method in this
domain, however, the computation of descriptors in ORB-SLAM2 is time-consuming
and the descriptors cannot be reused unless a frame is selected as a keyframe.
To overcome these problems, we present FastORB-SLAM which is light-weight and
efficient as it tracks keypoints between adjacent frames without computing
descriptors. To achieve this, a two-stage coarse-to-fine descriptor independent
keypoint matching method is proposed based on sparse optical flow. In the first
stage, we first predict initial keypoint correspondences via a uniform
acceleration motion model and then robustly establish the correspondences via a
pyramid-based sparse optical flow tracking method. In the second stage, we
leverage motion smoothness and the epipolar constraint to refine the
correspondences. In particular, our method computes descriptors only for
keyframes. We test FastORB-SLAM with an RGBD camera on \textit{TUM} and
\textit{ICL-NUIM} datasets and compare its accuracy and efficiency to nine
existing RGBD SLAM methods. Qualitative and quantitative results show that our
method achieves state-of-the-art performance in accuracy and is about twice as
fast as the ORB-SLAM2
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T01:27:27Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11454</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11454" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Vertex Ordering Algorithms for Graph Coloring Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598486400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Arda Asik, Ibrahim Bugra Demir, Berker Demirel, Baris Batuhan Topal, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kaya:Kamer.html">Kamer Kaya</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.11454">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Graph coloring is a fundamental problem in combinatorics with many
applications in practice. In this problem, the vertices in a given graph must
be colored by using the least number of colors in such a way that a vertex has
a different color than its neighbors. The problem, as well as its different
variants, has been proven to be NP-Hard. Therefore, there are greedy algorithms
in the literature aiming to use a small number of colors. These algorithms
traverse the vertices and color them one by one. The vertex visit order has a
significant impact on the number of colors used. In this work, we investigated
if social network analytics metrics can be used to find this order. Our
experiments showed that when closeness centrality is used to find vertex visit
order, a smaller number of colors is used by the greedy algorithms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-27T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11388</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11388" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A cost-scaling algorithm for computing the degree of determinants</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598486400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hirai:Hiroshi.html">Hiroshi Hirai</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Ikeda:Motoki.html">Motoki Ikeda</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.11388">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we address computation of the degree $\mathop{\rm deg Det} A$
of Dieudonn\'e determinant $\mathop{\rm Det} A$ of \[ A = \sum_{k=1}^m A_k x_k
t^{c_k}, \] where $A_k$ are $n \times n$ matrices over a field $\mathbb{K}$,
$x_k$ are noncommutative variables, $t$ is a variable commuting $x_k$, $c_k$
are integers, and the degree is considered for $t$. This problem generalizes
noncommutative Edmonds' problem and fundamental combinatorial optimization
problems including the weighted linear matroid intersection problem. It was
shown that $\mathop{\rm deg Det} A$ is obtained by a discrete convex
optimization on a Euclidean building. We extend this framework by incorporating
a cost scaling technique, and show that $\mathop{\rm deg Det} A$ can be
computed in time polynomial of $n,m,\log_2 C$, where $C:= \max_k |c_k|$. We
apply this result to an algebraic combinatorial optimization problem arising
from a symbolic matrix having $2 \times 2$-submatrix structure.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-27T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11321</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11321" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>High-Performance Parallel Graph Coloring with Strong Guarantees on Work, Depth, and Quality</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598486400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Besta:Maciej.html">Maciej Besta</a>, Armon Carigiet, Zur Vonarburg-Shmaria, Kacper Janda, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gianinazzi:Lukas.html">Lukas Gianinazzi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hoefler:Torsten.html">Torsten Hoefler</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.11321">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We develop the first parallel graph coloring heuristics with strong
theoretical guarantees on work and depth and coloring quality. The key idea is
to design a relaxation of the vertex degeneracy order, a well-known graph
theory concept, and to color vertices in the order dictated by this relaxation.
This introduces a tunable amount of parallelism into the degeneracy ordering
that is otherwise hard to parallelize. This simple idea enables significant
benefits in several key aspects of graph coloring. For example, one of our
algorithms ensures polylogarithmic depth and a bound on the number of used
colors that is superior to all other parallelizable schemes, while maintaining
work-efficiency. In addition to provable guarantees, the developed algorithms
have competitive run-times for several real-world graphs, while almost always
providing superior coloring quality. Our degeneracy ordering relaxation is of
separate interest for algorithms outside the context of coloring.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-27T23:20:22Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-27T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11315</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11315" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Inapproximability of Diameter in super-linear time: Beyond the 5/3 ratio</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598486400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bonnet:=Eacute=douard.html">Édouard Bonnet</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.11315">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We show, assuming the Strong Exponential Time Hypothesis, that for every
$\varepsilon &gt; 0$, approximating directed Diameter on $m$-arc graphs within
ratio $7/4 - \varepsilon$ requires $m^{4/3 - o(1)}$ time. Our construction uses
nonnegative edge weights but even holds for sparse digraphs, i.e., for which
the number of vertices $n$ and the number of arcs $m$ satisfy $m = n
\log^{O(1)} n$. This is the first result that conditionally rules out a
near-linear time $5/3$-approximation for Diameter.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-27T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11292</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11292" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Flip Paths Between Lattice Triangulations</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598486400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>William Sims, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sitharam:Meera.html">Meera Sitharam</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.11292">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The problem of finding a diagonal flip path between two triangulations has
been studied for nearly a century in the combinatorial (topological) setting
and for decades in the geometric setting. In the geometric setting, finding a
diagonal flip path between two triangulations that minimizes the number of
diagonal flips over all such paths is NP-complete. However, when restricted to
lattice triangulations - i.e. triangulations of a finite subset of the integer
lattice, or an affine transformation of this lattice, bounded by a simple,
closed polygon with lattice points as vertices - the problem has a polynomial
time algorithm. Lattice triangulations have been studied for their uses in
discriminant theory, Hilbert's 16th problem, toric varieties, quantum spin
systems, and material science. Our first main result shows that there is a
polynomial-time computable, unique partially-ordered set of diagonal flips such
that there is a bijection between valid linear-orderings of this set and
minimum diagonal flip paths between two lattice triangulations. This provides
an alternative proof of the previously known result, as well as new structural
insights into these diagonal flip paths. Our second main result characterizes
pairs of triangulations, containing sets of edges $E$ and $E'$ respectively,
such that the minimum diagonal flip path between them contains the minimum
number of diagonal flips over all minimum diagonal flip paths between pairs of
triangulations, containing sets of edges $E$ and $E'$ respectively. Remarkably,
all of our results are derived from a simple relationship between edges in
triangulations and Farey sequences.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-27T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11235</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.11235" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Accelerating Force-Directed Graph Drawing with RT Cores</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598486400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zellmann:Stefan.html">Stefan Zellmann</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Weier:Martin.html">Martin Weier</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wald:Ingo.html">Ingo Wald</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.11235">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Graph drawing with spring embedders employs a V x V computation phase over
the graph's vertex set to compute repulsive forces. Here, the efficacy of
forces diminishes with distance: a vertex can effectively only influence other
vertices in a certain radius around its position. Therefore, the algorithm
lends itself to an implementation using search data structures to reduce the
runtime complexity. NVIDIA RT cores implement hierarchical tree traversal in
hardware. We show how to map the problem of finding graph layouts with
force-directed methods to a ray tracing problem that can subsequently be
implemented with dedicated ray tracing hardware. With that, we observe speedups
of 4x to 13x over a CUDA software implementation.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-27T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/26/postdoc-at-uc-berkeley-apply-by-september-10-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/26/postdoc-at-uc-berkeley-apply-by-september-10-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at UC Berkeley (apply by September 10, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Please send a cover letter, CV, and research statement to the email below. In CV please list at least 3 references. In cover letter please identify faculty of interest. Also, have references submit letters to the e-mail below, with your name in the subject line. Multiple opportunities available; earliest deadline requires nomination by September 10th. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Please send a cover letter, CV, and research statement to the email below. In CV please list at least 3 references. In cover letter please identify faculty of interest. Also, have references submit letters to the e-mail below, with your name in the subject line. Multiple opportunities available; earliest deadline requires nomination by<br/>
September 10th.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://theory.cs.berkeley.edu/postdoc.html">http://theory.cs.berkeley.edu/postdoc.html</a><br/>
Email: tcs-postdoc-inquiries@lists.eecs.berkeley.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-26T04:54:53Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-26T04:54:53Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=790</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2020/08/25/my-monitor-setup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>My monitor setup</title>
    <summary>In the not-distant future there will be a single monitor that gets you the best of both worlds. For the contemporaneous, I maintain that the above is the best monitor setup available to us in 2020. I use the tiny E-ink monitor as much as possible, including now, for my blitz matches on chess.com, and […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-792" src="https://emanueleviola.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/webcam-toy-photo7.jpg?w=800"/></figure>

<p>In the not-distant future there will be a single monitor that gets you the best of both worlds. For the contemporaneous, I maintain that the above is the best monitor setup available to us in 2020. I use the tiny E-ink monitor as much as possible, including now, for my blitz matches on chess.com, and of course for writing and sometimes reviewing papers. But as I mentioned earlier unfortunately for certain bureaucratic tasks that not all of us can skip altogether you just need a bigger monitor with color. So I push a button on the hdmi switch, and the image blasts open on the 30-inch screen, <em>m’illumino d’immenso</em>, and suddenly the mouse feels like the interface from <em>Minority Reports</em>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-25T19:35:48Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-25T19:35:48Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="health"/>
    <category term="tech"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:21:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://differentialprivacy.org/colt2020/</id>
    <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/colt2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Conference Digest - COLT 2020</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/">COLT 2020</a> was held online in July, and featured nine papers on differential privacy, as well as a keynote talk by Salil Vadhan.
While differential privacy has always had a home in the COLT community, it seems like this year was truly exceptional in terms of the number of results.
We link all the content below, including pointers to the papers, videos on Youtube, and the page on the conference website. 
Please let us know if we missed any papers on differential privacy, either in the comments below or by email.</p>

<h2 id="keynote">Keynote</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/speaker_1.html">The Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4bpFDpT1t7I">video</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://salil.seas.harvard.edu/">Salil Vadhan</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="papers">Papers</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.08743">Domain Compression and its Application to Randomness-Optimal Distributed Goodness-of-Fit</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dgGdARyU6oY">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_96.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://people.ece.cornell.edu/acharya/">Jayadev Acharya</a>, <a href="http://www.cs.columbia.edu/~ccanonne/">Clément L. Canonne</a>, <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~yjhan/">Yanjun Han</a>, <a href="http://www.zitengsun.com/">Ziteng Sun</a>, <a href="https://ece.iisc.ac.in/~htyagi/">Himanshu Tyagi</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04509">Closure Properties for Private Classification and Online Prediction</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U9hqJH6sEyY">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_320.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://web.math.princeton.edu/~nalon/">Noga Alon</a>, <a href="https://www.cs.bgu.ac.il/~beimel/">Amos Beimel</a>, <a href="http://www.cs.technion.ac.il/~shaymrn/">Shay Moran</a>, <a href="https://www.uri.co.il/">Uri Stemmer</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01452">Pan-Private Uniformity Testing</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yMXAjEGDXdI">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_141.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="http://amin.kareemx.com/">Kareem Amin</a>, <a href="https://www.majos.net/">Matthew Joseph</a>, <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/jieming-mao">Jieming Mao</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.01100">Efficient, Noise-Tolerant, and Private Learning via Boosting</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xCh7oZKcINs">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_304.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://cs-people.bu.edu/mbun/">Mark Bun</a>, <a href="https://marco.ntime.org/">Marco L. Carmosino</a>, <a href="http://cseweb.ucsd.edu/~jlsorrel/">Jessica Sorrell</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.10541">PAC Learning with Stable and Private Predictions</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jZlgmBUQ4nU">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_37.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://yuvaldagan.wordpress.com/">Yuval Dagan</a>, <a href="http://vtaly.net/">Vitaly Feldman</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09465">Locally Private Hypothesis Selection</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MGeBYQ7lJYw">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_5.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/sigopi/">Sivakanth Gopi</a>, <a href="http://www.gautamkamath.com/">Gautam Kamath</a>, <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/jakul/">Janardhan D. Kulkarni</a>, <a href="http://www.cs.toronto.edu/~anikolov/">Aleksandar Nikolov</a>, <a href="https://zstevenwu.com/">Zhiwei Steven Wu</a>, <a href="https://huanyuzhang.github.io/">Huanyu Zhang</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09464">Private Mean Estimation of Heavy-Tailed Distributions</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6NVuAZqxrSE">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_6.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="http://www.gautamkamath.com/">Gautam Kamath</a>, <a href="http://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/vikrantsinghal/">Vikrant Singhal</a>, <a href="https://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/jullman/">Jonathan Ullman</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.10137">Privately Learning Thresholds: Closing the Exponential Gap</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uGTfJsJAkh0">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_219.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="http://www.cs.tau.ac.il/~haimk/">Haim Kaplan</a>, <a href="https://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~katrina/">Katrina Ligett</a>, <a href="https://www.tau.ac.il/~mansour/">Yishay Mansour</a>, <a href="http://www.wisdom.weizmann.ac.il/~naor/">Moni Naor</a>, <a href="https://www.uri.co.il/">Uri Stemmer</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.09122">Reasoning About Generalization via Conditional Mutual Information</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c5fzeqiTwWk">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_98.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="http://www.thomas-steinke.net/">Thomas Steinke</a>, <a href="http://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/lydiazak/">Lydia Zakynthinou</a></p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-25T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-25T14:00:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam Kamath</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://differentialprivacy.org</id>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Website for the differential privacy research community</subtitle>
      <title>Differential Privacy</title>
      <updated>2020-08-27T23:27:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/25/assistant-professor-tenure-track-and-professor-positions-in-computer-science-at-institute-of-science-and-technology-austria-apply-by-october-30-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/25/assistant-professor-tenure-track-and-professor-positions-in-computer-science-at-institute-of-science-and-technology-austria-apply-by-october-30-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor (tenure-track) and Professor positions in Computer Science at Institute of Science and Technology Austria (apply by October 30, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Institute of Science and Technology Austria (IST Austria) invites applications for several open positions in all areas of computer science. IST Austria values diversity and is committed to equal opportunity. We strive for increasing the number of women, particularly in fields where they are underrepresented, and therefore we strongly encourage female researchers to apply. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Institute of Science and Technology Austria (IST Austria) invites applications for several open positions in all areas of computer science.</p>
<p>IST Austria values diversity and is committed to equal opportunity. We strive for increasing the number of women, particularly in fields where they are underrepresented, and therefore we strongly encourage female researchers to apply.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://ist.ac.at/en/jobs/faculty/">https://ist.ac.at/en/jobs/faculty/</a><br/>
Email: faculty.recruiting@ist.ac.at</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-25T13:23:45Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-25T13:23:45Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7790</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/08/24/highlights-of-algorithms-halg-free-aug-31-sep-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Highlights of Algorithms (HALG) -free – Aug 31- Sep 2</title>
    <summary>[Guest post by Yossi Azar] The 5th Highlights of Algorithms conference (HALG 2020) will take place Aug 31- Sep 2, 2020. http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/ The Highlights of Algorithms conference is a forum for presenting the highlights of recent developments in algorithms and for discussing potential further advances in this area. The conference will provide a broad picture […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>[Guest post by Yossi Azar]</em></p>



<p>The 5th <strong>Highlights of Algorithms conference (HALG 2020)</strong> will take place Aug 31- Sep 2, 2020. <a href="http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/</a></p>



<p>The Highlights of Algorithms conference is a forum for presenting the highlights of recent developments in algorithms and for discussing potential further advances in this area. The conference will provide a broad picture of the latest research in algorithms through a series of invited talks, as well as short talks. <br/>Invited talks includes top algorithmic surveys and papers from FOCS/STOC/SODA/COLT/PODC/SPAA/ITCS/PODS (2019-20)</p>



<p><br/>PROGRAM<br/>The conference will take place online on Mon, Aug 31-Wed, Sep 2 from 12:00 noon until 19:30 CEST (Europe time) <a href="http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/programme" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/programme</a></p>



<p>The short contributed talk are on Sep 1-2, 9:45-11:30 CEST <a href="http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/shorttalks" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/shorttalks</a></p>



<p>REGISTRATION<br/>Registration is free but mandatory<br/>Please register on our webpage: <a href="https://highlightsofalgorithms2020.ethz.ch/registration" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://highlightsofalgorithms2020.ethz.ch/registration</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-24T19:17:23Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-24T19:17:23Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:50Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2020/08/24/ideal-special-quarter-theory-of-deep-learning/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2020/08/24/ideal-special-quarter-theory-of-deep-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>IDEAL Special Quarter (Theory of Deep Learning)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">September 21 – December 12, 2020 Online (https://www.ideal.northwestern.edu/special-quarters/fall-2020/) https://www.ideal.northwestern.edu/special-quarters/fall-2020/registration There will be a Special Quarter on Theory of Deep Learning this Fall as a part of IDEAL – The Institute for Data, Econometrics, Algorithms, and Learning, runs jointly with TTIC and the University of Chicago. The Special Quarter will be entirely online, and take place … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2020/08/24/ideal-special-quarter-theory-of-deep-learning/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">IDEAL Special Quarter (Theory of Deep Learning)</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-24T16:02:27Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-24T16:02:27Z</published>
    <category term="other"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:21:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-1663724076500583508</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/1663724076500583508/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/08/sharp-p-and-issue-of-natural-problems.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1663724076500583508" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1663724076500583508" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/08/sharp-p-and-issue-of-natural-problems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Sharp P and the issue of `natural problems'</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> #P was defined by Valiant as a way to pin down that the PERMANENT of a matrix is hard to compute.</p><p>The definition I give is equivalent to the one Valiant gave.</p><p>g is in #P if there exists p a poly and B in P such that</p><p>g(x) = | { y : |y| = p(|x|) and (x,y) \in B } |</p><p>A function f is #P-complete if g is in #P and for all g in #P,  f is poly-Turing reducible to g.</p><p>#SAT is the function that, given a formula, returns the number of satisfying assignments. It is #P-complete by looking at the proof the Cook-Levin Theorem. The reduction of f to #SAT only makes one query to #SAT. A common way to show that #A is #P-complete is to show that SAT \le A with a reduction that preserves the number of solutions. </p><p>Valiant proved that PERM was #P-complete (his reduction only used 1 call to PERM).</p><p>There are problems in P whose #-version is #-P complete: Matching and DNF-SAT are two of them.</p><p>Notice that I defined #SAT directly, not in terms of a poly p and a set B as above. Here is why: if you use poly p and set B one can do obnoxious things like: </p><p>SAT = { phi : exists yz 2n-bits long such that phi(y)=T and z is prime }</p><p>The # version of this definition is not really what I want (though I am sure its #P-complete).</p><p>Valiant (see <a href="https://www.math.cmu.edu/~af1p/Teaching/MCC17/Papers/enumerate.pdf">here</a> and <a href="http://www.math.cmu.edu/~af1p/Teaching/MCC17/Papers/permanent.pdf">here</a>) and Simon (see <a href="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2F3-540-08342-1_37.pdf">here</a>) showed that  for many known NPC-problems A, #A is #P-complete. They meant NATURAL problems. Is it true for all natural NP-complete problems?</p><p>Unfortunately the statement `All NATURAL NPC problems give rise to #P-complete functions' is hard (impossible?) to state rigorously and hence hard (impossible?) to prove. </p><p>1) Is there a natural A in NP such that #A is NOT #P-complete (under assumptions)?</p><p>2) Are there any theorems that show a large set of NPC problems have #P counterparts? Or are we doomed to, when we want to show some #A is #P-complete, come up with a new proof?</p><p>3) Can one PROVE there are NPC problems A such that #A is NOT #P-complete? (under assumptions).</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-24T01:40:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-24T01:40:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T07:36:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/08/22/bricards-jumping-octahedron</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/08/22/bricards-jumping-octahedron.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Bricard’s jumping octahedron</title>
    <summary>The Schönhardt polyhedron is a non-convex octahedron that can be formed from a convex regular octahedron by twisting two opposite faces, stretching and deforming the other faces as you twist. It’s well known for not having any interior diagonals, and for being impossible to subdivide into tetrahedra without introducing new vertices. But long before Erich Schönhardt described it in 1928 in connection with these properties, Raoul Bricard was investigating flexible octahedra, in connection with Cauchy’s theorem on the rigidity of polyhedra. The Schönhardt polyhedron forms an interesting example of flexibility, as I learned from a 1975 collection of lecture notes by Branko Grünbaum on “Lost Mathematics”). I’m not entirely sure that it was known to Bricard (it’s not clear from Bricard’s paper and Grünbaum doesn’t really say so) but it wouldn’t surprise me if it was.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sch%C3%B6nhardt_polyhedron">Schönhardt polyhedron</a> is a non-convex octahedron that can be formed from a convex regular octahedron by twisting two opposite faces, stretching and deforming the other faces as you twist. It’s well known for not having any interior diagonals, and for being impossible to subdivide into tetrahedra without introducing new vertices. But long before Erich Schönhardt described it in 1928 in connection with these properties, Raoul Bricard was investigating <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bricard_octahedron">flexible octahedra</a>, in connection with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cauchy%27s_theorem_(geometry)">Cauchy’s theorem on the rigidity of polyhedra</a>. The Schönhardt polyhedron forms an interesting example of flexibility, as I learned from a 1975 collection of lecture notes by Branko Grünbaum on “<a href="https://digital.lib.washington.edu/researchworks/bitstream/handle/1773/15700/Lost%20Mathematics.pdf?fterence=1">Lost Mathematics</a>”). I’m not entirely sure that it was known to Bricard (it’s not clear from Bricard’s paper and Grünbaum doesn’t really say so) but it wouldn’t surprise me if it was.</p>

<p>Cauchy’s theorem states that the shape of every convex polyhedron is uniquely determined by the shapes and connectivity of its faces. There can be no other convex polyhedron that has faces of the same shape, connected in the same way. But in some cases (like the regular icosahedron) you can dent some of the faces in to make a different, non-convex polyhedron with the same face shapes and connectivity. So Cauchy’s theorem doesn’t immediately extend to non-convex polyhedra. In fact, certain non-convex “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flexible_polyhedron">flexible polyhedra</a>” can deform continuously into an infinite range of shapes, without changing the shape or connectivity of their faces. Bricard’s octahedra are self-crossing examples and later investigators found examples without self-crossings.</p>

<p>But Grünbaum describes a different, non-self-crossing non-convex octahedron, the “jumping octahedron”. Rather than having a continuous range of rigid shapes, it has exactly two shapes, both of which have faces of the same shapes and connectivity. Unlike the example of the regular icosahedron and dented icosahedron, the two shapes have dihedral angles that are convex and concave in the same places. If you make this polyhedron out of perfectly rigid faces, with hinged connections at their edges, it could only be in one or the other of its two shapes: you wouldn’t be able to get it to the other shape without taking it apart and rebuilding it. But if you make it out of a material that’s stiff enough to hold its shape but flexible enough to deform a little, you can make a model that jumps or snaps from one shape to the other when you twist it. If you deform it a little out of shape, it will snap back to the nearest of its two valid shapes. Here’s one I made very roughly from some light cardstock and transparent tape, in its two shapes, one with only slightly-concave long diagonals down its sides and the other much more twisted and folded up:</p>

<div><table style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
<tbody><tr style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">
<td style="padding: 10px;"><img alt="Jumping octahedron" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/jumping-octahedron/1-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="315"/></td>
<td style="padding: 10px;"><img alt="Jumping octahedron" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/jumping-octahedron/2-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="315"/></td>
</tr></tbody></table></div>

<p>My model makes an interesting squelchy sound when I twist it from the more upright shape to the more twisted one, because these two shapes have different volumes and the air has to get out through the cracks between the faces. If I had perfectly sealed all these cracks, the pressure change would prevent it from changing shape. This change in volume is a big contrast from the Bricard octahedra and other continuously-flexible polyhedra, which must maintain constant volume as they flex.</p>

<p>The net I folded it from looks like this:</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Net for jumping octahedron" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/jumping-octahedron-net.svg"/></p>

<p>It’s in two parts in order to make the seams of my model be symmetric, but also that way it fits better onto a single sheet of paper or card. It consists of two equilateral-triangle faces (the faces at the top and bottom of the model shown above) and six identical obtuse triangles on the sides. In my net and model, these triangles are isosceles, but that’s not important. The important part is that, if one of these triangles is projected onto the line between it and the equilateral triangle, its projected length is slightly more than the length of the connecting edge (because it’s an obtuse triangle) but not too long: longer by a factor strictly between one and</p>

\[\frac{1}{2}+\frac{1}{\sqrt{3}}\approx 1.07735.\]

<p>If you make the projection too short (with a right or acute side triangle shape) then it will not have two different shapes that maintain the same faces and convex-concave relation at each dihedral. If you make the projection too long, then you won’t be able to put it together at all while keeping all the faces flat. An explanation for some of this behavior can be seen from the diagram below, which shows the bottom equilateral triangle and one of the obtuse side triangles of the polyhedron, flattened out into a single plane, from a top view.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Overhead view of two faces of the jumping octahedron" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/jumping-octahedron-overhead.svg"/></p>

<p>If you fold these two triangles on their connecting edge, keeping the bottom equilateral triangle fixed but lifting the obtuse triangle into space, then the outer vertex of the obtuse triangle will rotate through a semicircle, but the plane of this semicircle is perpendicular to the plane of view of the diagram, so in top view it just looks like a line, the red line in the diagram. The edge along which the two triangles are attached is the axis of rotation, so it’s perpendicular to the semicircle of rotation and to the projected red line. If you fold all three edges of the bottom equilateral triangle at equal angles, then by symmetry the tips of the three folded obtuse triangles will form another equilateral triangle, and the size of this equilateral triangle will depend on the fold angle. If the vertices of this second equilateral triangle project to points on the yellow circle (the circumcircle of the bottom equilateral triangle) then this triangle will have exactly the correct size to attach the top face. This is only possible when the vertex of the obtuse triangle in the drawing is folded to a point that projects to of the two crossings of the red line and the yellow circle. The two fold angles for which this happens give the two shapes of the jumping octahedron.</p>

<p>The constraint that the side triangles be obtuse is what is needed to make the two crossing points of the red line and the circle be in the same arc of the circle relative to the vertices of the bottom equilateral triangle. The constraint that their projected length should be only a little bit longer than the side length of the equilateral triangle is what is needed to make the red line cross the circle at all. So these two constraints are necessary to make the jumping octahedron work. There’s one more necessary constraint: the height of the obtuse triangle above the edge connecting it to the equilateral triangle has to be large enough to reach both of the crossing points of the red line. When I started to make the model I was worried about a different geometric constraint: maybe the twisted state of the model is so twisted that its inner folded parts cross each other near the center of the model? But that can’t happen. If it did happen, the projected view of the model would have the side triangles folded into a position where they cover the center of the yellow circle. But that would mean that the top triangle’s vertices are too far around the yellow circle, past the point where the farthest point of the red line can cross.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104737012685827990">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-22T17:46:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-22T17:46:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-08-23T07:53:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=20013</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/08/22/quantum-matters/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum Matters</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A comparison between the Google estimator U for the fidelity and two improved estimators that we studied  MLE (maximum likelihood estimator) and V (a variant of U). (More figures at the end of the post.) Here are some links on … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/08/22/quantum-matters/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/fig_2.jpeg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-20101" height="472" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/fig_2.jpeg?w=640&amp;h=472" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">A comparison between the Google estimator U for the fidelity and two improved estimators that we studied  MLE (maximum likelihood estimator) and V (a variant of U). (More figures at the end of the post.)</span></p>
<p>Here are some links on quantum matters. I hope to return to them in more detail in some future posts.</p>
<h2>1. A <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/11/stat-quantum2.pdf">paper</a> with Yosi Rinott and Tomer Shoham on the Statistics of Google’s experiment</h2>
<p>Yosef Rinott, Tomer Shoham and Gil Kalai:  <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/11/stat-quantum2.pdf">Statistical aspects of the quantum supremacy demonstration</a>, (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.05177">arXive</a>)</p>
<p><strong>Abstract:</strong></p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>The notable claim of quantum supremacy presented by Google’s team in 2019 consists of demonstrating the ability of a quantum circuit to generate, albeit with considerable noise, bitstrings from a distribution that is considered hard to simulate on classical computers. Verifying that the generated data is indeed from the claimed distribution and assessing the circuit’s noise level and its fidelity is a purely statistical undertaking.</em></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>The objective of this paper is to explain the relations between quantum computing and some of the statistical aspects involved in demonstrating quantum supremacy in terms that are accessible to statisticians, computer scientists, and mathematicians.</em></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>Starting with the statistical analysis in Google’s demonstration, which we explain, we study various estimators of the fidelity, and different approaches to testing the distributions generated by the quantum computer. We propose different noise models, and discuss their implications. A preliminary study of the Google data, focusing mostly on circuits of 12 and 14 qubits is discussed throughout the paper.</em></span></p></blockquote>
<p>I am greatly enjoying working with Yosi and Tomer, and I hope to devote a special post to the very interesting statistics of the Google supremacy experiment.</p>
<h2/>
<h2>2. My paper <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/laws-blog2.pdf">The Argument against Quantum Computers, the Quantum Laws of Nature, and Google’s Supremacy Claims</a></h2>
<p>Here is how the paper concludes</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>Over the past four decades, the very idea of quantum computation has led to many advances in several areas of physics, engineering, computer science, and mathematics. I expect that the most important application will eventually be the understanding of the impossibility of quantum error-correction and quantum computation. Overall, the debate over quantum computing is a fascinating one, and I can see a clear silver lining: major advances in human ability to simulate quantum physics and quantum chemistry are expected to emerge if quantum computational supremacy can be demonstrated and quantum computers can be built, but also if quantum computational supremacy cannot be demonstrated and quantum computers cannot be built.</em></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>Some of the insights and methods characteristic of the area of quantum computation might be useful for classical computation of realistic quantum systems – which is, apparently, what nature does.</em></span></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p>The link above is the most recent version that will be updated; Here is the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.05188">arXive version</a>. A discussion on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=23291071">Hacker News</a>.</p>
<h2/>
<h2>3. My Dec 2019 surprise lecture and the panel discussion</h2>
<p>My Dec  19 2019 (B.C.) surprise lecture at the mathematics of quantum computing school and the afternoon panel on the same day. It turned out that the lecture was videotaped. The slides can be seen in <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/27/the-google-quantum-supremacy-demo/">this post</a>. Remarkably, social distancing was pioneered by the session chair toward the end of the lecture (while not justified in that case).</p>
<p/>
<p>Here once again again is <a href="https://youtu.be/_Yb7uIGBynU">the link for the panel discussion on quantum supremacy</a> of the same day (<a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/27/the-google-quantum-supremacy-demo/">reviewed here</a>) . Here is a quote of mine from the panel.</p>
<blockquote><p><em><span style="color: #0000ff;">Of course, it is important to think what are the implications of quantum supremacy, is it useful? what does it say on the extended Church-Turing thesis? on prospects for quantum error-correction and universal quantum computers? etc. but I think that in the next few years one thing that we need to also concentrate on is the following question: Is the Google experiment correct? Is this a correct scientific verification of quantum supremacy?</span></em></p></blockquote>
<h2/>
<h2>4. My July 15 USTLC lecture</h2>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/4slides.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-20091" height="364" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/4slides.png?w=640&amp;h=364" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Four slides from my USTLC zoom lecture</span><span style="color: #ff0000;">. (Click to enlarge.)<br/>
</span></p>
<p>Here is the <a href="https://idc-il.zoom.us/rec/share/4v58MpbZ-CBJG7OO1E3SYYN-P426aaa82ndLr_cMyEgOuIwdOStnnIw18Xsg0dUr?fbclid=IwAR31ShatGHJ1bWpVCdBPUoWhG3VjqmhfD1kQBFVLGzmvtNlWNMW-T58_0dw">videotaped Zoom presentation</a> and <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/11/july1.pptx">here are the slides</a>.</p>
<h2/>
<h2>5. A small taste of quantum poetry for the skeptics. (A full post is coming.)</h2>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/dslide16.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-19013" height="362" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/dslide16.png?w=640&amp;h=362" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Poems by Peter Shor and Renan Gross (click to enlarge)</span></p>
<p>Peter Shor <a href="https://twitter.com/PeterShor1/status/1199299777743204354">pioneered</a> quantum poetry for the skeptics over Twitter. There were many very nice contributions all over social media by <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/dslide16.png">Renan Gross</a>, John Dowling, Nidit Nanda, ⟨dl|yonge|mallo⟩, Alfred Marcel Bruckstein, Kenneth Regan, and others. <strong>Keep the quantum poems coming!</strong> Of course, the poems should be taken with humor. Here is a small taste.</p>
<h3><span style="color: #993366;">My short response to Peter’s poem</span></h3>
<blockquote>
<h3><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>Understanding nature and ourselves is a worthy dream</em></span><br/>
<span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>Requiring no interaction with the supreme</em></span></h3>
</blockquote>
<h3><span style="color: #993366;">Limericks</span></h3>
<h3>Jon Dowling</h3>
<p><span id="more-20013"/></p>
<blockquote><p><em>A quantum computer from Google,</em><br/>
<em>Turned the Church-Turing thesis to strudel.</em><br/>
<em>And yet there remain,</em><br/>
<em>Many doubting this claim,</em><br/>
<em>And we lash all of them with wet noodles.</em></p></blockquote>
<h3>Avi Wigderson</h3>
<blockquote><p><em>“There once was a quantum computer</em><br/>
<em>Whose pet was a five-legged hamster …”</em><br/>
<em>So Peter and Gil</em><br/>
<em>Their grandchildren will</em><br/>
<em>Tell “…happy they lived ever after”</em></p></blockquote>
<p>Avi suggests a kids’ chorus saying “yeah, right” or “sure, sure”, after each line</p>
<h3><span style="color: #993366;">Six-word stories</span></h3>
<h3>Ehud Friedgut</h3>
<blockquote>
<h3><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>For sale: <span class="il">quantum</span> computer. Never used.</em></span></h3>
</blockquote>
<h3>Another 6-word story (mine) with a rhyme (of some sort)</h3>
<blockquote>
<h3><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>Michelson and Morley weren’t </em></span><em><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">G</span><span style="color: #ff0000;">o</span><span style="color: #ffcc00;">o</span><span style="color: #0000ff;">g</span><span style="color: #339966;">l</span><span style="color: #ff0000;">e</span></strong></em><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em> employees.</em></span></h3>
</blockquote>
<h2/>
<h2>6. More figures from my paper with Yosi and Tomer.</h2>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/plot_3.jpeg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-20102" height="350" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/plot_3.jpeg?w=640&amp;h=350" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Various estimators for the fidelity for the Google data compared to simulations. </span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/fig_8.jpeg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-20103" height="519" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/fig_8.jpeg?w=640&amp;h=519" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The model expected values compared to the empirical distribution. On the left for the real data and on the right for simulated data.  As it turned out the Google noise model does not fit for the sample data. (Our readout model provides only a small improvement.)  </span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/hists.jpeg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-20104" height="249" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/hists.jpeg?w=640&amp;h=249" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The size biased distribution fits the model very well.</span></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-22T17:02:49Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-22T17:02:49Z</published>
    <category term="Quantum"/>
    <category term="Statistics"/>
    <category term="Tomer Shoham"/>
    <category term="Yosi Rinott"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/127</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/127" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-127 |  $k$-Forrelation Optimally Separates Quantum and Classical Query Complexity | 

	Nikhil Bansal, 

	Makrand Sinha</title>
    <summary>Aaronson and Ambainis (SICOMP '18) showed that any partial function on $N$ bits that can be computed with an advantage $\delta$ over a random guess by making $q$ quantum queries, can also be computed classically with an advantage $\delta/2$ by a randomized decision tree making ${O}_q(N^{1-\frac{1}{2q}}\delta^{-2})$ queries. Moreover, they conjectured the $k$-Forrelation problem --- a partial function that can be computed with $q = \lceil k/2 \rceil$ quantum queries --- to be a suitable candidate for exhibiting such an extremal separation. 
    
     We prove their conjecture by showing a tight lower bound of $\widetilde{\Omega}_k(N^{1-1/k})$ for the randomized query complexity of $k$-Forrelation, where the advantage $\delta = 1/\mathrm{polylog}^k(N)$ and $\widetilde{\Omega}_k$ hides $\mathrm{polylog}^k(N)$ factors. Our proof relies on classical Gaussian tools, in particular, Gaussian interpolation and Gaussian integration by parts, and in fact, shows a more general statement, that to prove lower bounds for $k$-Forrelation against a family of functions, it suffices to bound the $\ell_1$-weight of the Fourier coefficients at levels $k, 2k, 3k, \ldots, (k-1)k$ for functions in the family.</summary>
    <updated>2020-08-21T19:02:19Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-21T19:02:19Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/21/phd-or-postdoc-at-goethe-university-frankfurt-apply-by-august-31-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/21/phd-or-postdoc-at-goethe-university-frankfurt-apply-by-august-31-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PhD or Postdoc at Goethe University Frankfurt (apply by August 31, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The research group by Holger Dell at Goethe University Frankfurt is inviting applications for a three-year PhD or Postdoc position, starting at the earliest possible date. Potential topics include the algorithmic theory of network science, algebraic graph algorithms, fine-grained and parameterized complexity, “classical” complexity theory, as well as adjacent areas. Website: https://www.t.cs.uni-frankfurt.de/positions/ Email: recruiting2020@holgerdell.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The research group by Holger Dell at Goethe University Frankfurt is inviting applications for a three-year PhD or Postdoc position, starting at the earliest possible date. Potential topics include the algorithmic theory of network science, algebraic graph algorithms, fine-grained and parameterized complexity, “classical” complexity theory, as well as adjacent areas.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.t.cs.uni-frankfurt.de/positions/">https://www.t.cs.uni-frankfurt.de/positions/</a><br/>
Email: recruiting2020@holgerdell.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-21T14:41:55Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-21T14:41:55Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17421</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/19/logical-complexity-of-proofs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Logical Complexity of Proofs</title>
    <summary>If you cannot find proofs, talk about them. Robert Reckhow with his advsior Stephen Cook famously started the formal study of the complexity of proofs with their 1979 paper. They were interested in the length of the shortest proofs of propositional statements. Georg Kreisel and others may have looked at proof length earlier, but one […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>If you cannot find proofs, talk about them.</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/19/logical-complexity-of-proofs/rr/" rel="attachment wp-att-17427"><img alt="" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-17427" height="119" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/rr.png?w=300&amp;h=119" width="300"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Robert Reckhow with his advsior Stephen Cook famously started the formal study of the complexity of proofs with their 1979 <a href="https://www.cs.toronto.edu/~sacook/homepage/cook_reckhow.pdf">paper</a>. They were interested in the length of the shortest <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proof_complexity">proofs</a> of propositional statements. Georg Kreisel and others may have looked at proof length earlier, but one of the key insights of Reckhow and Cook is that low level propositional logic is important.</p>
<p>
Today I thought we might look at the complexity of proofs.</p>
<p>
Cook and Reckhow were motivated by issues like: How hard is it to prove that a graph has no clique of a certain size? Or how hard to prove that some program halts on all inputs of length <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>? All of these questions ask about the length of proofs in a precise sense. Proofs have been around forever, back to Euclid at least, but Cook and Reckhow were the first to formally study the lengths of proofs. </p>
<p>
They were not directly interested in actual proofs. The kind you can find in the <a href="https://arxiv.org/archive/math">arXiv</a> or in a math journal, or at a conference—online or not. The kind that are in their paper.<br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/19/logical-complexity-of-proofs/paper-5/" rel="attachment wp-att-17432"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-17432" height="60" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/paper.png?w=300&amp;h=60" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>We are talking today about these types of proofs. Not proofs that graphs have cliques. But proofs that a no planar graph can have a <img alt="{5}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B5%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{5}"/> clique. </p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/19/logical-complexity-of-proofs/unknown-144/" rel="attachment wp-att-17430"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-17430" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/unknown.png?w=600"/></a></p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Proofs </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Proofs are what we strive to find ever day. They the coin that measures progress in a mathematical field like complexity theory. We do sometimes work out examples, sometimes do computations to confirm conjectures on small examples, sometimes consider analogies to other proofs. But mostly we want to understand proofs. We want to create new ones and understand others proofs. </p>
<p>
Years ago when studying the graph isomorphism problem, I did some extensive computations for the random case. That is for the case of isomorphism for a random dense graphs against a worst case other graph. The computations helped me improve my result. It did not yield a proof, of course, but helped me realize that a certain lemma could be improved from a bound <img alt="{\log n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log n}"/> to <img alt="{O(1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%281%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(1)}"/>. My results were dominated by <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Stanley_Selkow/publication/220618511_Random_Graph_Isomorphism/links/00463537d337e6a35d000000/Random-Graph-Isomorphism.pdf">paper</a> of Laszlo Babai, Paul Erdös, and Stanley Selkow. Oh well. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Proofs Complexity </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
There are several measures of complexity for proofs. One is the length. Long proofs are difficult to find, difficult to write up, difficult to read, and difficult to check. Another less obvious measure is the logical structure of a proof. What does this mean?</p>
<p>
Our idea is that a proof can be modeled by a formula from propositional logic. The <img alt="{P}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P}"/> is what we are trying to prove and the letters <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> and so on are for statements we already know.  </p>
<li>
<img alt="{(A \rightarrow P)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28A+%5Crightarrow+P%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(A \rightarrow P)}"/>  This is a direct proof. <p/>
</li><li>
<img alt="{(\neg P \rightarrow \neg A)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28%5Cneg+P+%5Crightarrow+%5Cneg+A%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(\neg P \rightarrow \neg A)}"/>  This is a proof by contradiction. <p/>
</li><li>
<img alt="{( A \vee \neg A \rightarrow P)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28+A+%5Cvee+%5Cneg+A+%5Crightarrow+P%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{( A \vee \neg A \rightarrow P)}"/>  This is proof that uses a statement <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> that may be true or false. <p/>
<p>
The last is a slight cheat, we use <img alt="{A \vee \neg A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA+%5Cvee+%5Cneg+A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A \vee \neg A}"/> to stand for a kind of axiom. A perfect example is from number theory. Let <img alt="{\pi(X)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%28X%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\pi(X)}"/> be the number of primes less than <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> and the function <img alt="{li(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bli%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{li(x)}"/> the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Logarithmic_integral_function&amp;action=edit&amp;section=1">logarithmic function</a>. 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  li(x) = \int_0^x \frac{dt}{\ln t}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++li%28x%29+%3D+%5Cint_0%5Ex+%5Cfrac%7Bdt%7D%7B%5Cln+t%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  li(x) = \int_0^x \frac{dt}{\ln t}. "/></p>
<p>The prime number <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prime_number_theorem">theorem</a> says that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \pi(x) = li(x) + E(x), " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cpi%28x%29+%3D+li%28x%29+%2B+E%28x%29%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \pi(x) = li(x) + E(x), "/></p>
<p>an error term. </p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/19/logical-complexity-of-proofs/graph/" rel="attachment wp-att-17425"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-17425" height="171" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/graph.png?w=300&amp;h=171" width="300"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
It was noted that <img alt="{li(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bli%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{li(x)}"/> is larger than <img alt="{\pi(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\pi(x)}"/> for known values. The obvious question was that could 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  li(x) \ge \pi(x), " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++li%28x%29+%5Cge+%5Cpi%28x%29%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  li(x) \ge \pi(x), "/></p>
<p>be always true? If so this would be an interesting inequality. In 1914 John Littlewood famously <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/_/2SUrpE8NK6sC?hl=en&amp;gbpv=1&amp;pg=PA33&amp;dq=John+Littlewood+pi+nd+li">proved</a> that this was not true: </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 1</b> <em> If the Riemann Hypothesis is true: 	</em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \pi(x) - li(x) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cpi%28x%29+-+li%28x%29+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \pi(x) - li(x) "/></p>
<p>is infinitely often positive and negative. If the Riemann Hypothesis is false: 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \pi(x) - li(x) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cpi%28x%29+-+li%28x%29+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \pi(x) - li(x) "/></p>
</em><p><em>is infinitely often positive and negative. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Thus he proved that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \pi(x) - li(x) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cpi%28x%29+-+li%28x%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \pi(x) - li(x) "/></p>
<p>is infinitely often positive and negative whether the the Riemann is true or not. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Proofs in Trouble </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
A sign of a proof in danger is, in my opinion, is not just the length. A better measure I think is the logical flow of proof. I know of no actual proof that uses this structure: 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  (A \rightarrow B) \rightarrow ((A \vee C) \rightarrow (B \vee C)) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%28A+%5Crightarrow+B%29+%5Crightarrow+%28%28A+%5Cvee+C%29+%5Crightarrow+%28B+%5Cvee+C%29%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  (A \rightarrow B) \rightarrow ((A \vee C) \rightarrow (B \vee C)) "/></p>
<p>Do you? Even if your proof is only a few lines or even pages, if the high level flow was the above tautology I would be worried. </p>
<p>
Another example is <img alt="{P \rightarrow P}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP+%5Crightarrow+P%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P \rightarrow P}"/>. This of course is a circular proof. It seems hard to believe we would actually do this, but it has happen. The key is that no one says: I will assume the theorem to prove it. The flaw is disguised better than that.</p>
<p>
I cannot formally define this measure. Perhaps it is known, but I do think that it would be an additional measure. For actual proofs, ones we use every day, perhaps it would be valuable. I know I have looked at an attempted proof of X and noticed the logical flow in this sense was too complex. So complex that it was wrong. The author of the potential proof was me. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Is this measure, the logical flow of a proof, of any interest? </p>
<p/></li></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-19T13:00:52Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-19T13:00:52Z</published>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="complexity proof"/>
    <category term="Logic"/>
    <category term="logical flow"/>
    <category term="proof length"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-25562705.post-41257542542066199</id>
    <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/feeds/41257542542066199/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=25562705&amp;postID=41257542542066199" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default/41257542542066199" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default/41257542542066199" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/2020/08/moment-multicalibration-for-uncertainty.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Moment Multicalibration for Uncertainty Estimation</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This blog post is about<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.08037" target="_blank"> a new paper</a> that I'm excited about, which is joint work with <a href="https://www.cis.upenn.edu/~chrjung/" target="_blank">Chris Jung</a>,<a href="https://economics.sas.upenn.edu/people/changhwa-lee" target="_blank"> Changhwa Lee</a>, <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/malleshpai/">Mallesh Pai</a>, and <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/quaerereverum9/">Ricky Vohra</a>. <div><br/></div><div>Suppose you are diagnosed with hypertension, and your doctor recommends that you take a certain drug to lower your blood pressure. The latest research, she tells you, finds that the drug lowers diastolic blood pressure by an average of 10 mm Hg. You remember your statistics class from college, and so you ask about confidence intervals. She looks up the paper, and tells you that it reports a 95% confidence interval of [5, 15]. How should you interpret this? </div><div><br/></div><div>What you might naively hope is that [5, 15] represents a <i>conditional prediction interval</i>. If you have some set of observable features $x$, and a label $y$ (in this case corresponding to your decrease in diastolic blood pressure after taking the drug), a 95% conditional prediction interval would promise that:</div><div>$$\Pr_y [y \in [5, 15] | x] \geq 0.95$$</div><div><br/></div><div>In other words, a conditional prediction interval would promise that given all of your observed features, <i>over the unrealized/unmeasured randomness of the world</i>, there is a 95% chance that your diastolic blood pressure will decrease by between 5 and 15 points. </div><div><br/></div><div>But if you think about it, coming up with a conditional prediction interval is essentially impossible in a rich feature space. If $x$ contains lots of information about you, then probably there was nobody in the original study population that exactly matched your set of features $x$, and so we have no information at all about the conditional distribution on $y$ given $x$ --- i.e. no samples at all from the distribution over which our coverage probability supposedly holds! So how can you expect any sort of promise at all? There are two typical ways around this difficulty. </div><div><br/></div><div>The first is to make heroic assumptions about the data generation process. For example, if we assume that the world looks like an ordinary least squares model, and that there is a linear relationship between $y$ and $x$, then we can form a confidence region around the parameters of the model, and from that derive prediction intervals. But these prediction intervals are not valid if the model fails to hold, which it inevitably will. </div><div><br/></div><div>The second is to give up on conditional prediction intervals, and instead give <i>marginal prediction intervals</i>. This is what the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0706.3188" target="_blank">conformal prediction</a> literature aims to do. A marginal prediction interval looks quite similar to a conditional prediction interval (at least syntactically), and promises:</div><div>$$\Pr_{(x,y)} [y \in [5, 15] ] \geq 0.95$$</div><div><br/></div><div>Rather than conditioning on your features $x$, a marginal prediction interval averages over all people, and promises that 95% of people who take the drug have their diastolic blood pressure lowered by between 5 and 15 points. But the semantics of this promise are quite different than that of a conditional prediction interval. Because the average is now taken over a large, heterogeneous population, very little is promised to <i>you</i>. For example, it might be that for patients in your demographic group (e.g. middle aged women with Sephardic Jewish ancestry and a family history of diabetes) that the drug is actually expected to raise blood pressure rather than lower it. Because this subgroup represents less than 5% of the population, it is entirely consistent with the marginal prediction interval being correct. Of course, if you are lucky, then perhaps someone has conducted a study of people from this demographic group and has computed marginal prediction intervals over it! But what if there are multiple different groups that you are a member of, over which the results seem to conflict? For example, you might also have a low BMI value and have unusually good cholesterol readings --- features of a group for which the drug works unusually well. Which uncertainty estimate should you trust, if you are a member of both groups? </div><div><br/></div><div>These concerns actually arise already when we think about the semantics of mean estimations ("the expected drop in blood pressure amongst patients who take this drug is 10 mm Hg"). Ideally, if you were a patient with features $x$, then 10 would be an estimate of $\mathbb{E}[y | x]$. But just as with uncertainty estimation, in a large feature space, we typically have no information about the distribution on $y$ conditional on $x$ (because we have never met anyone exactly like <i>you</i> before), and so instead what we have is just an estimate of $\mathbb{E}[y]$ --- i.e. averaging over people. If you have a method of making predictions $f(x)$ as a function of features $x$, then a standard performance metric is <i>calibration</i> --- which informally asks that for every prediction $p$, amongst all people for whom we predicted $f(x) = p$, the average of the realized labels $y$ should be $p$. Again, estimates of this form promise little to individuals, because they are averages over a large and heterogeneous population.   </div><div><br/></div><div>Several years ago, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.08513" target="_blank">Hebert-Johnson et al.</a> proposed a nice way to interpolate between the (impossible) ideal of offering conditional mean predictions  $f(x) = \mathbb{E}[y | x]$, and the weak guarantee of merely offering calibrated predictions $f$. Roughly speaking, they proposed to specify a very large collection of potentially intersecting groups $G$ (representing e.g. demographic groups like Sephardic Jewish women with a family history of diabetes, and hypertensive patients with low cholesterol and BMI values, etc) and to ask that a trained predictor be <i>simultaniously</i> calibrated on each sufficiently large group in $G$. They showed how to accomplish this using a polynomially sized sample from the underlying distribution, with polynomial running time overhead, on top of the cost of solving learning problems over $G$. </div><div><br/></div><div>In our paper, we --- roughly speaking --- show how to accomplish the same thing, but for variances and other higher moments, in addition to just means. And our "multicalibrated moment estimates" can be used to construct prediction intervals in exactly the same way that real moments of the conditional label distribution could be used. If you used the real (unknown) label distribution moments, you would have gotten conditional prediction intervals. If you use our multi-calibrated moments, you get marginal prediction intervals that are simultaneously valid as averaged over each of the groups in $G$. So, for example, our hypertensive patient above could interpret her prediction interval --- if it was constructed from multicalibrated moment estimates computed from her features --- as an average over each of the demographic groups that she is a member of (so long as they are contained within $G$), and all of those interpretations would be simultaneously valid. </div><div><br/></div><div>I'll leave the details to the paper --- including what exactly we mean by "moment multicalibration". I'll just note that a major difficulty is that variances and higher moments --- unlike expectations --- do not combine linearly, so it is no longer sensible to ask that "amongst all people for whom we predicted variance v, the true variance should be v" --- because even the true conditional label variances do not satisfy this property. But it <i>is </i>sensible to ask that a pair of mean and moment predictions be calibrated in this way: "amongst all people for whom we predicted mean $\mu$ and variance v, the true mean should be $\mu$ and the true variance should be $v$." This is what we call "mean-conditioned moment calibration", and it is satisfied by the true distributional moments. </div><div><br/></div><div>The paper is here: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.08037">Moment Multicalibration for Uncertainty Estimation</a>.</div><div><br/></div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-19T11:47:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-19T11:47:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Aaron</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/09952936358739421126</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-25562705</id>
      <category term="game theory"/>
      <category term="news"/>
      <author>
        <name>Aaron</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/09952936358739421126</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Adventures in Computation</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T14:42:14Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/126</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/126" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-126 |  Indistinguishability Obfuscation from Well-Founded Assumptions | 

	Aayush  Jain, 

	Huijia Lin, 

	Amit Sahai</title>
    <summary>In this work, we show how to construct indistinguishability obfuscation from subexponential hardness of four well-founded assumptions. We prove:

Let $\tau \in (0,\infty), \delta \in (0,1), \epsilon \in (0,1)$ be arbitrary constants. Assume sub-exponential security of the following assumptions, where $\lambda$ is a security parameter, and the parameters $\ell,k,n$ below are large enough polynomials in $\lambda$:

- The SXDH assumption on asymmetric bilinear groups of a prime order $p = O(2^\lambda)$,

- The LWE assumption over $\mathbb{Z}_{p}$ with subexponential modulus-to-noise ratio $2^{k^\epsilon}$, where $k$ is the dimension of the LWE secret,

- The LPN assumption over $\mathbb{Z}_p$ with polynomially many LPN samples and error rate $1/\ell^\delta$, where $\ell$ is the dimension of the LPN secret,

- The existence of a Boolean PRG in $\mathsf{NC}^0$ with stretch $n^{1+\tau}$,
 
Then, (subexponentially secure) indistinguishability obfuscation for all polynomial-size circuits exists.</summary>
    <updated>2020-08-19T11:37:19Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-19T11:37:19Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/125</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/125" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-125 |  Efficient reconstruction of depth three circuits with top fan-in two | 

	Gaurav  Sinha</title>
    <summary>In this paper we develop efficient randomized algorithms to solve the black-box reconstruction problem for polynomials(over finite fields) computable by depth three arithmetic circuits with alternating addition/multiplication gates, such that top(output) gate is an addition gate with in-degree $2$. Such circuits naturally compute polynomials of the form $G\times(T_1 + T_2)$, where $G,T_1,T_2$ are product of affine forms computed at the first(addition) layer in the circuit, and polynomials $T_1,T_2$ have no common factors. Rank of such a circuit is defined to be the dimension of vector space spanned by all affine factors of $T_1$ and $T_2$. For any polynomial $f$ computable by such a circuit, $rank(f)$ is defined to be the minimum rank of any such circuit computing it. Our work develops randomized algorithms, which take as input a black-box computing polynomial $f$, with coefficients in a finite field $\mathbb{F}$, exhibiting such a circuit. Here are the results. 

$[$Low rank$]:$ When $5\leq r = rank(f) = O(\log^3 d)$, it runs in time $(nd^{\log^3d}\log |\mathbb{F}|)^{O(1)}$ and outputs a depth three circuit computing $f$ (with high probability), with top addition gate having in-degree $\leq d^{rank(f)}$.

$[$High rank$]:$ When $rank(f) = \Omega(\log^3 d)$, it runs in time $(nd\log |\mathbb{F}|)^{O(1)}$, and with high probability outputs a depth three circuit computing $f$, with top addition gate having in-degree $2$.

Prior to our work, black-box reconstruction for this circuit class was addressed in [Shp07, KS09, Sin16b]. Reconstruction algorithm in [Shp07] runs in time quasi-polynomial in $n,d,|\mathbb{F}|$ and that in [KS09] is quasi-polynomial in $d,|\mathbb{F}|$. Algorithm in [Sin16b] works only for polynomials over characteristic zero fields. Thus ours is the first blackbox reconstruction algorithm for this class of circuits that runs in time polynomial in $\log |\mathbb{F}|$. This problem has been mentioned as an open problem in [GKL12] (STOC 2012). In the high rank case, our algorithm runs in $(nd\log|\mathbb{F}|)^{O(1)}$ time, thereby significantly improving the existing algorithms in [Shp07, KS09].</summary>
    <updated>2020-08-17T19:11:47Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-17T19:11:47Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/124</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/124" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-124 |  A Strong XOR Lemma for Randomized Query Complexity | 

	Joshua Brody, 

	JaeTak Kim, 

	Peem Lerdputtipongporn, 

	Hariharan Srinivasulu</title>
    <summary>We give a strong direct sum theorem for computing $XOR \circ g$.  Specifically, we show that the randomized query complexity of computing the XOR of $k$ instances of $g$ satisfies $\bar{R}_\varepsilon(XOR \circ g)=\Theta(\bar{R}_{\varepsilon/k}(g))$.  This matches the naive success amplification bound and answers a question of Blais and Brody.

As a consequence of our strong direct sum theorem, we give a total function $g$ for which $R(XOR \circ g) = \Theta(k\log(k)R(g))$, answering an open question from Ben-David et al.</summary>
    <updated>2020-08-17T13:19:41Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-17T13:19:41Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/123</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/123" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-123 |  An Optimal Tester for k-Linear | 

	Nader Bshouty</title>
    <summary>A Boolean function $f:\{0,1\}^n\to \{0,1\}$ is $k$-linear if it returns the sum (over the binary field $F_2$) of $k$ coordinates of the input. In this paper, we study property testing of the classes $k$-Linear, the class of all $k$-linear functions, and $k$-Linear$^*$, the class $\cup_{j=0}^kj$-Linear.
We give a non-adaptive distribution-free two-sided $\epsilon$-tester for $k$-Linear that makes
$$O\left(k\log k+\frac{1}{\epsilon}\right)$$ queries.
This matches the lower bound known from the literature.

We then give a non-adaptive distribution-free one-sided $\epsilon$-tester for $k$-Linear$^*$ that makes the same number of queries and show that any non-adaptive uniform-distribution one-sided $\epsilon$-tester for $k$-Linear must make at least $ \tilde\Omega(k)\log n+\Omega(1/\epsilon)$ queries. The latter bound, almost matches the upper bound $O(k\log n+1/\epsilon)$ known from the literature. We then show that any adaptive uniform-distribution one-sided $\epsilon$-tester for $k$-Linear must make at least $\tilde\Omega(\sqrt{k})\log n+\Omega(1/\epsilon)$ queries.</summary>
    <updated>2020-08-17T13:17:37Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-17T13:17:37Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6748297921609096715</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6748297921609096715/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/what-if-history-of-science-factoring.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6748297921609096715" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6748297921609096715" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/what-if-history-of-science-factoring.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Mathematics is not commutative</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In my poll of P vs NP and other issues, one of the questions was<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
                             <i>Is factoring in P?</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
One of the most interesting answers was<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
                            <i> I don't really see why it shouldn't be. - Peter Shor</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
Recall that Peter Shor proved Factoring is in Quantum-P which lead to intense interest in Quantum Computing.<br/>
<br/>
1) What if factoring was in P and this was shown before Shor's algorithm? Would Shor or someone else have ever proven factoring in quantum P? Would there be as much intense interest in quantum computing as there is now? Perhaps by physicists more than CS people?<br/>
<br/>
2) What if factoring was in P and this was shown before RSA? Where would crypto be now? Zip drives with a googleplex random (or nearly random) bits and more 1-time pads? More lattice based crypto? Or RSA but with larger numbers? This may depend on how good the factoring algorithm is.<br/>
<br/>
3) More generally, how much does the order of events matter for science?<br/>
<br/>
a) If the Banach-Tarski paradox was discovered early on, would we have just tossed out the Axiom of Choice before so much more was build on it? Darling thinks we should toss out AC NOW because of Banach-Tarski.<br/>
<br/>
b) In the model of set theory L you can do ALL of math except some parts of set theory and maybe a few other things (note quite: Harvey Friedman has found some combinatorial statements that need large cardinals to prove). Had L been discovered earlier then could we all now be working in L (except a few people who look at other models, but they are not in the mainstream)? We might know more about L and less about forcing. We would KNOW that AC and CH are true. Or we would think we know.<br/>
<br/>
c) If  Engineers were the first ones to look at SAT and reductions, might they have been content to know that  if SAT \le A then A is probably hard? No need for the Cook-Levin Theorem! And then when someone proved Cook-Levin would the Engineers not really cares since they already knew SAT was hard?<br/>
<br/>d) I can imagine Ramsey's Theorem being discovered much later for some application, or perhaps never being discovered at all.<div><br/></div><div>e) VDW's theorem has so few application, I can imagine it never being discovered. </div><div><br/></div><div>4) There are cases where if A was discovered before B then B has an easy proof, whereas if B was discovered before A, then B has a hard proof. I'll give one example:</div><div><br/></div><div>Given HALT is undecidable, Godel's theorem is easy.</div><div><br/></div><div>Assume HALT is undecidable. </div><div><br/></div><div>Let STAT(e) be the statement M_e(0) does not  halt.</div><div><br/></div><div>There is some e such that M_e(0) does not halt  but ZFC cannot prove this.</div><div><br/></div><div>PROOF: Assume, By Way of Contradiction that for all e such that M_e(0) does not halt,</div><div>ZFC could prove this. Then HALT is DECIDABLE:</div><div><br/>Given e, run M_e(0) and at the same time enumerate all proofs in ZFC. It is guaranteed that</div><div>you will either find M_e(0) halts or a proof that M_e(0) does not halt. Hence you will,</div><div>in finite time, know if M_e(0) halts OR NOT.</div><div><br/></div><div>END OF PROOF</div><div><br/></div><div>Is the sequence of events where HALT is proven undecidable  before Godel's theorem plausible.</div><div>I  think so</div><div><br/></div><div>I INVITE my readers to give there own examples of when Math is not commutative- meaning that</div><div>the order of events matters.</div><div>
<br/></div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-17T12:35:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-17T12:35:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T07:36:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/122</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/122" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-122 |  Size Bounds on Low Depth Circuits for Promise Majority | 

	Joshua Cook</title>
    <summary>We give two results on the size of AC0 circuits computing promise majority. $\epsilon$-promise majority is majority promised that either at most an $\epsilon$ fraction of the input bits are 1, or at most $\epsilon$ are 0.

First, we show super quadratic lower bounds on both monotone and general depth 3 circuits for promise majority.

For any $\epsilon \in (0, 1/2)$, monotone depth 3 AC0 circuits for $\epsilon$-promise majority have size 
$\tilde{\Omega}\left(\epsilon^3 n^{2 + \frac{\ln(1 - \epsilon)}{\ln(\epsilon)}}\right)$
         
For any $\epsilon \in (0, 1/2)$, general depth 3 AC0 circuits for $\epsilon$-promise majority have size
$\tilde{\Omega}\left(\epsilon^3 n^{2 + \frac{\ln(1 - \epsilon^2)}{2\ln(\epsilon)}}\right)$

These are the first nontrivial size lower bounds on depth 3 promise majority circuits for $\epsilon &lt; 0.45$.
        
Second, we give both uniform and non-uniform sub-quadratic size constant depth circuits for promise majority.

For integer $k \geq 1$, constant $\epsilon \in (0, 1/2)$, there exists monotone non uniform AC0 circuits of depth $2 + 2 \cdot k$ computing $\epsilon$-promise majority with size
$\tilde{O}\left(n^{\frac{1}{1 - 2^{-k}}}\right)$

For integer $k \geq 1$, constant $\epsilon \in (0, 1/2)$, there exists monotone uniform AC0 circuit of depth $2 + 2 \cdot k$ computing $\epsilon$-promise majority with size
$n^{\frac{1}{1 - \left(\frac{2}{3}\right)^k} + o(1)}$

These circuits are based on incremental improvements to existing depth 3 circuits for promise majority given by Ajtai and Viola combined with a divide and conquer strategy.</summary>
    <updated>2020-08-16T14:37:01Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-16T14:37:01Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/121</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/121" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-121 |  Fractional Pseudorandom Generators from the $k$th Fourier Level | 

	Eshan Chattopadhyay, 

	Jason Gaitonde, 

	Abhishek Shetty</title>
    <summary>In recent work by Chattopadhyay et al.[CHHL19,CHLT19], the authors exhibit a simple and flexible construction of pseudorandom generators for classes of Boolean functions that satisfy $L_1$ Fourier bounds. [CHHL19] show that if a class satisfies such tail bounds at all levels, this implies a PRG whose seed length depends on the quality of these bounds through their innovative random walk framework that composes together fractional PRGs that polarize quickly to the Boolean hypercube. On the other hand, [CHLT19] show that, by derandomizing the analysis of [RT19], just level-two Fourier bounds suffice to construct a pseudorandom generator using their framework; as this is a much weaker assumption on the class, [CHLT19] naturally obtain exponentially worse dependence on the error in the seed length compared to [CHHL19]. Moreover, this derandomization relies on simulating nearly independent Gaussians for the fractional pseudorandom generator, which necessitates the  polynomial dependence on $1/\epsilon$ in each fractional step.
    
    In this work, we attempt to bridge the gap between these two results. Namely, we partially answer an open question by [CHLT19] that nearly interpolates between them. In particular, we show that if one has bounds up to the level-$k$ $L_1$ Fourier mass of a closely related class of functions, where $k&gt;2$, one can obtain improved seed length, the degree to which is determined by how high $k$ can be taken. Our analysis shows that for error $\epsilon=1/\text{poly}(n)$, one needs control at just level $O(\log n)$ to recover the seed length of [CHHL19], without assumptions on the entire tail. We avoid this by providing a simple, alternate analysis of their fractional PRG that instead relies on Taylor's theorem and $p$-biased Fourier analysis to avoid assumptions on the weights of the higher-order terms. This further allows us to show that this framework can handle the class of low-degree polynomials over $\mathbb{F}_2$, with slightly worse dependence than the current state-of-the-art, which was not previously known. We hope that this alternate analysis will be fruitful in improving the understanding of this new and powerful framework.</summary>
    <updated>2020-08-16T14:35:43Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-16T14:35:43Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-08-28T15:20:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://differentialprivacy.org/privacy-composition/</id>
    <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/privacy-composition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Why Privacy Needs Composition</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We’re back!  In our last <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/\average-case-dp">post</a> we discussed some of the subtle pitfalls of formulating the assumptions underlying average-case relaxations of differential privacy.  This time we’re going to look at the composition property of differential privacy—that is, the fact that running two independent differentially private algorithms on your data and combining their outputs is still differentially private. This is a key property of differential privacy and is actually closely related to the worst-case nature of differential privacy.</p>

<p>Composition is really the crucial property that has made differential privacy successful. Data analysis doesn’t happen in a vacuum, and the greatest threat to privacy comes from combining multiple pieces of information. These pieces of information can come from a single source that releases detailed statistics, or they could come from separate sources. So it’s critical to understand how the composition of multiple pieces of information can affect privacy.</p>

<p>In this post we’ll give some examples to illustrate why we need composition, and why composition is challenging for average-case relaxations of differential privacy.  Composition is what allows you to design sophisticated differentially private algorithms out of simple building blocks, and it’s what allows one organization to release differentially private statistics without having to understand the entire ecosystem of related information that has been or will be released.  As we’ll see, the challenges of composing average-case privacy guarantees are also very closely related to the subtleties that arise in thinking about the adversary’s beliefs.</p>

<h3 id="differencing-attacks">Differencing Attacks</h3>

<p>Let’s start with a simple example of composition that was alluded to in our last post.</p>

<p>You’ve just started a new job and signed up for the health insurance provided by your employer. Thus, your employer is able to obtain aggregated data from the insurance provider. In particular, your employer can ask “How many of our employees have submitted claims for condition X?”  However, your employer should not be able to find out whether or not <em>you</em> have condition X. 
For concreteness, condition X could be a mental health condition, drug addiction, being pregnant, terminal cancer, or an expensive chronic illness. Each of these could result in some kind of employment discrimination.</p>

<p>The employer may find out that 417 employees have condition X.  That’s OK; on its own, this number reveals very little about whether or not <em>you</em> have condition X, as long as your employer is uncertain about how many employees <em>other than you</em> have condition X.  We can formalize this as some kind of average-case or Bayesian privacy guarantee. Thus the health-insurance company is comfortable releasing this number exactly.  But, yesterday, before you started your job, it also seemed reasonable to allow your employer to ask the exact same question, and yesterday the answer was 416. Thus your employer concludes that you have condition X.</p>

<p>In this example, we see how two pieces of information—the count before you started and the count after you started—each of which seems innocuous on its own can be combined to reveal private information. This is a simple example of a <em>differencing attack</em> and composition is important in part because it prevents these attacks.</p>

<p>This example involves only two pieces of information. However, an attack could combine many pieces of information. For example, the counts could be broken down by sex, race/ethnicity, age, location, and tobacco use.<sup id="fnref:1"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:1">1</a></sup> Additional data may also be obtained from other sources, such as public records, social media, voluntary disclosures, healthcare providers, financial records, employment records, or even illicit sources. The possibilities for attacks grow rapidly as more information is made available. And an employer is only one example of a potential privacy adversary.</p>

<p>The point of this example is that it’s easy to argue that one piece of information is harmless to privacy by making plausible-looking assumptions about the adversary. But this intuition rapidly breaks down once you consider the bigger picture where there are many pieces of information that can complete the puzzle. That’s why we need rigorous methods for understanding privacy and its composition.</p>

<h3 id="quantifying-composition">Quantifying Composition</h3>

<p>How does differential privacy prevent a differencing attack like the one we just discussed? The simplest way is to add a little bit of random noise to each answer. On the first day, instead of releasing the exact count 416, we could release a noisy count, say, 420. Then on the second day, instead of releasing the true count 417, we release another noisy count, say, 415. More precisely, it is common to add noise to counts drawn from a Laplace or Gaussian distribution.  These figures are still close enough to the true values to be useful, but the difference of 1 is now obscured by the noise, so your privacy is protected.</p>

<p>Since the noise is unknown to <em>any</em> potential adversary, it introduces uncertainty that protects the contribution that an individual makes to the count. Taking the difference of two independent noisy counts results in something that is still noisy. However, we must be careful to quantify this privacy guarantee, particularly when it comes to composition.</p>

<p>So, how much noise do we need to add? Let’s go back to the example and suppose the insurance company provides noisy answers where the noise has mean zero and some fixed variance. Your employer could simply ask the same question again and again and each time receive a different noisy answer. Averaging these noisy answers will effectively reduce the variance of the added noise and allow the true answer to be discerned. That leaves us back where we started.</p>

<p>The moral of this revised example is that the scale of the noise must increase if we allow more access to the data, so more questions means more noise in each answer.<sup id="fnref:2"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:2">2</a></sup> 
Asking the same question again and again may seem silly. There are easy ways to defend against this and some similar attacks. (E.g., by returning the same answer each time instead of generating fresh noise.) But, unfortunately, the underlying phenomenon cannot be circumvented. One of the seminal works that led to differential privacy <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/773153.773173" title="Irit Dinur, Kobbi Nissim. Revealing Information While Preserving Privacy. PODS 2003"><strong>[DN03]</strong></a> showed that there is an inherent tradeoff between the number of questions to be answered and the amount of noise that needs to be added to protect privacy. The general attack is simple: Instead of asking the same query again and again, the attacker asks “random” queries.<sup id="fnref:3"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:3">3</a></sup> This attack only requires basic linear algebra and, importantly, has been demonstrated on real systems <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.05692" title="Aloni Cohen, Kobbi Nissim. Linear Program Reconstruction in Practice. 2018."><strong>[CN18]</strong></a>.</p>

<h3 id="adaptive-composition">Adaptive Composition</h3>

<p>There are actually two kinds of composition to consider. There is <strong>non-adaptive composition</strong>, where the questions to be asked are pre-specified and thus independent of the data, and there is <strong>adaptive composition</strong>, where the questions may themselves depend on the results of prior access to the data. Adaptive composition arises in an interactive system where queries are submitted one-by-one and each answer is returned before the next query is submitted. So far, we have really only considered non-adaptive composition.</p>

<p>Any interactive system must take adaptive composition into account.  A natural algorithm which asks adaptive questions is gradient descent for minimizing a function that is determined by private data (e.g., for logistic regression on medical records). At each step, the algorithm asks for a gradient of the function, which depends on the private data, at the current point. Then the point is updated according to the reported gradient and the process repeats. Since the updated point depends on the previous answer, the next gradient computation is adaptive.</p>

<p>The good news is that differential privacy can handle adaptive composition just fine.  However, to handle adaptive composition, it’s really important that you have a worst-case privacy definition like differential privacy. As we will see below, average-case variants of differential privacy cannot handle adaptive composition. Intuitively, the problem is that whatever distributional assumption you might make about the data or query a priori is unlikely to hold when you condition on past interactions with the same data or related data.</p>

<p>Here’s a technical example that shows the difficulty of adaptive composition. Our data \(x \in \{-1,+1\}^n\) is a vector of \(n\) bits, one bit per person.<sup id="fnref:4"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:4">4</a></sup>  Because we’re considering average-case differential privacy, we’ll model this vector as uniformly random.  Consider the following slightly odd algorithm \(M_2(x,v)\)—it takes a vector \(v \in \{-1,+1\}^n\) from the user, and, if the correlation \(\langle x, v \rangle / n\) between \(v\) and \(x\) is smaller than \(\varepsilon/2\), the query returns \(\emptyset\), but, if the correlation between \(v\) and \(x\) is larger than \(\varepsilon/2\), the query returns the dataset \(x\).  In isolation this algorithm satisfies an average-case version of differential privacy, because if \(n\) is large enough and \(x\) is uniformly random, then it’s very unlikely that the user can guess a vector \(v\) that causes this algorithm to output anything other than \(\emptyset\).  This algorithm may seem contrived; it is a simple stand-in for any algorithm that behaves very well most of the time, but fails completely on some rare inputs.</p>

<p>Now, consider another, more familiar differentially private algorithm called randomized response <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2283137?seq=1" title="Stanley Warner. Randomized Response: A Survey Technique for Eliminating Evasive Answer Bias. Journal of the American Statistical Association 1965."><strong>[W65]</strong></a>.  For those not familiar, this algorithm \(M_1(x)\) outputs a vector \(y \in \{-1,+1\}^n\), where \(y_i\) is slightly more likely to be \(x_i\) than \(-x_i\).  Specifically, we set \(y_i = x_i\) with probability \((1+\varepsilon)/2\) and \(y_i = - x_i\) otherwise. This satisfies \(\log(\frac{1+\varepsilon}{1-\varepsilon})\)-differential privacy or, roughly, \(2\varepsilon\)-differential privacy. The upshot is that we obtain a vector \(y\) where the correlation between \(x\) and \(y\) is about \(\varepsilon\), i.e. \(\langle x , y \rangle / n \approx \varepsilon\).</p>

<p>OK, so \(M_1\) and \(M_2\) both satisfy strong average-case versions of differential privacy when the data is uniform, but what about their composition?  Well, the bad news is that running \(y = M_1(x)\) followed by \(M_2(x,y)\) is going to return the dataset \(x\) with probability approaching 100%!  That’s because \(y\) was designed precisely to be a vector with correlation about \(\varepsilon\) with \(x\), and this is exactly the key that gets \(M_2\) to unlock the dataset.</p>

<p>What went wrong here is that, even if \(x\) really is uniformly random, it’s very far from it when conditioned on the output \(y=M_1(x)\). To analyze \(M_2(x,y)\) we must look at the distribution of \(x\) conditioned on \(y\). This distribution is going to be messy and may as well be a worst-case distribution, which means we must leave the realm of average-case privacy.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>Composition guarantees that, as long as each part of your system is differentially private, then the overall system is too. It would be difficult to build sophisticated systems without this property. And it’s what allows one organization to release differentially private statistics without having to worry about what other information might be out there. In short, composition is what allows differential privacy to deal with the complexities of the real world.</p>

<p>It is unlikely that differential privacy would have taken off as a field of research without this composition property. Any proposal for an alternative approach to privacy-preserving data analysis should first be evaluated in terms of how it handles composition.</p>

<p>This post only scratches the surface. In particular, we haven’t talked about the quantitative aspects of composition; that’s where the fun really begins. We will leave you with some pointers to further reading on the topic:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.annualreviews.org/eprint/E84vbD3Yzw4ff7YPAjnv/full/10.1146/annurev-statistics-060116-054123" title="Cynthia Dwork, Adam Smith, Thomas Steinke, Jonathan Ullman. Exposed! A Survey of Attacks on Private Data. Annual Review of Statistics and its Applications 2017."><strong>[DSSU17]</strong></a> This is a survey of attacks which explains quantitatively the relationship between noise, number of questions, and privacy risks.</li>
  <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1311.0776" title="Peter Kairouz, Sewoong Oh, Pramod Viswanath. The Composition Theorem for Differential Privacy. ICML 2015."><strong>[KOV15]</strong></a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1507.03113" title="Jack Murtagh, Salil Vadhan. The Complexity of Computing the Optimal Composition of Differential Privacy. TCC 2016"><strong>[MV15]</strong></a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1603.01887" title="Cynthia Dwork, Guy Rothbum. Concentrated Differential Privacy. 2016."><strong>[DR16]</strong></a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1605.02065" title="Mark Bun, Thomas Steinke. Concentrated Differential Privacy: Simplifications, Extensions, and Lower Bounds. TCC 2016."><strong>[BS16]</strong></a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1702.07476" title="Ilya Mironov. Renyi Differential Privacy. CSF 2017."><strong>[M17]</strong></a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.02383" title="Jinshuo Dong, Aaron Roth, Weijie Su. Gaussian Differential Privacy. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B. 2020"><strong>[DRS19]</strong></a> On the positive side, these papers analyze how differential privacy composes, yielding sharp quantitative bounds.</li>
</ul>

<hr/>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>A good rule of thumb is that, if the number of released values is much larger than the number of people, then a privacy attack is probably possible. This is analogous to the rule from algebra that, if the number of constraints (released values) is greater than the number of unknown variables (people’s data), then the unknowns can be worked out. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:1">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Exactly quantifying how much noise is needed as the number of questions grows leads to the concept of a “privacy budget.” That is, we must precisely quantify how differential privacy degrades under composition. This is a very deep topic and is something we hope to discuss in future posts. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:2">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>The queries do not need to be random <strong><a href="https://iacr.org/archive/crypto2008/51570469/51570469.pdf" title="Cynthia Dwork, Sergey Yekhanin. New Efficient Attacks on Statistical Disclosure Control Mechanisms. CRYPTO 2008">[DY08]</a></strong>. The queries simply need to be “sufficiently distinct”, which can be formulated precisely as being nearly orthogonal vectors. Random, or even pseudorandom queries (e.g., hash functions), will almost certainly satisfy this property. In general, it is fairly likely that a set of queries will have this property and allow a reconstruction attack; that is, it is hard to <em>avoid</em> this phenomenon. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:3">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>This representation of the dataset as a vector of bits \(x \in \{-1,+1\}^n \) is an abstraction. The entries in the dataset would actually be something like a set of pairs \( ( u_i, x_i ) \) for \(i = 1, \cdots, n \), where \(u_i\) is various information that identifies the individual concerned (name, address, race, date of birth, etc.). <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:4">↩</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-16T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-16T14:00:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Jonathan Ullman</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://differentialprivacy.org</id>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Website for the differential privacy research community</subtitle>
      <title>Differential Privacy</title>
      <updated>2020-08-27T23:27:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/08/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/08/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>Two sites on toroidal polyhedra: Bonnie Stewarts Hohlkörper and Alex Doskey’s virtual reality models of Stewart’s polyhedra (\(\mathbb{M}\)). Found while researching a new WP article on Stewart’s book Adventures Among the Toroids. The first link is in German but readable through Google translate and has lots of pretty pictures. The second needs VR software to be usable.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p>Two sites on toroidal polyhedra: <a href="https://www.spektrum.de/alias/raeumliche-geometrie/bonnie-stewarts-hohlkoerper/681891">Bonnie Stewarts Hohlkörper</a> and <a href="http://polyhedra.doskey.com/Stewart00.html">Alex Doskey’s virtual reality models of Stewart’s polyhedra</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104618649607830730">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Found while researching a new WP article on Stewart’s book <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adventures_Among_the_Toroids">Adventures Among the Toroids</a></em>. The first link is in German but readable through Google translate and has lots of pretty pictures. The second needs VR software to be usable.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.robertdickau.com/mapfolding.html">The map folding problem, illustrated by Robert Dickau</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104630030819531499">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). See <a href="https://www.robertdickau.com/default.html#math">Dickau’s home page</a> for many more mathematical illustrations, mostly of combinatorial enumeration problems and fractals.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>For some reason I wanted the name of a surface of revolution of a circular arc less than \(\pi\) around its chord (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104635297508909080">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lemon_(geometry)">Wikipedia said “lemon”</a> but sourced to MathWorld so I thought maybe MathWorld had made it up. Not so. Better sources say the same. And the surface for the complementary arc is an “apple”. It looks like a North American football but <a href="http://modellsammlung.uni-goettingen.de/index.php?lang=en&amp;r=5&amp;sr=17&amp;m=182">a “football” is a different surface of revolution, of constant positive Gaussian curvature</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://link.springer.com/journal/454/64/2">Special issue of <em>Discrete &amp; Computational Geometry</em> in memory of Branko Grünbaum</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104643955543481823">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). I think many of the research papers in it are interesting but I want to draw particular attention to <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00454-020-00214-y">the preface by Gil Kalai, Bojan Mohar, and Isabella Novik</a>, which provides a nice brief survey both of Grünbaum’s many contributions to discrete geometry and of the lines of active research they have led to.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://gallery.bridgesmathart.org/exhibitions/2020-Bridges-Conference">2020 Bridges Conference Mathematical Art Gallery</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104646771923669610">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Many are great but a couple of my favorites are <a href="http://gallery.bridgesmathart.org/exhibitions/2020-bridges-conference/conan-chadbourne">Conan Chadbourne’s grid partition enumeration</a> and <a href="http://gallery.bridgesmathart.org/exhibitions/2020-bridges-conference/mdlevin_publicmsncom">Martin Levin’s ten-tetrahedron tensegrity</a>. I didn’t participate but apparently the Bridges conference itself was held virtually a few days ago; see <a href="https://2020.bridgesmathart.org/">the conference site</a> for more including papers and videos.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://felixboiii.github.io/paper-plotter/">Paper plotter</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104655233453519187">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24091297">via</a>): tool to make 3d paper cut-and-assemble models of the graphs of bivariate functions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Kowhaiwhai (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104663925881930344">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).  are repeating decorative patterns used in New Zealand on Maori buildings. <a href="https://natlib.govt.nz/photos?text=kowhaiwhai&amp;commit=Search">The National Library of NZ has a number of good examples</a>, including the <a href="https://natlib.govt.nz/records/23146518">sketches of patterns by Tamati Ngakoho (top) and of a traditional Arawa pattern (bottom)</a> shown below. There’s also <a href="http://www.maori.org.nz/whakairo/default.php?pid=sp55&amp;parent=52">a brief guide to their interpretation online</a>. I can’t find much analysis of their structure, though, beyond pointing to frieze groups for their symmetries. The part that interests me more is their fractal-like swooping structure, reminiscent of (and in some cases directly modeled on) fern fronds.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Godber, Albert Percy, 1875-1949. Godber, Albert Percy, 1876-1949. Drawings of Maori rafter patterns or kowhaiwhai. 16. 22W. MA22; 17. 21W. MA21; and, 18. 25W. MA25. Puhoro. [1939-1947]. Ref: E-302-q-1-016/018. Alexander Turnbull Library, Wellington, New Zealand. From https://natlib.govt.nz/records/23146518" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/Kowhaiwhai.jpg"/></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.wired.com/story/why-wikipedia-decided-to-stop-calling-fox-a-reliable-source/">Why Wikipedia decided to stop calling Fox a reliable source</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104666160845673755">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Note however that Fox has not actually been deemed unreliable, in general. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Reliable_sources/Noticeboard/Archive_303#RfC:_Fox_News">The discussion had a no-consensus close</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://sinews.siam.org/Details-Page/untangling-random-polygons-and-other-things">Untangling random polygons</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104677553383067578">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>): repeatedly rescaling midpoint polygons always leads to an ellipse.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/kek-lapis-sarawak">The mesmerizing geometry of Malaysia’s most complex cakes:
Bold colors and designs set kek lapis Sarawak apart</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104680812259935603">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24116775">via</a>). As seen on The Great British Bake Off. These cakes have many parallel layers in bright colors, cut and rearranged to form complex designs. Mostly they involve 45 and 90-degree angles but at least one of the examples uses hexagonal symmetry instead.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>My Google Scholar profile has mildly broken down (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104683176033821672">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). When I go there, it offers me two new profiles to link as my coauthors: Man-Kwun Chiu and Matí Korman. They are indeed coauthors, from my new CCCG papers. But when I click to accept them as listed coauthors, it tells me I have too many coauthors, refuses to add them, and returns to offering me new profiles to link. I can see no way out of this other than to not accept my coauthors, which would be wrong. Google, fix this limitation!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A use for old CDs: <a href="https://momath.org/home/math-monday-those-circles-are-great/">cut them up and glue the pieces together to make visualizations of great circle arrangements on the sphere</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104690896919723051">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). The mathematical question posed by this is: for which numbers of great circles is it possible to make an arrangement in which all the arcs between pairs of neighbors have equal lengths?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://thonyc.wordpress.com/">The Renaissance Mathematicus</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@pkra/104694183591138626">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), an interesting blogger on the history of science. See also the <a href="https://thonyc.wordpress.com/2020/08/15/keep-the-renaissance-mathematicus-online/">crowdfunding drive to replace their old creaky iMac</a>, from which I found this.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-15T17:02:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-15T17:02:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-08-23T07:53:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
