<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-03-26T23:29:45Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-03-29-private-set-intersection-a-soft-introduction/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-03-29-private-set-intersection-a-soft-introduction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Private Set Intersection</title>
    <summary>Private Set Intersection (PSI) is a problem within the broader field of secure computation. The PSI problem There are two friends Alice and Bob such that Alice has a set of items $A=(a_1,\ldots,a_n)$ and Bob has the set $B=(b_1,\ldots,b_n)$. The goal is to design a protocol by which Alice and...</summary>
    <updated>2020-03-30T02:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-30T02:00:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:29:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3461</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2020/03/27/calendar-of-virtual-csecon-seminars/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Calendar of Virtual CS+Econ Seminars</title>
    <summary>Our community has some outstanding long-running virtual seminars, and there are many traditional seminars now moving to a virtual format.  Northwestern Ph.D. students Modibo Camara and Yiding Feng have a collection of them in a Google Calendar at Virtual CS+Econ Seminars.  Don’t miss any of the action! The topics include but not limited to theoretical […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Our community has some outstanding long-running virtual seminars, and there are many traditional seminars now moving to a virtual format.  Northwestern Ph.D. students <a href="https://mkcamara.github.io/">Modibo Camara</a> and <a href="https://sites.northwestern.edu/yiding/">Yiding Feng</a> have a collection of them in a Google Calendar at <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/virtualcseconseminars/">Virtual CS+Econ Seminars</a>.  Don’t miss any of the action!</p>
<p>The topics include but not limited to theoretical computer science, economic theory, theoretical machine learning, and econometrics.  The calendar currently tracks talks in <a href="https://mobile.twitter.com/CaltechEconThry">Caltech Econ Theory</a>, <a href="https://www.chamberlainseminar.org">Chamberlain Seminar in Econometrics</a>, <a href="https://www.ideal.northwestern.edu/">IDEAL</a>, <a href="http://md4sg.com">MD4SG</a>, and <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs">TCS+</a>. Send other relevant talk series or one-off events to Modibo and Yiding at <a class="c-link" href="mailto:VirtualCSEconSeminar@gmail.com" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">VirtualCSEconSeminar@gmail.com</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-26T22:24:40Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-26T22:24:40Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Hartline</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:25:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/040</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/040" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-040 |  Topology and adjunction in promise constraint satisfaction | 

	Andrei Krokhin, 

	Jakub Opršal, 

	Marcin Wrochna, 

	Stanislav Zivny</title>
    <summary>The approximate graph colouring problem concerns colouring a $k$-colourable
  graph with $c$ colours, where $c\geq k$. This problem naturally generalises
  to promise graph homomorphism and further to promise constraint satisfaction
  problems. Complexity analysis of all these problems is notoriously difficult.
  In this paper, we introduce two new techniques to analyse the complexity of
  promise CSPs: one is based on topology and the other on adjunction. We apply
  these techniques, together with the previously introduced algebraic approach,
  to obtain new NP-hardness results for a significant class of approximate
  graph colouring and promise graph homomorphism problems.</summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T14:25:32Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-26T14:25:32Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:24:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7660</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/03/26/technology-for-theory-covid-19-edition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Technology for theory: COVID-19 edition</title>
    <summary>The new coronavirus upended much of society, including our little corner of it. I believe at this point almost all theorists are teaching and doing research at home, and I thought it would be good to share some of the tools we use for doing so. Below I will describe my setup, but I hope […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The new coronavirus upended much of society, including our little corner of it. I believe at this point almost all theorists are teaching and doing research at home, and I thought it would be good to share some of the tools we use for doing so. Below I will describe my setup, but I hope other people share theirs too.</p>



<h2>Teaching and virtual whiteboards</h2>



<p>I am teaching using Zoom and using an iPad pro with a pencil to simulate a whiteboard. I use a laptop to connect to Zoom and for the camera, laptop, and chat window, and then join the iPad.There are several ways to connect an iPad to a Zoom session:</p>



<ol><li>Join the session from the iPad separately using the iPad Zoom app. (To do so you need to logout of your other account.)</li><li>Within desktop Zoom you can choose “share screen” and then one of the option is to join an iPad connected to the same wireless network as the laptop/desktop and use “screen mirroring”.</li><li>You can use a wired connection, which is either by just connecting through USB (in a Mac) or a complex combination of combining an adapter to take an HDMI signal out of an iPad with an HDMI capture card to stream this signal to the computer.</li></ol>



<p>I use option 2. The main reason I prefer it is because the application I use for a whiteboard –  <a href="https://www.goodnotes.com/">GoodNotes</a> – has a <a href="https://support.goodnotes.com/hc/en-us/articles/360001100576-How-to-use-Presentation-Mode">presentation mode</a> that behaves differently when you are connected to an external display or use AirPlay (which is what option 2 does). In this presentation mode the students don’t see your interface, and so you can Zoom, go to the page selector and more without it disturbing what they see. GoodNotes also has a great “laser pointer”. I set the pages at a landscape orientation,  and pre-write a good chunk of what I plan to present before the lecture. I also use the ability to “duplicate pages” to achieve the PowerPoint like effect of gradual reveal.</p>



<p>It is not perfect – I’ve discovered that the screen share sometimes stops refreshing and I need to leave GoodNotes and return to it for it to go back.</p>



<p>Monitoring the chat window and raised hands in Zoom is non-trivial. It helps a lot that I have a teaching assistant that participates in lecture and notices if I missed something. </p>



<p>Some people say that a “matte screen protector” such as <a href="https://paperlike.com/">PaperLike</a> makes the iPad more comfortable to write on – haven’t yet tried it.</p>



<p>I have a good Webcam (<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Logitech-BRIO-Conferencing-Recording-Streaming/dp/B01N5UOYC4">Logitech Brio</a>) but at the moment I’m not using it since it seems too taxing on my laptop and so I went back to the native webcam. I have a very nice wireless headset/mic combo (<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Jabra-Bluetooth-Headphones-Including-Packaging/dp/B072JWYJMC">Jabra Evolve 75</a>) that I am constantly using and have been very happy with. I particularly like the feature of being able to unmute and mute yourself by raising and lowering the mike. </p>



<p/>



<h2>Research</h2>



<p>For research Slack continues to extremely useful. For working jointly on a paper <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/">Overleaf </a> is of course great, but for maintaining a shared document it sometimes useful to use simpler platform that are not full fledged LaTeX. Some options include:</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://hackmd.io/">Hackmd.io</a> for markdown (supports LaTeX math)</li><li>Google docs of course. I heard about the <a href="https://gsuite.google.com/marketplace/app/autolatex_equations/850293439076">Auto-LaTeX plugin</a> but haven’t used it yet.</li><li><a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper">Dropbox Paper</a> supports LaTeX natively.</li></ul>



<p><a href="https://jamboard.google.com/">Google JamBoard</a> is an interactive whiteboard, also with an <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/jamboard/id1143591418">iPad app</a>. I haven’t tried it yet but it seems promising.</p>



<p/>



<h2>Keeping children busy</h2>



<p>For many people I imagine childcare is one of the most challenging aspects. At the moment at least the Cambridge Public Schools are not keeping my kids too busy. While probably most of their time is spent in non educational pursuits, we try to also encourage (i.e., bribe/extort/threaten/beg) them to do some learning. If your kids are interested in math, I highly recommend the courses offered by the <a href="https://artofproblemsolving.com/">Art of Problem Solving</a> (they also have a theory connection: one of their books was co-authored by theorist Ravi Boppana). For younger kids you can also try their <a href="https://beastacademy.com/">Beast Academy</a>.</p>



<p>The AOPS program is not free but over the years my kids (especially my 13 year old daughter Alma) have also spent a lot of time on the free and amazing <a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/">Khan Academy</a>. In fact, last year she was inspired enough by Khan’s JavaScript course to write the following poem which (for obvious reasons)  moved me very much:</p>



<p>Tending / Alma Barak</p>



<p>My mind is a desert<br/>of boredom<br/>of blankness<br/>of leaning-back-in-your-chairness<br/>and of simply-staring-at-the-ceilingness<br/>I kick at a crumpled<br/>deserted baby-blonde post-it<br/>with my spotted socked feet<br/>waiting for Aba to come.</p>



<p>We dive when he comes<br/>into the seas of Khan<br/>free-styling our way<br/>into the lakes of Java<br/>we pass codes we already<br/>knew<br/>while loops<br/>for loops<br/>arrays<br/>reminding me of what I’d learned</p>



<p>We frog-kick to an<br/>uncharted<br/>unfamiliar<br/>lagoon of code I don’t know<br/>sometimes I get swept away by currents<br/>of confusion<br/>but my aba, my dad<br/>grabs my hand<br/>and shows me the way through<br/>teaching me<br/>tending to me<br/>washing away the sands of boredom with the sea of Khan.</p>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-26T12:52:26Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-26T12:52:26Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:25:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11538</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11538" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Exact Query Complexity of Yes-No Permutation Mastermind</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1585180800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Moura El Ouali, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sauerland:Volkmar.html">Volkmar Sauerland</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.11538">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Mastermind is famous two-players game. The ?rst player (codemaker) chooses a
secret code which the second player (codebreaker) is supposed to crack within a
minimum number of code guesses (queries). Therefore, codemaker's duty is to
help codebreaker by providing a well-de?ned error measure between the secret
code and the guessed code after each query. We consider a variant, called
Yes-No AB-Mastermind, where both secret code and queries must be
repetition-free and the provided information by codemaker only indicates if a
query contains any correct position at all. For this Mastermind version with n
positions and $k\le n$ colors we prove a lower bound of
$\log_2(k+1-n)+\log_2(k+2-n)+\dots+\log_2(k)$ and an upper bound of
$n\log_2(n)+k$ on the number of queries necessary to break the secret code. For
the important case $k=n$, where both secret code and queries represent
permutations, our results imply an exact asymptotic complexity of
$\Theta(n\log_2(n))$ queries.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11527</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11527" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Implicit Representation of Swept Volumes based on Local Shapes and Movements</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1585180800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Laroche:Cl=eacute=ment.html">Clément Laroche</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.11527">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We introduce a new way to implicitly represent swept volumes in 3D. We first
implicitize the base volume and then apply the time-dependent rigid
transformation to build an implicit representation of the swept volume. This
way, we build a fitting representation, where geometric details generated by
the rigid transformation and details of the base volume itself are both taken
into account. This representation relies on a partition of a boundary box of
the swept volume according to portions of the space related either to parts of
the base volume or to time span of the transformation.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11490</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11490" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Two almost-circles, and two real ones</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1585180800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kov=aacute=cs:Zolt=aacute=n.html">Zoltán Kovács</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.11490">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Implicit locus equations in GeoGebra allow the user to do experiments with
generalization of the concept of ellipses, namely with $n$-ellipses. By
experimenting we obtain a geometric object that is very similar to a set of two
circles.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11468</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11468" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Hybrid MPI+Threads Approach to Particle Group Finding Using Union-Find</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1585180800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Willis:James_S=.html">James S. Willis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schaller:Matthieu.html">Matthieu Schaller</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gonnet:Pedro.html">Pedro Gonnet</a>, John C. Helly <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.11468">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Friends-of-Friends (FoF) algorithm is a standard technique used in
cosmological $N$-body simulations to identify structures. Its goal is to find
clusters of particles (called groups) that are separated by at most a cut-off
radius. $N$-body simulations typically use most of the memory present on a
node, leaving very little free for a FoF algorithm to run on-the-fly. We
propose a new method that utilises the common Union-Find data structure and a
hybrid MPI+threads approach. The algorithm can also be expressed elegantly in a
task-based formalism if such a framework is used in the rest of the
application. We have implemented our algorithm in the open-source cosmological
code, SWIFT. Our implementation displays excellent strong- and weak-scaling
behaviour on realistic problems and compares favourably (speed-up of 18x) over
other methods commonly used in the $N$-body community.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11450</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11450" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tight Algorithms for the Submodular Multiple Knapsack Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1585180800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sun:Xiaoming.html">Xiaoming Sun</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Jialin.html">Jialin Zhang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Zhijie.html">Zhijie Zhang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.11450">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Submodular function maximization has been a central topic in the theoretical
computer science community over the last decade. A plenty of well-performed
approximation algorithms have been designed for the maximization of
monotone/non-monotone submodular functions over a variety of constraints. In
this paper, we consider the submodular multiple knapsack problem (SMKP), which
is the submodular version of the well-studied multiple knapsack problem (MKP).
Roughly speaking, the problem asks to maximize a monotone submodular function
over multiple bins (knapsacks). Despite lots of known results in the field of
submodular maximization, surprisingly, it remains unknown whether or not this
problem enjoys the well-known tight $(1 - 1 / e)$-approximation. In this paper,
we answer this question affirmatively by proposing tight $(1 - 1 / e -
\epsilon)$-approximation algorithms for this problem in most cases.
</p>
<p>We first considered the case when the number of bins is a constant.
Previously a randomized approximation algorithm can obtain approximation ratio
$(1 - 1 / e-\epsilon)$ based on the involved continuous greedy technique. Here
we provide a simple combinatorial deterministic algorithm with ratio $(1-1/e)$
by directly applying the greedy technique. We then generalized the result to
arbitrary number of bins. When the capacity of bins are identical, we design a
combinatorial and deterministic algorithm which can achieve the tight
approximation ratio $(1 - 1 / e-\epsilon)$. When the ratio between the maximum
capacity and the minimum capacity of the bins is bounded by a constant, we
provide a $(1/2-\epsilon)$-approximation algorithm which is also combinatorial
and deterministic. We can further boost the approximation ratio to $(1 - 1 / e
- \epsilon)$ with the help of continuous greedy technique, which gives a tight
randomized approximation algorithm for this case.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11381</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11381" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Polymake.jl: A new interface to polymake</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1585180800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kaluba:Marek.html">Marek Kaluba</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lorenz:Benjamin.html">Benjamin Lorenz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Timme:Sascha.html">Sascha Timme</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.11381">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present the Julia interface Polymake.jl to polymake, a software for
research in polyhedral geometry. We describe the technical design and how the
integration into Julia makes it possible to combine polymake with
state-of-the-art numerical software.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11351</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11351" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Topology and adjunction in promise constraint satisfaction</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1585180800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Andrei Krokhin, Jakub Opršal, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wrochna:Marcin.html">Marcin Wrochna</a>, Stanislav Živný <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.11351">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The approximate graph colouring problem concerns colouring a $k$-colourable
graph with $c$ colours, where $c\geq k$. This problem naturally generalises to
promise graph homomorphism and further to promise constraint satisfaction
problems. Complexity analysis of all these problems is notoriously difficult.
In this paper, we introduce two new techniques to analyse the complexity of
promise CSPs: one is based on topology and the other on adjunction. We apply
these techniques, together with the previously introduced algebraic approach,
to obtain new NP-hardness results for a significant class of approximate graph
colouring and promise graph homomorphism problems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T23:20:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11313</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11313" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fair packing of independent sets</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1585180800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chiarelli:Nina.html">Nina Chiarelli</a>, Matjaž Krnc, Martin Milanič, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pferschy:Ulrich.html">Ulrich Pferschy</a>, Nevena Pivač, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schauer:Joachim.html">Joachim Schauer</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.11313">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this work we add a graph theoretical perspective to a classical problem of
fairly allocating indivisible items to several agents. Agents have different
profit valuations of items and we allow an incompatibility relation between
pairs of items described in terms of a conflict graph. Hence, every feasible
allocation of items to the agents corresponds to a partial coloring, that is, a
collection of pairwise disjoint independent sets. The sum of profits of
vertices/items assigned to one color/agent should be optimized in a maxi-min
sense. We derive complexity and algorithmic results for this problem, which is
a generalization of the classical Partition and Independent Set problems. In
particular, we show that the problem is strongly NP-complete in the classes of
bipartite graphs and their line graphs, and solvable in pseudo-polynomial time
in the classes of cocomparability graphs and biconvex bipartite graphs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11273</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11273" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Polynomial Kernels for Paw-free Edge Modification Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1585180800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cao:Yixin.html">Yixin Cao</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Ke:Yuping.html">Yuping Ke</a>, Hanchun Yuan <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.11273">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Let $H$ be a fixed graph. Given a graph $G$ and an integer $k$, the $H$-free
edge modification problem asks whether it is possible to modify at most $k$
edges in $G$ to make it $H$-free. Sandeep and Sivadasan (IPEC 2015) asks
whether the paw-free completion problem and the paw-free edge deletion problem
admit polynomial kernels. We answer both questions affirmatively by presenting,
respectively, $O(k)$-vertex and $O(k^4)$-vertex kernels for them. This is part
of an ongoing program that aims at understanding compressibility of $H$-free
edge modification problems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11086</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.11086" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Efficient Algorithms for Multidimensional Segmented Regression</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1585180800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Diakonikolas:Ilias.html">Ilias Diakonikolas</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Jerry.html">Jerry Li</a>, Anastasia Voloshinov <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.11086">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the fundamental problem of fixed design {\em multidimensional
segmented regression}: Given noisy samples from a function $f$, promised to be
piecewise linear on an unknown set of $k$ rectangles, we want to recover $f$ up
to a desired accuracy in mean-squared error. We provide the first sample and
computationally efficient algorithm for this problem in any fixed dimension.
Our algorithm relies on a simple iterative merging approach, which is novel in
the multidimensional setting. Our experimental evaluation on both synthetic and
real datasets shows that our algorithm is competitive and in some cases
outperforms state-of-the-art heuristics. Code of our implementation is
available at
\url{https://github.com/avoloshinov/multidimensional-segmented-regression}.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/039</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/039" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-039 |  Lower bounds on the sum of 25th-powers of univariates lead to complete derandomization of PIT | 

	Pranjal Dutta, 

	Nitin Saxena, 

	Thomas Thierauf</title>
    <summary>We consider the univariate polynomial $f_d:=(x+1)^d$ when represented as a sum of constant-powers of univariate polynomials. We define a natural measure for the model, the support-union, and conjecture that it is $\Omega(d)$ for $f_d$. 

We show a stunning connection of the conjecture to the two main problems in algebraic complexity: Polynomial Identity Testing (PIT) and VP vs VNP. Our conjecture on $f_d$ implies blackbox-PIT in P. Assuming the  Generalized Riemann Hypothesis (GRH), it also implies VP $\neq$ VNP. No such connection to PIT, from lower bounds on constant-powers representation of polynomials was known before. We establish that studying the expression of $(x+1)^d$, as the sum of $25^{th}$-powers of univariates, suffices to solve the two major open questions.   

In support, we show that our conjecture holds over the integer ring of any number field. We also establish a connection with the well-studied notion of matrix rigidity.</summary>
    <updated>2020-03-25T21:21:25Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-25T21:21:25Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:24:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7657</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/03/25/new-cs-theory-talk-aggragator/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>New CS theory talk aggragator</title>
    <summary>Shcachar Lovett has put together a new website aggregating information about virtual talks in CS theory: https://cstheorytalks.wordpress.com/  It has a Google calendar that people can add to their own, and a form to submit a new talk that automatically gets added to the Google calendar.  This can be a fantastic resource these days that almost […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Shcachar Lovett has put together a new website aggregating information about virtual talks in CS theory: <a href="https://cstheorytalks.wordpress.com/">https://cstheorytalks.wordpress.com/</a></p>



<p> It has a Google calendar that people can add to their own, and a form to submit a new talk that automatically gets added to the Google calendar. </p>



<p>This can be a fantastic resource these days that almost no one can travel – please publicize this and also submit to it talks that you are organizing.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-25T17:00:17Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-25T17:00:17Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:25:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/03/24/full-professor-w3-at-tu-dortmund-university-apply-by-april-15-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/03/24/full-professor-w3-at-tu-dortmund-university-apply-by-april-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Full Professor (W3)  at TU Dortmund University (apply by April 15, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at TU Dortmund University (https://tu-dortmund.de/en) is seeking to fill the position of a Full Professor Position (W3) in “Efficient Algorithms and Complexity Theory” commencing as soon as possible. Website: https://service.tu-dortmund.de/documents/18/2120803/Professor+W3+in+Efficient+Algorithms+and+Complexity+Theory.pdf/64785b24-b188-fbaa-e337-a2405661868f Email: thomas.schwentick@tu-dortmund.de</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at TU Dortmund University (<a href="https://tu-dortmund.de/en">https://tu-dortmund.de/en</a>) is seeking to fill the position of a Full Professor Position (W3) in “Efficient Algorithms and Complexity Theory” commencing as soon as possible.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://service.tu-dortmund.de/documents/18/2120803/Professor+W3+in+Efficient+Algorithms+and+Complexity+Theory.pdf/64785b24-b188-fbaa-e337-a2405661868f">https://service.tu-dortmund.de/documents/18/2120803/Professor+W3+in+Efficient+Algorithms+and+Complexity+Theory.pdf/64785b24-b188-fbaa-e337-a2405661868f</a><br/>
Email: thomas.schwentick@tu-dortmund.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-24T10:41:04Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-24T10:41:04Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:25:18Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7044506782591278327</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7044506782591278327/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/what-do-do-while-stuck-at-homeother.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7044506782591278327" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7044506782591278327" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/what-do-do-while-stuck-at-homeother.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What to do while ``stuck'' at home/Other thoughts on the virus</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lance had a great post on what to do while you are stuck at home, which is of course relevant to whats happening now. Lance's post is <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/what-to-do-while-stuck-at-home-part-i.html">here</a>.<br/>
<br/>
I will add to it, and then have other comments.<br/>
<br/>
1) In our current electronic society we can do a lot from home. Don't think of it as being `stuck at home'<br/>
<br/>
2) Lance points out that you should read a paper, read a textbook, etc. I of course agree and add some advice. Be Goldlocks!<br/>
<br/>
This paper is too hard (e.g., a text on quantum gravity)<br/>
<br/>
This paper is too easy (e.g., a discrete  math textbook for a freshman course)<br/>
<br/>
This paper is just right (e.g., working out the large canonical Ramsey theorem)<br/>
<br/>
3) If you catch up on your TV viewing on your DVR then beware: you will see commercials for Bloomberg.<br/>
<br/>
4) DO NOT binge watch TV.  You will hate yourself in the morning.<br/>
<br/>
5) Simons Inst Theory talks:<br/>
<br/>
<a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/videos">https://simons.berkeley.edu/videos</a><br/>
<br/>
TCS+ talks<br/>
<br/>
<a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks">https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks</a><br/>
<br/>
or<br/>
<a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/">https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/</a><br/>
<br/>
The Gathering for Gardner records all of their talks and puts the on you-tube<br/>
so goto youtube and search for Gathering for Gardners. These are Goldilocks talks since they<br/>
are easy but on stuff you prob don't know.<br/>
<br/>
6) Keep fit. I used to go on treadmill for 45 minutes a day, now I am doing an hour.<br/>
<br/>
7) Go for walks with a person who already shares your house, but avoid other people.<br/>
<br/>
8) Book reviews, surveys, orig articles, that you were putting off writing- now write them.<br/>
but see next item.<br/>
<br/>
10) Catch up on your blog reading. My favorite was Scott Aaronson's blog post about Davos:<a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4536">here</a>. I also read every single comment. I hated myself in the morning. So that part may have been a mistake.<br/>
<br/>
OTHER THOUGHTS<br/>
<br/>
1) Do you really have more free time? No commuting, no teaching, but you still have the rest of your job, and perhaps it is harder if some things are easier at work. And calling relatives and friends to make sure they are okay, and just to talk, is a great thing to do, but its time consuming.<br/>
<br/>
2) I'm beginning to lose track of what day-of-the-week it is since I don't have school to keep me on track, and I only watch TV shows on DVR so I watching a show on a day does not mean I know what day it is.<br/>
<br/>
3) Avoid being price-gouged. The first few days that I tried to buy TP for my mom on amazon (I do this in normal times--- I order lots for my mom on amazon--- she is tech shy. She is also over 90.) her usual brand was out of stock, and the other brands were either higher quality so higher prices or just<br/>
absurdly priced. She wisely said to wait a week. She was right- it was easy to get at the usual price.<br/>
<br/>
4) More generally, it seems like the shortages are people-created. For example, if in a store you see they are low on X, then you buy LOTS of X, and everyone does that, so then their really is a shortage of X. But I think thats calmed down some.<br/>
<br/>
5) It important to have a `we will recover from this, life will go on' attitude (while following the things ALL experts say- wash your hands a lot, drink lots of water, get lots of sleep, which is prob<br/>
good advice anyway) and hence I will try to, for the next few weeks, blog on NORMAL things----Hilberts's 10th problem, Large Ramsey, etc.<br/>
<br/>
ADDED LATER- there is a very nice contrarian view in the comment by Steve, the first comment. You should read that!<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-24T04:01:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-24T04:01:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T13:06:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4340</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/03/22/on-virus-containment-as-dieting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On virus containment as dieting</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Protezione Civile, the Italian equivalent of FEMA, holds a daily press conference to announce coronavirus data from the previous 24 hours. Today they had relatively good news, of which we hope to hear more soon. The Protezione Civile puts … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/03/22/on-virus-containment-as-dieting/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Protezione Civile, the Italian equivalent of FEMA, holds a daily press conference to announce coronavirus data from the previous 24 hours. Today they had relatively good news, of which we hope to hear more soon. The Protezione Civile  puts a lot of data online every day, on <a href="https://github.com/pcm-dpc/COVID-19">github</a>, which allows any interested party to monitor the situation and will allow people in other countries to see the effect of our various restrictive measures over time. </p>
<p>The graph below, which is courtesy of <a href="http://didattica.unibocconi.it/mypage/index.php?IdUte=202443&amp;cognome=LUCIBELLO&amp;nome=CARLO&amp;urlBackMy=">Carlo Lucibello</a>, shows the number of deaths in Italy on a logarithmic scale, compared with data from China from 36 days before.<br/>
<img alt="90441248_574660963135651_9199184881282711552_n" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4342" src="https://lucatrevisan.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/90441248_574660963135651_9199184881282711552_n.png?w=584"/><br/>
(Image credit: Carlo Lucibello)</p>
<p>At the start, Italian deaths rose like in China, at the same exponential rate. About twenty days after the lockdown of Wuhan, the Chinese data started deviating from the exponential rate and leveled off. In Italy, about ten days ago, there was a slowdown, which followed the institution of the “yellow zone” by about 15 days. The “yellow zone” measures closed schools, universities, museums, cinemas, and clubs, and restricted hours of bars and coffee shops, in Lombardy. Apparently, although these measures made a difference, they still allowed the spread of the virus to continue at an exponential rate.</p>
<p>On March 8, Lombardy was put on a stricter lockdown, with travel restrictions, and on March 10 the lockdown was extended to the rest of the country. So we may hope to see a stronger slowdown and maybe a leveling-off two or three weeks after these measures, that is, any day now. It may seem premature to ask this question, but what happens next?</p>
<p>Today the Italian government announced additional measures to facilitate “social distancing,” halting all “non-essential” manufacturing and other work activities, forbidding people from leaving the house to walk or jog (even alone), and  further restricting the cases in which it is allowed to travel between different cities.</p>
<p>These measures, which apply nationwide, are meant to be in place for two weeks. They will be economically devastating (even more so than the already devastating nationwide lockdown of March 10), and they will be difficult to keep in place for longer than the expected two weeks.</p>
<p>When a nationwide “lockdown” was first instituted, the prime minister announced it by saying “let’s be distant today in order to more warmly hug each other tomorrow”. In general, the spirit of these measures has been to suffer for a short time and then return to normal.</p>
<p>This feels like the national mood in general, and the government took today’s further restrictive measures somewhat reluctantly, because there was strong popular support for them.</p>
<p>Here I am worried that we are approaching this crisis the way many people attempt to lose weight: by going on a starvation diet, then losing some weight, then celebrating and finally gaining back more weight than they lost.</p>
<p>The point being that I worry about what will happen once the worst is over and these restrictive measures will be lifted. Until there is a vaccine or a cure, we will not be able to really go back to normal, and we will have to make some sustainable “lifestyle changes” to “maintain” what we got, just like people who maintain weight loss for a long time do so by making sustainable changes for the long term.</p>
<p>Concretely, we will need a very efficient system to monitor new cases and trace contacts, perhaps similar to Taiwan’s, and to follow the kind of stricter hygiene precautions in public places that have been common in East Asia since SARS. Let’s hope that we will have to worry about such problems soon.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-22T22:08:31Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-22T22:08:31Z</published>
    <category term="Milan"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:20:09Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/03/22/uci-ecological-preserve</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/03/22/uci-ecological-preserve.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>UCI Ecological Preserve</title>
    <summary>The UCI Ecological Preserve is a 60-acre patch of coastal sage scrub, adjoining the housing complex in which I live.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The <a href="http://ecopreserve.ucnrs.org/">UCI Ecological Preserve</a> is a 60-acre patch of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coastal_sage_scrub">coastal sage scrub</a>, adjoining <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_Hills,_Irvine">the housing complex in which I live</a>.</p>

<p>Like most of the rest of the world, I’m stuck at home for an indefinite duration, but the level of lockdown that we’re under allows us to go for walks outside, and like many of my neighbors (keeping a safe distance from each other) I took advantage of the opportunity to do so yesterday in the preserve. It was a gorgeous day, with very clear air from the recent rains: so clear that I could see individual buildings in downtown Los Angeles, 40 miles away.</p>

<p>I brought my camera along, but chose to focus on the nearby brush rather than the more distant views. Here’s one of my shots:</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="UCI Ecological Preserve" src="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/uciep/6-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;"/></p>

<p>The rest are in <a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/uciep/index.html">my online gallery</a>.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103869119505106054">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-22T15:28:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-22T15:28:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-03-22T22:44:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=19400</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/03/22/kelman-kindler-lifshitz-minzer-and-safra-towards-the-entropy-influence-conjecture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Kelman, Kindler, Lifshitz, Minzer, and Safra: Towards the Entropy-Influence Conjecture</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Let me briefly report on a remarkable new paper by Esty Kelman, Guy Kindler, Noam Lifshitz, Dor Minzer, and Muli Safra, Revisiting Bourgain-Kalai and Fourier Entropies. The paper describes substantial progress towards the Entropy-Influence conjecture, posed by Ehud Friedgut and … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/03/22/kelman-kindler-lifshitz-minzer-and-safra-towards-the-entropy-influence-conjecture/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Let me briefly report on a remarkable new paper by Esty Kelman, Guy Kindler, Noam Lifshitz, Dor Minzer, and Muli Safra, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.10579">Revisiting Bourgain-Kalai and Fourier Entropies</a>. The paper describes substantial progress towards the Entropy-Influence conjecture, posed by <a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/proc/1996-124-10/S0002-9939-96-03732-X/S0002-9939-96-03732-X.pdf">Ehud Friedgut and me in 1996</a>. (See this <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2007/08/16/gil-kalai-the-entropyinfluence-conjecture/">blog post from 2007</a>.)</p>
<p><strong>Abstract:</strong> The total inﬂuence of a function is a central notion in analysis of Boolean functions, and characterizing functions that have small total inﬂuence is one of the most fundamental questions associated with it. The KKL theorem and the Friedgut junta theorem give a strong characterization of such functions whenever the bound on the total inﬂuence is <em>o(logn)</em>, however, both results become useless when the total inﬂuence of the function is <em>ω(logn)</em>. The only case in which this logarithmic barrier has been broken for an interesting class of function was proved by Bourgain and Kalai, who focused on functions that are symmetric under large enough subgroups of <img alt="S_n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S_n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="S_n"/>.</p>
<p>In this paper, we revisit the key ideas of the Bourgain-Kalai paper. We prove a new general inequality that upper bounds the correlation between a Boolean function <em>f</em> and a real-valued, low degree function<em> g</em> in terms of their norms, Fourier coefﬁcients and total inﬂuences.</p>
<p>Some corollaries of this inequality are:</p>
<ol>
<li>The Bourgain-Kalai result.</li>
<li>A slightly weaker version of the Fourier-Entropy Conjecture. More precisely, we prove that the Fourier entropy of the low-degree part of<em> f</em> is at most <img alt="O(I[f]log^2 I[f])" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=O%28I%5Bf%5Dlog%5E2+I%5Bf%5D%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="O(I[f]log^2 I[f])"/>, where<em> I[f]</em> is the total inﬂuence of <em>f</em>. In particular, we conclude that the Fourier spectrum of a Boolean function is concentrated on at most <img alt="2O(I[f]log^2 I[f])" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2O%28I%5Bf%5Dlog%5E2+I%5Bf%5D%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="2O(I[f]log^2 I[f])"/> Fourier coefﬁcients.</li>
<li>Using well-known learning algorithms of sparse functions, the previous point implies that the class of functions with sub-logarithmic total inﬂuence (i.e. at most <img alt="O(\log n/(\log \log n)2))" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=O%28%5Clog+n%2F%28%5Clog+%5Clog+n%292%29%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="O(\log n/(\log \log n)2))"/> is learnable in polynomial time, using membership queries.</li>
</ol>
<h2><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/bour-kal.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-19597" height="435" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/bour-kal.png?w=640&amp;h=435" width="640"/></a></h2>
<p>Our theorem on influence under symmetry. From my <a href="https://youtu.be/35saSZ93PlI">videotaped lecture</a> on Jean Bourgain. See <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/01/02/jean/">this post</a> about Jean Bourgain.</p>
<h2>A few remarks:</h2>
<p>A) Given a Boolean function <img alt="f:\{-1,1\}^n\to \{-1,1\}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f%3A%5C%7B-1%2C1%5C%7D%5En%5Cto+%5C%7B-1%2C1%5C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="f:\{-1,1\}^n\to \{-1,1\}"/> let <img alt="f=\sum_{S \subset \{1,2,\dots ,n\}}\hat f(S)W_S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f%3D%5Csum_%7BS+%5Csubset+%5C%7B1%2C2%2C%5Cdots+%2Cn%5C%7D%7D%5Chat+f%28S%29W_S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="f=\sum_{S \subset \{1,2,\dots ,n\}}\hat f(S)W_S"/> be its Fourier-Walsh expansion. (Here <img alt="W_S(x_1,x_2,\dots ,x_n)=\prod_{i\in S}x_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W_S%28x_1%2Cx_2%2C%5Cdots+%2Cx_n%29%3D%5Cprod_%7Bi%5Cin+S%7Dx_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="W_S(x_1,x_2,\dots ,x_n)=\prod_{i\in S}x_i"/>.) The total influence <img alt="I(f)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=I%28f%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="I(f)"/> of <img alt="f" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="f"/> is described by</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="I(f)=\sum {S \subset \{1,2,\dots ,n\}}\hat f^2(S)|S|" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=I%28f%29%3D%5Csum+%7BS+%5Csubset+%5C%7B1%2C2%2C%5Cdots+%2Cn%5C%7D%7D%5Chat+f%5E2%28S%29%7CS%7C&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="I(f)=\sum {S \subset \{1,2,\dots ,n\}}\hat f^2(S)|S|"/>.</p>
<p>The spectral entropy <img alt="E(f)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=E%28f%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="E(f)"/> of <img alt="f" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="f"/> is defined by</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="E(f)=\sum_{S \subset \{1,2,\dots ,n\}}\hat f^2(S) \log (\hat f^2(S))" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=E%28f%29%3D%5Csum_%7BS+%5Csubset+%5C%7B1%2C2%2C%5Cdots+%2Cn%5C%7D%7D%5Chat+f%5E2%28S%29+%5Clog+%28%5Chat+f%5E2%28S%29%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="E(f)=\sum_{S \subset \{1,2,\dots ,n\}}\hat f^2(S) \log (\hat f^2(S))"/>.</p>
<p>The entropy-influence conjecture (here called the Fourier-entropy conjecture) asserts that for some universal constant <em>C</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="I(f) \ge C E(f)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=I%28f%29+%5Cge+C+E%28f%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="I(f) \ge C E(f)"/>.</p>
<p>B) One interesting feature of the conjecture is that the RHS is invariant under arbitrary linear transformations of <img alt="\{-1,1\}^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%7B-1%2C1%5C%7D%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\{-1,1\}^n"/> (regarded as an <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="n"/>-dimensional vector space) while the LHS is invariant only to permutations of the variables.</p>
<p>C) My paper with Jean Bourgain, <a href="http://www.ma.huji.ac.il/~kalai/bki.pdf">Influences of variables and threshold intervals under group symmetries</a>, describes lower bounds on total influences for Boolean function invariant under certain groups of permutations (of the variables). Those results are stronger (but more restrictive) than what the Entropy/influence conjecture directly implies. (This was overlooked for a while.) The new paper gives (much hoped for, see below) simpler proofs and stronger results compared to those in my paper with Jean Bourgain.</p>
<p>D) <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2018/12/29/jean-bourgain/#comment-509792">Ryan O’Donnel wrote</a> about Bourgain and some of his contributions to the analysis of Boolean functions:</p>
<p><em>“I spent close to 5 years understanding one 6-page paper of his (“On the distribution of the Fourier spectrum of Boolean functions”), and also close to 10 years understanding a 10-page paper of his (the k-SAT sharp threshold ‘appendix’). If anyone’s up for a challenge, I’m pretty sure no one on earth fully understands the second half of his paper “Influences of variables and threshold intervals under group symmetries” with Kalai (including Gil <img alt="&#x1F642;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f642.png" style="height: 1em;"/> )”</em></p>
<p>It looks that by now we have pretty good understanding and even some far-reaching progress regarding all three papers that Ryan mentioned. (It is unclear if we can hope now for an exponential spread of understanding for Bourgain’s proofs.)</p>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-22T10:43:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-22T10:43:00Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Open problems"/>
    <category term="Dor Minzer"/>
    <category term="Esty Kelman"/>
    <category term="Guy Kindler"/>
    <category term="Muli Safra"/>
    <category term="Noam Lifshitz"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:25:07Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/038</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/038" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-038 |  Error Correcting Codes for Uncompressed Messages | 

	Ofer Grossman, 

	Justin Holmgren</title>
    <summary>Most types of messages we transmit (e.g., video, audio, images, text) are not fully compressed, since they do not have known efficient and information theoretically optimal compression algorithms.  When transmitting such messages, standard error correcting codes fail to take advantage of the fact that messages are not fully compressed.

We show that in this setting, it is sub-optimal to use standard error correction. We consider a model where there is a set of “valid messages” which the sender may send that may not be efficiently compressible, but where it is possible for the receiver to recognize valid messages. In this model, we construct a (probabilistic) encoding procedure that achieves better tradeoffs between data rates and error-resilience (compared to just applying a standard error correcting code).

Additionally, our techniques yield improved efficiently decodable (probabilistic) codes for fully compressed messages (the standard setting where the set of valid messages is all binary strings) in the high-rate regime.</summary>
    <updated>2020-03-22T08:59:44Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-22T08:59:44Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:24:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16828</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/21/star-free-regular-languages-and-logic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Star-Free Regular Languages and Logic</title>
    <summary>Part 1 of a two-part series Daniel Winton is a graduate student in mathematics at Buffalo. He did an independent study with me last semester on descriptive complexity. Today we begin a two-part series written by Daniel on a foundational result in this area involving first-order logic and star-free languages. Dick and I have discussed […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Part 1 of a two-part series</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/21/star-free-regular-languages-and-logic/wintonprofile/" rel="attachment wp-att-16830"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16830" height="165" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/wintonprofile.png?w=150&amp;h=165" width="150"/></a></p>
<p>
Daniel Winton is a graduate student in mathematics at Buffalo. He did an independent study with me last semester on descriptive complexity.</p>
<p>
Today we begin a two-part series written by Daniel on a foundational result in this area involving first-order logic and <em>star-free</em> languages.</p>
<p>
Dick and I have discussed how GLL might act during the terrible coronavirus developments. We could collect quantitative and theoretical insights to help understand what is happening and possibly contribute to background for attempts to deal with it. Our March 12 <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/12/group-testing-for-the-coronavirus/">post</a> was this kind, and was on the wavelength of an actual advance in group testing announced in Israel two days ago, as noted in a <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/12/group-testing-for-the-coronavirus/#comment-109506">comment</a>. We could try to be even more active than that. We could focus on entertainment and diversion. Our annual St. Patrick’s Day <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/17/leprechauns-stay-home/">post</a> mentioned the ongoing <a href="https://en.candidates-2020.com/main">Candidates</a> <a href="https://new.uschess.org/news/2020-candidates-couch-potatoes/">Tournament</a> in chess, with links to follow it live 7am–noon EDT. Game analysis may be found <a href="http://www.thechessmind.net/">here</a> and elsewhere.</p>
<p>
Here we’re doing what we most often do: present a hopefully sprightly angle on a technical subject. We offer this in solidarity with the many professors and teachers who are beginning to teach online to many students. The subject of regular languages is the start of many theory courses and sometimes taught in high schools. Accordingly, Dick and I decided to prefix a section introducing regular languages as a teaching topic and motivating the use of logic, before entering the main body written by Daniel.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Regular Languages and Logic </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regular_language">Regular</a> languages are building blocks used throughout computer science. They can be defined in many ways. Two major types of descriptions are:</p>
<ol>
<li>
Regular expressions. For example, the regular expression <p/>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  b^{*}(a b^{*} a b^{*})^{*} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++b%5E%7B%2A%7D%28a+b%5E%7B%2A%7D+a+b%5E%7B%2A%7D%29%5E%7B%2A%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  b^{*}(a b^{*} a b^{*})^{*} "/></p>
<p>describes the set of strings over the alphabet <img alt="{\{a,b\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%7Ba%2Cb%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\{a,b\}}"/> that have an even number of <img alt="{a}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a}"/>‘s. </p>
</li><li>
Finite automata, for example:
</li></ol>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/21/star-free-regular-languages-and-logic/evendfa/" rel="attachment wp-att-16832"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-16832" height="140" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/evendfa.jpg?w=300&amp;h=140" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>
The regular languages defined by (1) and (2) are the same. All regular expressions have corresponding finite automata. This equivalence makes a powerful statement about the concept of regular languages. The more and more diverse definitions we have, the better we understand a concept. This leads us to consider other possible definitions.</p>
<p>
A natural kind of definition involves <em>logic</em>. Studying complexity classes through logic and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model_theory">model theory</a> has proven fruitful, creating <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Descriptive_complexity_theory">descriptive complexity</a> as an area. <em>Good news:</em> there are logic definitions equivalent to the regular languages. <em>Bad news:</em> they require going up to second-order logic. We would like to stay with first-order logic. So we ask:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> What kind of languages can we define using only first-order logic (FOL) and simple predicates like “the <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/>th bit of <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> is <img alt="{a}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a}"/>” and “place <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/> comes before place <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{j}"/>“? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The answer is the <em>star-free</em> languages, which form a subclass <img alt="{\mathsf{SF}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BSF%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{SF}}"/> of the regular languages. They were made famous in the book <em>Counter-Free Automata</em> by Robert McNaughton and Seymour Papert, where the equivalence to FOL was proved. A portentous fact is that these automata cannot solve simple tasks involving modular counting. Nor can <em>perceptrons</em>—the title subject of a book at the same time by Papert with Marvin Minsky, which we <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2016/01/27/minsky-the-theorist/">discussed</a> in relation to both AI and circuit complexity. This post will introduce <img alt="{\mathsf{SF}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BSF%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{SF}}"/> and FOL, prove the easier direction of the characterization, and give two lemmas for next time. The second post will present a new way to visualize the other direction. <b>The rest of this post is by Daniel Winton.</b></p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> No Stars Upon Thars </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
A regular language over an alphabet <img alt="{\Sigma}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma}"/> is one with an expression that can be obtained by applying the union, concatenation, and Kleene star operations a finite number of times on the empty set and singleton subsets of <img alt="{\Sigma}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma}"/>. Star-free languages are defined similarly but give up the use of the Kleene star <img alt="{{}^*}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7B%7D%5E%2A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{{}^*}"/> operation, while adding complementation (<img alt="{\sim}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csim%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sim}"/>) as a basic operation. The star-free languages are a subset of the regular languages, because regular languages are closed under complementation. </p>
<p>
Complementation often helps find star-free expressions that we ordinarily write using stars. For instance, if the alphabet <img alt="{\Sigma}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma}"/> is <img alt="{\{a,b\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%7Ba%2Cb%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\{a,b\}}"/>, then <img alt="{(\sim \emptyset)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28%5Csim+%5Cemptyset%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(\sim \emptyset)}"/> gives <img alt="{(a + b)^*}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28a+%2B+b%29%5E%2A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(a + b)^*}"/>. The following lemma gives a family of regular expressions that use Kleene star but are really star-free.</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Lemma 1</b> <em> The language given by taking the Kleene star operation on a union of singleton elements in an alphabet <img alt="{\Sigma}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma}"/> is star-free. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
<em>Proof.</em> For <img alt="{\Sigma=\{a_1, ..., a_n, b_1, ..., b_m\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%3D%5C%7Ba_1%2C+...%2C+a_n%2C+b_1%2C+...%2C+b_m%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma=\{a_1, ..., a_n, b_1, ..., b_m\}}"/> we have that <img alt="{(b_1+ ... + b_m)^*}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28b_1%2B+...+%2B+b_m%29%5E%2A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(b_1+ ... + b_m)^*}"/> can be given by </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \sim((\sim\emptyset) (a_1+ ... + a_n) (\sim\emptyset)). \quad  " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Csim%28%28%5Csim%5Cemptyset%29+%28a_1%2B+...+%2B+a_n%29+%28%5Csim%5Cemptyset%29%29.+%5Cquad++&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \sim((\sim\emptyset) (a_1+ ... + a_n) (\sim\emptyset)). \quad  "/></p>
<p><img alt="\Box" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5CBox&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\Box"/></p>
<p>For example, the language <img alt="{b^*ab^*ab^*}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%5E%2Aab%5E%2Aab%5E%2A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b^*ab^*ab^*}"/> is star-free because <img alt="{b^*}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%5E%2A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b^*}"/> is by this lemma. This idea extends also to forbidden substrings—e.g., the set of strings with no <img alt="{aa}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Baa%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{aa}"/> is <img alt="{\;\sim((\sim\emptyset)aa(\sim\emptyset))}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%3B%5Csim%28%28%5Csim%5Cemptyset%29aa%28%5Csim%5Cemptyset%29%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\;\sim((\sim\emptyset)aa(\sim\emptyset))}"/>. </p>
<p>
The language <img alt="{(ab + ba + bb)^*}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28ab+%2B+ba+%2B+bb%29%5E%2A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(ab + ba + bb)^*}"/> is not the same, however, and it is not star-free. Intuitively this is because it involves modular counting: an <img alt="{aa}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Baa%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{aa}"/> in an odd position is OK but not even. The parity language <img alt="{b^*(ab^*ab^*)^*}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%5E%2A%28ab%5E%2Aab%5E%2A%29%5E%2A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b^*(ab^*ab^*)^*}"/> from the introduction is another example. So <img alt="{\mathsf{SF}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BSF%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{SF}}"/> is a proper subset of the regular languages. What kind of subset? This is where having a third description via logic is really useful.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The First Order of Business </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
In addition to the familiar Boolean operations <img alt="{\wedge,\vee,\neg,\rightarrow,\leftrightarrow}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cwedge%2C%5Cvee%2C%5Cneg%2C%5Crightarrow%2C%5Cleftrightarrow%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\wedge,\vee,\neg,\rightarrow,\leftrightarrow}"/> and truth values, <em>first-order logic</em> provides variables that range over elements of a structure and quantifiers on those variables. Since we will be concerned with Boolean strings <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/>, the variables will range over places in the string <img alt="{0,\dots,n-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%2C%5Cdots%2Cn-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0,\dots,n-1}"/>, where <img alt="{n = |x|}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn+%3D+%7Cx%7C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n = |x|}"/>. A logic also specifies a set of predicates that relate variables and interact with the structure. For strings we have:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<img alt="{X_c(i)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX_c%28i%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{X_c(i)}"/>, meaning that the symbol indexed <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/> in <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> is the character <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/>. The logic gives one such predicate for each <img alt="{c \in \Sigma}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc+%5Cin+%5CSigma%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c \in \Sigma}"/>. <p/>
</li><li>
<img alt="{i &lt; j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi+%3C+j%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i &lt; j}"/>, with the obvious meaning for natural numbers <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/> and <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{j}"/>.
</li></ul>
<p>
We can take the <img alt="{X_c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX_c%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{X_c}"/> for granted since we are talking about strings, but we need to say that predicates like <img alt="{i + j = k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi+%2B+j+%3D+k%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i + j = k}"/> and <img alt="{i\cdot j = k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%5Ccdot+j+%3D+k%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i\cdot j = k}"/> are excluded, so we call this <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}"/>. We could define equality by <img alt="{i = j \equiv \lnot(i &lt; j \lor j &lt; i)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi+%3D+j+%5Cequiv+%5Clnot%28i+%3C+j+%5Clor+j+%3C+i%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i = j \equiv \lnot(i &lt; j \lor j &lt; i)}"/> but we regard equality as inherent.</p>
<p>
We can use <img alt="{&lt;}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{&lt;}"/> to define the successor relation <img alt="{S(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S(i,j)}"/>, which denotes that position <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{j}"/> comes immediately after position <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/>:</p>
<p/><p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  S(i,j) \equiv i&lt;j \land \forall k (i&lt;k \rightarrow j\leq k). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++S%28i%2Cj%29+%5Cequiv+i%3Cj+%5Cland+%5Cforall+k+%28i%3Ck+%5Crightarrow+j%5Cleq+k%29.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  S(i,j) \equiv i&lt;j \land \forall k (i&lt;k \rightarrow j\leq k). "/></p>
<p>
Note the use of quantifiers. We can use quantifiers to say things about the string <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> too. For instance, the language <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> of strings having no <img alt="{aa}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Baa%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{aa}"/> substrings is defined by the logical sentence</p>
<p/><p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \sigma_L = (\forall i,j):S(i,j) \rightarrow \neg (X_a(i) \land X_a(j)). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Csigma_L+%3D+%28%5Cforall+i%2Cj%29%3AS%28i%2Cj%29+%5Crightarrow+%5Cneg+%28X_a%28i%29+%5Cland+X_a%28j%29%29.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \sigma_L = (\forall i,j):S(i,j) \rightarrow \neg (X_a(i) \land X_a(j)). "/></p>
<p>
It is implicit here that <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/> and <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{j}"/> are always in-bounds. If <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> were a legal constant with <img alt="{X_c(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX_c%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{X_c(n)}"/> always false then a string like <img alt="{bbba}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bbbba%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{bbba}"/> (which belongs to <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/>) would falsify <img alt="{\sigma_L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csigma_L%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sigma_L}"/> with <img alt="{i = n-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi+%3D+n-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i = n-1}"/> and <img alt="{j = n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj+%3D+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{j = n}"/>. </p>
<p>
How big is <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}"/>? We'll see it is no more and no less than <img alt="{\mathsf{SF}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BSF%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{SF}}"/>.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> From SF to FO </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
To prove that any language <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> in <img alt="{\mathsf{SF}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BSF%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{SF}}"/> has a definition in <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}}"/>, we will not only give a sentence <img alt="{\sigma_L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csigma_L%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sigma_L}"/> but also a <em>formula</em> <img alt="{\phi_L(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi_L%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi_L(i,j)}"/>. We will define this formula to indicate that for a given string <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/>, the portion of the string between indices <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/> and <img alt="{j-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{j-1}"/> is in <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/>. Then for the correct choices of <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/> and <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{j}"/>, <img alt="{\phi_L(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi_L%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi_L(i,j)}"/> gives <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/>. We define <img alt="{\phi}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi}"/> to test middle portions of strings, because it handles lengths better for the induction in the concatenation case. </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 2</b> <em/></p><em>
<p>
Every language in <img alt="{\mathsf{SF}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BSF%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{SF}}"/> is definable in <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}"/>.</p>
</em><p><em>
</em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
The proof is a nice example where “building up” to prove something more general—involving two extra variables—makes induction go smoothly.</p>
<p>
<em>Proof:</em>  Let <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> be a star-free regular language and <img alt="{L'=\{\langle x, i ,j \rangle:}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%27%3D%5C%7B%5Clangle+x%2C+i+%2Cj+%5Crangle%3A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L'=\{\langle x, i ,j \rangle:}"/> the portion of the string <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> between indices <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/> (inclusive) and <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{j}"/> (exclusive) is contained in <img alt="{L\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L\}}"/>. Let <img alt="{\phi_L(i,j)\in \sf{FO}[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi_L%28i%2Cj%29%5Cin+%5Csf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi_L(i,j)\in \sf{FO}[&lt;]}"/> be the formula denoting that for a given string <img alt="{x, x[i,j)\in L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%2C+x%5Bi%2Cj%29%5Cin+L%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x, x[i,j)\in L}"/>, that is, <img alt="{\phi_L(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi_L%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi_L(i,j)}"/> is the representation of <img alt="{L'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L'}"/> in <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}"/>. We will show that such a <img alt="{\phi_L(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi_L%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi_L(i,j)}"/> exists via induction on <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/>. This is sufficient, as for a given symbol <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> that always represents the length of a string <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/>, <img alt="{\phi_L(0,n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi_L%280%2Cn%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi_L(0,n)}"/> is the formula in <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}"/> representing the language <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/>. </p>
<p>
First, we must show that <img alt="{\phi_L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi_L%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi_L}"/> is in <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}"/> for <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> one of the basis languages, <img alt="{\emptyset, \epsilon}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cemptyset%2C+%5Cepsilon%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\emptyset, \epsilon}"/>, and <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/>, for some <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/> in <img alt="{\Sigma}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma}"/>. We have that:</p>
<p/><p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  \phi_\emptyset(i,j) &amp;=&amp; \texttt{false};\\ \phi_\epsilon(i,j) &amp;=&amp; i=j;\\ \phi_c(i,j) &amp;=&amp; (X_c(i)\land S(i,j)). \end{array} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Brcl%7D++%5Cphi_%5Cemptyset%28i%2Cj%29+%26%3D%26+%5Ctexttt%7Bfalse%7D%3B%5C%5C+%5Cphi_%5Cepsilon%28i%2Cj%29+%26%3D%26+i%3Dj%3B%5C%5C+%5Cphi_c%28i%2Cj%29+%26%3D%26+%28X_c%28i%29%5Cland+S%28i%2Cj%29%29.+%5Cend%7Barray%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  \phi_\emptyset(i,j) &amp;=&amp; \texttt{false};\\ \phi_\epsilon(i,j) &amp;=&amp; i=j;\\ \phi_c(i,j) &amp;=&amp; (X_c(i)\land S(i,j)). \end{array} "/></p>
<p>
Now, we must show that given star-free languages <img alt="{L_1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL_1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L_1}"/> and <img alt="{L_2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL_2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L_2}"/> with FO<img alt="{[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{[&lt;]}"/> translations <img alt="{\psi_1(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpsi_1%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\psi_1(i,j)}"/> and <img alt="{\psi_2(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpsi_2%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\psi_2(i,j)}"/> respectively, we have <img alt="{\phi_{L_1\cup L_2}(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi_%7BL_1%5Ccup+L_2%7D%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi_{L_1\cup L_2}(i,j)}"/>, <img alt="{\phi_{L_1\cdot L_2}(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi_%7BL_1%5Ccdot+L_2%7D%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi_{L_1\cdot L_2}(i,j)}"/>, and <img alt="{\phi_{\sim L_1}(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cphi_%7B%5Csim+L_1%7D%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\phi_{\sim L_1}(i,j)}"/> are in <img alt="{\sf{FO}[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sf{FO}[&lt;]}"/>. Then: </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  \phi_{L_1\cup L_2}(i,j)&amp;=&amp;\psi_1(i,j) \lor \psi_2(i,j);\\ \\ \phi_{L_1\cdot L_2}(i,j)&amp;=&amp;\exists k(i\leq k \land k \leq j) (\psi_1(i,k) \land \psi_2(k,j));\\ \\ \phi_{\sim L_1}(i,j)&amp;=&amp;\lnot \psi_{1}(i,j). \end{array} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Brcl%7D++%5Cphi_%7BL_1%5Ccup+L_2%7D%28i%2Cj%29%26%3D%26%5Cpsi_1%28i%2Cj%29+%5Clor+%5Cpsi_2%28i%2Cj%29%3B%5C%5C+%5C%5C+%5Cphi_%7BL_1%5Ccdot+L_2%7D%28i%2Cj%29%26%3D%26%5Cexists+k%28i%5Cleq+k+%5Cland+k+%5Cleq+j%29+%28%5Cpsi_1%28i%2Ck%29+%5Cland+%5Cpsi_2%28k%2Cj%29%29%3B%5C%5C+%5C%5C+%5Cphi_%7B%5Csim+L_1%7D%28i%2Cj%29%26%3D%26%5Clnot+%5Cpsi_%7B1%7D%28i%2Cj%29.+%5Cend%7Barray%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  \phi_{L_1\cup L_2}(i,j)&amp;=&amp;\psi_1(i,j) \lor \psi_2(i,j);\\ \\ \phi_{L_1\cdot L_2}(i,j)&amp;=&amp;\exists k(i\leq k \land k \leq j) (\psi_1(i,k) \land \psi_2(k,j));\\ \\ \phi_{\sim L_1}(i,j)&amp;=&amp;\lnot \psi_{1}(i,j). \end{array} "/></p>
<p>
Since star-free languages can be obtained by applying the union, concatenation, and complementation operations a finite number of times on <img alt="{\emptyset}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cemptyset%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\emptyset}"/> and singleton subsets of <img alt="{\Sigma}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma}"/>, this completes the proof of <img alt="{\mathsf{SF} \subseteq \mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BSF%7D+%5Csubseteq+%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{SF} \subseteq \mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}"/>. <img alt="\Box" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5CBox&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\Box"/></p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Two Lemmas For Next Time </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Prefatory to showing (in the next post) that <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;]}"/> is contained in <img alt="{\mathsf{SF}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BSF%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{SF}}"/>, we prove properties about substrings on the ends of star-free languages, rather than in the middle as with the trick in the proof of Theorem 2.</p>
<p>
Let <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> be a language over an alphabet <img alt="{\Sigma}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma}"/> and <img alt="{w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w}"/> be a word in <img alt="{\Sigma^n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%5En%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma^n}"/> for some <img alt="{n\in \mathbb{N}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5Cin+%5Cmathbb%7BN%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n\in \mathbb{N}}"/>. Define <img alt="{L/w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%2Fw%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L/w}"/>, the <em>right quotient</em> of <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> by <img alt="{w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w}"/>, by <img alt="{L/w =\{v: vw \in L\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%2Fw+%3D%5C%7Bv%3A+vw+%5Cin+L%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L/w =\{v: vw \in L\}}"/> and <img alt="{L\backslash w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%5Cbackslash+w%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L\backslash w}"/>, the <em>left quotient</em> of <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> by <img alt="{w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w}"/>, by <img alt="{L\backslash w=\{v:wv \in L\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%5Cbackslash+w%3D%5C%7Bv%3Awv+%5Cin+L%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L\backslash w=\{v:wv \in L\}}"/>.  First we handle right quotients:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Lemma 3</b> <em> If <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> is star-free, then <img alt="{L/w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%2Fw%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L/w}"/> is star-free. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
<em>Proof:</em>  For any word <img alt="{w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w}"/> over <img alt="{\Sigma}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma}"/> we define a function <img alt="{f_w(\alpha)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_w%28%5Calpha%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_w(\alpha)}"/> by <img alt="{f_w(\alpha)=\alpha'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_w%28%5Calpha%29%3D%5Calpha%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_w(\alpha)=\alpha'}"/> where <img alt="{L(\alpha')=L(\alpha)/w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%28%5Calpha%27%29%3DL%28%5Calpha%29%2Fw%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L(\alpha')=L(\alpha)/w}"/>. If <img alt="{w = \epsilon}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw+%3D+%5Cepsilon%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w = \epsilon}"/>, then <img alt="{f_w(\alpha)=\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_w%28%5Calpha%29%3D%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_w(\alpha)=\alpha}"/>, and so the statement of the lemma trivially holds. So let <img alt="{w = vc}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw+%3D+vc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w = vc}"/> for some string <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> and character <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/>. Note that <img alt="{L/(vc) = (L/c)/v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%2F%28vc%29+%3D+%28L%2Fc%29%2Fv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L/(vc) = (L/c)/v}"/>. Thus <img alt="{f_{vc}(\alpha) = f_v(f_c(\alpha))}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_%7Bvc%7D%28%5Calpha%29+%3D+f_v%28f_c%28%5Calpha%29%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_{vc}(\alpha) = f_v(f_c(\alpha))}"/> for all <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/>. Hence it suffices to define <img alt="{f_c(\alpha)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_c%28%5Calpha%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_c(\alpha)}"/> for any single character <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/> by recursion on <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/>. We have:</p>
<p/><p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  f_c(\emptyset)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset;\\ f_c(\epsilon)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset;\\ f_c(c)&amp;=&amp;\epsilon;\\ f_c(a)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset, \end{array} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Brcl%7D++f_c%28%5Cemptyset%29%26%3D%26%5Cemptyset%3B%5C%5C+f_c%28%5Cepsilon%29%26%3D%26%5Cemptyset%3B%5C%5C+f_c%28c%29%26%3D%26%5Cepsilon%3B%5C%5C+f_c%28a%29%26%3D%26%5Cemptyset%2C+%5Cend%7Barray%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  f_c(\emptyset)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset;\\ f_c(\epsilon)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset;\\ f_c(c)&amp;=&amp;\epsilon;\\ f_c(a)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset, \end{array} "/></p>
<p>
and recursively:</p>
<p/><p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  f_c(\alpha \cup\beta)&amp;=&amp;f_c(\alpha) \cup f_c(\beta);\\\\ f_c(\alpha\cdot\beta)&amp;=&amp;\begin{cases} \alpha\cdot f_c(\beta) &amp; \epsilon\not\in L(\beta), \\ \alpha\cdot f_c(\beta) \cup f_c(\alpha) &amp; otherwise\text{;} \end{cases}\\\\ f_c(\sim\alpha)&amp;=&amp;\sim f_c(\alpha). \end{array} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Brcl%7D++f_c%28%5Calpha+%5Ccup%5Cbeta%29%26%3D%26f_c%28%5Calpha%29+%5Ccup+f_c%28%5Cbeta%29%3B%5C%5C%5C%5C+f_c%28%5Calpha%5Ccdot%5Cbeta%29%26%3D%26%5Cbegin%7Bcases%7D+%5Calpha%5Ccdot+f_c%28%5Cbeta%29+%26+%5Cepsilon%5Cnot%5Cin+L%28%5Cbeta%29%2C+%5C%5C+%5Calpha%5Ccdot+f_c%28%5Cbeta%29+%5Ccup+f_c%28%5Calpha%29+%26+otherwise%5Ctext%7B%3B%7D+%5Cend%7Bcases%7D%5C%5C%5C%5C+f_c%28%5Csim%5Calpha%29%26%3D%26%5Csim+f_c%28%5Calpha%29.+%5Cend%7Barray%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  f_c(\alpha \cup\beta)&amp;=&amp;f_c(\alpha) \cup f_c(\beta);\\\\ f_c(\alpha\cdot\beta)&amp;=&amp;\begin{cases} \alpha\cdot f_c(\beta) &amp; \epsilon\not\in L(\beta), \\ \alpha\cdot f_c(\beta) \cup f_c(\alpha) &amp; otherwise\text{;} \end{cases}\\\\ f_c(\sim\alpha)&amp;=&amp;\sim f_c(\alpha). \end{array} "/></p>
<p>
In general, if <img alt="{w = c_1 c_2 \cdots c_{n-1} c_n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw+%3D+c_1+c_2+%5Ccdots+c_%7Bn-1%7D+c_n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w = c_1 c_2 \cdots c_{n-1} c_n}"/>, then</p>
<p/><p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle L/w = f_{c_1}(f_{c_2}(\dots f_{c_{n-1}}(f_{c_n}(\alpha))\dots))." class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+L%2Fw+%3D+f_%7Bc_1%7D%28f_%7Bc_2%7D%28%5Cdots+f_%7Bc_%7Bn-1%7D%7D%28f_%7Bc_n%7D%28%5Calpha%29%29%5Cdots%29%29.&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle L/w = f_{c_1}(f_{c_2}(\dots f_{c_{n-1}}(f_{c_n}(\alpha))\dots))."/></p>
<p><img alt="\Box" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5CBox&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\Box"/></p>
<blockquote><p><b>Lemma 4</b> <em> If <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> is star-free, then <img alt="{L\backslash w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%5Cbackslash+w%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L\backslash w}"/> is star-free. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The proof of Lemma 4 is similar to the proof of Lemma 3. The main differences lie in the concatenation subcase for the <img alt="{w=c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw%3Dc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w=c}"/> case and the order of quotienting when using this operation repeatedly.</p>
<p>
<em>Proof:</em>  For any word <img alt="{w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w}"/> over <img alt="{\Sigma}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CSigma%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Sigma}"/> we define a function <img alt="{f_w(\alpha)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_w%28%5Calpha%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_w(\alpha)}"/> by <img alt="{f_w(\alpha)=\alpha'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_w%28%5Calpha%29%3D%5Calpha%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_w(\alpha)=\alpha'}"/> where <img alt="{L(\alpha')=L(\alpha)\backslash w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%28%5Calpha%27%29%3DL%28%5Calpha%29%5Cbackslash+w%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L(\alpha')=L(\alpha)\backslash w}"/>. If <img alt="{w = \epsilon}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw+%3D+%5Cepsilon%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w = \epsilon}"/>, then <img alt="{f_w(\alpha)=\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_w%28%5Calpha%29%3D%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_w(\alpha)=\alpha}"/>, and so the statement of the lemma trivially holds. So let <img alt="{w = vc}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw+%3D+vc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w = vc}"/> for some string <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> and character <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/>. Note that <img alt="{L\backslash(vc) = (L\backslash v)\backslash c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%5Cbackslash%28vc%29+%3D+%28L%5Cbackslash+v%29%5Cbackslash+c%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L\backslash(vc) = (L\backslash v)\backslash c}"/>. Thus <img alt="{f_{vc}(\alpha) = f_c(f_v(\alpha))}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_%7Bvc%7D%28%5Calpha%29+%3D+f_c%28f_v%28%5Calpha%29%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_{vc}(\alpha) = f_c(f_v(\alpha))}"/> for all <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/>. Hence it suffices to define <img alt="{f_c(\alpha)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_c%28%5Calpha%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_c(\alpha)}"/> for any single character <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/> by recursion on <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/>. We have:</p>
<p/><p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  f_c(\emptyset)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset;\\ f_c(\epsilon)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset;\\ f_c(c)&amp;=&amp;\epsilon;\\ f_c(a)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset.\\ \end{array} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Brcl%7D++f_c%28%5Cemptyset%29%26%3D%26%5Cemptyset%3B%5C%5C+f_c%28%5Cepsilon%29%26%3D%26%5Cemptyset%3B%5C%5C+f_c%28c%29%26%3D%26%5Cepsilon%3B%5C%5C+f_c%28a%29%26%3D%26%5Cemptyset.%5C%5C+%5Cend%7Barray%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  f_c(\emptyset)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset;\\ f_c(\epsilon)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset;\\ f_c(c)&amp;=&amp;\epsilon;\\ f_c(a)&amp;=&amp;\emptyset.\\ \end{array} "/></p>
<p>
and recursively:</p>
<p/><p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  f_c(\alpha\cup\beta)&amp;=&amp;f_c(\alpha)\cup f_c(\beta);\\\\ f_c(\alpha\cdot\beta)&amp;=&amp;\begin{cases} f_c(\alpha)\cdot\beta &amp; \epsilon\not\in L(\alpha), \\ f_c(\alpha)\cdot\beta \cup f_c\beta) &amp; otherwise\text{;} \end{cases}\\\\ f_c(\sim \alpha)&amp;=&amp;\sim f_c(\alpha). \end{array} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Brcl%7D++f_c%28%5Calpha%5Ccup%5Cbeta%29%26%3D%26f_c%28%5Calpha%29%5Ccup+f_c%28%5Cbeta%29%3B%5C%5C%5C%5C+f_c%28%5Calpha%5Ccdot%5Cbeta%29%26%3D%26%5Cbegin%7Bcases%7D+f_c%28%5Calpha%29%5Ccdot%5Cbeta+%26+%5Cepsilon%5Cnot%5Cin+L%28%5Calpha%29%2C+%5C%5C+f_c%28%5Calpha%29%5Ccdot%5Cbeta+%5Ccup+f_c%5Cbeta%29+%26+otherwise%5Ctext%7B%3B%7D+%5Cend%7Bcases%7D%5C%5C%5C%5C+f_c%28%5Csim+%5Calpha%29%26%3D%26%5Csim+f_c%28%5Calpha%29.+%5Cend%7Barray%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  f_c(\alpha\cup\beta)&amp;=&amp;f_c(\alpha)\cup f_c(\beta);\\\\ f_c(\alpha\cdot\beta)&amp;=&amp;\begin{cases} f_c(\alpha)\cdot\beta &amp; \epsilon\not\in L(\alpha), \\ f_c(\alpha)\cdot\beta \cup f_c\beta) &amp; otherwise\text{;} \end{cases}\\\\ f_c(\sim \alpha)&amp;=&amp;\sim f_c(\alpha). \end{array} "/></p>
<p>
In general, if <img alt="{w = c_1 c_2 \cdots c_{n-1} c_n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw+%3D+c_1+c_2+%5Ccdots+c_%7Bn-1%7D+c_n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w = c_1 c_2 \cdots c_{n-1} c_n}"/>, then</p>
<p/><p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle L\backslash w = f_{c_n}(f_{c_{n-1}}(\dots f_{c_{2}}(f_{c_1}(\alpha))\dots))." class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+L%5Cbackslash+w+%3D+f_%7Bc_n%7D%28f_%7Bc_%7Bn-1%7D%7D%28%5Cdots+f_%7Bc_%7B2%7D%7D%28f_%7Bc_1%7D%28%5Calpha%29%29%5Cdots%29%29.&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle L\backslash w = f_{c_n}(f_{c_{n-1}}(\dots f_{c_{2}}(f_{c_1}(\alpha))\dots))."/></p>
<p><img alt="\Box" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5CBox&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\Box"/></p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
There are richer systems such as <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}(+)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%28%2B%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}(+)}"/> and <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}(+,\cdot)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%28%2B%2C%5Ccdot%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}(+,\cdot)}"/>. Note that <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}(+)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%28%2B%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}(+)}"/> allows defining the <img alt="{&lt;}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{&lt;}"/> relation via <img alt="{i &lt; j \equiv (\exists k) \lnot(k= 0) \land i + k = j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi+%3C+j+%5Cequiv+%28%5Cexists+k%29+%5Clnot%28k%3D+0%29+%5Cland+i+%2B+k+%3D+j%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i &lt; j \equiv (\exists k) \lnot(k= 0) \land i + k = j}"/>. We can define non-regular languages such as <img alt="{{a^n b^n}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7Ba%5En+b%5En%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{{a^n b^n}}"/> in <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}(+)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%28%2B%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}(+)}"/>. The class <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}(+,\times)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%28%2B%2C%5Ctimes%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}(+,\times)}"/> famously equals uniform <img alt="{\mathsf{AC^0}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BAC%5E0%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{AC^0}}"/>, see chapter 5 of Neil Immerman's <a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-1-4612-0539-5">book</a> <em>Descriptive Complexity</em>. Thus we hope our new style for proving <img alt="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;] \subseteq \mathsf{SF}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BFO%7D%5B%3C%5D+%5Csubseteq+%5Cmathsf%7BSF%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{FO}[&lt;] \subseteq \mathsf{SF}}"/> (to come in the next part) will build a nice foundation for visualizing these higher results.</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-21T20:54:45Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-21T20:54:45Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Teaching"/>
    <category term="trick"/>
    <category term="Daniel Winton"/>
    <category term="Robert McNaughton"/>
    <category term="Seymour Papert"/>
    <author>
      <name>KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:25:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/037</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/037" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-037 |  Failure of Feasible Disjunction Property for $k$-DNF Resolution and NP-hardness of Automating It | 

	Michal Garlik</title>
    <summary>We show that for every integer $k \geq 2$, the Res($k$) propositional proof system does not have the weak feasible disjunction property. Next, we generalize a recent result of Atserias and Müller [FOCS, 2019] to Res($k$). We show that if NP is not included in P (resp. QP, SUBEXP) then for every integer $k \geq 1$, Res($k$) is not automatable in polynomial (resp. quasi-polynomial, subexponential) time.</summary>
    <updated>2020-03-21T11:53:33Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-21T11:53:33Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:24:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4331</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/03/20/what-is-next/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What is next?</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Greetings from the future! The progression of covid-19 in Italy is running about eight days ahead of France and Spain and about 16 days ahead of the United States. Here in Lombardy, which is about ten days ahead of NYC, … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/03/20/what-is-next/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Greetings from the future! The progression of covid-19 in Italy is running about eight days ahead of France and Spain and about 16 days ahead of the United States. Here in Lombardy, which is about ten days ahead of NYC, we have been “sheltering at home” for 13 days already.</p>
<p>How is social distancing working out for me? I thought that I was well prepared for it, but it is still not easy. I have started to talk to the furniture, and apparently this is perfectly normal, at least as long as the furniture does not talk back. </p>
<p>As I have been telling my dining table, it has been very dismaying to read news from the US, where there seemed to be a very dangerous complacency. I am relieved to see that this is changing, especially at the state level, which makes me much more hopeful.</p>
<p>I have also found media coverage to be disappointing. Apparently, many highly educated people, including people whose job involves understanding policy issues, have no idea how numbers work (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ordODDzVso8">source</a>). This is a problem because a lot of issues concerning this epidemic have to do with numbers, which can be misleading if they are not reported in context.</p>
<p>For example, before the time when Trump decided that he had retroactively been concerned about a pandemic since January, conservative media emphasized the estimate of a 2% mortality rate, in a way that made it sound, well, 98% of people survive, and 98% is approximately 100%, so what is the big deal. For context, the Space Shuttle only exploded 1.5% of the times, and this was deemed <i>too dangerous for astronauts</i>. This is the kind of intuitive reference that I would like to see more of.</p>
<p>Even now, there is a valid debate on whether measures that will cost the economy trillions of dollars are justified. After all, it would be absurd to spend trillions of dollars to save, say, 10,000 lives, it would be questionable to do so to save 100,000 lives, and it would be undoubtedly right to do so to save millions of lives and a collapse of the health care system (especially considering that a collapse of the health care system might create its own financial panic that would also cost trillions of dollars).</p>
<p>So which one is it? Would doing nothing cost 10,000 American lives? A million? How long will people have to “shelter at home”? And what is next? I can recommend two well-researched articles: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/20/opinion/coronavirus-outcomes.html">this</a> on plausible scenarios and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/17/opinion/coronavirus-social-distancing-effect.html">this</a> on what’s next.</p>
<p>Kristof’s article cites an <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2020/03/17/a-fiasco-in-the-making-as-the-coronavirus-pandemic-takes-hold-we-are-making-decisions-without-reliable-data/">essay</a> by Stanford professor John Ioannidis who notes that it is within the realm of possibilities, given the available data, that the true mortality rate could be as low as 0.05%, that is, wait for it, lower than the mortality rate of the flu. Accordingly, in a plausible scenario, “If we had not known about a new virus out there, and had not checked individuals with PCR tests, the number of total deaths due to “influenza-like illness” would not seem unusual this year.”</p>
<p>Ioannidis’ essay was written without reference to data from Italy, which was probably not available in peer-reviewed form at the time of writing.</p>
<p>I would not want professor Ioannidis to tell me how to design graph algorithms, and I don’t mean to argue for the plausibility of the above scenario, but let me complement it with some data from Italy.</p>
<p>Lombardy is Italy’s richest and most developed region, and the second richest (in absolute and PPP GDP) administrative region in Europe after the Ile de France (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_European_regions_by_GDP">source</a>). It has a rather good health care system. In 2018, on average, 273 people died per day in Lombardy of all causes (<a href="https://ugeo.urbistat.com/AdminStat/it/it/demografia/popolazione/lombardia/3/2">source</a>). Yesterday, 381 people died in Lombardy with coronavirus (<a href="https://github.com/pcm-dpc/COVID-19/tree/master/schede-riepilogative/regioni">source</a>). This is spread out over a region with more than 10 million residents.</p>
<p>Some areas are harder-hit hotspots. Three days ago, a Bergamo newspaper <a href="https://www.bergamonews.it/2020/03/17/coronavirus-a-bergamo-in-una-settimana-330-morti-14-volte-in-piu-rispetto-a-un-anno-fa/360586/">reported</a> that 330 people had died in the previous week of all causes in the city. In the same week of March in 2019, 23 people had died. That’s a 14x increase of mortality of all causes. <b>Edited to add (3/22/2020):</b> <i>the mayor of Bergamo <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-health-coronavirus-italy-homes-insigh/uncounted-among-coronavirus-victims-deaths-sweep-through-italys-nursing-homes-idUSKBN2152V0">told Reuters</a> that 164 people died in Bergamo of all causes in the first two weeks of March 2020, versus 56 in the first two weeks of March 2019, a 3x increase instead of the 14x increase reported by Bergamo News.</i></p>
<p>Bergamo’s hospital had 16 beds in its intensive care unit, in line with international standards (it is typical to have of the order of an ICU bed per 5000-10,000 people, and Bergamo has a population of 120,000). Right now there are 80 people in intensive care in Bergamo, a 5x increase in capacity that was possible by bringing in a lot of ventilators and moving other sick people to other hospitals. Nonetheless, there have been reports of shortages of ICU beds, and of people needing to intubated that could not be. There are also reports of people dying of pneumonia at home, without being tested.</p>
<p>Because of this surge in deaths, Bergamo’s funeral homes have not been able to keep up. It’s not that they have not been able to keep up with arranging funerals, because funerals are banned. They just do not have the capacity to perform the burials.</p>
<p>So coffins have been accumulating. A couple of days ago, a motorcade of army vehicles came to Bergamo to pick up 70 coffins and take them to other cities.</p>
<p/>
<p>It should be noted that this is happening after 20 days of “social distancing” measures and after 13 days of “sheltering at home” in Lombardy.</p>
<p>My point being, if we had not known that a news virus was going around, the number of excess deaths in Bergamo would have not been hidden by the random noise in the number of deaths due to influenza-like illness.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-20T19:37:09Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-20T19:37:09Z</published>
    <category term="Italy"/>
    <category term="lies damn lies and ..."/>
    <category term="Bergamo"/>
    <category term="covid-19"/>
    <category term="things that are terrible"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:20:09Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/?p=113</id>
    <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2020/03/workshop-lattices-new-cryptographic-capabilities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Workshop “Lattices: New Cryptographic Capabilities”</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the behalf of the organizers, I am excited to announce that the next Simons workshop Lattices: New Cryptographic Capabilities will take place next week Mar 23-27, 2020 over Zoom! schedule 8.20 am-noon PDT (4.20 – 8 pm, CET) zoom … <a href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2020/03/workshop-lattices-new-cryptographic-capabilities/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>On the behalf of the organizers, I am excited to announce that the next Simons workshop <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/workshops/lattices-2020-2">Lattices: New Cryptographic Capabilities</a> will take place next week <strong>Mar 23-27, 2020</strong> over Zoom!</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/workshops/schedule/10566">schedule</a> 8.20 am-noon PDT (4.20 – 8 pm, CET)</li>
<li>zoom <a href="https://berkeley.zoom.us/j/912850168">berkeley.zoom.us/j/912850168</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The workshop will cover advanced lattice-based cryptographic constructions, while also highlighting some of the recurring themes and techniques, reiterated through a game of Bingo! The rest of this post provides a sneak preview along with the Bingo puzzle.</p>
<p><!--
Here is a quick overview of
the workshop

* Day 1: fully homomorphic encryption, attribute-based encryption, homomorphic signatures and non-interactive zero knowledge, all from a simple equation!

* Day 2: obfuscation, obfuscation, obfuscation

* Day 3: -->Looking forward to seeing everyone at the workshop!</p>
<p>Hoeteck, together with Shweta, Zvika and Vinod</p>
<hr/>
<h2 id="zoom-guidelinestips">Zoom Guidelines/Tips</h2>
<ul>
<li>To ask a question, use the “raise hand” feature.</li>
<li>If the speaker’s slide is not displaying in its entirety, try “side-by-side mode” under “view options”.</li>
<li>Please log in to Zoom with your full name.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="a-sneak-preview">A Sneak Preview</h2>
<p>Let <span class="math inline"><strong>A</strong><sub>1</sub>, <strong>A</strong><sub>2</sub></span> be square matrices and <span class="math inline"><strong>t</strong></span> a row vector such that</p>
<p><span class="math display"><strong>t</strong><strong>A</strong><sub>1</sub> = <em>x</em><sub>1</sub><strong>t</strong>, <strong>t</strong><strong>A</strong><sub>2</sub> = <em>x</em><sub>2</sub><strong>t</strong></span><br/>
Using high-school algebra lingo, we would refer to <span class="math inline"><strong>t</strong></span> as the eigenvector of <span class="math inline"><strong>A</strong><sub>1</sub>, <strong>A</strong><sub>2</sub></span>. It is easy to see that</p>
<p><span class="math display"><strong>t</strong> ⋅ (<strong>A</strong><sub>1</sub> + <strong>A</strong><sub>2</sub>) = (<em>x</em><sub>1</sub> + <em>x</em><sub>2</sub>)<strong>t</strong>, <em>t</em> ⋅ <strong>A</strong><sub>1</sub><strong>A</strong><sub>2</sub> = <em>x</em><sub>1</sub><em>x</em><sub>2</sub><strong>t</strong></span><br/>
This extends readily to any polynomial <span class="math inline"><em>p</em>(<em>x</em><sub>1</sub>, …, <em>x</em><sub><em>n</em></sub>)</span>, namely: if <span class="math inline"><strong>t</strong><strong>A</strong><sub><em>i</em></sub> = <em>x</em><sub><em>i</em></sub><strong>t</strong></span>, then</p>
<p><span class="math display"><strong>t</strong> ⋅ <em>f</em>(<strong>A</strong><sub>1</sub>, …, <strong>A</strong><sub><em>n</em></sub>) = <em>f</em>(<em>x</em><sub>1</sub>, …, <em>x</em><sub><em>n</em></sub>)<strong>t</strong></span><br/>
As in turns out, much of advanced lattice-based crypto boils down to a generalization of this statement! The generalization is along two orthogonal dimensions:</p>
<ol type="i">
<li>arbitrary matrices <span class="math inline"><strong>A</strong><sub>1</sub>, …, <strong>A</strong><sub><em>n</em></sub></span> that may not share the same eigenvector <span class="math inline"><strong>t</strong></span>, and</li>
<li>a relaxation to “approximate” equality, namely <span class="math inline"><strong>t</strong><strong>A</strong><sub><em>i</em></sub> ≈ <em>x</em><sub><em>i</em></sub><strong>t</strong></span>.</li>
</ol>
<p>The generalization underlies fully homomorphic encryption, homomorphic signatures, attribute-based encryption schemes and many more!</p>
<h2 id="bingo">Bingo!</h2>
<p>Here’s the 4×4 bingo puzzle:</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>GGH15</td>
<td>Bonsai</td>
<td><span class="math inline"><strong>A</strong><strong>R</strong> <strong>+</strong> <strong>G</strong></span></td>
<td>noise growth</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><span class="math inline"><strong>G</strong><sup> − 1</sup></span></td>
<td>LWE</td>
<td>Vinod</td>
<td>LHL</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Gaussian</td>
<td><span class="math inline"><strong>A</strong><sub><em>f</em></sub></span></td>
<td>FHE Dec <span class="math inline">≈</span> linear</td>
<td>noise flooding</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>homomorphic</td>
<td>trapdoor</td>
<td>smoothing parameter</td>
<td><span class="math inline"><strong>H</strong><sub><em>f</em>, <em>x</em></sub></span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-20T15:07:05Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-20T15:07:05Z</published>
    <category term="General"/>
    <author>
      <name>Hoeteck Wee</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu</id>
      <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>What's New at the Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing.</subtitle>
      <title>Calvin Café: The Simons Institute Blog</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:26:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7654</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/03/19/focs-deadline-pushed-back-6-days/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>FOCS deadline pushed back 6 days</title>
    <summary>From Sandy Irani, FOCS 2020 PC chair: In light of the very unusual developments in the world due to the spread of Covid-19 and the disruption it is causing to many people in our field, especially those with young children at home, the FOCS PC has decided to push back the final deadline for papers […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>From Sandy Irani, FOCS 2020 PC chair:</p>



<p>In light of the very unusual developments in the world due to the spread of Covid-19 and the disruption it is causing to many people in our field, especially those with young children at home, the FOCS PC has decided to push back the final deadline for papers by six days. We would have liked to do more, but we still are trying to stick to our timeline for notification since that date is coordinated with other deadlines in the theory community. In addition, some members of the committee are also affected by this crisis and there is concern that we may not be able to do our job as a committee in a shorter time frame. Pre-registration (including titles and abstracts) is still required by the original deadline. Here are the new dates:</p>



<p><strong>Pre-registration (including titles and abstracts):</strong> Thursday <strong>April 9</strong>, 11:59 PM (EDT)</p>



<p><strong>Final Paper Submission:</strong> Wednesday <strong>April 15</strong>, 11:59 PM (EDT)</p>



<p>Conference url: <a href="https://focs2020.cs.duke.edu/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://focs2020.cs.duke.edu/</a></p>



<p>We hope you all stay healthy!</p>



<p>–Sandy Irani, for the FOCS 2020 Committee</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-19T16:27:50Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-19T16:27:50Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:25:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6639109407429165166</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6639109407429165166/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/what-to-do-while-stuck-at-home-part-i.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6639109407429165166" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6639109407429165166" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/what-to-do-while-stuck-at-home-part-i.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What to do while stuck at home Part I</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First of all both the <a href="https://amturing.acm.org/">Turing award</a> and <a href="https://www.abelprize.no/seksjon/vis.html?tid=76020">Abel Prize</a> announced yesterday.<br/>
<br/>
As we start moving from the panic phase of the coronavirus to the boring phase, what kinds of things should you do or not do while stuck at home for the next two weeks to eighteen months.<br/>
<br/>
First of all still do your job. Teach your online classes. Try to do some research. Meet with your colleagues/students/advisor virtually (best with Zoom or something similar). Submit to conferences. What else? Use the situation for your advantage.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Attend virtual conferences: </b>Really attend. Pretend that you flew there and devote the entire day to going to virtual talks or chatting with other attendees in virtual hallways. I <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/the-importance-of-networking.html">said it wouldn't happen this way</a> last week so prove me wrong.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Create a Virtual Workshop: </b>Because you can. Invite people to give online talks. Open it up for all to listen. Find ways to discuss together.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Connect: </b>Make a virtual get-together with an old colleague or someone you've always wanted to meet. Researchers around the world will be holed up and happy to get some interactions.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Learn Something New: </b>Read a textbook. Take an online course in CS or something completely different. There are plenty.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Help Others Learn: </b>Start that book you've always wanted to write. Or just write a short survey article giving your view of a slice of the theory world. Create some videos or a podcast to explain stuff.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Pick up a hobby: </b>Something outside computer science just to keep your sanity.<br/>
<b><br/></b>
<b>Watch some fun computer-related movies: </b>Her, Sneakers, The Computer wore Tennis Shoes, 2001, The Imitation Game, Hidden Figures, Colossus: The Forbin Project, Ex Machina. Add your own favorites in the comments.<br/>
<br/>
And on the other hand don't<br/>
<br/>
<b>Become an epidemiologist: </b>As a computer scientist you are an expert in networks, graph theory and exponential growth so you can create models that show we are grossly under preparing and/or overreacting to the virus and want to tell the world how you are right and the so-called "experts" are wrong. Please don't.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Prove P ≠ NP</b>: Trying to settle P v NP and failing is instructive. Trying to settle P v NP and thinking you succeeded is delusional.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Freak Out: </b>We will get past this virus and the world will recover.<br/>
<br/>
Bill will follow up with his own ideas in part II next week.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-19T13:45:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-19T13:45:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T13:06:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://dstheory.wordpress.com/?p=39</id>
    <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2020/03/19/friday-march-27-sujay-sanghavi-from-ut-austin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Friday, March 27 — Sujay Sanghavi from UT Austin</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second Foundations of Data Science virtual talk will take place next Friday, March 27th at 11:00 AM Pacific Time (2:00 pm Eastern Time, 20:00 Central European Time, 19:00 UTC).  Sujay Sanghavi from University of Texas at Austin will speak about “Towards Model Agnostic Robustness”. Abstract: It is now common practice to try and solve machine<a class="more-link" href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2020/03/19/friday-march-27-sujay-sanghavi-from-ut-austin/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">"Friday, March 27 — Sujay Sanghavi from UT Austin"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The second Foundations of Data Science virtual talk will take place next Friday, March 27th at 11:00 AM Pacific Time (2:00 pm Eastern Time, 20:00 Central European Time, 19:00 UTC).  <strong>Sujay Sanghavi</strong> from University of Texas at Austin will speak about “<em>Towards Model Agnostic Robustness</em>”.</p>



<p><strong>Abstract</strong>: It is now common practice to try and solve machine learning problems by starting with a complex existing model or architecture, and fine-tuning/adapting it to the task at hand. However, outliers, errors or even just sloppiness in training data often lead to drastic drops in performance. </p>



<p>We investigate a simple generic approach to correct for this, motivated by a classic statistical idea: trimmed loss. This advocates jointly (a) selecting which training samples to ignore, and (b) fitting a model on the remaining samples. As such this is computationally infeasible even for linear regression. We propose and study the natural iterative variant that alternates between these two steps (a) and (b) – each of which individually can be easily accomplished in pretty much any statistical setting. We also study the batch-SGD variant of this idea. We demonstrate both theoretically (for generalized linear models) and empirically (for vision and NLP neural network models) that this effectively recovers accuracy in the presence of bad training data.</p>



<p>This work is joint with Yanyao Shen and Vatsal Shah and appears in NeurIPS 2019, ICML 2019 and AISTATS 2020.</p>



<p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory">Link to join the virtual talk.</a></p>



<p>The series is supported by the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1934846&amp;HistoricalAwards=false">NSF HDR TRIPODS Grant 1934846</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-19T02:29:19Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-19T02:29:19Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>dstheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://dstheory.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Foundation of Data Science – Virtual Talk Series</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:29:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://theorydish.blog/?p=1570</id>
    <link href="https://theorydish.blog/2020/03/18/private-and-secure-distributed-matrix-multiplication/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Private and Secure Distributed Matrix Multiplication</title>
    <summary>Machine learning on big data sets takes a significant amount of computational power, so it is often necessary to offload some of the work to external distributed systems, such as an Amazon EC2 cluster. It is useful to be able to utilize external resources for computation tasks while keeping the actual data private and secure. In particular, matrix multiplication is an essential step in many machine learning processes, but the owner of the matrices may have reasons to keep the actual values protected. In this post, we’ll discuss four works about secure distributed computation. First, we’ll talk about a method of using MDS (maximum distance separable) error correcting codes to add security and privacy to general data storage (“Cross Subspace Alignment and the Asymptotic Capacity of X-Secure T-Private Information Retrieval” by Jia, Sun, Jafar). Then we’ll discuss method of adapting a coding strategy for straggler mitigation (“Polynomial codes: an optimal design for high-dimensional coded matrix multiplication” by Yu, Qian, Maddah-Ali, Avestimehr) in matrix multiplication to instead add security or privacy (“On the capacity of secure distributed matrix multiplication” by Chang, Tandon and “Private Coded Matrix Multiplication” by Kim, Yang, Lee) Throughout this post we will use variations on the following communication model: The [...]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Machine learning on big data sets takes a significant amount of computational power, so it  is often necessary to offload some of the work to external distributed systems, such as an Amazon EC2 cluster. It is useful to be able to utilize external resources for computation tasks while keeping the actual data <em>private</em> and<em> secure</em>. In particular, matrix multiplication is an essential step in many machine learning processes, but the owner of the matrices may have reasons to keep the actual values protected.</p>



<p>In this post, we’ll discuss four works about secure distributed computation. First, we’ll talk about a method of using MDS (maximum distance separable) error correcting codes to add security and privacy to general data storage (“<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1808.07457.pdf">Cross Subspace Alignment and the Asymptotic Capacity of X-Secure T-Private Information Retrieval”</a> by Jia, Sun, Jafar). </p>



<p>Then we’ll discuss method of adapting a coding strategy for straggler mitigation (<a href="http://papers.nips.cc/paper/7027-polynomial-codes-an-optimal-design-for-high-dimensional-coded-matrix-multiplication.pdf">“Polynomial codes: an optimal design for high-dimensional coded matrix multiplication”</a> by Yu, Qian, Maddah-Ali, Avestimehr) in matrix multiplication to instead add security or privacy (<a href="https://uweb.engr.arizona.edu/~wchang/Globecom-SecureMM-2018.pdf">“On the capacity of secure distributed matrix multiplication”</a> by Chang, Tandon and <a href="https://ieeexplore-ieee-org.stanford.idm.oclc.org/abstract/document/8832193">“Private Coded Matrix Multiplication”</a> by Kim, Yang, Lee)</p>



<p>Throughout this post we will use variations on the following communication model:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1572" height="192" src="https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/blog_fig1.png?w=1024" width="404"/></figure>



<p>The data in the grey box is only given to the master, so workers only have access to what they receive (via green arrows). Later on we will also suppose the workers have a shared library not available to the master. The workers do not communicate with each other as part of the computation, but we want to prevent them from figuring out anything about the data if they do talk to each other.</p>



<p> This model is related to <em>private computation</em> but not exactly the same. We assume the servers are “honest but curious”, meaning they won’t introduce malicious computations. We also only require the master to receive the final result, and don’t need to protect any data from the master. This is close to the BGW scheme ([Ben-Or, Goldwasser, Wigderson ’88]), but we do not allow workers to communicate with each other as part of the computation of the result.</p>



<p> We consider <em>unconditional</em> or <em>information-theoretic</em> security, meaning the data is protected even if the workers have unbounded computational power. Furthermore, we will consider having <em>perfect  secrecy</em>, in which the mutual information between the information revealed to the workers and the actual messages is zero.</p>



<h2>X-Secure T-Private Information Retrieval</h2>



<p> Before we get into matrix-matrix multiplication, consider the problem of storing information on the workers to be retrieved by the master, such that it is “protected.” What do we mean by that? [Jia, Sun, and Jafar ’19] define X-secure T-private information retrieval as follows: </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Let <img alt="W_1,...,W_{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W_1%2C...%2CW_%7BK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="W_1,...,W_{K}"/> be a data set of messages, such that each <img alt="W_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="W_i"/> consists of <img alt="L" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="L"/> random bits. A storage scheme of <img alt="W_{1},...,W_{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W_%7B1%7D%2C...%2CW_%7BK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="W_{1},...,W_{K}"/> on <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/> nodes is </p><p>1. <em>X-secure</em> if any set of up to <img alt="X" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=X&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="X"/> servers cannot determine anything about any <img alt="W_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="W_i"/> and</p><p>2. <em>T-private </em> if given a query from the user to retrieve some data element <img alt="W_{\theta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W_%7B%5Ctheta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="W_{\theta}"/>, any set of up to <img alt="T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=T&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="T"/> users cannot determine the value of <img alt="\theta" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctheta&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\theta"/>.</p><cite>[Jia, Sun, and Jafar ’19]</cite></blockquote>



<p>Letting <img alt="Q_{1}^{[\theta]},...,Q_{N}^{[\theta]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=Q_%7B1%7D%5E%7B%5B%5Ctheta%5D%7D%2C...%2CQ_%7BN%7D%5E%7B%5B%5Ctheta%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="Q_{1}^{[\theta]},...,Q_{N}^{[\theta]}"/> be the set of queries sent to each node and <img alt="S_1,...,S_N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S_1%2C...%2CS_N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="S_1,...,S_N"/> be the information stored on each node  (all vectors of length L), we depict this as:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1581" height="223" src="https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/blog_fig2.png?w=1024" width="452"/></figure>



<p>The information theoretic requirements of this system to be correct can be summarized as follows (using notation <img alt="S_{[1:N]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S_%7B%5B1%3AN%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="S_{[1:N]}"/> for set <img alt="S_1,...,S_N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S_1%2C...%2CS_N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="S_1,...,S_N"/>):</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td><strong>Property</strong></td><td><strong>Information Theoretic Requirement</strong></td></tr><tr><td>Data messages are size <img alt="L" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="L"/> bits</td><td><img alt="H(W_1)=H(W_2)=....=H(W_K) = L" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H%28W_1%29%3DH%28W_2%29%3D....%3DH%28W_K%29+%3D+L&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="H(W_1)=H(W_2)=....=H(W_K) = L"/></td></tr><tr><td>Data messages are independent</td><td><img alt="H(W_1,...,W_K) = KL" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H%28W_1%2C...%2CW_K%29+%3D+KL&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="H(W_1,...,W_K) = KL"/></td></tr><tr><td>Data can be determined from the stored information</td><td><img alt="H(W_1,....,W_K)|S_{[1:N]}) = 0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H%28W_1%2C....%2CW_K%29%7CS_%7B%5B1%3AN%5D%7D%29+%3D+0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="H(W_1,....,W_K)|S_{[1:N]}) = 0"/></td></tr><tr><td>User has no prior knowledge of server data</td><td><img alt="I(S_{[1:N]};Q^{[\theta]}_{[1:N]},\theta) = 0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=I%28S_%7B%5B1%3AN%5D%7D%3BQ%5E%7B%5B%5Ctheta%5D%7D_%7B%5B1%3AN%5D%7D%2C%5Ctheta%29+%3D+0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="I(S_{[1:N]};Q^{[\theta]}_{[1:N]},\theta) = 0"/></td></tr><tr><td>X-Security</td><td><img alt="I(S_{\mathcal{X}};W_1,...,W_K) = 0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=I%28S_%7B%5Cmathcal%7BX%7D%7D%3BW_1%2C...%2CW_K%29+%3D+0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="I(S_{\mathcal{X}};W_1,...,W_K) = 0"/>, <img alt="\forall \mathcal{X}\subset [1:N],|\mathcal{X}|=X" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cforall+%5Cmathcal%7BX%7D%5Csubset+%5B1%3AN%5D%2C%7C%5Cmathcal%7BX%7D%7C%3DX&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\forall \mathcal{X}\subset [1:N],|\mathcal{X}|=X"/></td></tr><tr><td> T-Privacy</td><td><img alt="I(Q_{\mathcal{T}}^{[\theta]},S_{\mathcal{T}}; \theta) = 0," class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=I%28Q_%7B%5Cmathcal%7BT%7D%7D%5E%7B%5B%5Ctheta%5D%7D%2CS_%7B%5Cmathcal%7BT%7D%7D%3B+%5Ctheta%29+%3D+0%2C&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="I(Q_{\mathcal{T}}^{[\theta]},S_{\mathcal{T}}; \theta) = 0,"/>  <img alt="\forall \mathcal{T} \subset [1:N], |\mathcal{T}|=T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cforall+%5Cmathcal%7BT%7D+%5Csubset+%5B1%3AN%5D%2C+%7C%5Cmathcal%7BT%7D%7C%3DT&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\forall \mathcal{T} \subset [1:N], |\mathcal{T}|=T"/></td></tr><tr><td>Nodes answer only based on their data and received query </td><td><img alt="H(A_n^{[\theta]}| Q_n^{[\theta]},S_n) =0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H%28A_n%5E%7B%5B%5Ctheta%5D%7D%7C+Q_n%5E%7B%5B%5Ctheta%5D%7D%2CS_n%29+%3D0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="H(A_n^{[\theta]}| Q_n^{[\theta]},S_n) =0"/></td></tr><tr><td>User can decode desired message from answers</td><td><img alt="H(W_{\theta} | A_{[1:N]}^{[\theta]},Q_{[1:N]}^{[\theta]} ,\theta) = 0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H%28W_%7B%5Ctheta%7D+%7C+A_%7B%5B1%3AN%5D%7D%5E%7B%5B%5Ctheta%5D%7D%2CQ_%7B%5B1%3AN%5D%7D%5E%7B%5B%5Ctheta%5D%7D+%2C%5Ctheta%29+%3D+0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="H(W_{\theta} | A_{[1:N]}^{[\theta]},Q_{[1:N]}^{[\theta]} ,\theta) = 0"/></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>Given these constraints, Jia et al. give bounds on the capacity of the system. Capacity is the maximum rate achievable, where rate is defined as bits requested by the worker (<img alt="L" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="L"/>, the length of a single message) divided by the number of bits downloaded by the worker. The bounds are in terms of the capacity of T-Private Information Retrieval, (which is the same as the above definition, with only requirement 2).</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>If <img alt="N \leq X+T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N+%5Cleq+X%2BT&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N \leq X+T"/> then for arbitrary <img alt="K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="K"/>, <img alt="C_{XSTPIR}(N,K,X,T) = \frac{N-X}{N}C_{TPIR}(N-X,K,T) = \frac{N-X}{NK}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_%7BXSTPIR%7D%28N%2CK%2CX%2CT%29+%3D+%5Cfrac%7BN-X%7D%7BN%7DC_%7BTPIR%7D%28N-X%2CK%2CT%29+%3D+%5Cfrac%7BN-X%7D%7BNK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="C_{XSTPIR}(N,K,X,T) = \frac{N-X}{N}C_{TPIR}(N-X,K,T) = \frac{N-X}{NK}"/>.</p><p><img alt="\displaystyle C_{XSTPIR}(N,K,X,T) \leq \left(\frac{N-X}{N}\right) C_{TPIR}(N-X,K,T)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+C_%7BXSTPIR%7D%28N%2CK%2CX%2CT%29+%5Cleq+%5Cleft%28%5Cfrac%7BN-X%7D%7BN%7D%5Cright%29+C_%7BTPIR%7D%28N-X%2CK%2CT%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle C_{XSTPIR}(N,K,X,T) \leq \left(\frac{N-X}{N}\right) C_{TPIR}(N-X,K,T)"/></p><p> When <img alt="N\leq X+T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%5Cleq+X%2BT&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N\leq X+T"/>: <img alt="\displaystyle C_{XSTPIR}(N,K,X,T) = \left(\frac{N-X}{N}\right) C_{TPIR}(N-X,K,T) = \frac{N-X}{NK}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+C_%7BXSTPIR%7D%28N%2CK%2CX%2CT%29+%3D+%5Cleft%28%5Cfrac%7BN-X%7D%7BN%7D%5Cright%29+C_%7BTPIR%7D%28N-X%2CK%2CT%29+%3D+%5Cfrac%7BN-X%7D%7BNK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle C_{XSTPIR}(N,K,X,T) = \left(\frac{N-X}{N}\right) C_{TPIR}(N-X,K,T) = \frac{N-X}{NK}"/> </p><p> <img alt="\displaystyle\lim_{K\to \infty} C_{XSTPIR}(N,K,X,T) = \lim_{K\to \infty} \left(\frac{N-K}{N}\right) C_{TPIR}(N-X,K,T) =\begin{cases}&#xA0; &#xA0;1-(\frac{X+T}{N}) &amp; N&gt;X+T  \\&#xA0;  0 &amp; N\leq X+T \end{cases}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle%5Clim_%7BK%5Cto+%5Cinfty%7D+C_%7BXSTPIR%7D%28N%2CK%2CX%2CT%29+%3D+%5Clim_%7BK%5Cto+%5Cinfty%7D+%5Cleft%28%5Cfrac%7BN-K%7D%7BN%7D%5Cright%29+C_%7BTPIR%7D%28N-X%2CK%2CT%29+%3D%5Cbegin%7Bcases%7D%C2%A0+%C2%A01-%28%5Cfrac%7BX%2BT%7D%7BN%7D%29+%26+N%3EX%2BT++%5C%5C%C2%A0++0+%26+N%5Cleq+X%2BT+%5Cend%7Bcases%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle\lim_{K\to \infty} C_{XSTPIR}(N,K,X,T) = \lim_{K\to \infty} \left(\frac{N-K}{N}\right) C_{TPIR}(N-X,K,T) =\begin{cases}&#xA0; &#xA0;1-(\frac{X+T}{N}) &amp; N&gt;X+T  \\&#xA0;  0 &amp; N\leq X+T \end{cases}"/></p><cite>[Jia, Sun, and Jafar ’19]</cite></blockquote>



<p>Jia et al. give schemes that achieve these bounds while preserving the privacy and security constraints by introducing random noise vectors into how data is stored and queries are constructed. The general scheme for <img alt="N&gt;X+T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%3EX%2BT&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N&gt;X+T"/> uses <em>cross subspace alignment</em>, which essentially chooses how to construct the stored information and the queries such that the added noise mostly “cancels out” when the master combines all the response from the servers. The scheme for <img alt="N\leq X+T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N%5Cleq+X%2BT&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N\leq X+T"/> is straightforward to explain, and demonstrates the idea of using error correcting codes that treat the random values as the message and the actual data as the “noise.”</p>



<p>For this scheme, the message length <img alt="L" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="L"/> is set to <img alt="N-X" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N-X&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N-X"/> (the number of nodes <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/>, minus the maximum number of colluding servers <img alt="X" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=X&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="X"/>). First, we generate <img alt="K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="K"/> random bit vectors of length <img alt="X" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=X&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="X"/>:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1590" height="157" src="https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/blog_fig3.png?w=856" width="370"/></figure>



<p>Next, apply an <img alt="(N,X)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28N%2CX%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="(N,X)"/> MDS code to <img alt="Z_1,...,Z_K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=Z_1%2C...%2CZ_K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="Z_1,...,Z_K"/> to get <img alt="\bar{Z}_1,..,\bar{Z}_K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbar%7BZ%7D_1%2C..%2C%5Cbar%7BZ%7D_K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bar{Z}_1,..,\bar{Z}_K"/>, which are <img alt="K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="K"/> encoded vectors of length <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/>:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1591" src="https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/blog_fig4.png?w=1024"/></figure>



<p>For our data <img alt="W_1,...,W_K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W_1%2C...%2CW_K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="W_1,...,W_K"/>, we pad each vector with zeros to get <img alt="\bar{W}_1,..,\bar{W}_K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbar%7BW%7D_1%2C..%2C%5Cbar%7BW%7D_K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bar{W}_1,..,\bar{W}_K"/> of length <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/>:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1592" src="https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/blog_fig5.png?w=1024"/></figure>



<p>Now that the dimensions line up, we can add the two together and store each column <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n"/> at the <img alt="n^{th}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7Bth%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n^{th}"/> node:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1593" src="https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/blog_fig6.png?w=1024"/></figure>



<p>To access the data, the user downloads all <img alt="NK" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=NK&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="NK"/> bits. The length <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/> string downloaded from  row <img alt="i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="i"/> can be used to decode <img alt="\bar{Z}_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbar%7BZ%7D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bar{Z}_i"/>: <img alt="\bar{W}_{L+1},\bar{W}_{L+2},...,\bar{W}_{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbar%7BW%7D_%7BL%2B1%7D%2C%5Cbar%7BW%7D_%7BL%2B2%7D%2C...%2C%5Cbar%7BW%7D_%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bar{W}_{L+1},\bar{W}_{L+2},...,\bar{W}_{N}"/> are all zero, so columns <img alt="L+1 = N-X+1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%2B1+%3D+N-X%2B1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="L+1 = N-X+1"/> through <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/> have the values of <img alt="\bar{Z}_{i,N-X+1},...,\bar{Z}_{i,N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbar%7BZ%7D_%7Bi%2CN-X%2B1%7D%2C...%2C%5Cbar%7BZ%7D_%7Bi%2CN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bar{Z}_{i,N-X+1},...,\bar{Z}_{i,N}"/>. This gives the user <img alt="X" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=X&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="X"/> values from the MDS code used on each row, so they can decode and get <img alt="Z_1,...,Z_K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=Z_1%2C...%2CZ_K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="Z_1,...,Z_K"/> and <img alt="\bar{Z}_{1},...,\bar{Z}_K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbar%7BZ%7D_%7B1%7D%2C...%2C%5Cbar%7BZ%7D_K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bar{Z}_{1},...,\bar{Z}_K"/>. Then a subtraction from the downloaded data gives <img alt="W_1,...,W_{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W_1%2C...%2CW_%7BK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="W_1,...,W_{K}"/>. Because of the MDS property of the code used to get <img alt="\bar{Z}_1,...,\bar{Z}_K" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbar%7BZ%7D_1%2C...%2C%5Cbar%7BZ%7D_K&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bar{Z}_1,...,\bar{Z}_K"/>, this scheme is X-secure and because the user downloads all bits, it is T-private.</p>



<h2>Matrix Multiplication with Polynomial Codes</h2>



<p>We now move on to the task of matrix-matrix multiplication. The methods for secure and private distributed matrix multiplication we will discuss shortly are based on <em>polynomial codes</em>, used by [Yu, Maddah-Ali, Avestimehr ’17] for doing distributed matrix multiplications robust to stragglers. Suppose the master has matrices <img alt="{\bf{A}} \in \mathbb{F}_q^{m\times n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbf%7BA%7D%7D+%5Cin+%5Cmathbb%7BF%7D_q%5E%7Bm%5Ctimes+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bf{A}} \in \mathbb{F}_q^{m\times n}"/> and <img alt="{\bf{B}} \in \mathbb{F}_q^{n \times p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbf%7BB%7D%7D+%5Cin+%5Cmathbb%7BF%7D_q%5E%7Bn+%5Ctimes+p%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bf{B}} \in \mathbb{F}_q^{n \times p}"/> for some finite field <img alt="\mathbb{F}_q" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb%7BF%7D_q&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\mathbb{F}_q"/>, and <img alt="m,n,p \in \mathbb{Z}^+" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m%2Cn%2Cp+%5Cin+%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5E%2B&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="m,n,p \in \mathbb{Z}^+"/>. Assume <img alt="m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="m"/> and <img alt="p" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=p&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="p"/> are divisible by <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/>, so we can represent the matrices divided into <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/> submatrices: </p>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><img alt="{\bf{A}}= \begin{bmatrix}A_1\\ A_2 \\ \vdots \\ A_m\end{bmatrix}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbf%7BA%7D%7D%3D+%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7DA_1%5C%5C+A_2+%5C%5C+%5Cvdots+%5C%5C+A_m%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bf{A}}= \begin{bmatrix}A_1\\ A_2 \\ \vdots \\ A_m\end{bmatrix}"/>               and        <img alt="{\bf{B}}= \begin{bmatrix}B_1&amp; B_2 &amp; \dots &amp;B_n\end{bmatrix}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbf%7BB%7D%7D%3D+%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7DB_1%26+B_2+%26+%5Cdots+%26B_n%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bf{B}}= \begin{bmatrix}B_1&amp; B_2 &amp; \dots &amp;B_n\end{bmatrix}"/> </p>



<p>So to recover <img alt="\bf{AB}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbf%7BAB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bf{AB}"/>, the master needs each entry of: </p>



<p><img alt="{\bf{AB}} = \begin{bmatrix}A_1B_1 &amp; A_1B_2 &amp; \dots &amp; A_1B_n\\A_2B_1 &amp; A_2B_2 &amp; \dots &amp; A_2 B_n\\\vdots &amp; \vdots &amp;\vdots &amp;\vdots\\A_mB_1 &amp;A_mB_2 &amp; \dots&#xA0; &amp; A_mB_n \end{bmatrix}." class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbf%7BAB%7D%7D+%3D+%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7DA_1B_1+%26+A_1B_2+%26+%5Cdots+%26+A_1B_n%5C%5CA_2B_1+%26+A_2B_2+%26+%5Cdots+%26+A_2+B_n%5C%5C%5Cvdots+%26+%5Cvdots+%26%5Cvdots+%26%5Cvdots%5C%5CA_mB_1+%26A_mB_2+%26+%5Cdots%C2%A0+%26+A_mB_n+%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D.&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bf{AB}} = \begin{bmatrix}A_1B_1 &amp; A_1B_2 &amp; \dots &amp; A_1B_n\\A_2B_1 &amp; A_2B_2 &amp; \dots &amp; A_2 B_n\\\vdots &amp; \vdots &amp;\vdots &amp;\vdots\\A_mB_1 &amp;A_mB_2 &amp; \dots&#xA0; &amp; A_mB_n \end{bmatrix}."/></p>



<p>The key idea of polynomial codes is to encode <img alt="A_1,...,A_m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A_1%2C...%2CA_m&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="A_1,...,A_m"/> and <img alt="B_1,...,B_n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=B_1%2C...%2CB_n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="B_1,...,B_n"/> in polynomials <img alt="\tilde{A}_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctilde%7BA%7D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\tilde{A}_i"/> and <img alt="\tilde{B}_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctilde%7BB%7D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\tilde{B}_i"/> to be sent to the <img alt="i^{th}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=i%5E%7Bth%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="i^{th}"/> worker,  where they are multiplied and the result is returned. The goal of Yu et al. was to create robustness to stragglers, and so they add redundancy in this process so that not all workers need to return a result for the master to be able to determine <img alt="\bf{AB}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbf%7BAB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bf{AB}"/>. In particular, only <img alt="mn" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=mn&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="mn"/> returned values are needed, so <img alt="N-mn" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N-mn&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N-mn"/> servers can be slow or fail completely without hurting the computation. This method can be thought of as setting up the encodings of <img alt="\bf{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbf%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bf{A}"/> and <img alt="\bf{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cbf%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\bf{B}"/> so that the resulting multiplications <img alt="\tilde{C}_1=\tilde{A}_1\tilde{B}_1,...,\tilde{C}_N=\tilde{A}_N\tilde{B}_N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctilde%7BC%7D_1%3D%5Ctilde%7BA%7D_1%5Ctilde%7BB%7D_1%2C...%2C%5Ctilde%7BC%7D_N%3D%5Ctilde%7BA%7D_N%5Ctilde%7BB%7D_N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\tilde{C}_1=\tilde{A}_1\tilde{B}_1,...,\tilde{C}_N=\tilde{A}_N\tilde{B}_N"/> are evaluations of a polynomial with coefficients  <img alt="A_1B_1,A_1B_2,...,A_2B_1....,A_mB_n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A_1B_1%2CA_1B_2%2C...%2CA_2B_1....%2CA_mB_n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="A_1B_1,A_1B_2,...,A_2B_1....,A_mB_n"/> at <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/> different points — equivalent to a Reed-Solomon code. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1603" src="https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/blog_fig7.png?w=1024"/></figure>



<p>This idea is adapted by [Chang, Tandon ’18] to protect the data from colluding servers: noise is incorporated into the encodings such that the number of encoded matrices required to determine anything about the data is greater than the security threshold <img alt="X &lt; N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=X+%3C+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="X &lt; N"/>. Since the master receives all <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/> responses it is able to decode the result of <img alt="\textbf{AB}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctextbf%7BAB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\textbf{AB}"/>, but no set of <img alt="X" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=X&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="X"/> nodes can decode <img alt="\textbf{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctextbf%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\textbf{A}"/>, <img alt="\textbf{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctextbf%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\textbf{B}"/>, or <img alt="\textbf{AB}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctextbf%7BAB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\textbf{AB}"/>. Similarly, [Kim, Yang, Li ’19] adapts this idea to impose privacy on a matrix-matrix multiplication: workers are assumed to have a shared library <img alt="\{{\textbf{B}}_i\}_{i=1}^M" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%7B%7B%5Ctextbf%7BB%7D%7D_i%5C%7D_%7Bi%3D1%7D%5EM&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\{{\textbf{B}}_i\}_{i=1}^M"/>, and the user would like to multiply <img alt="{\textbf{A}}{\textbf{B}}_{D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctextbf%7BA%7D%7D%7B%5Ctextbf%7BB%7D%7D_%7BD%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\textbf{A}}{\textbf{B}}_{D}"/> for some <img alt="D \in[1:M]" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=D+%5Cin%5B1%3AM%5D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="D \in[1:M]"/> without revealing the value of <img alt="D" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="D"/> to the workers. The workers encode the entire library such that when the  encoding is multiplied by an encoded input <img alt="\tilde{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctilde%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\tilde{A}"/> from the master, the result is useful to the master in decoding <img alt="{\textbf{A}}{\textbf{B}}_D" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctextbf%7BA%7D%7D%7B%5Ctextbf%7BB%7D%7D_D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\textbf{A}}{\textbf{B}}_D"/>.</p>



<p>Chang and Tandon consider the following two privacy models, where up to <img alt="\ell" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cell&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\ell"/> servers may collude. The master also has <img alt="K^{(A)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=K%5E%7B%28A%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="K^{(A)}"/> (and in the second model, <img alt="K^{(B)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=K%5E%7B%28B%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="K^{(B)}"/>), which are matrices of random values with the same dimensions as <img alt="\textbf{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctextbf%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\textbf{A}"/> (and <img alt="\textbf{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctextbf%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\textbf{B}"/>). These are used in creating the encodings <img alt="\tilde{A}_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctilde%7BA%7D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\tilde{A}_i"/> (and <img alt="\tilde{B}_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctilde%7BB%7D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\tilde{B}_i"/>).</p>



<p> <img alt="\textbf{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctextbf%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\textbf{B}"/> is public, <img alt="\textbf{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctextbf%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\textbf{A}"/> is private:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1604" src="https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/blog_fig8.png?w=1024"/></figure>



<p>Both private:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1605" src="https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/blog_fig9.png?w=1024"/></figure>



<p>Kim, Yang, and Lee take a similar approach of applying the method of polynomial code to <em>private</em> matrix multiplication. As before, there are <img alt="N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="N"/> workers, but now the master wants to multiply <img alt="\textbf{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctextbf%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\textbf{A}"/> with some <img alt="{\textbf{B}}_D" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctextbf%7BB%7D%7D_D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\textbf{B}}_D"/> in shared library <img alt="\{{\textbf{B}}_i\}_{i=1}^M" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%7B%7B%5Ctextbf%7BB%7D%7D_i%5C%7D_%7Bi%3D1%7D%5EM&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\{{\textbf{B}}_i\}_{i=1}^M"/> (all the workers have the shared library). </p>



<p>Since the master isn’t itself encoding <img alt="\{{\textbf{B}}\}_{i=1}^M" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%7B%7B%5Ctextbf%7BB%7D%7D%5C%7D_%7Bi%3D1%7D%5EM&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\{{\textbf{B}}\}_{i=1}^M"/> it has to tell the workers how to encode the library so that it can reconstruct the desired product. This is done by having the master tell the workers what values of <img alt="\vec{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cvec%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\vec{y}"/> they should use to evaluate the polynomial that corresponds to encoding each library matrix. We denote the encoding of the library done by each worker <img alt="i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="i"/> as the multivariate polynomial <img alt="h" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=h&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="h"/> which is evaluated at <img alt="\{{\textbf{B}}\}_{i=1}^M" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%7B%7B%5Ctextbf%7BB%7D%7D%5C%7D_%7Bi%3D1%7D%5EM&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\{{\textbf{B}}\}_{i=1}^M"/> and the node-specific vector <img alt="y^{(i)}_{[1:M]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=y%5E%7B%28i%29%7D_%7B%5B1%3AM%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="y^{(i)}_{[1:M]}"/> to get the node’s encoding, <img alt="\tilde{B}_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctilde%7BB%7D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\tilde{B}_i"/>. The worker multiplies this with the encoding of <img alt="\textbf{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctextbf%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\textbf{A}"/> it receives, <img alt="\tilde{A}_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctilde%7BA%7D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\tilde{A}_i"/> and returns the resulting value <img alt="Z_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=Z_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="Z_i"/>. All together, we get the following communication model: </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1611" src="https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/blog_fig10.png?w=1024"/></figure>



<h2>Conclusion</h2>



<p>As we’ve seen, coding techniques originally designed to add redundancy and protect against data loss can also be used to intentionally incorporate noise for data protection. In particular, this can be done when out-sourcing matrix multiplications, making it a useful technique in many data processing and machine learning applications.</p>



<p>References:</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1808.07457.pdf">Jia, Zhuqing, Hua Sun, and Syed Ali Jafar. “Cross Subspace Alignment and the Asymptotic Capacity of  X-Secure T-Private Information Retrieval.” <em>IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</em> 65.9 (2019): 5783-5798.</a></li><li><a href="http://papers.nips.cc/paper/7027-polynomial-codes-an-optimal-design-for-high-dimensional-coded-matrix-multiplication.pdf">Yu, Qian, Mohammad Maddah-Ali, and Salman Avestimehr. “Polynomial codes: an optimal design for high-dimensional coded matrix multiplication.” <em>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</em>. 2017.</a></li><li><a href="https://uweb.engr.arizona.edu/~wchang/Globecom-SecureMM-2018.pdf">Chang, Wei-Ting, and Ravi Tandon. “On the capacity of secure distributed matrix multiplication.” <em>2018 IEEE Global Communications Conference (GLOBECOM)</em>. IEEE, 2018.</a></li><li><a href="https://ieeexplore-ieee-org.stanford.idm.oclc.org/abstract/document/8832193">Kim, Minchul, Heecheol Yang, and Jungwoo Lee. “Private Coded Matrix Multiplication.” <em>IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security</em> (2019).</a></li></ul>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-18T23:14:58Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-18T23:14:58Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Porter</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://theorydish.blog</id>
      <logo>https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/cropped-nightdish1.jpg?w=32</logo>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Stanford's CS Theory Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Theory Dish</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:26:09Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=405</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2020/03/18/tcs-talk-wednesday-march-25-dana-moshkovitz-ut-austin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, March 25 — Dana Moshkovitz, UT Austin</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, March 25th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 18:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). Dana Moshkovitz from UT Austin will speak about “Nearly Optimal Pseudorandomness From Hardness” (abstract below). You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, March 25th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 18:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). <strong>Dana Moshkovitz</strong> from UT Austin will speak about “<em>Nearly Optimal Pseudorandomness From Hardness</em>” (abstract below).</p>
<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk/live-seat-reservation">the online form</a>. (The link will also be posted <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk">on our website</a> on the day of the talk, so people who did not sign up will still be able to join, until the maximum capacity of 300 seats is reached.) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/">the website</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Abstract: Existing proofs that deduce BPP=P from circuit lower bounds convert randomized algorithms into deterministic algorithms with a large polynomial slowdown. We convert randomized algorithms into deterministic ones with little slowdown. Specifically, assuming exponential lower bounds against randomized single-valued nondeterministic (SVN) circuits, we convert any randomized algorithm over inputs of length n running in time <img alt="t\geq n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=t%5Cgeq+n&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0" title="t\geq n"/> to a deterministic one running in time <img alt="t^{2+\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=t%5E%7B2%2B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0" title="t^{2+\alpha}"/> for an arbitrarily small constant <img alt="\alpha &gt; 0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha+%3E+0&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0" title="\alpha &gt; 0"/>. Such a slowdown is nearly optimal, as, under complexity-theoretic assumptions, there are problems with an inherent quadratic derandomization slowdown. We also convert any randomized algorithm that errs rarely into a deterministic algorithm having a similar running time (with pre-processing). The latter derandomization result holds under weaker assumptions, of exponential lower bounds against deterministic SVN circuits. Our results follow from a new, nearly optimal, explicit pseudorandom generator. The construction uses, among other ideas, a new connection between pseudoentropy generators and locally list recoverable codes.</p></blockquote>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-18T23:13:21Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-18T23:13:21Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:26:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4684" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Ask Me Anything: Apocalypse Edition</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">So far, I confess, this pandemic is not shaping up for me like for Isaac Newton. It’s not just that I haven’t invented calculus or mechanics: I feel little motivation to think about research at all. Or to catch up on classic literature or films … or even to shower, shave, or brush my teeth. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>So far, I confess, this pandemic is not shaping up for me like for Isaac Newton.  It’s not just that I haven’t invented calculus or mechanics: I feel little motivation to think about research at all.  Or to catch up on classic literature or films … or even to shower, shave, or brush my teeth.  I’m quarantined in the house with my wife, our two kids, and my parents, so certainly there’s been plenty of family time, although my 7-year-daughter would inexplicably rather play fashion games on her iPad than get personalized math lessons from the author of <em>Quantum Computing Since Democritus</em>.</p>



<p>Mostly, it seems, I’ve been spending the time sleeping.  Or curled up in bed, phone to face, transfixed by the disaster movie that’s the world’s new reality.  Have you ever had one of those nightmares where you know the catastrophe is approaching—whether that means a missed flight, a botched presentation at your old high school, or (perhaps) more people dying than in any event since WWII—but you don’t know exactly when, and you can do nothing to avert it?  Yeah, that feeling is what I now close my eyes to <em>escape</em>.  And then I wake up, and I’m back in bizarro-nightmare-land, where the US is in no rush whatsoever to test people or to build ventilators or hospitals to cope with the coming deluge, and where ideas that could save millions have no chance against rotting institutions.</p>



<p>If nothing else, I guess we now have a decisive answer to the question of why humanity can’t get its act together on climate change.  Namely, if we can’t wrap our heads around a catastrophe that explodes exponentially over <strong>a few weeks</strong>—if those who denied or minimized it face no consequences even when they’re dramatically refuted before everyone’s eyes—then what chance could we possibly have against a catastrophe that explodes exponentially over a century?  (Note that I reject the view that the virus was sent by some guardian angel as the only possible <em>solution</em> to climate change, one crisis cancelling another one.  For one thing, I expect emissions to roar back as soon as this new Black Death is over; for another, the virus punishes public transportation but not cars.)</p>



<p>Anyway, I realized I needed something, not necessarily to take my mind off the crisis, but to break me out of an unproductive spiral.  Also, what better time than the present for things that I wouldn’t normally have time for?  So, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?cat=34">continuing a tradition</a> from 2008, 2009, 2011, 2013, 2015, and 2018, we’re going to do an Ask Me Anything session.  Questions directly or tangentially related to the crisis (continuing the discussion from the previous thread) are okay, questions <em>totally unrelated</em> to the crisis are even okayer, goofball questions are great, and questions that I can involve my two kids in answering are greatest of all.  Here are this year’s ground rules:</p>



<ul><li>24 hours or until I get bored</li><li>One question per person total</li><li><strong>Absolutely no</strong> multi-part questions</li><li>Self-contained questions only—nothing that requires me to read a paper, watch a video, etc.</li><li>Scan the previous AMAs to see if your question is already there</li><li>Any sufficiently patronizing, hostile, or annoying questions might be left in the moderation queue, 100% at my discretion</li></ul>



<p>So ask away!  And <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SJUhlRoBL8M">always look on the bright side of life</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Update (March 19): No more questions, please.</strong>  Thanks, everyone!  It will take me a few days just to work through all the great questions that are already in the queue. </p>



<p><strong>Update (March 24):</strong> Thanks again for the 90-odd questions!  For your reading convenience, here are links to all my answers, with some answers that I’m happy with bolded.</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833095">Could non-biological entities be conscious?</a>  (Short answer: presumably)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833103">Is online teaching here to stay, even after coronavirus passes?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833116">Would a parliament of randomly-chosen high SAT-scorers be better than the current US government?</a>  (Short answer: probably.  Low bar!)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833123">Am I optimistic about NISQ algorithms like QAOA?</a>  (Short answer: no)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833128">Have I tried sitting under an apple tree?</a>  (Answer: No, only laying under the covers)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833152">Something something about radical bio-isolationism to defend against engineered super-plagues?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833155"><strong>Will the corona crisis help teach people about climate change?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833159"><strong>Will the crisis make academics reevaluate the need for so many conferences?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833161">How should we teach undergrad Theory of Computation?</a></li><li><strong><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833166">How do I feel about the progress in TCS over the last decade?</a></strong>  (Short answer: good)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833169">Is MIP*=RE evidence for quantum being stronger in general?</a>  (Short answer: no)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833174">Should voters be blamed, or only politicians?</a>  (Short answer: voters)</li><li><strong><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833180">Could quantum computing help with future pandemics?</a></strong>  (Short answer: conceivably but let’s start with masks and ventilators)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833183">What’s my estimate for the number of COVID victims?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833184">Will Trump’s debased response to the pandemic make him lose the election?</a>  (Short answer: I hope so!)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833185"><strong>What recently-read books do I recommend?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833229">What are my daughter’s favorite fashion games?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833246">Are there quantum size-depth tradeoffs for problems in NC or RNC?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833249">How do I combat the feeling that the pandemic makes all my research useless?</a>  (Short answer: my research was useless already!)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833252">Is time already involved at the commutator level in QM?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833253">What potential use of QCs brings me the most joy?</a>  (Short answer: disproving people who claimed QCs were impossible!)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833256">Why aren’t I more terrified of the flu than of coronavirus?</a>  (Short answer: Do you live in a frigging cave?)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833290"><strong>Why are physicists so ignorant of theoretical CS, if all their experiments rely on computers?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833294">How much economic cost should we bear to flatten the curve?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833295">Which two historical figures would I like to watch debating the human condition?</a>  (Answer: Bertrand Russell and Jesus)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833297">Is CRISPR being used to help search for coronavirus vaccines?</a></li><li><strong><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833301">Have I ever grown a beard?</a></strong>  (Short answer: sadly, yes)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833302">Why are hard-to-simulate Mikado sticks not “Mikado supremacy”?</a></li><li><strong><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833306">What advice would I give a postdoc who dreams of pursuing big questions?</a></strong>  (Short answer: do it!)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833308">What recent research idea did I have that didn’t pan out?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833309">How will QCs help advance materials science?</a>  (Short answer: no one knows)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833312">Are Parity Games in P?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833314">Boxers or briefs?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833316">How do I know I retain transtemporal identity?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833319"><strong>What positives will come out of this pandemic?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833324">Will I try Beeminder?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833325">Am I worried about dysgenic fertility trends?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833326">How do you know if something’s conscious?</a>  (Short answer: you don’t)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833327">What non-political decree would I issue as king?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833329">Do Borel determinacy and the measurability of projective sets have metaphysical truth-values?</a>  (Short answer: dunno)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833330">Why haven’t we previously seen lots of viruses with asymptomatic spread?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833332">How is Gil Kalai faring now that his worldview has been shattered?</a>  (Short answer: he’s fine)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833335"><strong>Have things gotten so awful that we should stop working on fundamental questions?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833336"><strong>Do non-physical realms exist?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833379">Is consciousness a quantum phenomenon?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833382">Can one separate the completeness and soundness aspects of MIP*?</a></li><li><strong><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833382">Why do I still feel the need to bring up Amanda Marcotte?</a></strong>  (Short answer: Because ironically, she showed the world why my teenage fears <em>weren’t</em> completely delusional)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833402">How would I apportion money to different research areas?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833405">Can one end music infringement lawsuits by putting 68 billion computer-generated melodies into the public domain?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833406"><strong>What’s the second piece of information people should take from this blog?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833408">How likely am I to win a Nobel Prize?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833409">What research area would I choose were I starting today?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833410">Will my math lessons for my daughter be made more widely available?</a>  (Short answer: That’s the plan!)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833415"><strong>How should Turing-universality be defined for dynamical systems?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833428"><strong>Has the coronavirus crisis inspired me to take existential risks in general, including AI risks, more seriously?</strong></a>  (Short answer: yes)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833429">Why do world leaders say we’re now in a war?</a>  (Short answer: because we are)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833451"><strong>Why doesn’t chemistry get more respect?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833454">What other catastrophes do I worry might hit us in the next decade?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833463"><strong>Have I ever experienced “true free will”?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833472">Why do many top PhD programs now expect applicants to already have research experience?</a>  (Short answer: arms race)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833473">Do I believe in telepathy?</a>  (Answer: no)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833474">Is what’s mathematically possible a strict subset of what’s logically possible?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833491">What do I think of the Law of the Excluded Middle?</a>  (Short answer: 100% for, 0% against)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833493">What do I think of bounded arithmetic and proof complexity?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833497">Who are leading candidates for the next Turing Award?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833510"><strong>Could an infinite amount of computation be done just before a Big Rip?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833513">What is quantum discord and is it useful for anything?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833564"><strong>What do I think of academics having to write diversity statements?</strong></a>  (Short answer: for diversity, against mandatory statements)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833606"><strong>What’s my frank opinion of geometry-from-entanglement, and what does the new replica wormhole result tell us?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833609"><strong>What do I think of Sabine Hossenfelder’s view that impossibility theorems are only about theories, not about nature itself?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833610">Do I own a gun, or have I considered getting one?</a>  (Short answer: no and no)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833611">Are the asymptotically best quantum error-correcting codes likely to be stabilizer codes?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833612">What was the flavor of the last piece of cake I ate?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833664">Why is it called computer science if we don’t do experiments?</a>  (Short answer: for starters, we do do experiments)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833665">Is there such a thing as non-maximal entanglement?</a>  (Short answer: yes)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833667">At what fatality rate do you order shelter-in-place?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833670">Are logistics and optimization promising applications of QC?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833672">What problems in quantum complexity do I think will be solved next?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833675"><strong>What changes would I (and my kids) make to elementary education in the US?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833677"><strong>What do my kids think that my wife and I do at work?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833684">Do I think Theory A and Theory B will join forces to tackle the P=?NP problem?</a>  (Short answer: No, I think Theory A will tackle it, while Theory B explains how it could’ve been tackled more elegantly)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833687">What’s a good quantum computing project idea?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833688">What’s the role of error-correcting codes in the PCP Theorem?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1833689">Is the Blum Speedup Theorem true?</a>  (Answer: yes)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1834134"><strong>Which type of entanglement better captures the real world: tensor-product or commuting-operator?</strong></a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1834135">Is Ewin Tang’s algorithm practical?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1834138"><strong>What motivates me to get out of bed?</strong></a>  (Answer: Dana yelling at me to come help with the kids)</li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1834172">Would George Washington’s descendants, ruling as kings, be preferable to Trump?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1834174">What big question would I love to solve?</a></li><li><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4684#comment-1834176">Am I planning a revision of <em>Quantum Computing Since Democritus</em>?</a>  (Short answer: no)</li></ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-18T21:02:37Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-18T21:02:37Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Ask Me Anything"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-03-25T04:48:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=19473</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/03/18/or-ordentlich-oded-regev-and-barak-weiss-new-bounds-for-covering-density/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Or Ordentlich, Oded Regev and Barak Weiss: New bounds for Covering Density!</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Barak Weiss lectured about his breakthrough results with Or Ordentlich, and Oded Regev, at a Simons Institute workshop: Lattices: Geometry, Algorithms and Hardness. It is a famous problem what is the densest (or, most efficient) packing of unit balls in Euclidean … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/03/18/or-ordentlich-oded-regev-and-barak-weiss-new-bounds-for-covering-density/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p/>
<p>Barak Weiss <a href="https://youtu.be/s_WRRVSM8ts">lectured about his breakthrough results</a> with Or Ordentlich, and Oded Regev, at a Simons Institute workshop: <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/workshops/lattices-2020-1">Lattices: Geometry, Algorithms and Hardness.</a></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/rogers.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19530" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/rogers.jpg?w=640"/></a></p>
<p>It is a famous problem what is the densest (or, most efficient) packing of unit balls in Euclidean n-dimensional spaces and, of course, you can ask the same questions for other convex bodies. A sort of a dual problem, also famous, is the question of the most efficient covering the n-dimensional Euclidean space by balls or by translates of other convex bodies.</p>
<p>A very basic insight is that covering is much more efficient than packing. Can you explain the reason for that? The only thing that came up to my mind was that convex sets are roundish from the outside but not from the inside which makes it easier to cover with them.</p>
<p>But how efficiently can we cover the n-dimensional Euclidean space with translates of a convex body $K$?</p>
<p>C.A. Rogers with coauthors had some very fundamental results regarding covering (and packing) in the 50s and 60s. Or Ordentlich, Oded Regev and Barak Weiss have made a terrific improvement for one of the main questions in this area. They showed that for every convex set <em>K,</em> you can find a lattice <em>L </em> of determinant 1, and <em>r&gt;0</em>  such that <img alt="rK+L = \mathbb R^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=rK%2BL+%3D+%5Cmathbb+R%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="rK+L = \mathbb R^n"/> and</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="{\rm vol} (rK) \le cn^2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Crm+vol%7D+%28rK%29+%5Cle+cn%5E2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="{\rm vol} (rK) \le cn^2"/>.</p>
<p>The best earlier upper bound was <img alt="n^{\log \log n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B%5Clog+%5Clog+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="n^{\log \log n}"/>.</p>
<p>One surprising aspect of the proof is the use of finite field Kakeya-type questions. Since the<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0803.2336"> breakthrough</a> by <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2008/03/24/dvirs-proof-of-the-finite-field-kakeya-conjecture/">Zeev Dvir</a>, many people had hopes for applications from the finite fields results to the Euclidean setting (in particular, to the Euclidean Kakeya problem itself) and it is rare to see such applications. The proof here relies on results by  Dvir, Kopparty, Saraf, Sudan, and Lev. The Ordentlich-Regev-Weiss paper is not yet on the arXiv but the lecture gives a good picture about the results and the proofs.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/covering-radius.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19534" height="325" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/covering-radius.png?w=640&amp;h=325" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The definition of the covering density of L with respect to a convex body K</span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/coveringdensity.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19536" height="291" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/coveringdensity.png?w=640&amp;h=291" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The definition of the covering density of K</span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/bw2.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19537" height="388" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/bw2.png?w=640&amp;h=388" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Old results for the Euclidean ball</span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/bw3.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19538" height="453" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/bw3.png?w=640&amp;h=453" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Old results for general convex bodies</span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/bw6.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19539" height="519" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/bw6.png?w=640&amp;h=519" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The first main result</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/bw7.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19541" height="474" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/bw7.png?w=640&amp;h=474" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The required finite field Kakeya theorem.</span></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-18T10:39:56Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-18T10:39:56Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <category term="Barak Weiss"/>
    <category term="Oded Regev"/>
    <category term="Or Ordentlich"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:25:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=398</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2020/03/17/updated-spring-schedule-increased-talk-frequency-and-joining-as-individuals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Updated Spring schedule: increased talk frequency, and joining as individuals</title>
    <summary>We hope you are all as safe and sound as possible these days, and will be for the weeks to come. For those of you confined at home, it may be hard to remain connected with the TCS community or stay up-to-date with the current research, as in-person seminars and conferences are cancelled. In case […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We hope you are all as safe and sound as possible these days, and will be for the weeks to come.</p>
<p>For those of you confined at home, it may be hard to remain connected with the TCS community or stay up-to-date with the current research, as in-person seminars and conferences are cancelled. In case this may help, we have decided to <strong>increase for now the frequency of our online seminars</strong>, to try and mitigate this aspect. This won’t restore normalcy, but every little thing counts.</p>
<p>Here is our current, now <strong>weekly</strong> schedule: we may add more talks to it in the days to come, so keep an eye on <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/">our calendar</a> and don’t hesitate to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">suggest talks and results</a> you are curious about.</p>
<ul>
<li>03/25: <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~danama/">Dana Moshkovitz</a> (UT Austin) on <em>“Nearly Optimal Pseudorandomness From Hardness”</em></li>
<li>04/01: <a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~venkatg/">Venkat Guruswami</a> (CMU) on <em>“Arıkan meets Shannon: Polar codes with near-optimal convergence to channel capacity”</em></li>
<li>04/08: Rahul Ilango (MIT) on <em>“NP-Hardness of Circuit Minimization for Multi-Output Functions”</em></li>
<li>04/15: <span class="JtukPc"><span id="rAECCd"><a href="https://web.math.princeton.edu/~rvan/">Ramon van Handel</a> (Princeton) </span></span>on <em>“Rademacher type and Enflo type coincide”</em></li>
<li>04/22: <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~hy2/">Huacheng Yu</a> (Princeton) on <em>“Nearly Optimal Static Las Vegas Succinct Dictionary”</em></li>
<li>04/29: <a href="https://www.mit.edu/~mahabadi/">Sepideh Mahabadi</a> (TTIC) on<em> “Non-Adaptive Adaptive Sampling on Turnstile Streams”</em></li>
</ul>
<p>We emphasize that <strong>you can</strong> (and <em>should</em>) <strong>join as individuals</strong>, from home: if you are interested in a talk, ask for a spot for yourself, no need to go to your institution. We have the live audience capacity for this to work, so don’t hesitate!</p>
<p>We will post individual announcements several days before each talk, including the abstracts and how to ask for a spot, as usual; and the talks will of course be available on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/TCSplusSeminars/">YouTube</a> and <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks">our website</a> afterwards if you couldn’t make it to the live, interactive one. Crucially, <strong>we would like your feedback</strong>: not only talk suggestions as pointed out before, but also any idea or suggestion you may have of things we could do or implement, or of content you would like to see. You can send us feedback by <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/credits">emailing any of our organizers</a>, or leaving a comment below.</p>
<p>Stay safe,</p>
<p>The TCS+ team</p>
<p><span class="css-901oao css-16my406 r-1qd0xha r-ad9z0x r-bcqeeo r-qvutc0"><strong>Note:</strong> <em>you don’t need to sign up in advance</em> (the link will be made public on <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk">our website</a></span><span class="css-901oao css-16my406 r-1qd0xha r-ad9z0x r-bcqeeo r-qvutc0"> the day of the talk, and you can just join then). We only encourage you to do so in order for us to get a sense of the audience size, but it’s optional: don’t feel you have to plan ahead!</span></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-18T00:01:04Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-18T00:01:04Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:26:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16804</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/17/leprechauns-stay-home/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Leprechauns Stay Home</title>
    <summary>Stay safe, everyone Cropped from Floss Dance source Neil L. is a Leprechaun. He has visited me once every year since I started GLL. I had never seen a leprechaun before I began the blog—there must be some connection. Today, Ken and I want to share the experiences we had with him on this morning […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Stay safe, everyone</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/leprechaunlaptop.png"><img alt="" class="alignright size-full wp-image-16806" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/leprechaunlaptop.png?w=600"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Cropped from Floss Dance <a href="https://www.redbubble.com/people/wanitadesign/works/45006990-floss-dance-leprechaun-st-patricks-day-girls?p=laptop-skin">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Neil L. is a Leprechaun. He has visited me once every year since I started GLL. I had never seen a leprechaun before I began the blog—there must be some connection.</p>
<p>
Today, Ken and I want to share the experiences we had with him on this morning of St. Patrick’s Day.<br/>
<span id="more-16804"/></p>
<p>
I thought because of the pandemic that he might not come. I thought that since New York City is on virtual lock-down he might not come. So I decided not to wait up for his visit, which always occurs in the wee hours of the morning. I looked it up: Wee hours is between 1am and 4am. We—that is Kathryn and I not wee—went to bed before midnight.</p>
<p>
Something woke me up at 3am. Not any noise but a bright green light. It was coming from my laptop, which was on the dresser but closed and switched off. I took it out of the bedroom and opened the lid and there he was.</p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">Top o’ the morning to ye. </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p>
</p><p/><h2> Neil Says Hi </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The first thing I noticed was: no pipe. There was no puff of smoke in my living room. Neil smokes a special brand of tobacco—green of course—that I would recognize in an instant. Otherwise he looked as usual: green coat and hat, brown vest and shoes, red beard. I could see all of him.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<em>“Glad as always to see you Neil. But why no pipe?”</em></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Neil started his usual pipe-puffing gesture but stopped his hand from touching his face.</p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">‘Tis virus not microbe. Smoke nae gan do good. All of us doing without. Least of our troubles. </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Wow—that was hard for me to fathom. I thought of the travel bans. <em>“Are you all having to stay home?”</em></p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">Aye. We obey the bans. Crown or Republic, nae matter. </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
I had to wrap my mind around this—leprechauns too? <em>“The virus applies to you?”</em></p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">Sadly, we can carry it. Were it not, we could help folks point-to-point. </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
I realized: leprechauns can go anywhere instantly. The planar aspects of simulations like <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2020/world/corona-simulator/">this</a> do not apply to them. Neil read my mind—at least he could do <em>that</em> remotely:</p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">Aye. I noted <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/12/group-testing-for-the-coronavirus/#comment-109232">all</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/12/group-testing-for-the-coronavirus/#comment-109234">your</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/12/group-testing-for-the-coronavirus/#comment-109244">comment</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/12/group-testing-for-the-coronavirus/#comment-109268">thread</a> about expander graphs and spreading the disease. Fixed dimensions don’t constrain us. This compounds our main trouble, which be…  </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Of course <em>our</em> main trouble and concern is the danger of the virus—our being able to care for those who catch it and measures to ensure many do not catch it. I realize leprechauns, being immortal, have fewer worries there—and I did not ask Neil if they can get sick. So I thought of all the canceled St. Patrick’s Day parades, bars closing, no public merriment, sporting events gone too. But Neil’s next word went straight to the heart.</p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">Boredom. </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Boredom and Randomness </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I thought about fun things Neil had recounted in the past: tricks with <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2014/03/17/happy-st-patricks-day-2014/">math</a> and <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2016/03/17/happy-st-patricks-day-2/">codes</a> and <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/16/leprechauns-go-universal/">logic</a>, tricks on <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2015/03/17/leprechauns-will-find-you/">people</a>, even tricks during <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2017/03/17/leprechauns-are-multiplying/">March</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/03/17/leprechauns-know-what-it-feels/">Madness</a>. The NCAA tournament got completely canceled, unpostponable. Neil read my mind again and picked up on the topic of sporting events.</p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">Consider me neighbor Bertie. He had his accommodations booked on the wee island in the pond of the 17th hole at TPC Sawgrass. For last weekend during the Players Championship. That’s why they built the island, ye know.  </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/tpc17sawgrass.jpg"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-16808" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/tpc17sawgrass.jpg?w=600"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">“The Purest Test in Golf” <a href="https://www.theplayers.com/news/2016/03/01/tpc-sawgrass-purest-test-in-golf.html">source</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
But of course, the Players was canceled. Even the Masters has been postponed. Neil continued,</p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">He and his fellows’ best craic was playing with the balls goon o’er the water. Not in a nasty way. Ye know by the <b>Rule of Indistinguishability</b> we canna do them bad. Not allowed to make them play worse than other tough holes so ye could tell it is more than the usual hobgoblins in your head and butterflies in your chest. What we do must have the same expectation and other moments as random variation. But random is measure-1 so it is easy to comply. </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p>
Of course. We have written about <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2013/08/23/a-world-without-randomness/">feigned</a> randomness, and we haven’t yet had time to write a post this year on scientists <a href="http://backreaction.blogspot.com/2020/03/essays-elsewhere.html">taking</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superdeterminism">superdeterminism</a> <a href="http://backreaction.blogspot.com/2019/12/the-path-we-didnt-take.html">seriously</a>—<a href="http://backreaction.blogspot.com/2020/02/guest-post-undecidability.html">even</a> <a href="http://backreaction.blogspot.com/2020/02/guest-post-undecidability_10.html">computationally</a>. How could we <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1401.0286.pdf">tell</a> that stuff apart from leprechauns? But thinking of Bertie gave me a more obvious question:</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<em>“Neil, can’t Bertie and his pals do that remotely? Like lots of other things we’re doing now.”</em></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Neil’s answer exposed my lack of basic leprechaun knowledge.</p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">In every story of leprechaun tricks, who is present? The leprechaun. He cannot be remote—and he must run the risk of being catched. He can dance, run to the end of the rainbow, and disappear, but fun happens only when he is around. </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Hearing this, I would have puffed my own pipe, if I smoked and had one. Neil continued:</p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">Besides, remotely we cannot control well enough to abide the Rule of Indistinguishability. </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
All this about randomness and conspiracy physics, with the world already weighing heavily, was too much. I winked out on the couch, without closing my laptop or seeing if Neil said goodbye with his usual flourish. </p>
<p>
I woke up in late morning and called Ken. As I told this part, Ken was instantly alarmed and horrified.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<em>“We must get Neil back. Is he still on your laptop?”</em> </p>
<p/><p><br/>
He was not. Ken plugged in and opened his own laptop—Neil has in the past visited him too—but nothing. He could not find any leprechauns registered on Skype or Zoom or Hangouts. Then Ken had a thought: “See if your laptop has the IP records.”</p>
<p>
It did. I could not tell what they signified, but my old IT contact at Tech said he could pinpoint the origin in minutes. Meanwhile, Ken calmed down enough to explain. I’ll let him write the rest of the story.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The One Uncanceled Competition </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
What is apparently the lone major human sporting competition in the world not to be canceled began today. It is chess—the Candidates Tournament to determine who will face Magnus Carlsen in the next world championship match. It is taking place in Yekaterinburg, Russia—in Siberia, still far from the worst virus activity. It has only the 8 players plus officials onsite—no spectators, press limited—and they are all subject to daily screenings. The players shake hands only <a href="https://worldchess.com/news/players-replicas-to-pose-for-photos-while-real-players-avoid-being-in-public">virtually</a>.</p>
<p>
Controversy about its starting continued today with one former World Champion, Vladimir Kramnik, stepping down from a broadcast commentary team “considering the nowadays disastrous humanitarian situation in the world.” But I’m with those saying that its value as a diversion—something to follow live in community—outweighs the concerns. I said this after some reflection on risks from our previous <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/12/group-testing-for-the-coronavirus/">post</a> and before being contacted about monitoring the tournament. One Chinese <a href="http://tiyutai.qingk.cn/comprehensivelive-info/sfbsrbdcpawqsxrbxrrvvudpcsvxpwfw/6fabf42212b308041e861a2005d12572/6b1607c0df6745e7b59e54f8a87a6309?from=singlemessage&amp;isappinstalled=0&amp;fbclid=IwAR06QhidyVdArI_RPSjTBWo2iUDVSbrJRkRvkPppohNtWT2J3AMRQxRD8Vk">broadcast</a> had over <a href="https://twitter.com/FIDE_chess/status/1239946569404817408">1 million</a> viewers today. Other broadcasts can be found on the official <a href="https://en.candidates-2020.com/main">site</a> and <a href="https://www.chess.com/tv">several</a> <a href="https://chess24.com/en/watch/live-tournaments/fide-candidates-2020/1/1/1">other</a> <a href="https://new.uschess.org/news/2020-candidates-couch-potatoes/">places</a>. Today’s first round was vigorous, with all four games going beyond the turn-40 time control and two decisive.</p>
<p>
But if it is a lone attraction for us, omigosh, for the leprechauns… Dick’s story proved they can at least <em>read</em> minds remotely. What if they all banded together to mess with the players’ moves? Neil had told of the Indistinguishability constraint, but I realized <em>my own work</em> could enable getting around it. My model enables randomly simulating a human distribution of moves at any rating level. I’ve had the idea to try a “Turing Test” akin to one Garry Kasparov turned aside, as part of the Turing Centennial in 2012, by distinguishing five games played by human 2200-level players from five by computers set to play at 2200 strength. If the leprechauns passed the Turing test at a 2800 rating level they could derange the tournament. This all verges on real concerns in my statistical anti-cheating work, with humans not leprechauns.</p>
<p>
I quickly looked up the lore for <a href="https://mysticinvestigations.com/leprechaun-summoning-spell/">summoning</a> a leprechaun. This is far more audacious than knocking on a professor’s door outside office hours—not that that will happen anytime soon. I did not have real shamrocks but strewed countryside photos from my family’s trip to Ireland last summer around my laptop. I needed Kathryn as well as Dick online by videoconference to make the quorum of three. The IT person came back with the coordinates so that uniquely Neil would be summoned. I adapted the ancient incantation to our new age of interaction by laptop: </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Oh Leprechaun, Leprechaun, I humbly call unto thee,<br/>
Ride the Irish rainbows of joy across the virtual sea,<br/>
Let the cables be lit with the beacon of your Shillelagh,<br/>
In dire peril of bad luck I make this plea,<br/>
For an unknown evil lies near, I ween:<br/>
Oh Leprechaun, Leprechaun, please appear on my screen! </b>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
It worked. Neil crackled into view. After a short greeting I blurted out my concerns.</p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">Nae worry. Nae worry. The International Chess Federation—FIDE—took the most important step to assure the fair play.</font>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Wait—I know the fair-play measures FIDE developed. I’ve been part of them. That didn’t assuage what I’d just said.</p>
<blockquote><p><font color="green">FIDE put not just one but two Scotsmen on the tournament staff. One of them is in charge of fair play. Nae Leprechaun gan cross a Scotsman! </font>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
And with that Neil was gone.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Our hearts go out to all those affected more immediately than we so far. Amid all the worries, we wish you a happy and safe St. Patrick’s Day.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
[some formatting and wording tweaks]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-17T22:58:18Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-17T22:58:18Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="chess"/>
    <category term="detection"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="coronavirus"/>
    <category term="leprechauns"/>
    <category term="Neil L."/>
    <category term="Physics"/>
    <category term="randomness"/>
    <category term="St. Patrick's Day"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:25:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-3321636530900479641</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/3321636530900479641/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/richard-guy-passed-away-at-age-of-103.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3321636530900479641" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3321636530900479641" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/richard-guy-passed-away-at-age-of-103.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Richard Guy passed away at the age of 103</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Richard Guy passed away on March 9, 2020 at the age of 103. Before he died he was the worlds oldest living mathematician (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_centenarians_(scientists_and_mathematicians)">here</a> for a list of centenarians who are famous scientists or mathematicians). He was also the oldest <i>active </i>mathematician-- he had a paper on arxiv (see <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03379">here</a>) in October of 2019.  (ADDED later since a commenter pointed it out to me--- a paper by Berlekamp and Guy posted in 2020: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.03705">here</a>)<br/>
<br/>
I met him twice- once at a Gathering for Gardner, and once at an AMS meeting. I told him that Berlekamp-Conway-Guy had a great influence on me. He asked if it was a positive or negative influence. He also seemed to like my talk on The Muffin Problem, though he might have been being polite.<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
I did a blog about Richard Guy on his 103rd birthday, so I recommend readers to go <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/09/richard-guy-is-102-years-old-today.html">there</a><br/>
for more about him.  One point I want to re-iterate:<br/>
<br/>
Richard Guy thought of himself of an amateur mathematician. If he means someone who does it for love of the subject then this is clearly true.  If it is a measure of how good he is (the term `amateur' is sometimes used as an insult) then it is clearly false. If it means someone who does not have formal training than it is partially true.<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-17T16:43:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-17T16:43:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T13:06:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/03/15/stay-home-linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/03/15/stay-home-linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Stay-at-home linkage</title>
    <summary>Looks like we’ll all be seeing a long time at home with little to do but go online. So here is my usual update of links I recently found interesting. (I’m deliberately not linking Coronavirus information, despite its importance, both because I’m not an expert and have neither useful original opinions to contribute nor adequate filters between information and misinformation, and because I suspect that many people’s mental health depends on not getting overloaded with that stuff while there’s so little to do but staying isolated and avoiding becoming part of the problem).</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Looks like we’ll all be seeing a long time at home with little to do but go online. So here is my usual update of links I recently found interesting. (I’m deliberately not linking Coronavirus information, despite its importance, both because I’m not an expert and have neither useful original opinions to contribute nor adequate filters between information and misinformation, and because I suspect that many people’s mental health depends on not getting overloaded with that stuff while there’s so little to do but staying isolated and avoiding becoming part of the problem).</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103750490648260310">Claim: Any partition of a unit square into  rectangles has an axis-parallel line crossing a subset of rectangles with area </a>. Proof: Rectangles of area  cover less than half the square, so larger ones cover at least half. Random axis-parallel lines cross rectangles with probability proportional to perimeter,  for large rectangles. Some line crosses at least the expected area: the sum over rectangles of area × probability.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Mary Beard is “Britain’s best known classicist, a Cambridge don with formidable intellect and a knack for getting people interested in all things ancient”. She was also a nominee for trustee of the British Museum, but (in the latest iteration of politicians sticking their nose where it isn’t wanted or needed) <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2020/mar/01/british-museum-put-mary-beard-on-the-board-despite-downing-st-veto">was vetoed by the Tory government for opposing Brexit</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103756819167366612"/>). Result: the museum will use one of the slots it controls to appoint her despite the veto.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you really want to see some links I posted on US politics related to the Coronavirus, a couple weeks before we realized how immediate the problem was, see <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103763260041701547">here</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://emathgroup.github.io/blog/orchard-planting-problem">A Chinese blog on new solutions to the orchard planting problem with four trees per line</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103769258677244712"/>, <a href="http://www.mathpuzzle.com/">via</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orchard-planting_problem">see also</a>). It seems to be quite readable through Google translate.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/when-bloom-filters-dont-bloom/">When Bloom filters don’t bloom</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103774986303898695"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=22463979">via</a>). A cautionary tale by Marek Majkowski of how when your filter doesn’t fit into cache it can actually slow you down instead of speeding you up.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2020/02/27/numerical-heron/">Computing the area of a thin triangle</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@jsiehler/103765201263486902"/>). How to avoid numerical accuracy issues when using Heron’s formula.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2020/mar/08/melbourne-professor-quits-after-health-department-pressures-her-over-data-breach">Australian cryptographer Vanessa Teague resigns from her University of Melbourne professorship</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103785134816639696"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=22515193">via</a>), in protest of the government refusal to notify citizens whose medical data was breached, pressure to silence her over the discovery of the breach, and efforts to prevent her from continuing to study the problem. See also <a href="https://twitter.com/VTeagueAus/status/1233241830994481152">Teague’s twitter post</a> and <a href="https://www.righttoknow.org.au/request/correspondence_on_re_identificat">government-university correspondence</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04280">Adjacency labelling for planar graphs (and beyond)</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@patmorin/103796330052092318"/>). You can assign labels to the vertices of a planar graph, with  bits per label, and test whether vertices are adjacent by looking over their label. This implies also that planar graphs are induced subgraphs of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal_graph">universal graphs</a> of near-linear size. New preprint by Dujmović, Esperet, Joret, Gavoille, Micek, and Morin.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2020/03/10/options-for-giving-math-talks-and-lectures-online/">Options for giving math talks and lectures online</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103800856267350730"/>, <a href="https://erikdemaine.org/classes/recording/">see also</a>). Now that we have to. Best choices for me at this point are looking like YuJa and Zoom.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.wunderlist.com/blog/join-us-on-our-new-journey/">My favorite shared to-do-list, Wunderlist, is going away</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103810987800264328"/>) and being replaced by a Microsoft thing requiring a Microsoft account that I don’t want or have. All I want is multiple to-do lists, with or without deadlines; ability to share individual lists with other users; OS X, iPhone, and Android integration. Anyone have suggestions for replacements?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@jsiehler/103810743052286323">Pair up!</a> @jsiehler posts an animation of a result from <a href="https://doi.org/10.4153%2FCMB-1959-013-x">Lambek and Moser (1959)</a>: the partition of the non-negative integers into <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odious_number">odious numbers</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evil_number">evil numbers</a> is uniquely determined by the property that the two subsets have equal multisets of pairwise sums.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://bit-player.org/2020/mathjax-turns-3-0">Brian Hayes converts to MathJax 3.0</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103825076990194154"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=22582343">see also</a>). With an interesting discussion at the end about how, after initially seeming like a hack and a patchover of the failure of more principled solutions like MathML to actually work, browser-side MathJax is starting to seem like the right way to do things after all.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@kimreece/103812593467637467">People with “and” in their names cause problems in BibTeX</a>. And they <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alex_And">actually exist</a>. Probably you can work around it using extra curly brackets in the name.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-15T16:40:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-15T16:40:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-03-22T22:44:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/036</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/036" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-036 |  Strong (D)QBF Dependency Schemes via Tautology-free Resolution Paths | 

	Olaf Beyersdorff, 

	Joshua Blinkhorn, 

	Tomáš Peitl</title>
    <summary>We suggest a general framework to study dependency schemes for dependency quantified Boolean formulas (DQBF). As our main contribution, we exhibit a new tautology-free DQBF dependency scheme that generalises the reflexive resolution path dependency scheme. We establish soundness of the tautology-free scheme, implying that it can be used in any DQBF proof system. We further explore the power of DQBF resolution systems parameterised by dependency schemes and show that our new scheme results in exponentially shorter proofs in comparison to the reflexive resolution path dependency scheme when used in the basic DQBF expansion proof system.

On QBFs, we demonstrate that our new scheme is exponentially stronger than the reflexive resolution path dependency scheme when used in Q Resolution, thus resulting in the strongest QBF dependency scheme known to date.</summary>
    <updated>2020-03-15T09:16:59Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-15T09:16:59Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:24:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/035</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/035" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-035 |  No-Signaling MIPs and Faster-Than-Light Communication, Revisited | 

	Justin Holmgren</title>
    <summary>We revisit one original motivation for the study of no-signaling multi-prover
  interactive proofs (NS-MIPs): specifically, that two spatially separated
  provers are guaranteed to be no-signaling by the physical principle that
  information cannot travel from one point to another faster than light.

  We observe that with more than two provers, the physical connection between
  no-signaling and faster-than-light communication is more nuanced, depending on
  the relative positioning of the provers.  In particular, we observe that
  provers are guaranteed to be no-signaling if and only if their positions are
  convexly independent.  Other prover positionings provide weaker guaranteees.

  We consider a new issue that thus arises only in the many-prover setting:
  how precisely must provers be positioned in order to guarantee the
    soundness of a (NS-)MIP?  We prove that substantially more precision is
  required to guarantee full no-signaling than to guarantee soundness of a
  specific NS-MIP for PSPACE implicit in the work of Kalai and Raz (CRYPTO 2009).</summary>
    <updated>2020-03-15T06:28:11Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-15T06:28:11Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:24:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=19479</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/03/14/to-cheer-you-up-in-complicated-times-a-book-proof-by-rom-pinchasi-and-alexandr-polyanskii-for-a-1978-conjecture-by-erdos-and-purdy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>To cheer you up in complicated times – A book proof by Rom Pinchasi and Alexandr Polyanskii for a 1978 Conjecture by Erdős and Purdy!</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Things do not look that good, and these are difficult times. But here on the blog we have plenty of things to cheer you up and assure you. And today we point to two book proofs — two book proofs … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/03/14/to-cheer-you-up-in-complicated-times-a-book-proof-by-rom-pinchasi-and-alexandr-polyanskii-for-a-1978-conjecture-by-erdos-and-purdy/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Things do not look that good, and these are difficult times. But here on the blog we have plenty of things to cheer you up and assure you. And today we point to two book proofs — two book proofs to the same theorem– and, as a matter of fact, two book proofs to the same theorem by the same person, <a href="http://www2.math.technion.ac.il/~room/">Rom Pinchasi</a>.  One of the proofs, the one chosen for presentation, is by Rom Pinchasi and  <a href="http://polyanskii.com/">Alexandr Polyanskii</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/drg_1567-douglas-guthrie-photos.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-13104" height="424" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2015/08/drg_1567-douglas-guthrie-photos.jpg?w=640&amp;h=424" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Rom Pinchasi has an immense proving power, both for difficult proofs at all costs, for book proofs, and for a large variety of proofs in between. (See, for example, <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2010/02/03/a-discrepency-problem-for-planar-configurations/"> this post</a>.)</span></p>
<p>Before moving on, let me mention that there is a <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2020/03/10/options-for-giving-math-talks-and-lectures-online/">timely blog post</a> by Terry Tao on Online teaching, and here is <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/349283/software-and-ideas-for-workshops-and-conferences-with-long-distance-participants">a related MO question about online conferences</a> that I asked last December.</p>
<h2>Proofs from the book</h2>
<p>Famously, the mathematician Paul Erdős, often referred to “The Book” in which God keeps the most elegant proof of each mathematical theorem. During a lecture in 1985, Erdős said, “You don’t have to believe in God, but you should believe in The Book.” (And you do not have even to believe in the book to enjoy proofs from the book.)</p>
<h2>The Theorem: a 1978 conjecture by Erdős and Purdy</h2>
<p><strong>Theorem: </strong> Let <em>P</em> be a set of <em>n</em> points in general position in the plane. Suppose that <em>R</em> is a set of red points disjoint from <em>P</em> such that every line determined by <em>P</em> passes through a point in <em>R</em>. Then <em>|R|≥ n</em> for <em>n &gt; 6</em>.</p>
<p>This theorem settles a problem by Erdős and Purdy from 1978. Erdős and Purdy also asked about the case where the set of points is not required to be in general position. For that problem the best known lower bound, also proved by Rom Pinchasi, is <em>n/3</em>.</p>
<p>Book Proof I: <a href="http://www2.math.technion.ac.il/~room/ps_files/EP_genpos.pdf">An algebraic solution of a problem of Erdős and Purdy</a>, by Rom Pinchasi</p>
<p>Book Proof II: <a href="http://www2.math.technion.ac.il/~room/ps_files/EP_book.pdf">A one-page solution of a problem of Erdős and Purdy, by Rom Pinchasi and Alexandr Polyanskii</a></p>
<h2>Murty’s magic configurations conjecture.</h2>
<p>The <a href="http://www2.math.technion.ac.il/~room/ps_files/magic.pdf">first proof of the Erdős-Purdy 1978 Conjecture</a> was achieved in 2008 by Eyal Ackerman, Kevin Buchin, Christian Knauer, Rom Pinchasi, and Günter Rote. They derived it from their solution to the 1971 conjecture on magic configurations by Murty. A planar set of points P is called magic if it possible to assign positive weights to the points so that the sum of weights in every line determined by the points is one. Murty conjectured that the only magic configurations are those in general position, and those which have a line missing at most one of the points, and a certain configuration of seven points.</p>
<h2>The Pinchasi-Polyanskii Book-Proof:</h2>
<p>Here, we very closely follow the Pinchasi-Polyanskii’s paper.</p>
<p>We say that a line is determined by a set of points in the plane if it contains at least two of the points. Since the points in P are in general position, each pair of points determines a different line.</p>
<p>Under the contrary assumption we must have <em>|R| = n−1</em>. Then it must be that every point in <em>R</em> is incident to precisely <em>n/2</em> lines determined by <em>P</em> and every line determined by <em>P</em> is incident to precisely one point in <em>R</em>. We would like to reach a contradiction.</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;">Preliminary step: apply a projective transformation to the plane such that the convex hull of <em>P</em> becomes a triangle.</span></p>
<p><strong>Observation 1:</strong>  No point of R lies outside the convex hull of P.</p>
<p>Such a point <em>r</em> should be incident to two lines supporting the convex hull of <em>P</em>. Each of these supporting lines must contain precisely two points of <em>P</em>. Since the convex hull of <em>P</em> is a triangle this is impossible.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><strong>Regard the points in the plane as complex numbers. </strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #339966;">(This is really cool. I am not aware of many examples in discrete geometry that thinking about planar points as complex numbers helps.)</span></p>
<p>Notation: for every point<em> p</em> in the plane we denote by <img alt="p_x" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=p_x&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="p_x"/>  the <em>x</em>-coordinate of <em>p</em>.</p>
<p>Crucial definition: For every point <em>p ∈ P</em> deﬁne</p>
<p><img alt="f(p) = \prod_{r \in R}(p-r) / \prod_{p' \in P\backslash \{p\}}(p-p')." class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f%28p%29+%3D+%5Cprod_%7Br+%5Cin+R%7D%28p-r%29+%2F+%5Cprod_%7Bp%27+%5Cin+P%5Cbackslash+%5C%7Bp%5C%7D%7D%28p-p%27%29.&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="f(p) = \prod_{r \in R}(p-r) / \prod_{p' \in P\backslash \{p\}}(p-p')."/></p>
<p><strong>Observation 2:</strong> <em>f(p)</em> is a real number!</p>
<p>The proof will surely make you smile: For every <em>p’ ∈ P \{p}</em> there is a unique <em>r ∈ R</em> such that <em>p, p’</em>, and <em>r</em> are collinear. So <em>(p-r)/(p-p’)</em> is real. And the big ratio between products split to many small fractions that are all real.  <span style="color: #993366;"><strong>Walla!</strong></span></p>
<p>Note that <em>f(p)</em> is thus also invariant under rotations of the plane.</p>
<p>Now, if the vertical line through p does not contain any other point in P ∪ R, then, for the unique <em>r ∈ R</em> such that <em>p, p’</em>, and<em> r</em> are collinear, we have that:</p>
<p><img alt="(1)~~~(p-r)/(p-p')~=~(p_x-r_x)/(p_x-p'_x)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%281%29%7E%7E%7E%28p-r%29%2F%28p-p%27%29%7E%3D%7E%28p_x-r_x%29%2F%28p_x-p%27_x%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="(1)~~~(p-r)/(p-p')~=~(p_x-r_x)/(p_x-p'_x)"/>.</p>
<p>This leads to:</p>
<p><strong>Observation 3:</strong>  if the vertical line through <em>p</em> does not contain any other point in <em>P ∪ R</em>, then</p>
<p><img alt="(2)~~~ f(p) = \prod_{r \in R}(p_x-r_x) / \prod_{p' \in P\backslash \{p\}}(p_x-p'_x)." class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%282%29%7E%7E%7E+f%28p%29+%3D+%5Cprod_%7Br+%5Cin+R%7D%28p_x-r_x%29+%2F+%5Cprod_%7Bp%27+%5Cin+P%5Cbackslash+%5C%7Bp%5C%7D%7D%28p_x-p%27_x%29.&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="(2)~~~ f(p) = \prod_{r \in R}(p_x-r_x) / \prod_{p' \in P\backslash \{p\}}(p_x-p'_x)."/></p>
<p><strong>Crucial observation 4:</strong>  Let <em>p</em> and <em>q</em> be any two points in <em>P</em> and let <em>r</em> be the unique point in <em>R</em> collinear with <em>p</em> and<em> q</em>. Then</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><em>f(p)/f(q)=-(p-r)/(q-r).</em></h3>
<p>To see this rotate the plane so that the x-coordinates of <em>p,q</em>, and <em>r</em> are equal (or nearly equal) and apply Equations (2) and (1). (You will get the same, or nearly the same, contributions for <em>r’ ≠ r</em>  and you are left with the contribution for <em>r</em>. ) This also leads to:</p>
<p><strong>Observation 5:</strong> <em>f(p)/f(q)</em> <em>&gt;0</em>  if and only if the unique point <em>r ∈ R</em> that is collinear with <em>p</em> and<em> q</em> lies in the straight line segment delimited by <em>p</em> and <em>q</em>.</p>
<h3>A complete graph with green and red edges.</h3>
<p>Consider the complete graph <em>G</em> whose vertices are the points in <em>P</em>. For every two points <em>p, q ∈ P</em> we color the edge connecting  <em>p</em> and <em>q</em> <span style="color: #ff0000;"><strong>red</strong></span> if the unique point in <em>R</em> collinear with <em>p</em> and <em>q</em> lies outside the straight line segment connecting <em>p</em> and<em> q. </em>Otherwise we color the edge <span style="color: #008000;"><strong>green</strong></span>. In other words, the edge is <strong><span style="color: #ff0000;">red</span></strong> if<strong><span style="color: #ff0000;"> f(p)/f(q) &lt; 0</span></strong>, and <strong><span style="color: #339966;">green</span></strong> if <strong><span style="color: #339966;">f(p)/f(q) &gt; 0</span></strong>.</p>
<p>The vertices of G can naturally be partitioned into two sets:<i> U = {p ∈ P | f(p) &gt; 0}</i> and<i> W = {p ∈ P | f(p) &lt; 0}</i>.</p>
<p>Without loss of generality assume that the three vertices of the convex hull of P belong to <em>U</em>. (Since no point of R is outside this convex hull all edges of the triangle forming the convex hull are green.)</p>
<p><strong>Observation 6:</strong> <em>|U| = n/2 + 1.</em></p>
<p>To see this let <em>a,b</em> ∈ <em>U</em> be two vertices of the convex hull of <em>P</em>. Let <em>c</em> ∈ <em>R</em> be the point in <em>R</em> collinear with <em>a</em> and <em>b</em>. The point <em>c</em> must be between <em>a</em> and <em>b</em> on the boundary of the convex hull of <em>P</em>. Therefore, all the other n/2 −1 pairs of points of <em>P</em> that are collinear with c must form red edges. Consequently, precisely one point of every such pair belongs to U. Together with <em>a</em> and <em>b</em>, we obtain <em>|U| = n/2+1</em>.</p>
<p><strong>End of proof:</strong></p>
<p><span id="more-19479"/></p>
<p>Consider now any triangulation of the convex hull of <em>P</em> using all the vertices of <em>U</em>. This triangulation contains precisely <em>3|U|−6</em> edges all of which correspond to green edges in the graph <em>G</em>. Each edge in the triangulation contains a unique point in <em>R</em>. Therefore,</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>|R|≥ 3|1|−6 = 3n/2 −3.</em></p>
<p>This expression is greater than or equal to <em>n</em> for every <em>n ≥ 6</em>, as desired. <span style="color: #993366;"><strong>ahla!</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #339966;">(Good old Euler’s theorem is used.)</span></p>
<h2>Related things.</h2>
<p>Yesterday, our PM explained on TV what geometric (exponential) growth is.  If I try to describe related results and problems to the theorem presented here, and move on to related results and problems to those and so on, the amount of beautiful results from discrete geometry will grow exponentially but this post will never be completed.</p>
<p>So let me mention just a few things.</p>
<ol>
<li>The result is related to the Motzkin-Rabin Colorful Sylvester-Gallai theorem. Given a set of red points and blue points in the plane, not all on a line, the Motzkin-Rabin theorem asserts that there is a line that contains two or more points in the set, such that all the points on the line have the same color.</li>
<li>Starting with the Sylvester-Gallai theorem itself, there is a rich Gallai-Sylvester theory, with recent deep connections to the theory of computing; My <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/4661/the-sylvester-gallai-theorem-and-sections-of-varieties-with-simple-topology">third MathOverflow question</a> was about a Sylvester-Gallai type problem and here is a link to <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/4661/the-sylvester-gallai-theorem-and-sections-of-varieties-with-simple-topology#comment8133_4661">Greg Kuperberg remark</a>‘s regarding potential Gylvester-Kalai theorems.</li>
<li>Let me mention the <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2012/08/24/on-sets-defining-few-ordinary-lines/">2012 solution by Ben Green and Terry Tao</a> of the ordinary line conjecture and the Orchard conjecture.</li>
<li>Let me mention the proof of Andreii Kupavskii and Alexandr Polyanskii to <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1402.3694.pdf">Shur’s conjecture</a>.</li>
<li>Here is a <a href="http://www2.math.technion.ac.il/~room/ps_files/EPnCubic_s2.pdf">link to a very recent paper</a> by Chaya Keller and Rom Pinchasi. There they make the following <strong>bold conjecture</strong>: Let <em>P</em> be a set of n points in general position and and let <em>R</em> be a set of n points disjoint from P. If every line determined by P passes through a point in<em> R,</em> then <em>P </em>∪<em> R</em> is contained in a cubic curve.</li>
<li>There is, of course the famous book by Martin Aigner and Günter Ziegler: Proofs from the book.</li>
<li>At some point I tried to interest Günter with a companion book: The book of examples. We did not proceed with this project but this motivated my successful <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/4994/fundamental-examples">MathOverflow questions about fundamental examples</a>.</li>
<li>Eventually, Günter and I decided to write instead: the book of examples of polytopes. We went as far as writing a list of chapters of the book! (Which is a very advanced stage of writing a book, I suppose.)</li>
<li>When I took a class for high-school students interested in mathematics, the Sylvester problem was a starred problem in the first problem set and the assertion of the Motzkin-Rabin colored theorem was a double starred problem. Among the 20-30 students none of us found a (correct) solution. (We referred to it in a trivia question in <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/05/26/natis-influence/">this post</a>.) Years later, I gave the same class and gave the same starred problems, and one student managed to prove the Gallai-Sylvester theorem. Can you guess who he was?</li>
</ol>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-14T18:47:47Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-14T18:47:47Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <category term="What is Mathematics"/>
    <category term="Alexandr Polyanskii"/>
    <category term="Rom Pinchasi"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-03-26T23:25:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
