<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-12-16T19:38:42Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-411297283565155244</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/411297283565155244/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/12/optiland.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/411297283565155244" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/411297283565155244" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/12/optiland.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optiland</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Many of you have heard of Russell Impagliazzo's <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2004/06/impagliazzos-five-worlds.html">five worlds</a> from his 1995 classic <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/SCT.1995.514853">A personal view of average-case complexity</a> In short </p><ul><li><i>Algorithmica</i>: P = NP or something "morally equivalent" like fast probabilistic algorithms for NP. </li><li><i>Heuristica</i>: NP problems are hard in the worst case but easy on average.</li><li><i>Pessiland</i>: NP problems hard on average but no one-way functions exist. We can easily create hard NP problems, but not hard NP problems where we know the solution. </li><li><i>Minicrypt</i>: One-way functions exist but we do not have public-key cryptography.</li><li><i>Cryptomania</i>: Public-key cryptography is possible, i.e. two parties can exchange secret messages over open channels.</li></ul><div>Impagliazzo's world has an explicit "you can't have your cake and eat it too", either you can solve NP-hard problems on average, or have cryptography but not both (neither is possible). That's the mathematical world of P v NP. </div><div><br/></div><div>The reality is looking more and more like <i>Optiland</i>, where we can solve difficult NP problems and still have cryptography thanks to vast improvements in machine learning and optimization on faster computers with specialized hardware.</div><div><br/></div><div>Back in 2004 I <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2004/05/what-if-p-np.html">gave my guess</a> of the world of P = NP</div><div><blockquote>Learning becomes easy by using the principle of Occam's razor--we simply find the smallest program consistent with the data. Near perfect vision recognition, language comprehension and translation and all other learning tasks become trivial. We will also have much better predictions of weather and earthquakes and other natural phenomenon.</blockquote><p>Today you can take your smartphone, unlock it by having the phone scan your face, and ask it a question by talking and often get a reasonable answer, or have your question translated into a different language. You get alerts on your phone for weather and earthquakes, with far better predictions than we would have though possible a dozen years ago.</p><p>We have computed the <a href="http://www.math.uwaterloo.ca/tsp/uk/index.html">shortest traveling-salesman tour</a> through nearly 50K UK pubs. <a href="https://deepmind.com/blog/article/alphafold-a-solution-to-a-50-year-old-grand-challenge-in-biology">AlphaFold</a> can simulate protein folding with an accuracy nearly as good as what we get with real-world experiments. You can view GPT-3 as generating a form of a universal prior. Even beyond P = NP, we have self-trained computers easily besting humans in Chess, Go and Poker.</p><p>Meanwhile these techniques have done little to break cryptographic functions. Plenty of cybersecurity attacks but rarely by breaking the cryptography. </p><p>Not all is rosy--there is still much more we could do positively if P = NP  and we are already seeing some of the negative effects of learning such as loss of privacy. Nevertheless we are heading to a de facto best of both worlds when complexity theory tells us those worlds are incompatible. </p></div><p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-16T14:59:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-16T14:59:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T14:59:23Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5159</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5159" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5159#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5159" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Chinese BosonSampling: The gloves are off</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Two weeks ago, I blogged about the striking claim, by the group headed by Chaoyang Lu and Jianwei Pan at USTC in China, to have achieved quantum supremacy via BosonSampling with 50-70 detected photons. I also did a four-part interview on the subject with Jonathan Tennenbaum at Asia Times, and many other interviews elsewhere. None […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Two weeks ago, I <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5122">blogged about</a> the striking claim, by the group headed by Chaoyang Lu and Jianwei Pan at USTC in China, to have achieved quantum supremacy via BosonSampling with 50-70 detected photons.  I also did a <a href="https://asiatimes.com/2020/12/chinas-quantum-computer-a-step-not-a-leap/">four-part interview</a> on the subject with Jonathan Tennenbaum at Asia Times, and many other interviews elsewhere.  None of that stopped various people, who I guess didn’t google, from writing to tell me how disappointed they were by my silence!</p>



<p>The reality, though, is that a lot has happened since the original announcement, and it’s way past time for an update.</p>



<p><strong>I. The Quest to Spoof</strong></p>



<p>Most importantly, other groups almost immediately went to work trying to refute the quantum supremacy claim, by finding some efficient classical algorithm to spoof the reported results.  It’s important to understand that this is exactly how the process is <em>supposed</em> to work: as I’ve often stressed, a quantum supremacy claim is credible only if it’s open to the community to refute and if no one can.  It’s also important to understand that, for reasons we’ll go into, there’s a decent chance that people <em>will</em> succeed in simulating the new experiment classically, although they haven’t yet.  All parties to the discussion agree that the new experiment is, far and away, the closest any BosonSampling experiment has ever gotten to the quantum supremacy regime; the hard part is to figure out if it’s already there.</p>



<p>Part of me feels guilty that, as one of reviewers on the <em>Science</em> paper—albeit, one stressed and harried by kids and covid—it’s now clear that I didn’t exercise the amount of diligence that I could have, in searching for ways to kill the new supremacy claim.  But another part of me feels that, with quantum supremacy claims, much like with proposals for new cryptographic codes, vetting <em>can’t be the responsibility of one or two reviewers</em>.  Instead, provided the claim is serious—as this one obviously is—the only thing to do is to get the paper out, so that the <em>entire community</em> can then work to knock it down.  Communication between authors and skeptics is also a hell of a lot faster when it doesn’t need to go through a journal’s editorial system.</p>



<p>Not surprisingly, one skeptic of the new quantum supremacy claim is Gil Kalai, who (despite Google’s result last year, which Gil still believes must be in error) rejects the entire possibility of quantum supremacy on quasi-metaphysical grounds.  But other skeptics are current and former members of the Google team, including Sergio Boixo and John Martinis!  And—pause to enjoy the irony—<em>Gil has effectively teamed up with the Google folks</em> on questioning the new claim.  Another central figure in the vetting effort—one from whom I’ve learned much of what I know about the relevant issues over the last week—is Dutch quantum optics professor and frequent <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em> commenter <a href="https://people.utwente.nl/j.j.renema">Jelmer Renema</a>.</p>



<p>Without further ado, why might the new experiment, impressive though it was, be efficiently simulable classically?  A central reason for concern is photon loss: as Chaoyang Lu has now explicitly confirmed (it was implicit in the paper), up to ~70% of the photons get lost on their way through the beamsplitter network, leaving only ~30% to be detected.  At least with “Fock state” BosonSampling—i.e., the original kind, the kind with single-photon inputs that Alex Arkhipov and I proposed in 2011—it seems likely to me that such a loss rate would be fatal for quantum supremacy; see for example <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1809.01953">this 2019 paper</a> by Renema, Shchesnovich, and Garcia-Patron.</p>



<p>Incidentally, if anything’s become clear over the last two weeks, it’s that I, the co-inventor of BosonSampling, am no longer any sort of expert on the subject’s literature!</p>



<p>Anyway, one source of uncertainty regarding the photon loss issue is that, as I said in my last post, the USTC experiment implemented a 2016 variant of BosonSampling called <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.01199">Gaussian BosonSampling (GBS)</a>—and Jelmer tells me that the computational complexity of GBS in the presence of losses hasn’t yet been analyzed in the relevant regime, though there’s been <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.12075">work aiming in that direction</a>.  A second source of uncertainty is simply that the classical simulations work in a certain limit—namely, fixing the rate of noise and then letting the numbers of photons and modes go to infinity—but any real experiment has a fixed number of photons and modes (in USTC’s case, they’re ~50 and ~100 respectively).  It wouldn’t do to reject USTC’s claim via a theoretical asymptotic argument that would equally well apply to <em>any</em> non-error-corrected quantum supremacy demonstration!</p>



<p>OK, but if an efficient classical simulation of lossy GBS experiments exists, then <em>what is it?</em>  How does it work?  It turns out that we have a plausible candidate for the answer to that, originating with a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1409.3093">2014 paper</a> by Gil Kalai and Guy Kindler.  Given a beamsplitter network, Kalai and Kindler considered an infinite hierarchy of better and better approximations to the BosonSampling distribution for that network.  Roughly speaking, at the first level (k=1), one pretends that the photons are just classical distinguishable particles.  At the second level (k=2), one correctly models quantum interference involving <em>pairs</em> of photons, but none of the higher-order interference.  At the third level (k=3), one correctly models three-photon interference, and so on until k=n (where n is the total number of photons), when one has reproduced the original BosonSampling distribution.  At least when k is small, the time needed to spoof outputs at the k<sup>th</sup> level of the hierarchy should grow like n<sup>k</sup>.  As theoretical computer scientists, Kalai and Kindler didn’t care whether their hierarchy produced any physically realistic kind of noise, but later work, by Shchesnovich, Renema, and others, showed that (as it happens) it does.</p>



<p>In its original paper, the USTC team ruled out the possibility that the first, k=1 level of this hierarchy could explain its experimental results.  More recently, in response to inquiries by Sergio, Gil, Jelmer, and others, Chaoyang tells me they’ve ruled out the possibility that the k=2 level can explain their results either.  We’re now eagerly awaiting the answer for larger values of k.</p>



<p>Let me add that I owe Gil Kalai the following public <em>mea culpa</em>.  While his objections to QC have often struck me as unmotivated and weird, in the case at hand, Gil’s 2014 work with Kindler is clearly helping drive the scientific discussion forward.  In other words, at least with BosonSampling, it turns out that Gil put his finger precisely on a key issue.  He did exactly what every QC skeptic should do, and what I’ve always implored the skeptics to do.</p>



<p><strong>II. BosonSampling vs. Random Circuit Sampling: A Tale of HOG and CHOG and LXEB</strong></p>



<p>There’s a broader question: why should skeptics of a BosonSampling experiment even have to <em>think</em> about messy details like the rate of photon losses?  Why shouldn’t that be solely the <em>experimenters’</em> job?</p>



<p>To understand what I mean, consider the situation with Random Circuit Sampling, the task Google demonstrated last year with 53 qubits.  There, the Google team simply collected the output samples and fed them into a benchmark that they called “Linear Cross-Entropy” (LXEB), closely related to what Lijie Chen and I called “Heavy Output Generation” (HOG) in a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.05903">2017 paper</a>.  With suitable normalization, an ideal quantum computer would achieve an LXEB score of 2, while classical random guessing would achieve an LXEB score of 1.  Crucially, according to a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.12085">2019 result</a> by me and Sam Gunn, under a plausible (albeit strong) complexity assumption, <em>no</em> subexponential-time classical spoofing algorithm should be able to achieve an LXEB score that’s even slightly bounded above 1.  In its experiment, Google reported an LXEB score of about 1.002, with a confidence interval <em>much</em> smaller than 0.002.  Hence: quantum supremacy (subject to our computational assumption), with no further need to know anything about the sources of noise in Google’s chip!  (More explicitly, Boixo, Smelyansky, and Neven <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1708.01875">did a calculation</a> in 2017 to show that the Kalai-Kindler type of spoofing strategy <em>definitely</em> isn’t going to work against RCS and Linear XEB, with no computational assumption needed.)</p>



<p>So then why couldn’t the USTC team do something analogous with BosonSampling?  Well, they tried to.   They defined a measure that they called “HOG,” although it’s different from my and Lijie Chen’s HOG, more similar to a cross-entropy.  Following Jelmer, let me call their measure CHOG, where the C could stand for Chinese, Chaoyang’s, or Changed.  They calculated the CHOG for their experimental samples, and showed that it exceeds the CHOG that you’d get from the k=1 and k=2 levels of the Kalai-Kindler hierarchy, as well as from various other spoofing strategies, thereby ruling those out as classical explanations for their results.</p>



<p>The trouble is this: <em>unlike </em>with Random Circuit Sampling and LXEB, with BosonSampling and CHOG, we <em>know</em> that there are fast classical algorithms that achieve better scores than the trivial algorithm, the algorithm that just picks samples at random.  That follows from Kalai and Kindler’s work, and it even more simply follows from a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1309.7460">2013 paper</a> by me and Arkhipov, entitled “BosonSampling Is Far From Uniform.”  Worse yet, with BosonSampling, we currently have no analogue of my 2019 result with Sam Gunn: that is, a result that would tell us (under suitable complexity assumptions) the highest possible CHOG score that we expect any efficient classical algorithm to be able to get.  And since we don’t know exactly where that ceiling is, we can’t tell the experimentalists exactly what target they need to surpass in order to claim quantum supremacy.  Absent such definitive guidance from us, the experimentalists are left playing whac-a-mole against <em>this</em> possible classical spoofing strategy, and <em>that</em> one, and <em>that</em> one.</p>



<p>This is an issue that I and others were aware of for years, although the new experiment has certainly underscored it.  Had I understood <em>just how serious</em> the USTC group was about scaling up BosonSampling, and fast, I might’ve given the issue some more attention!</p>



<p><strong>III. Fock vs. Gaussian BosonSampling</strong></p>



<p>Above, I mentioned another complication in understanding the USTC experiment: namely, their reliance on Gaussian BosonSampling (GBS) rather than Fock BosonSampling (FBS), sometimes also called Aaronson-Arkhipov BosonSampling (AABS).  Since I gave this issue short shrift in my previous post, let me make up for it now.</p>



<p>In FBS, the initial state consists of either 0 or 1 photons in each input mode, like so: |1,…,1,0,…,0⟩.  We then pass the photons through our beamsplitter network, and measure the number of photons in each output mode.  The result is that the amplitude of each possible output configuration can be expressed as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permanent_(mathematics)">permanent</a> of some n×n matrix, where n is the total number of photons.  It was interest in the permanent, which plays a central role in classical computational complexity, that led me and Arkhipov to study BosonSampling in the first place.</p>



<p>The trouble is, preparing initial states like |1,…,1,0,…,0⟩ turns out to be really hard.  No one has yet build a source that reliably outputs <em>one and only one photon</em> at exactly a specified time.  This led two experimental groups to propose an idea that, in a <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=1579">2013 post on this blog</a>, I named Scattershot BosonSampling (SBS).  In SBS, you get to use the more readily available “Spontaneous Parametric Down-Conversion” (SPDC) photon sources, which output superpositions over different numbers of photons, of the form $$\sum_{n=0}^{\infty} \alpha_n |n \rangle |n \rangle, $$ where α<sub>n</sub> decreases exponentially with n.  You then measure the left half of each entangled pair, <em>hope</em> to see exactly one photon, and are guaranteed that if you do, then there’s also exactly one photon in the right half.  Crucially, one can show that, if Fock BosonSampling is hard to simulate approximately using a classical computer, then the Scattershot kind must be as well.</p>



<p>OK, so what’s <em>Gaussian</em> BosonSampling?  It’s simply the generalization of SBS where, instead of SPDC states, our input can be an arbitrary “Gaussian state”: for those in the know, a state that’s exponential in some quadratic polynomial in the creation operators.  If there are m modes, then such a state requires ~m<sup>2</sup> independent parameters to specify.  The quantum optics people have a much easier time creating these Gaussian states than they do creating single-photon Fock states.</p>



<p>While the amplitudes in FBS are given by permanents of matrices (and thus, the probabilities by the absolute squares of permanents), the probabilities in GBS are given by a more complicated matrix function called the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hafnian">Hafnian</a>.  Roughly speaking, while the permanent counts the number of perfect matchings in a bipartite graph, the Hafnian counts the number of perfect matchings in an <em>arbitrary</em> graph.  The permanent and the Hafnian are both #P-complete.  In the USTC paper, they talk about yet another matrix function called the “Torontonian,” which was <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1807.01639.pdf">invented two years ago</a>.  I gather that the Torontonian is just the modification of the Hafnian for the situation where you only have “threshold detectors” (which decide whether one or more photons are present in a given mode), rather than “number-resolving detectors” (which <em>count</em> how many photons are present).</p>



<p>If Gaussian BosonSampling includes Scattershot BosonSampling as a special case, and if Scattershot BosonSampling is at least as hard to simulate classically as the original BosonSampling, then you might hope that GBS would <em>also</em> be at least as hard to simulate classically as the original BosonSampling.  Alas, this doesn’t follow.  Why doesn’t it?  Because for all we know, a <em>random</em> GBS instance might be a lot easier than a <em>random</em> SBS instance.  Just because permanents can be expressed using Hafnians, doesn’t mean that a random Hafnian is as hard as a random permanent.</p>



<p>Nevertheless, I think it’s very likely that the sort of analysis Arkhipov and I did back in 2011 could be mirrored in the Gaussian case.  I.e., instead of starting with reasonable assumptions about the distribution and hardness of random permanents, and then concluding the classical hardness of approximate BosonSampling, one would simply start with reasonable assumptions about the distribution and hardness of random Hafnians (or “Torontonians”), and conclude the classical hardness of approximate GBS.  But this is theoretical work that remains to be done!</p>



<p><strong>IV. Application to Molecular Vibronic Spectra?</strong></p>



<p>In 2014, Alan Aspuru-Guzik and collaborators put out a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1412.8427">paper</a> that made an amazing claim: namely that, contrary to what I and others had said, BosonSampling was <em>not</em> an intrinsically useless model of computation, good only for refuting QC skeptics like Gil Kalai!  Instead, they said, a BosonSampling device (specifically, what would later be called a GBS device) could be directly applied to solve a practical problem in quantum chemistry.  This is the computation of “molecular vibronic spectra,” also known as “Franck-Condon profiles,” whatever those are.</p>



<p>I never understood nearly enough about chemistry to evaluate this striking proposal, but I was always a bit skeptical of it, for the following reason.  Nothing in the proposal seemed to take seriously that BosonSampling is a <em>sampling</em> task!  A chemist would typically have some <em>specific numbers</em> that she wants to estimate, of which these “vibronic spectra” seemed to be an example.  But while it’s often convenient to estimate physical quantities via Monte Carlo sampling over simulated observations of the physical system you care about, that’s not the <em>only</em> way to estimate physical quantities!  And worryingly, in all the other examples we’d seen where BosonSampling could be used to estimate a number, the same number could <em>also</em> be estimated using one of several polynomial-time classical algorithms invented by Leonid Gurvits.  So why should vibronic spectra be an exception?</p>



<p>After an email exchange with Alex Arkhipov, Juan Miguel Arrazola, Leonardo Novo, Raul Garcia-Patron, I believe we finally got to the bottom of it, and the answer is: vibronic spectra are <em>not</em> an exception.  In terms of BosonSampling, the vibronic spectra task is simply to estimate the probability histogram of some weighted linear combination like $$ w_1 s_1 + \cdots + w_ m s_m, $$ where w<sub>1</sub>,…,w<sub>m</sub> are fixed real numbers, and (s<sub>1</sub>,…,s<sub>m</sub>) is a possible outcome of the BosonSampling experiment, s<sub>i</sub> representing the number of photons observed in mode i.  Alas, while it takes some work, it turns out that Gurvits’s classical algorithms can be adapted to estimate these histograms.  Granted, running the actual BosonSampling experiment would provide <em>slightly</em> more detailed information—namely, some exact sampled values of $$ w_1 s_1 + \cdots + w_ m s_m, $$ rather than merely additive approximations to the values—but since we’d still need to sort those sampled values into coarse “bins” in order to compute a histogram, it’s not clear why that additional precision would ever be of chemical interest.</p>



<p>This is a pity, since if it <em>had</em> beaten what was doable classically, then it would’ve provided not merely a first practical application of BosonSampling, but also a lovely way to <em>verify</em> that a BosonSampling device was working as intended.</p>



<p><strong>V. Application to Finding Dense Subgraphs?</strong></p>



<p>A different potential application of Gaussian BosonSampling was suggested by the Toronto-based startup <a href="https://www.xanadu.ai/">Xanadu</a>: namely, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.10730">finding dense subgraphs in a graph</a>.  (Or at least, providing an initial seed to classical optimization methods that search for dense subgraphs.)</p>



<p>This is an NP-hard problem, so to say that I was skeptical of the proposal would be a gross understatement.  Nevertheless, it turns out that there <em>is</em> a striking new observation by the Xanadu team at the core of the proposal: namely, that given a graph G and a positive even integer k, a GBS device can be used to sample a random subgraph of G of size k, with probability <em>proportional to the square of the number of perfect matchings in that subgraph</em>.  Cool, right?  And potentially even useful, especially if the number of perfect matchings could serve as a rough indicator of the subgraph’s density!  Alas, Xanadu’s Juan Miguel Arrazola himself recently told me that there’s a cubic-time classical algorithm for the same sampling task, so that the possible quantum speedup that one could get from GBS in this way is at most polynomial.  The search for a useful application of BosonSampling continues!</p>



<p/><hr/><p/>



<p>And that’s all for now!  I’m grateful to all the colleagues I talked to over the last couple weeks, including Alex Arkhipov, Juan Miguel Arrazola, Sergio Boixo, Raul Garcia-Patron, Leonid Gurvits, Gil Kalai, Chaoyang Lu, John Martinis, and Jelmer Renema, while obviously taking sole responsibility for any errors in the above.  I look forward to a spirited discussion in the comments, and of course I’ll post updates as I learn more!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-16T08:16:30Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-16T08:16:30Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:07:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/12/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/12/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>3d-printed models of the chaotic attractors from dynamical systems (\(\mathbb{M}\)). Stephen K. Lucas, Evelyn Sander, and Laura Taalman in the cover article of the latest Notices.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/202011/rnoti-p1692.pdf">3d-printed models of the chaotic attractors from dynamical systems</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105309562849621245">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Stephen K. Lucas, Evelyn Sander, and Laura Taalman in the cover article of the latest <em>Notices</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1333670741590503425.html">Complete classification of tetrahedra whose angles are all rational multiples of \(\pi\)</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105311921075649463">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://aperiodical.com/2020/12/aperiodical-news-roundup-november-2020/">via</a>). The original paper is “<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.14232">Space vectors forming rational angles</a>”, by Kiran S. Kedlaya, Alexander Kolpakov, Bjorn Poonen, and Michael Rubinstein.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.maa.org/programs/faculty-and-departments/classroom-capsules-and-notes/geometry-strikes-again">Geometry strikes again</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105320692550081128">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://www.metafilter.com/189571/slaps-roof-this-bad-boy-can-fit-so-many-fucking-polyhedra-in-it">via</a>), Branko Grünbaum, <em>Math. Mag.</em> 1985. Somehow I don’t think I’d encountered this short paper before but it’s filled with many examples of horribly-drawn mathematics, one in the logo of the MAA. Worth reading as a warning for what not to do. Also for clear instructions on how to draw regular icosahedra correctly.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2020/12/04/1013294/google-ai-ethics-research-paper-forced-out-timnit-gebru">Ethical issues in large-corpus natural language processing, or what’s behind the research that got Timnit Gebru kicked out of Google</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105326128589157740">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25311402">via</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://jack.wrenn.fyi/blog/brown-location-surveillance/">How one university (Brown) tracks the physical locations of its students to ensure compliance with its pandemic safety policies</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105330487336321470">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25319392">via</a>). Most of it is pretty obvious: if you use a campus keycard or connect to a campus wireless network, they know you’re on campus.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/madhukarpai/2020/11/30/how-prestige-journals-remain-elite-exclusive-and-exclusionary/?sh=1c14baef4d48">How prestige journals remain elite, exclusive and exclusionary</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105345990074471874">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://retractionwatch.com/2020/12/05/weekend-reads-google-ai-researcher-fired-after-being-asked-to-retract-paper-journal-accused-of-stonewalling-on-paper-used-to-justify-human-rights-violations-reflecting-on-a-covid-19-retraction/">via</a>). Nature is charging up to €9,500 per paper in open-access fees, as much as some scientists in third-world countries earn in a year, making open-access publication inaccessible to people from low- and middle-income countries.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclidean_distance">Euclidean distance</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105348855359182047">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), now a Good Article on Wikipedia.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematician-solves-centuries-old-grazing-goat-problem-exactly-20201209/">Ingo Ullisch and the goats</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@btcprox/105354303333088090">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). A new solution to the problem of how to bisect the area of a circle by another circular arc centered on the first circle. But, given that it involves integrals and trig, is it really fair to call it “more exact” than the previous solution? I don’t think we even know whether the solution radius is transcendental (or transcendental over \(\pi\)).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.anilaagha.com/sculpturelooksee">Anila Quayyum Agha’s openwork sculptures cast intricate tessellated shadows on the surrounding surfaces</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105360602658987905">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). See also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anila_Quayyum_Agha">her Wikipedia article</a> and two stories on her work, “<a href="http://canjournal.org/2019/11/between-light-and-shadow-at-the-toledo-museum-of-art/">Between light and shadow at the Toledo Museum of Art</a>” and “<a href="https://news.artnet.com/art-world/anila-quayyum-agha-interview-741371">Anila Quayyum Agha on drawing inspiration from darkness</a>”.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Pat Morin notes that it’s “good to see that the pandemic hasn’t affected every aspect of our lives”: <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@patmorin/105362925062596140">the registration fees for the online SODA conference are still way too high</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2020/12/10/ieees-refusal-to-issue-corrections/">IEEE has no mechanism to publish corrections or errata to conference proceedings papers</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105369247233466112">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://retractionwatch.com/2020/12/12/weekend-reads-p-hacking-the-us-election-an-apparently-fake-author-sinks-a-stock-sued-for-using-a-research-tool/">via</a>), violating IEEE’s own code of ethics requiring authors “to acknowledge and correct errors”:  Probably many other conference proceedings have similar issues.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://cp4space.hatsya.com/2020/12/13/shallow-trees-with-heavy-leaves/">Shallow trees with heavy leaves</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105375238890363766">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). On “the general strategy of searching much fewer positions and expending more effort on each position”, and its application in using SAT solvers to find new spaceships in cellular automata.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.flyingcoloursmaths.co.uk/dictionary-of-mathematical-eponymy-the-xuong-tree">Dictionary of mathematical eponymy: The Xuong tree</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105382771623486905">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xuong_tree">see also</a>), a special kind of spanning tree in graphs, used to embed them into surfaces with as high a genus as possible.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://journals.carleton.ca/jocg/index.php/jocg/article/view/461">An explicit PL-embedding of the square flat torus into \(\mathbb{E}^3\)</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105385674493868301">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). The square torus is like the old Asteroids arcade game: a Euclidean square with boundary conditions that wrap around so if you move off one edge you re-enter at the corresponding point of the opposite edge. In 4d, it has a nice representation as the set \(\{(a,b,c,d)\mid a^2+b^2=c^2+d^2=1\}\), the Cartesian product of two circles. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nash_embedding_theorem">Nash embedding theorem</a> gives it fractal embeddings in 3d, but Tanessi Quintanar finds it as a bona fide polyhedron.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-15T21:28:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-15T21:28:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T05:54:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/15/postdoc-at-microsoft-research-apply-by-january-15-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/15/postdoc-at-microsoft-research-apply-by-january-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at Microsoft Research (apply by January 15, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Algorithms group at Microsoft Research Redmond seeks exceptional researchers who are passionate about advancing the state of the art in theoretical computer science and having impact on the industry. Applicants must have a demonstrated ability for independent research and a strong academic publication record in theoretical computer science. Website: https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/group/algorithms-redmond/ Email: yekhanin@microsoft.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Algorithms group at Microsoft Research Redmond seeks exceptional researchers who are passionate about advancing the state of the art in theoretical computer science and having impact on the industry. Applicants must have a demonstrated ability for independent research and a strong academic publication record in theoretical computer science.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/group/algorithms-redmond/">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/group/algorithms-redmond/</a><br/>
Email: yekhanin@microsoft.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-15T20:30:15Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-15T20:30:15Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/15/researcher-at-microsoft-research-apply-by-january-31-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/15/researcher-at-microsoft-research-apply-by-january-31-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Researcher at Microsoft Research (apply by January 31, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Algorithms group at Microsoft Research Redmond seeks exceptional researchers who are passionate about advancing the state of the art in theoretical computer science and having impact on the industry. Applicants must have a demonstrated ability for independent research and a strong academic publication record in theoretical computer science. Website: https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/group/algorithms-redmond/ Email: yekhanin@microsoft.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Algorithms group at Microsoft Research Redmond seeks exceptional researchers who are passionate about advancing the state of the art in theoretical computer science and having impact on the industry. Applicants must have a demonstrated ability for independent research and a strong academic publication record in theoretical computer science.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/group/algorithms-redmond/">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/group/algorithms-redmond/</a><br/>
Email: yekhanin@microsoft.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-15T20:27:56Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-15T20:27:56Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/15/postdoc-at-university-of-michigan-apply-by-january-10-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/15/postdoc-at-university-of-michigan-apply-by-january-10-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at University of Michigan (apply by January 10, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Theory Group at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor invites applications for a postdoctoral position beginning September, 2021. The position will have an initial appointment for one year, but may be extended depending on circumstances. Applicants should be recent PhDs with interests that align well with our ongoing research. Please email a CV, research […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Theory Group at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor invites applications for a postdoctoral position beginning September, 2021. The position will have an initial appointment for one year, but may be extended depending on circumstances.</p>
<p>Applicants should be recent PhDs with interests that align well with our ongoing research.</p>
<p>Please email a CV, research statement, and names of references.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://theory.engin.umich.edu">https://theory.engin.umich.edu</a><br/>
Email: pettie@umich.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-15T18:18:05Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-15T18:18:05Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4446</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/12/15/kim-ki-duk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Kim Ki-duk</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(Last call for the postdoc positions I advertised earlier. Application deadline is tomorrow morning Italian time, tonight American time.) Last weekend I was saddened to hear of the death of Korean filmmaker Kim Ki-duk. Kim was in Latvia, preparing to … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/12/15/kim-ki-duk/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>(Last call for the <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/11/22/post-doc-opportunities-in-milan/">postdoc positions I advertised earlier</a>. Application deadline is tomorrow morning Italian time, tonight American time.)<br/><br/>Last weekend I was saddened to hear of the death of Korean filmmaker Kim Ki-duk. Kim was in Latvia, preparing to shoot a movie there. He disappeared about a week ago, and it then transpired that he had been hospitalized with Covid symptoms, and died last Friday from Covid complications.</p>



<p>In the early 2000s, living in the San Francisco Bay Area offered me several opportunities to discover cinema that was new to me. There were the several film festivals held each year in San Francisco, the wonderful retrospectives at the Castro Theater. There was also Netflix, that at the time operated by renting DVDs by mail (I am feeling like grandpa Simpson telling stories here) and whose catalog was basically every movie ever released in the US. I discovered the work of Hirokazu Kore-eda and Wong Kar-Wai, whose movies are now among my favorites, and I watched some challenging but rewarding movies by the likes of Tsai Ming-Lian and Hou Hsiao-Hsien. So, when it came out, I watched “3-iron” by Kim Ki-duk, an amazing movie on the theme of the poor being invisible to the rich, but taken to extreme and fantastical places.</p>



<p>I was reminded of that time during our first lockdown last Spring. After having watched a lot of TV series, I felt like I had to do something a bit more soul-nourishing before the lockdown ended. So I resolved to watch Tarkovsky’s “Solaris” and “Stalker”, which I had never seen. Compared with movies I had watched 15+ years ago like those of Tsai Ming-Lian and Hou Hsiao-Hsien, or like “3-iron”, “Solaris” was like a Michael Bay movie full of explosions and car chases, but I still had a really hard time getting into it. I ended up watching it over five or six sittings, across a couple of weeks (the lockdown actually ended before I was done watching it). I still haven’t seen “Stalker”. I suppose that twelve years of smartphone usage accounts for the difference in attention span.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-15T10:29:11Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-15T10:29:11Z</published>
    <category term="movies"/>
    <category term="3-iron"/>
    <category term="Goodbye Dragon Inn"/>
    <category term="Kim Ki-duk"/>
    <category term="Solaris"/>
    <category term="Stalker"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:09Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/15/tenure-track-faculty-at-bar-ilan-university-apply-by-february-2-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/15/tenure-track-faculty-at-bar-ilan-university-apply-by-february-2-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure Track Faculty at Bar Ilan University (apply by February 2, 2021)</title>
    <summary>We are recruiting excellent tenure-track faculty for our Industrial and Information Systems Engineering track (and the respective IISE degree—the only one in Israel that formally meets the requirements for both IE and IS disciplines with a strong DS flavor). Requirements: A PhD in Information Systems, Computer Science, and related fields, post-doctoral training. Want to hear […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We are recruiting excellent tenure-track faculty for our Industrial and Information Systems Engineering track (and the respective IISE degree—the only one in Israel that formally meets the requirements for both IE and IS disciplines with a strong DS flavor). Requirements: A PhD in Information Systems, Computer Science, and related fields, post-doctoral training.<br/>
Want to hear more? Let’s talk.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://engineering.biu.ac.il/en/node/8797">https://engineering.biu.ac.il/en/node/8797</a><br/>
Email: izack.cohen@biu.ac.il</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-15T09:31:54Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-15T09:31:54Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/15/postdoc-senior-researcher-at-hamburg-university-of-technology-apply-by-january-11-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/15/postdoc-senior-researcher-at-hamburg-university-of-technology-apply-by-january-11-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc/Senior Researcher at Hamburg University of Technology (apply by January 11, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Institute for Algorithms and Complexity at TUHH: Hamburg University of Technology invites applications for a 5-year postdoc position (attached to DASHH: Data Science in Hamburg). The focus is on algorithms and combinatorial optimization with applications in the natural sciences. Data-driven algorithms and algorithm engineering are supported through world-class data facilities at DESY/XFEL. Website: https://www.tuhh.de/algo/jobs.html […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Institute for Algorithms and Complexity at TUHH: Hamburg University of Technology invites applications for a 5-year postdoc position (attached to DASHH: Data Science in Hamburg). The focus is on algorithms and combinatorial optimization with applications in the natural sciences. Data-driven algorithms and algorithm engineering are supported through world-class data facilities at DESY/XFEL.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.tuhh.de/algo/jobs.html">https://www.tuhh.de/algo/jobs.html</a><br/>
Email: algo@tuhh.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-15T08:50:14Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-15T08:50:14Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.07214</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.07214" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Sketch for traffic measurement: design, optimization, application and implementation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1607990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Shangsen.html">Shangsen Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Luo:Lailong.html">Lailong Luo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Guo:Deke.html">Deke Guo</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.07214">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Network measurement probes the underlying network to support upper-level
decisions such as network management, network update, network maintenance,
network defense and beyond. Due to the massive, speedy, unpredictable features
of network flows, sketches are widely implemented in measurement nodes to
record the frequency or estimate the cardinality of flows approximately. At
their cores, sketches usually maintain one or multiple counter array(s), and
relies on hash functions to select the counter(s) for each flow. Then the
space-efficient sketches from the distributed measurement nodes are aggregated
to provide statistics of the undergoing flows. Currently, tremendous redesigns
and optimizations have been proposed to further improve the sketches for better
network measurement performance. However, the existing reviews or surveys
mainly focus on one particular aspect of measurement tasks. Researchers and
engineers in the network measurement community desire an all-in-one survey
which covers the whole processing pipeline of sketch-based network measurement.
To this end, we present the first comprehensive survey in this area. We first
introduce the preparation of flows for measurement, then detail the most recent
investigations of design, aggregation, decoding, application and implementation
of sketches for network measurement. To summary the existing efforts, we
conduct an in-depth study of the existing literature, covering more than 80
sketch designs and optimization strategies. Furthermore, we conduct a
comprehensive analysis and qualitative/quantitative comparison of the sketch
designs. Finally, we highlight the open issues for future sketch-based network
measurement research.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-15T22:42:03Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.07135</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.07135" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Uniform Capacitated Facility Location Problems with Penalties/Outliers</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1607990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Rajni Dabas, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gupta:Neelima.html">Neelima Gupta</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grover:Sapna.html">Sapna Grover</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.07135">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we present a framework to design approximation algorithms for
capacitated facility location problems with penalties/outliers using
LP-rounding. Primal-dual technique, which has been particularly successful in
dealing with outliers and penalties, has not been very successful in dealing
with capacities. On the other hand, no primal-dual solution has been able to
break the hardness of capacitated facility location problem(CFLP). LP-rounding
techniques had also not been very successful in dealing with capacities until a
recent work by Grover et al. \cite{GroverGKP18}. Their constant factor
approximation violating the capacities by a small factor ($1 + \epsilon$) is
promising while dealing with capacities.Though LP-rounding has not been very
promising while dealing with penalties and outliers, we successfully apply it
to deal with them along with capacities. That is, our results are obtained by
rounding the solution to the natural LP once again exhibiting the power of
LP-rounding technique. Solutions obtained by LP-rounding are easy to integrate
with other LP-based algorithms.In this paper, we apply our framework to obtain
first constant factor approximations for capacitated facility location problem
with outlier (CFLPO) and capacitated $k$-facility location problem with
penalty(C$k$FLPP) for hard uniform capacities using LP-rounding. Our solutions
incur slight violations in capacities, ($1 + \epsilon$) for the problems
without cardinality($k$) constraint and ($2 + \epsilon$) for the problems with
the cardinality constraint. For the outlier variant, we also incur a small loss
($1 + \epsilon$) in outliers. Due to the hardness of the underlying problems,
the violations are inevitable. Thus we achieve the best possible by rounding
the solution of natural LP for these problems. To the best of our knowledge, no
results are known for CFLPO and C$k$FLPP.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-15T22:41:14Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.07056</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.07056" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>If VNP is hard, then so are equations for it</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1607990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kumar:Mrinal.html">Mrinal Kumar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ramya:C=.html">C. Ramya</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saptharishi:Ramprasad.html">Ramprasad Saptharishi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tengse:Anamay.html">Anamay Tengse</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.07056">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Assuming that the Permanent polynomial requires algebraic circuits of
exponential size, we show that the class VNP does not have efficiently
computable equations. In other words, any nonzero polynomial that vanishes on
the coefficient vectors of all polynomials in the class VNP requires algebraic
circuits of super-polynomial size.
</p>
<p>In a recent work of Chatterjee and the authors (FOCS 2020), it was shown that
the subclasses of VP and VNP consisting of polynomials with bounded integer
coefficients do have equations with small algebraic circuits. Their work left
open the possibility that these results could perhaps be extended to all of VP
or VNP. The results in this paper show that assuming the hardness of Permanent,
at least for VNP, allowing polynomials with large coefficients does indeed
incur a significant blow up in the circuit complexity of equations.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-15T22:38:04Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.06978</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.06978" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Largest similar copies of convex polygons amidst polygonal obstacles</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1607990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Eom:Taekang.html">Taekang Eom</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lee:Seungjun.html">Seungjun Lee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Ahn:Hee=Kap.html">Hee-Kap Ahn</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.06978">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a convex polygon $P$ with $k$ vertices and a polygonal domain $Q$
consisting of polygonal obstacles with total size $n$ in the plane, we study
the optimization problem of finding a largest similar copy of $P$ that can be
placed in $Q$ without intersecting the obstacles. We improve the time
complexity for solving the problem to $O(k^2n^2\lambda_4(k)\log{n})$. This is
progress of improving the previously best known results by Chew and Kedem
[SoCG89, CGTA93] and Sharir and Toledo [SoCG91, CGTA94] on the problem in more
than 25 years.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-15T22:43:54Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.06874</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.06874" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Book Embeddings of k-Map Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1607990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Brandenburg:Franz_J=.html">Franz J. Brandenburg</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.06874">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A map is a partition of the sphere into regions that are labeled as countries
or holes. The vertices of a map graph are the countries of a map. There is an
edge if and only if the countries are adjacent and meet in at least one point.
For a k-map graph, at most k countries meet in a point. A graph is k-planar if
it can be drawn in the plane with at most k crossings per edge. A p-page book
embedding of a graph is a linear ordering of the vertices and an assignment of
the edges to p pages, so that there is no conflict for edges assigned to the
same page. The minimum number of pages is the book thickness of a graph, also
known as stack number or page number. We show that every k-map graph has a book
embedding in $6\lfloor k/2 \rfloor+5$ pages, which, for n-vertex graphs, can be
computed in O(kn) time from its map. Our result improves the best known upper
bound. Towards a lower bound, it is shown that some k-map graphs need $\lfloor
3k/4 \rfloor$ pages. In passing, we obtain an improved upper bound of eleven
pages for 1-planar graphs, which are subgraphs of 4-map graphs, and of 17 pages
for optimal 2-planar graphs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-15T22:43:17Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.06779</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.06779" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hard QBFs for Merge Resolution</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1607990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Beyersdorff:Olaf.html">Olaf Beyersdorff</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Blinkhorn:Joshua.html">Joshua Blinkhorn</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mahajan:Meena.html">Meena Mahajan</a>, Tomáš Peitl, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sood:Gaurav.html">Gaurav Sood</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.06779">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We prove the first proof size lower bounds for the proof system Merge
Resolution (MRes [Olaf Beyersdorff et al., 2020]), a refutational proof system
for prenex quantified Boolean formulas (QBF) with a CNF matrix. Unlike most QBF
resolution systems in the literature, proofs in MRes consist of resolution
steps together with information on countermodels, which are syntactically
stored in the proofs as merge maps. As demonstrated in [Olaf Beyersdorff et
al., 2020], this makes MRes quite powerful: it has strategy extraction by
design and allows short proofs for formulas which are hard for classical QBF
resolution systems.
</p>
<p>Here we show the first exponential lower bounds for MRes, thereby uncovering
limitations of MRes. Technically, the results are either transferred from
bounds from circuit complexity (for restricted versions of MRes) or directly
obtained by combinatorial arguments (for full MRes). Our results imply that the
MRes approach is largely orthogonal to other QBF resolution models such as the
QCDCL resolution systems QRes and QURes and the expansion systems
$\forall$Exp+Res and IR.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-15T22:39:10Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.06713</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.06713" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximate Trace Reconstruction</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1607990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Davies:Sami.html">Sami Davies</a>, Miklos Z. Racz, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rashtchian:Cyrus.html">Cyrus Rashtchian</a>, Benjamin G. Schiffer <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.06713">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the usual trace reconstruction problem, the goal is to exactly reconstruct
an unknown string of length $n$ after it passes through a deletion channel many
times independently, producing a set of traces (i.e., random subsequences of
the string). We consider the relaxed problem of approximate reconstruction.
Here, the goal is to output a string that is close to the original one in edit
distance while using much fewer traces than is needed for exact reconstruction.
We present several algorithms that can approximately reconstruct strings that
belong to certain classes, where the estimate is within $n/\mathrm{polylog}(n)$
edit distance, and where we only use $\mathrm{polylog}(n)$ traces (or sometimes
just a single trace). These classes contain strings that require a linear
number of traces for exact reconstruction and which are quite different from a
typical random string. From a technical point of view, our algorithms
approximately reconstruct consecutive substrings of the unknown string by
aligning dense regions of traces and using a run of a suitable length to
approximate each region. To complement our algorithms, we present a general
black-box lower bound for approximate reconstruction, building on a lower bound
for distinguishing between two candidate input strings in the worst case. In
particular, this shows that approximating to within $n^{1/3 - \delta}$ edit
distance requires $n^{1 + 3\delta/2}/\mathrm{polylog}(n)$ traces for $0&lt; \delta
&lt; 1/3$ in the worst case.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.06702</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.06702" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Lions and contamination, triangular grids, and Cheeger constants</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1607990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Adams:Henry.html">Henry Adams</a>, Leah Gibson, Jack Pfaffinger <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.06702">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Suppose each vertex of a graph is originally occupied by contamination,
except for those vertices occupied by lions. As the lions wander on the graph,
they clear the contamination from each vertex they visit. However, the
contamination simultaneously spreads to any adjacent vertex not occupied by a
lion. How many lions are required in order to clear the graph of contamination?
We give a lower bound on the number of lions needed in terms of the Cheeger
constant of the graph. Furthermore, the lion and contamination problem has been
studied in detail on square grid graphs by Brass et al. and Berger et al., and
we extend this analysis to the setting of triangular grid graphs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-15T22:41:52Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2010.10272</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2010.10272" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Scalable Shared-Memory Hypergraph Partitioning</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1607990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gottesb=uuml=ren:Lars.html">Lars Gottesbüren</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Heuer:Tobias.html">Tobias Heuer</a>, Peter Sanders, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schlag:Sebastian.html">Sebastian Schlag</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2010.10272">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Hypergraph partitioning is an important preprocessing step for optimizing
data placement and minimizing communication volumes in high-performance
computing applications. To cope with ever growing problem sizes, it has become
increasingly important to develop fast parallel partitioning algorithms whose
solution quality is competitive with existing sequential algorithms. To this
end, we present Mt-KaHyPar, the first shared-memory multilevel hypergraph
partitioner with parallel implementations of many techniques used by the
sequential, high-quality partitioning systems: a parallel coarsening algorithm
that uses parallel community detection as guidance, initial partitioning via
parallel recursive bipartitioning with work-stealing, a scalable label
propagation refinement algorithm, and the first fully-parallel direct $k$-way
formulation of the classical FM algorithm. Experiments performed on a large
benchmark set of instances from various application domains demonstrate the
scalability and effectiveness of our approach. With 64 cores, we observe
self-relative speedups of up to 51 and a harmonic mean speedup of 23.5. In
terms of solution quality, we outperform the distributed hypergraph partitioner
Zoltan on 95% of the instances while also being a factor of 2.1 faster. With
just four cores,Mt-KaHyPar is also slightly faster than the fastest sequential
multilevel partitioner PaToH while producing better solutions on 83% of all
instances. The sequential high-quality partitioner KaHyPar still finds better
solutions than our parallel approach, especially when using max-flow-based
refinement. This, however, comes at the cost of considerably longer running
times.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-15T22:40:52Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5171</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5171" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5171#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5171" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Beth Harmon and the Inner World of Squares</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">The other day Dana and I finished watching The Queen’s Gambit, Netflix’s fictional saga of an orphaned girl in the 1960’s, Beth Harmon, who breaks into competitive chess and destroys one opponent after the next in her quest to become the world champion, while confronting her inner demons and addictions. The show is every bit as astoundingly […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The other day Dana and I finished watching <em>The Queen’s Gambit</em>, Netflix’s fictional saga of an orphaned girl in the 1960’s, Beth Harmon, who breaks into competitive chess and destroys one opponent after the next in her quest to become the world champion, while confronting her inner demons and addictions.</p>



<p>The show is every bit as astoundingly good as everyone says it is, and I might be able to articulate why.  It’s because, perhaps surprisingly given the description, this is a story where <em>chess actually matters</em>—and indeed, the fact that chess matters so deeply to Beth and most of the other characters is central to the narrative.  (As in two pivotal scenes where Beth has sex with a male player, and then either she or he goes right back to working on chess.)</p>



<p>I’ve watched a lot of TV shows and movies, supposedly about scientists, where the science was just an interchangeable backdrop to what the writers clearly regarded as a more important story.  (As one random example, the drama <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Numbers_(TV_series)">NUMB3RS</a>, supposedly about an FBI mathematician, where “math” could’ve been swapped out for “mystical crime-fighting intuition” with barely any change.)</p>



<p>It’s true that a fictional work about scientists shouldn’t try to be a science documentary, just like <em>Queen’s Gambit</em> doesn’t try to be a chess documentary.  But if you’re telling a story about characters who are obsessed with topic X, then you need to <em>make their obsession plausible</em>, make the entire story hinge on it, and even make the audience vicariously feel the same obsession.</p>



<p>This is precisely what <em>Queen’s Gambit</em> does for chess.  It’s a chess drama where the characters are <em>constantly</em> talking about chess, thinking about chess, and playing chess—and that actually succeeds in making that riveting.  (Even if most of the audience can’t follow what’s happening on the board, it turns out that it doesn’t matter, since you can simply convey the drama through the characters’ faces and the reactions of those around them.)</p>



<p>Granted, a few aspects of competitive chess in the series stood out as jarringly unrealistic even to a novice like me: for example, the almost complete lack of draws.  But as for the board positions—well, apparently Kasparov was a consultant, and he helped meticulously design each one to reflect the characters’ skill levels and what was happening in the plot.</p>



<p>While the premise sounds like a feminist wish-fulfillment fantasy—orphan girl faces hundreds of intimidating white men in the sexist 1960s, orphan girl beats them all at their own game with style and aplomb—this is not at all a MeToo story, or a story about male crudity or predation.  It’s after bigger fish than that.  The series, you might say, conforms to all the external requirements of modern woke ideology, yet the actual plot subverts the tenets of that ideology, or maybe just ignores them, in its pursuit of more timeless themes.</p>



<p>At least once Beth Harmon enters the professional chess world, the central challenges she needs to overcome are internal and mental—just like they’re supposed to be in chess.  It’s not the Man or the Patriarchy or any other external power (besides, of course, skilled opponents) holding her down.  Again and again, the top male players are portrayed not as sexist brutes but as gracious, deferential, and even awestruck by Beth’s genius after she’s humiliated them on the chessboard.  And much of the story is about how those vanquished opponents then turn around and try to help Beth, and about how she needs to learn to accept their help in order to evolve as a player and a human being.</p>



<p>There’s also that, after defeating male player after male player, Beth sleeps with them, or at least wants to.  I confess that, as a teenager, I would’ve found that unlikely and astonishing.  I would’ve said: obviously, the only guys who’d even have a <em>chance</em> to prove themselves worthy of the affection of such a brilliant and unique woman would be those who could beat her at chess.  Anyone else would just be dirt between her toes.  In the series, though, each male player propositions Beth only <em>after</em> she’s soundly annihilated him.  And she’s never once shown refusing.</p>



<p>Obviously, I’m no Beth Harmon; I’ll never be close in my field to what she is in hers.  Equally obviously, I grew up in a loving family, not an orphanage.  Still, I was what some people would call a “child prodigy,” what with the finishing my PhD at 22 and whatnot, so naturally that colored my reaction to the show.</p>



<p>There’s a pattern that goes like this: you’re obsessively interested, from your first childhood exposure, in something that most people aren’t.  Once you learn what the something is, it’s evident to you that your life’s vocation couldn’t possibly be anything else, unless some external force prevents you.  Alas, in order to pursue the something, you first need to get past bullies and bureaucrats, who dismiss you as a nobody, put barriers in your way, despise whatever you represent to them.  After a few years, though, the bullies can no longer stop you: you’re finally among peers or superiors in your chosen field, regularly chatting with them on college campuses or at conferences in swanky hotels, and the main limiting factor is just the one between your ears. </p>



<p>You feel intense rivalries with your new colleagues, of course, you desperately want to excel them, but the fact that they’re all on the same obsessive quest as you means you can never actually hate them, as you did the bureaucrats or the bullies.  There’s too much of you in your competitors, and of them in you.</p>



<p>As you pursue your calling, you feel yourself torn in the following way.  On the one hand, you feel close to a moral obligation to humanity not to throw away whatever “gift” you were “given” (what loaded terms), to take the calling as far as it will go.  On the other hand, you also want the same things other people want, like friendship, validation, and of course sex.</p>



<p>In such a case, two paths naturally beckon.  The first is that of asceticism: making a virtue of eschewing all temporal attachments, romance or even friendship, in order to devote yourself entirely to the calling.  The second is that of renouncing the calling, pretending it never existed, in order to fit in and have a normal life.  Your fundamental challenge is to figure out a third path, to plug yourself into a community where the relentless pursuit of the unusual vocation and the friendship and the sex can all complement each other rather than being at odds.</p>



<p>It would be an understatement to say that I have some familiarity with this narrative arc.</p>



<p>I’m aware, of course, of the irony, that I can identify with so many contours of Beth Harmon’s journey—I, Scott Aaronson, who half the Internet denounced six years ago as a misogynist monster who denies the personhood and interiority of women.  In that life-alteringly cruel slur, there was a microscopic grain of truth, and it’s this: I’m not talented at imagining myself into the situations of people different from me.  It’s never been my strong suit.  I might <em>like</em> and <em>admire</em> people different from me, I might sympathize with their struggles and wish them every happiness, but I still don’t know what they’re thinking until they tell me.  And even then, I don’t fully understand it.</p>



<p>As one small but illustrative example, I have no intuitive understanding—zero—of what it’s like to be romantically attracted to men, or what any man could do or say or look like that could possibly be attractive to women.  If you have such an understanding, then imagine yourself sighted and me blind.  Intellectually, I might know that confidence or height or deep brown eyes or brooding artistry are supposed to be attractive in human males, but only because I’m told.  As far as my intuition is concerned, pretty much all men are equally hairy, smelly, and gross, a large fraction of women are alluring and beautiful and angelic, and both of those are just objective features of reality that no one could possibly see otherwise.</p>



<p>Thus, whenever I read or watch fiction starring a female protagonist who dates men, it’s very easy for me to imagine that protagonist judging me, enumerating my faults, and rejecting me, and very hard for me to do what I’m supposed to do, which is to <em>put myself into her shoes</em>.  I could watch a thousand female protagonists kiss a thousand guys onscreen, or wake up in bed next to them, and the thousandth-and-first time I’d still be equally mystified about what she saw in such a sweaty oaf and why she didn’t run from him screaming, and I’d snap out of vicariously identifying with her.  (Understanding gay men of course presents similar difficulties; understanding lesbians is comparatively easy.)</p>



<p>It’s possible to overcome this, but it takes an extraordinary female protagonist, brought to life by an extraordinary writer.  Off the top of my head, I can think of only a few.  There were Renee Feuer and Eva Mueller, the cerebral protagonists of Rebecca Newberger Goldstein’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mind-Body-Problem-Contemporary-American-Fiction/dp/0140172459"><em>The Mind-Body Problem</em></a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Summer-Passion-Woman-Vintage-Contemporaries/dp/0679728236"><em>The Late Summer Passion of a Woman of Mind</em></a>.  Maybe Ellie Arroway from Carl Sagan’s <em>Contact</em>.  And then there’s Beth Harmon.  With characters like these, I can briefly enter a space where their crushes on men seem no weirder or more inexplicable to me than my own teenage crushes … just, you know, inverted.  Sex is in any case secondary to the character’s primary urge to discover timeless truths, an urge that I fully understand because I’ve shared it.</p>



<p>Granted, the timeless truths of chess, an arbitrary and invented game, are less profound than those of quantum gravity or the P vs. NP problem, but the psychology is much the same, and <em>The Queen’s Gambit</em> does a good job of showing that.  To understand the characters of this series is to understand why they could be happier to lose an interesting game than to win a boring one.  And I could appreciate that, even if I was by no means the strongest player at my elementary school’s chess club, and the handicap with which I can beat my 7-year-old daughter is steadily decreasing.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-14T23:31:26Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-14T23:31:26Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Embarrassing Myself"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Procrastination"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:07:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/187</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/187" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-187 |  If VNP is hard, then so are equations for it | 

	Mrinal Kumar, 

	C Ramya, 

	Ramprasad Saptharishi, 

	Anamay Tengse</title>
    <summary>Assuming that the Permanent polynomial requires algebraic circuits of exponential size, we show that the class VNP *does not* have efficiently computable equations. In other words, any nonzero polynomial that vanishes on the coefficient vectors of all polynomials in the class VNP requires algebraic circuits of super-polynomial size.

In a recent work of Chatterjee and the authors (FOCS 2020), it was shown that the subclasses of VP and VNP consisting of polynomials with bounded integer coefficients *do*  have equations with small algebraic circuits. Their work left open the possibility that these results could perhaps be extended to all of VP or VNP. The results in this paper show that assuming the hardness of Permanent, at least for VNP, allowing polynomials with large coefficients does indeed incur a significant blow up in the circuit complexity of equations.</summary>
    <updated>2020-12-13T14:31:53Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-13T14:31:53Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/186</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/186" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-186 |  Shrinkage of Decision Lists and DNF Formulas | 

	Benjamin Rossman</title>
    <summary>We establish nearly tight bounds on the expected shrinkage of decision lists and DNF formulas under the $p$-random restriction $\mathbf R_p$ for all values of $p \in [0,1]$. For a function $f$ with domain $\{0,1\}^n$, let $\mathrm{DL}(f)$ denote the minimum size of a decision list that computes $f$. We show that
\[
  \mathbb E[\ \mathrm{DL}(f|\mathbf R_p)\ ] \le 
  \mathrm{DL}(f)^{\log_{2/(1-p)}(\frac{1+p}{1-p})}.
\]
For example, this bound is $\sqrt{\mathrm{DL}(f)}$ when $p = \sqrt{5}-2 \approx 0.24$. For Boolean functions $f$, we obtain the same shrinkage bound with respect to DNF formula size plus $1$ (i.e.,\ replacing $\mathrm{DL}(\cdot)$ with $\mathrm{DNF}(\cdot)+1$ on both sides of the inequality).</summary>
    <updated>2020-12-13T07:19:56Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-13T07:19:56Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/185</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/185" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-185 |  Quantum learning algorithms imply circuit lower bounds | 

	Tom Gur, 

	Alex Grilo, 

	Igor Oliveira, 

	Srinivasan Arunachalam, 

	Aarthi Sundaram</title>
    <summary>We establish the first general connection between the design of quantum algorithms and  circuit lower bounds. Specifically, let $\mathrm{C}$ be a class of polynomial-size concepts, and suppose that $\mathrm{C}$ can be PAC-learned with membership queries under the uniform distribution with error $1/2 - \gamma$ by a time $T$ quantum algorithm. We prove that if $\gamma^2 \cdot T \ll 2^n/n$, then $\mathrm{BQE} \not\subseteq \mathrm{C}$, where $\mathrm{BQE} = \mathrm{BQTIME}[2^{O(n)}]$ is an exponential-time analogue of $\mathrm{BQP}$. This result is optimal in both $\gamma$ and $T$, since it is not hard to learn any class $\mathcal{C}$ of functions in (classical) time $T = 2^n$  (with no error), or in quantum time $T = \mathrm{poly}(n)$ with error at most $1/2 - \Omega(2^{-n/2})$ via Fourier sampling. In other words, even a marginal improvement on these generic learning algorithms would lead to major consequences in complexity theory. 

Our proof builds on several works in learning theory, pseudorandomness, and computational complexity, and crucially, on a connection between non-trivial classical learning algorithms and circuit lower bounds established by Oliveira and Santhanam (CCC 2017). Extending their approach to quantum learning algorithms turns out to create significant challenges. To achieve that, we show among other results how pseudorandom generators imply learning-to-lower-bound connections in a generic fashion, construct the first conditional pseudorandom generator secure against uniform quantum computations, and extend the local list-decoding algorithm of Impagliazzo, Jaiswal, Kabanets and Wigderson (SICOMP 2010) to quantum circuits via a delicate analysis. We believe that these contributions are of independent interest and might find other applications.</summary>
    <updated>2020-12-13T07:09:56Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-13T07:09:56Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-4105007709227774779</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/4105007709227774779/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/12/quarterly-theory-workshop-any-lessons.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/4105007709227774779" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/4105007709227774779" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/12/quarterly-theory-workshop-any-lessons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quarterly Th. Wksp `at' Northwestern, and thoughts inspired by it</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> On the <a href="https://theory.cs.northwestern.edu/events/">Northwestern CS Theory Group</a> there is a set of Quarterly Theory Workshops. There is one coming up on Dec 17-18, 2020, called the <a href="https://theory.cs.northwestern.edu/events/2020-junior-theorists-workshop/">Junior Theorists Workshop</a>. Take a look and possibly go to it! Because it is virtual you do not need to plan that much ahead- though they do want you to register. </p><p>1) I notice broadly two kinds of meetings:</p><p><br/>Based on WHO will be there, e.g., JUNIOR theorists</p><p><br/>Based on TOPIC: e.g., there was a meeting on ALGORITHMIC FAIRNESS.</p><p><br/></p><p>2) These types of meetings (NY Theory day is another) are, I believe, intended to be for people that are local (more on that later). But because the meeting will be on zoom, geography is no longer an impediment for either the attendees or the speakers. </p><p><br/></p><p>3) Before covid there was some talk of  `Gee, flying off to STOC, FOCS, other conferences is bad for the environment, what to do about that?'. With that in mind, here is a history which might not be true but makes a point:</p><p><i>In an earlier era FOCS/STOC were attended by mostly Americans and ICALP was attended by mostly Europeans.  I do not think there was any policy of discrimination on admissions, but it was more like Americans just did not submit to ICALP as much, nor Europeans  to FOCS/STOC. But over time when these conferences got to be considered prestigious people would routinely submit to either one depending on timing. If your paper was done in time for Conf X deadline, that's where you submit. If it does not get in then  you edit it some, perhaps add some new results, and submit to Conf Y. </i></p><p>So one solution to the air-travel-global-Warming   problem of conferences is go back to a time (which may not have ever existed) where it was just understood that you go to LOCAL conferences. Math does this, but it helps that their regional conferences are not  prestigious. But even they don't quite get it right: the joint AMS-MAA meeting alternates coasts. One year when it was in California they invited me to be a guest speaker (on the Muffin Problem). The following year it was in Baltimore. Note that I live in Maryland, so perhaps they should have waited a year. </p><p>How to encourage people to submit locally. I DO NOT want to have a rule or a diff standard for those who don't. As such... I have no idea. </p><p><br/></p><p>4)  Are virtual conferences a good idea? This is a hot topic now so I won't dwell on it, just to say that there is still something about being there IN PERSON, meeting people, serendipity that makes live confs better.</p><p>However, to have it at the same time be virtual and recorded will be VERY HELPFL to those who can't afford to go for whatever reason. </p><p>And of course there is the whole issue of if we should have prestigious conferences, which I won't get into now. Or later. That's more Lance's issue (he thinks no). </p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-12T20:33:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-12T20:33:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T14:59:23Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17885</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/12/12/is-the-end-near/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Is The End Near?</title>
    <summary>Queen’s Gambit and more Kenneth Regan is my partner here at GLL and a dear friend. He is a longtime faculty member in computer science at the University of Buffalo, a longtime fan of the Buffalo NFL football team, and a longtime international master of chess. He is also one of the world experts on […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Queen’s Gambit and more</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p>
Kenneth Regan is my partner here at GLL and a dear friend. </p>
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/12/12/is-the-end-near/ken-2/" rel="attachment wp-att-17887"><img alt="" class="alignright  wp-image-17887" height="180" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/ken.jpg?w=140&amp;h=180" width="140"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>He is a longtime faculty member in computer science at the University of Buffalo, a longtime fan of the Buffalo NFL football team, and a longtime international master of chess. He is also one of the world experts on detecting cheating at chess. Players cheat by making their moves based on computer programs instead of relying on their brains. The key issue is: computer programs play chess better than any human. </p>
<p>
Today I thought we might send Ken a tip-of-the-hat for being in the Wall Street Journal. </p>
<p>
That is he is featured in a WSJ article called <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-real-queens-gambit-catching-chess-cheaters-11607439491">Queen’s Gambit</a> about chess cheating. </p>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/12/12/is-the-end-near/tip3/" rel="attachment wp-att-17888"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-17888" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/tip3.png?w=200" width="200"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>

</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
This is not his first mention in the WSJ—see <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/high-tech-chess-cheaters-charge-ahead-1444404660">here</a>. See <a href="http://www.buffalo.edu/news/releases/2020/12/010.html">this</a> for additional comments by Cory Nealon, who says: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> The game of chess is no stranger to cheating. But since the pandemic hit and tournaments have moved online, the services of chess detectives have never been more in demand. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Ken is perhaps the world’s most feared chess detective. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Beyond Chess </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Chess is important, but it is a game. Yet chess cheating may be an early warning of things to come. Might robotic methods in other areas soon start to dominate humans? Might chess be one of first areas to be lost to robots?</p>
<p>
A 1970 movie that comes to mind is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colossus:_The_Forbin_Project">The Forbin Project</a>. The plot is what happens when a computer system, Colossus, takes over the world. Its creator is Dr. Forbin, has the following exchange with it at the end of the movie: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Colossus later tells Forbin that the world, now freed from war, will create a new human millennium that will raise mankind to new heights, but only under its absolute rule. Colossus informs Forbin that “freedom is an illusion” and that “in time you will come to regard me not only with respect and awe, but with love”. Forbin responds, “Never!” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
I think there is a reason to worry about computers like Colossus wiping us out. Perhaps not taking absolute control, but nevertheless making us second class citizens. I wonder if the following areas could be potential ones where we lose out to computers:</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>Protein folding?</i> They already are doing quite <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/12/02/too-long-didnt-read/">well</a>.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>Play calling in the NFL?</i> I made this one up, but I do wonder if using all the statistics available programs could do a better job than players and coaches. They probably could already do better than the Jets defensive coach, who was recently <a href="https://sports.yahoo.com/report-jets-fire-defensive-coordinator-gregg-williams-after-legendarily-awful-loss-to-raiders-161424493.html">fired</a>. </p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>Solving Open Math Problems?</i> We recently talked about <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2013/07/14/surely-you-are-joking/#comment-114892">Lean</a> the proof checking system. But what if Lean could start to conjecture, to suggest directions, and give a proof outline? This would be, I believe, much more disruptive than the ability to check proofs.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
What are some areas that you think could be next? That could be taken over by robots?<br/>
Moreover, as more areas are dominated by robots, we will need more Ken’s to stop cheaters. </p>
<p>
Thanks again Ken. </p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-12T16:16:21Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-12T16:16:21Z</published>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="arrows"/>
    <category term="cheating"/>
    <category term="chess"/>
    <category term="Ken Regan"/>
    <category term="Wall Street Journal"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=20470</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/12/12/open-problem-session-of-huji-combsem-problem-3-ehud-friedgut-independent-sets-and-lionel-levins-infamous-hat-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Open problem session of HUJI-COMBSEM: Problem #3, Ehud Friedgut – Independent sets and Lionel Levine’s infamous hat problem.</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here are the two problems presented by Ehud Friedgut. The first arose by Friedgut, Kindler, and me in the context of studying  Lionel Levine’s infamous hat problem. The second is Lionel Levine’s infamous hat problem. Ehud Friedgut with a few … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/12/12/open-problem-session-of-huji-combsem-problem-3-ehud-friedgut-independent-sets-and-lionel-levins-infamous-hat-problem/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Here are the two problems presented by Ehud Friedgut. The first arose by Friedgut, Kindler, and me in the context of studying  Lionel Levine’s infamous hat problem. The second<em> is</em> Lionel Levine’s infamous hat problem.</p>
<h2><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/ef3h.jpeg"><img alt="" class="size-medium wp-image-20618 aligncenter" height="300" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/ef3h.jpeg?w=169&amp;h=300" width="169"/></a></h2>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Ehud Friedgut with a few hats</span></p>
<p>Earlier problems in this series: #1 <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/25/open-problem-session-of-huji-combsem-problem-1-nati-linial-turan-type-theorems-for-simplicial-complexes/">Nati Linial</a>; #2<a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/12/10/open-problem-session-of-huji-combsem-problem-2-chaya-keller-the-krasnoselskii-number/"> Chaya Keller</a>; <a href="https://huji.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=1ac330a2-d6b7-4b86-9bac-ac7500d14205">videotaped session</a>.</p>
<h2>Problem 1: Independence numbers for random induced subgraphs</h2>
<p>For a graph <img alt="G" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G"/> let <img alt="\alpha (G)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha+%28G%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\alpha (G)"/> be its independence number, namely the maximum  size of an independent set of vertices in <img alt="G" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G"/>. Now consider a random subset <img alt="W" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="W"/> of the set <img alt="V" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=V&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="V"/> of vertices of <img alt="G" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G"/>. A vertex <img alt="v \in V" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v+%5Cin+V&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v \in V"/> belongs to <img alt="W" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="W"/> with probability 1/2, independently.  Now let <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="H"/> be the induced graph from <img alt="G" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G"/> on <img alt="W" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="W"/>. Denote by <img alt="\alpha^-(G)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha%5E-%28G%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\alpha^-(G)"/> the expected value of <img alt="\alpha (H)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha+%28H%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\alpha (H)"/> over all such random induced subgraphs <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="H"/>.</p>
<p><strong>Conjecture:</strong> For every real number <img alt="\tau" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctau&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tau"/>, <img alt="0&lt;\tau&lt;1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=0%3C%5Ctau%3C1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="0&lt;\tau&lt;1"/> there is <img alt="\epsilon(\tau ) &gt;0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cepsilon%28%5Ctau+%29+%3E0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\epsilon(\tau ) &gt;0"/> such that if <img alt="\alpha (G) =\tau n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha+%28G%29+%3D%5Ctau+n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\alpha (G) =\tau n"/> then <img alt="\alpha^-(G) \le (\tau-\epsilon(\tau ))n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha%5E-%28G%29+%5Cle+%28%5Ctau-%5Cepsilon%28%5Ctau+%29%29n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\alpha^-(G) \le (\tau-\epsilon(\tau ))n"/>.</p>
<p>If we look at the example <img alt="G" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G"/> of the complete graph on 1/τ vertices we get that <img alt="\alpha^-(G) =&#xA0; (1-2^{-1/\tau})" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha%5E-%28G%29+%3D%C2%A0+%281-2%5E%7B-1%2F%5Ctau%7D%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\alpha^-(G) =&#xA0; (1-2^{-1/\tau})"/>. The reason is that the independence number of <img alt="G" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G"/> is always 1 except in one case occurring with probability <img alt="2^{-1/\tau}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2%5E%7B-1%2F%5Ctau%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="2^{-1/\tau}"/> where <img alt="W" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=W&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="W"/> is empty.</p>
<p>An example coming from a random graph <img alt="G(n,p)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G%28n%2Cp%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G(n,p)"/>  gives that <img alt="\epsilon (\tau)&#xA0; = \tau (1-2^{c(-1/\tau)\cdot (\log (1/\tau)}) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cepsilon+%28%5Ctau%29%C2%A0+%3D+%5Ctau+%281-2%5E%7Bc%28-1%2F%5Ctau%29%5Ccdot+%28%5Clog+%281%2F%5Ctau%29%7D%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\epsilon (\tau)&#xA0; = \tau (1-2^{c(-1/\tau)\cdot (\log (1/\tau)}) "/> and the strong conjecture is that <img alt="\epsilon(\tau )" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cepsilon%28%5Ctau+%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\epsilon(\tau )"/> can be taken to be <img alt="2^{C(-1/\tau)\cdot&#xA0; (\log (1/\tau)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2%5E%7BC%28-1%2F%5Ctau%29%5Ccdot%C2%A0+%28%5Clog+%281%2F%5Ctau%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="2^{C(-1/\tau)\cdot&#xA0; (\log (1/\tau)}"/>. (Here, <img alt="c,C" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=c%2CC&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="c,C"/> are constants.)</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/fkk.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-20603" height="149" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/fkk.png?w=640&amp;h=149" width="640"/></a></p>
<div class="wp-caption alignnone" id="attachment_20597" style="width: 650px;"><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/ll.jpg"><img alt="" class="size-full wp-image-20597" height="212" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/ll.jpg?w=640&amp;h=212" width="640"/></a><p class="wp-caption-text" id="caption-attachment-20597"><span style="color: #ff0000;">LIONEL LEVINE</span></p></div>
<h2>Problem 2: Lionel Levine’s infamous hat problem.</h2>
<h3>Warm up problem:</h3>
<p><img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n"/> people are assigned at random white/black hats, Each person sees the hats of the other and need to guess the color of her own hat. They can decide in advance on the guessing strategy and their aim is maximize the probability that they all guessed correctly. How well they can do?</p>
<p>It turns out that there is a strategy with 50% chance of winning. They all need to assume that there are overall an even number of black hats.</p>
<h3>The real infamous hat problem by Lionel Levine</h3>
<p>Now every player has an infinite tower of hats on her head and, again, the hats are taken to be white or black at random. Again each players see all the hats of other players and again the players can plan in advance a strategy for success, This time each player has to point to one of the hats on her head and  the players WIN if all these hats are black.</p>
<p>Again, based on the hats of all others the k-th player says something like “I think the 7th hat on my head is black” or “I think the 3rd hat on my head is black” and the players win if all these statement are correct.</p>
<p><strong>Conjecture:</strong> As the number of players grows the probability for success tends to zero.</p>
<p>Let <img alt="p_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=p_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="p_k"/> be the success probability for <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/> players. (Remark: instead of having infinite number of hats we can assume that <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/> is fixed, each player has <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n"/> hats, and then let <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n"/> goes to infinity.</p>
<p>Ehud explained why <img alt="1/3 \le p_2 \le 3/8" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1%2F3+%5Cle+p_2+%5Cle+3%2F8&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="1/3 \le p_2 \le 3/8"/>. He challenged the audience to prove that <img alt="p_3 &lt; p_2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=p_3+%3C+p_2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="p_3 &lt; p_2"/> which is unknown.</p>
<p>The problem was presented in <a href="https://blog.tanyakhovanova.com/2011/04/how-many-hats-can-fit-on-your-head/">this 2011 post</a>  on <a href="https://blog.tanyakhovanova.com/" title="Tanya Khovanova's Math Blog: Mathematics, applications of mathematics to life in general, and my life as a mathematician.">Tanya Khovanova’s Math Blog.</a> Tanya also offered a new variant of her own.  It was also <a href="https://www.brand.site.co.il/riddles/201607q.html">July 2016 riddle</a> further discussed <a href="https://www.brand.site.co.il/riddles/201607a.html">here</a> on the math riddles site “<a href="https://www.brand.site.co.il/riddles/">Using your head is permitted</a>”</p>
<p>Below:<span style="color: #ff0000;"> Ehud and Guy</span><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/namaste.jpg"><img alt="" class="size-medium wp-image-20607 aligncenter" height="300" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/namaste.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300" width="225"/></a><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/gk-zoom-yoga.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-20621" height="173" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/gk-zoom-yoga.png?w=300&amp;h=173" width="300"/></a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-12T16:07:26Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-12T16:07:26Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Probability"/>
    <category term="Ehud Friedgut"/>
    <category term="Guy Kindler"/>
    <category term="Lionel Levine"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-12-12-raft-liveness-full-omission/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-12-12-raft-liveness-full-omission/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Raft does not Guarantee Liveness in the face of Network Faults</title>
    <summary>Last month, Cloudflare published a postmortem of a recent 6-hour outage caused by a partial switch failure which left etcd unavailable as it was unable to establish a stable leader. This outage has understandably led to discussion online about exactly what liveness guarantees are provided by the Raft consensus algorithm...</summary>
    <updated>2020-12-12T14:01:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-12T14:01:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T04:38:48Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5162</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5162" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5162#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5162" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Happy Chanukah / Vaccine Approval Day!</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Inspired by my survey article, John Pavlus has now published an article on Busy Beaver for Quanta magazine. This week, I flitted back and forth between two virtual conferences: the Institute for Advanced Study’s Online Workshop on Qubits and Black Holes (which I co-organized with Juan Maldacena and Mark Van Raamsdonk), and Q2B (Quantum 2 […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ol><li>Inspired by my <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/papers/bb.pdf">survey article</a>, John Pavlus has now published an <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/the-busy-beaver-game-illuminates-the-fundamental-limits-of-math-20201210/">article on Busy Beaver</a> for <em>Quanta</em> magazine.<br/></li><li>This week, I flitted back and forth between <em>two</em> virtual conferences: the Institute for Advanced Study’s <a href="https://www.ias.edu/sns/quantum-information-workshop-2020">Online Workshop on Qubits and Black Holes</a> (which I co-organized with Juan Maldacena and Mark Van Raamsdonk), and <a href="https://q2b.qcware.com/">Q2B (Quantum 2 Business) 2020</a>, organized by QC Ware, for which I did my now-annual Ask-Me-Anything session.  It was an interesting experience, switching between Euclidean path integrals and replica wormholes that I barely understood, and corporate pitches for near-term quantum computing that I … well, <em>did</em> understand!  Anyway, happy to discuss either conference in the comments.<br/></li><li>For anyone interested in the new Chinese quantum supremacy claim based on Gaussian BosonSampling—the story has developing rapidly all week, with multiple groups trying to understand the classical difficulty of simulating the experiment.  I’ll plan to write a followup post soon!<br/></li><li>The Complexity Zoo has now officially moved from the University of Waterloo to <a href="https://complexityzoo.net/Complexity_Zoo">complexityzoo.net</a>, hosted by the LessWrong folks!  Thanks so much to Oliver Habryka for setting this up.  <strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update (Dec. 12):</span></strong> Alas, complexityzoo.com no longer works if you use https.  I don’t know how to fix it—the Bluehost control panel provides no options—and I’m not at a point in life where I can deal again with Bluehost SSL certificate hell.  (How does everyone else deal with this shit?  That’s the one part I don’t understand.)  So, for now, you’ll need to update your bookmarks to complexityzoo.net.<br/></li><li>In return for his help with Zoo, Oliver asked me to help publicize a handsome $29 five-book set, <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/books">“A Map that Reflects the Territory,”</a> containing a selection of the best essays from LessWrong, including multiple essays by the much-missed Scott Alexander, and an essay on common knowledge inspired by my own <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=2410">Common Knowledge and Aumann’s Agreement Theorem</a>.  (See also the <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/TTPux7QFBpKxZtMKE/the-lesswrong-book-is-available-for-pre-order">FAQ</a>.)  If you know any LW fans, I can think of few better gifts to go under their Christmas tree or secular rationalist equivalent.</li></ol></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-11T17:54:54Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-11T17:54:54Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:07:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4438</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/12/11/bocconi-is-looking-for-assistant-professors-in-computer-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Bocconi is Looking for Assistant Professors in Computer Science</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[application page] [call for applications] Bocconi University is looking for two Tenure-Track Assistant Professors in Computer Science, for positions starting in Fall 2021. This is in the context of a build-up toward a new department focused on Computer Science, which … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/12/11/bocconi-is-looking-for-assistant-professors-in-computer-science/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://jobmarket.unibocconi.eu/application.php?f=YjA2NGMyYjczODcyYTkxMWMxNzE5MDVjZWM5NGFkNTJeNjI=">[application page]</a> <a href="https://jobmarket.unibocconi.eu/include/dwload.php?a=Mjg2XmVhOWY0MWYzNzJlMTJmYjI2NDhiZmU0MDI2ODZjMjQyXi9kMC9qb2JtYXJrZXQudW5pYm9jY29uaS5ldS91cGxvYWQvREVDL3Nlc3Npb25fNjItMjAyMDExMTNeam1rX3Nlc3Npb25eam1zX15qbXNfZmlsZV9kZXRhaWxzX2VuXjYy">[call for applications]</a></p>



<p>Bocconi University is looking for two Tenure-Track Assistant Professors in Computer Science, for positions starting in Fall 2021. This is in the context of a build-up toward a new department focused on Computer Science, which is part of the University’s strategic plan, and which is expected to be launched by Fall 2022.</p>



<p>Bocconi is Italy’s premiere private University, located in Milan. It is well known for its excellence in Economics and Management, and a few years ago it has begun a push into the hard sciences and engineering. Currently it offers a <em>Bachelor on Economics, Management and Computer Science</em>, a <em>Bachelor on Mathematical and Computing Sciences for Artificial Intelligence</em>, and a <em>Master’s in Data Science and Analytics</em>. There is a PhD program in Statistics and Computer Science. Additional programs related to computing are being planned.</p>



<p>The University negotiates salaries on an individual basis, and is able to put together very competitive offer packages. Scholars moving to Milan from outside Italy gain, in addition, a 6+ year tax break (90% of the salary is exempt from income tax). The University provides relocation benefits and employs full time staff to assist non-Italian-speaking faculty. Students are admitted on the basis of a competitive admission exam. A large fraction of them are foreigners, and the general academic level is fairly high.</p>



<p>A special note for Italians on how the position relates to positions in public Universities (in Italian because this is only a local concern): la posizione di “assistant professor” è simile a quella di RTDA, ma è un contratto di diritto privato. Dopo una valutazione intermedia, si passa ad una posizione simile a RTDB, ma sempre con un contratto distinto di diritto privato, e dopo una tenure review si viene promossi ad associati. I ruoli di associati ed ordinari sono inquadrati nel sistema nazionale e parificati (a parte la possibilità di una integrazione salariale) ai corrispettivi ruoli nell’università pubblica. Anche se non sono io la persona più qualificata per discutere questi aspetti, rispondo volentieri a qualunque domanda.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-11T15:12:34Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-11T15:12:34Z</published>
    <category term="Milan"/>
    <category term="Bocconi"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/184</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/184" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-184 |  Proof complexity of natural formulas via communication arguments | 

	Dmitry Itsykson, 

	Artur Riazanov</title>
    <summary>A canonical communication problem ${\rm Search}(\phi)$ is defined for every unsatisfiable CNF $\phi$: an assignment to the variables of $\phi$ is distributed among the communicating parties, they are to find a clause of $\phi$ falsified by this assignment. Lower bounds on the randomized $k$-party communication complexity of ${\rm Search}(\phi)$ in the number-on-forehead (NOF) model imply tree-size lower bounds, rank lower bounds, and size-space tradeoffs for the formula $\phi$ in the semantic proof system ${\rm T}^{cc}(k,c)$ that operates with proof lines that can be computed by $k$-party randomized communication protocol using at most $c$ bits of communication [Göös, Pitassi, 2014]. All known lower bounds on ${\rm Search}(\phi)$ (e.g. [Beame, Pitassi, Segerlind, 2007; Göös, Pitassi, 2014; Impagliazzo, Pitassi, Urquhart, 1994]) are realized on ad-hoc formulas $\phi$ (i.e. they were introduced specifically for these lower bounds). We introduce a new communication complexity approach that allows establishing proof complexity lower bounds for natural formulas.
  
  First, we demonstrate our approach for two-party communication and apply it to the proof system ${\rm Res}(\oplus)$ that operates with disjunctions of linear equalities over $\mathbb{F}_2$ [Itsykson, Sokolov, 2014]. Let a formula ${\rm PMP}_G$ encode that a graph $G$ has a perfect matching. 
    If $G$ has an odd number of vertices, then ${\rm PMP}_{G}$ has a tree-like ${\rm Res}(\oplus)$-refutation of a polynomial-size [Itsykson, Sokolov, 2014]. It was unknown whether this is the case for graphs with an even number of vertices. Using our approach we resolve this question and show a lower bound $2^{\Omega(n)}$ on size of tree-like ${\rm Res}(\oplus)$-refutations of ${\rm PMP}_{K_{n+2,n}}$.
  
  Then we apply our approach for $k$-party communication complexity in the NOF model and obtain a $\Omega\left(\frac{1}{k} 2^{n/2k - 3k/2}\right)$ lower bound on the randomized $k$-party communication complexity of ${\rm Search}({\rm BPHP}^{M}_{2^n})$ w.r.t. to some natural partition of the variables, where ${\rm BPHP}^{M}_{2^n}$ is the bit pigeonhole principle and $M=2^n+2^{n(1-1/k)}$. 
  In particular, our result implies that the bit pigeonhole requires exponential tree-like ${\rm Th}(k)$ proofs, where ${\rm Th}(k)$ is the semantic proof system operating with polynomial inequalities of degree at most $k$ and $k= O(\log^{1-\epsilon} n)$ for some $\epsilon &gt; 0$.
 We also show that ${\rm BPHP}^{2^n+1}_{2^n}$ superpolynomially separates tree-like ${\rm Th}(\log^{1-\epsilon} m)$ from tree-like ${\rm Th}(\log m)$, where $m$ is the number of variables in the refuted formula.</summary>
    <updated>2020-12-11T10:25:57Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-11T10:25:57Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/11/postdoctoral-position-in-combinatorial-optimization-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-january-24-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/11/postdoctoral-position-in-combinatorial-optimization-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-january-24-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral position in combinatorial optimization  at University of Copenhagen (apply by January 24, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for a postdoc position in combinatorial optimization. The application deadline is January 24, 2021. See https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=153126 for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to Jakob Nordström (jn@di.ku.dk). Website: https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=153126 Email: jn@di.ku.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for a postdoc position in combinatorial optimization. The application deadline is January 24, 2021. See <a href="https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=153126">https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=153126</a> for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to Jakob Nordström (jn@di.ku.dk).</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=153126">https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=153126</a><br/>
Email: jn@di.ku.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-11T08:14:42Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-11T08:14:42Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/11/postdoc-positions-in-tcs-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-january-24-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/11/postdoc-positions-in-tcs-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-january-24-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc positions in TCS at University of Copenhagen (apply by January 24, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for postdoc positions in TCS. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to Jakob Nordström (jn@di.ku.dk), Rasmus Pagh (pagh@di.ku.dk), Mikkel Thorup (mthorup@di.ku.dk) or Christian Wulff-Nilsen (koolooz@di.ku.dk). Website: https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=153103 Email: jn@di.ku.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for postdoc positions in TCS. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to Jakob Nordström (jn@di.ku.dk), Rasmus Pagh (pagh@di.ku.dk), Mikkel Thorup (mthorup@di.ku.dk) or Christian Wulff-Nilsen (koolooz@di.ku.dk).</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=153103">https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=153103</a><br/>
Email: jn@di.ku.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-11T07:44:30Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-11T07:44:30Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/10/tenure-track-assistant-professorship-in-complexity-theory-at-university-of-copenhagenuniversity-of-copenhagen-apply-by-january-17-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/10/tenure-track-assistant-professorship-in-complexity-theory-at-university-of-copenhagenuniversity-of-copenhagen-apply-by-january-17-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure-track assistant professorship in complexity theory at University of CopenhagenUniversity of Copenhagen (apply by January 17, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for a tenure-track assistant professorship in computational complexity theory. The application deadline is January 17, 2021. See https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=152981 for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jn@di.ku.dk. Website: https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=152981 Email: jn@di.ku.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for a tenure-track assistant professorship in computational complexity theory. The application deadline is January 17, 2021.<br/>
See <a href="https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=152981">https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=152981</a> for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jn@di.ku.dk.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=152981">https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=152981</a><br/>
Email: jn@di.ku.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-10T21:55:56Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-10T21:55:56Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2020/12/10/2020-northwestern-cs-junior-theorists-workshop/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2020/12/10/2020-northwestern-cs-junior-theorists-workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>2020 Northwestern CS Junior Theorists Workshop</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">December 17-18, 2020 Virtual on gather.town and zoom https://theory.cs.northwestern.edu/events/2020-junior-theorists-workshop/ The 2020 Junior Theorists Workshop is part of the Northwestern CS Quarterly Theory Workshop Series. The focus of this workshop will be on showcasing junior researchers in all areas of theoretical computer science. The event will be held online from December 17 to 18 (Thursday to … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2020/12/10/2020-northwestern-cs-junior-theorists-workshop/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">2020 Northwestern CS Junior Theorists Workshop</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-10T21:08:34Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-10T21:08:34Z</published>
    <category term="workshop"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:38:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17849</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/12/10/the-future-of-mathematics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Future of Mathematics?</title>
    <summary>Proving proofs are proven Kevin Buzzard is Professor of Pure Mathematics at Imperial College London. Wikipedia says that he specialises in algebraic number theory, rather than “specializes.” Is this because he was born in Britain, works in Britain, both, or could it be neither? This month, he has an article in the AMS Notices that […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><span style="color: #0044cc;"><br/>
<em>Proving proofs are proven</em><br/>
</span></p>
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/12/10/the-future-of-mathematics/k1/" rel="attachment wp-att-17853"><img alt="" class="alignright  wp-image-17853" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/k1.jpg?w=150" width="150"/></a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Kevin Buzzard is Professor of Pure Mathematics at Imperial College London. Wikipedia says that he <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin_Buzzard">specialises</a> in algebraic number theory, rather than “specializes.” Is this because he was born in Britain, works in Britain, both, or could it be neither?</p>
<p>This month, he has an <a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/202011/rnoti-p1791.pdf">article</a> in the <em>AMS Notices</em> that highlights the system <a href="https://leanprover.github.io/about/"><img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/></a>. We thought we’d discuss <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> and its potential to change math—or <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SbZCECvoaTA">maths</a>—as we know it.</p>
<p>For starters we should say that <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> is:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Lean is an open source theorem prover and programming language being developed at Microsoft Research. Lean aims to bridge the gap between interactive and automated theorem proving, by situating automated tools and methods in a framework that supports user interaction and the construction of fully specified axiomatic proofs. </em></p></blockquote>
<p>This wording should perk up the ear of us complexity theorists. We know that polynomial-size interactive proofs have the power of <img alt="{\mathsf{PSPACE}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BPSPACE%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\mathsf{PSPACE}}"/> for one prover, <img alt="{\mathsf{NEXP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BNEXP%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\mathsf{NEXP}}"/> for two, and the Halting Problem for two quantum provers, all of which are believed bigger than <img alt="{\mathsf{NP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BNP%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\mathsf{NP}}"/> as for non-interactive proofs. We believe that our concrete capabilities are shaped by this abstract lay-of-the-land, though this is a meta-scientific assertion that we could never try to prove. What Buzzard’s article and <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> are on about is the scientific state of what we do try to prove, or think we have proved.</p>
<h2>Aftermath as We Know It</h2>
<p>Buzzard spoke early this year at the second annual “Lean Together” segment of the Formal Methods in Mathematics <a href="http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/avigad/meetings/fomm2020/index.html">conference</a> at CMU.</p>
<p>His <a href="https://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/avigad/meetings/fomm2020/slides/fomm_buzzard.pdf">talk</a> was not so much about details of <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> but about the fact of errors and specter of gaps in published mathematics. While a student of Richard Taylor, he had a front-row seat to a major instance. As he relates on a slide marked <b>Gaps</b> in big letters:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>In 1993, Andrew Wiles announced a proof of Fermat’s Last Theorem. There was a gap in the proof.</li>
<li>In 1994, Wiles and Taylor fixed the gap, the papers were published, and our community accepted the proof.</li>
<li>In 1995, I pointed out to Taylor that the proof used work of Gross which was known to be incomplete.<br/>
<img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\dots}"/><br/>
Taylor told me it was OK, because he knew another argument which avoided Gross’s work completely.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>He also highlights the current unfinished state of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classification_of_finite_simple_groups">classification</a> theorem. The process of writing its proof may outlive all of the first generation of provers. We at GLL have accepted it almost all of our working lives. The “after math” can be harder than the initial publication even in the traditional process, let alone the totally free dissemination we have today.</p>
<p>Buzzard points out that some long proofs have now been written in <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> or related systems. These include the famous Feit-Thompson odd order theorem in <a href="https://coq.inria.fr">Coq</a>, and the 2017 Ellenberg-Gijswijt proof of the cap set conjecture. This shows that complex arguments can be written in systems like <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> and others. He maintains his own <a href="https://xenaproject.wordpress.com/what-is-the-xena-project/">blog</a>, “The Xena Project,” on practical and educational uses of <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> and similar software.</p>
<h2>Really Proved?</h2>
<p>But there is a problem with <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> and all the other similar systems.</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Their correct proofs may be incorrect. </em></p></blockquote>
<p><img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> is a large software system and may have bugs. This is of course a major concern, but perhaps one that can be handled. Perhaps not.</p>
<p>I thought about this issue years ago when people argued for verification of operating systems to prove that they had no errors. They wanted to argue that software systems could be error-free only by making a formal proof that they were correct. Over forty years ago, Rich DeMillo and Alan Perlis and I wrote a <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/social.pdf">paper</a> on this issue. Our paper starts with</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Many people have argued that computer programming should strive to become more like mathematics. Maybe so, but not in the way they seem to think. </em></p></blockquote>
<p>We go on to argue against formal verification as the answer to correctness. It is interesting to see that now the argument is flipped: Should mathematics become more like programming?</p>
<p>Ken opines out that a bug in <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> would probably be more catchable because it would likely replicate. Mistakes in proofs ought by nature to be more recognizable than telling whether a <a href="https://leanprover.github.io/lean4/doc/tactics.html">tactic</a> to try to build a proof is likely to succeed.</p>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/12/10/the-future-of-mathematics/group_photo_leaning/" rel="attachment wp-att-17869"><img alt="" class="wp-image-17869" height="150" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/group_photo_leaning.jpeg?w=550&amp;h=150" width="550"/></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><span>Leaning Together at CMU <a href="http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/avigad/meetings/fomm2020/participants.html">src</a><br/>
</span></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2>Leaning Into <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/></h2>
<p>The fundamental idea of <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> is to create a language that does make proofs more like programming. The key is that a proof written in <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> can be checked automatically. This is like saying that a program in Python can be executed.</p>
<p>The project that Buzzard and others are interested in is several-fold. One is that <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> can be a teaching tool. Another is it can help us ensure that the proofs we write down are correct.</p>
<p>The use of <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> is akin to LaTeX. Most of us now write our proofs in LaTeX or some similar typesetting language. We love and hate the issues involved in getting the LaTeX to compile and to look good. Buzzard argues that adding the new ability to be sure that one’s proof is solid is a great leap. LaTeX lets us be sure the proof looks good, while <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> allows us to be sure it is correct.</p>
<p>We have generally taken a reserved attitude toward formal methods on this blog—or maybe <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2013/07/14/surely-you-are-joking/">not</a> so reserved. We keep our reservations expressed above. But what may help <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> overcome them is its emphasis on interaction—on being an assistant. Maybe writing a proof in <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> won’t be like taking castor oil proverbially used to be—it might be more like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marmite">Marmite</a>.</p>
<h2>Open Problems</h2>
<p>Two final thoughts. For the main one: Proofs are not as important as discoveries. Can we use <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> to suggest ideas, open problems, approaches, and more? The gene folding program we discussed recently does not claim to prove its fold is correct. But it seems useful. If <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> could help make guesses or provided intuition that would be valuable. Perhaps more valuable than assuring that a long proof is correct.</p>
<p>Another possible idea: How about we insist that claimed proofs of P<img alt="{=}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{=}"/>NP or other famous conjectures must be presented using <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/>. The “claimed” proofs are all relatively short, so it would not be too hard for the authors of these results to write them out in the <img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> system. They already LaTeX them, so why not? This would have a double benefit: The false claims that are made about famous problems might decrease; and the chance that a correct proof would not be overlooked might increase. The cost would be the time to write up the<img alt="L\exists \forall N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%5Cexists+%5Cforall+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L\exists \forall N"/> proof.</p>
<p>Buzzard is a colorful (or colourful?) character, and may also be gaining a reputation for being well ahead of the times. In 2017 he gave a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jQPb7DRMoZY&amp;list=LLuXRsVD2rJdPs_rstTQZeow&amp;index=9">talk</a> on P<img alt="{=}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{=}"/>NP for the Royal Institution, but what we note in the video is how he was presciently dressed for Zoom.</p>
<p>[some format fixes]</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-10T15:07:03Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-10T15:07:03Z</published>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="checking"/>
    <category term="errors"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=20503</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/12/10/open-problem-session-of-huji-combsem-problem-2-chaya-keller-the-krasnoselskii-number/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Open problem session of HUJI-COMBSEM: Problem #2 Chaya Keller: The Krasnoselskii number</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">  Marilyn Breen This is our second post on the open problem session of the HUJI combinatorics seminar. The video of the session is here. Today’s problem was presented by Chaya Keller. The Krasnoselskii number One of the best-known applications … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/12/10/open-problem-session-of-huji-combsem-problem-2-chaya-keller-the-krasnoselskii-number/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div class="wp-caption alignnone" id="attachment_20545" style="width: 650px;"><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/chaya-keller.jpg"><img alt="" class="size-full wp-image-20545" height="479" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/chaya-keller.jpg?w=640&amp;h=479" width="640"/></a><p class="wp-caption-text" id="caption-attachment-20545"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Chaya Keller</span></p></div>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/mbreen.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-20544" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/mbreen.jpg?w=640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Marilyn Breen</span></p>
<p>This is our second post on the open problem session of the HUJI combinatorics seminar. <a href="https://huji.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=1ac330a2-d6b7-4b86-9bac-ac7500d14205">The video of the session is here</a>. Today’s problem was presented by <a href="http://www.ma.huji.ac.il/~ckeller/">Chaya Keller</a>.</p>
<h2>The Krasnoselskii number</h2>
<p>One of the best-known applications of Helly’s theorem (that is, actually, equivalent to Helly’s theorem, see [Bo]) is the following theorem, due to Krasnoselskii [K]:</p>
<p><strong>Theorem 1 (Krasnoselskii):</strong> Let <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> be an infinite compact set in <img alt="{\mathbb{R}^d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5Ed%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\mathbb{R}^d}"/>. If every <img alt="{d+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%2B1%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{d+1}"/> points of <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> are visible from a common point, then <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> is starshaped, that is there exists some <img alt="{x_0 \in S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_0+%5Cin+S%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{x_0 \in S}"/> that sees all points in <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/>.</p>
<p>Krasnoselskii’s theorem does not hold for non-compact sets. However, all known counter-examples satisfy the weaker requirement of being finitely starlike, namely that any finite subset of <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> is visible from a common point. This led Peterson [P] to ask the following:</p>
<p>Does there exist a Krasnoselskii number <img alt="{K(d)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%28d%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{K(d)}"/> such that for any infinite set <img alt="{S \subset \mathbb{R}^d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS+%5Csubset+%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5Ed%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S \subset \mathbb{R}^d}"/>, if every <img alt="{K(d)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%28d%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{K(d)}"/> points of <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> are visible from a single point, then <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> is finitely starlike?</p>
<p>Marilyn Breen obtained positive results for special cases of sets that satisfy additional topological conditions [Br1,Br2,Br3], e.g., Krasnoselskii number 3 for closed sets in the plane. On the other hand, she proved that if <img alt="{K(2)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%282%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{K(2)}"/> exists, then it must be larger than <img alt="{8}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B8%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{8}"/>.</p>
<p>Recently, Micha Perles and me (Chaya Keller) proved that under no restriction on the set, the Krasnoselskii number does not exist. More precisely, we proved that for any <img alt="{k \geq 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk+%5Cgeq+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{k \geq 2}"/>, there exists a set <img alt="{S \subset \mathbb{R}^2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS+%5Csubset+%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5E2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S \subset \mathbb{R}^2}"/> such that any <img alt="{2k+3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2k%2B3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{2k+3}"/> points in <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> are visible from a common point, but there exist <img alt="{2k+4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2k%2B4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{2k+4}"/> points in <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> that are not visible from a common point. But this counter example is absolutely not constructive (since it is based on a transfinite induction), and the resulting set <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> admits no resonable topological structure.</p>
<p>This leads to the following two problems:</p>
<h3><span style="color: #0000ff;">Problem 1: Can you show constructively that the Krasnoselskii number does not exist?</span></h3>
<h3><span style="color: #0000ff;">Problem 2: Can you find more natural topological conditions under which the Krasnoselskii number exists?</span></h3>
<h3><span style="color: #ff0000;">References</span></h3>
<p>[Bo] Borwein, J., A proof of the equivalence of Helly’s and Krasnosselsky’s theorems,Canad. Math. Bull., 20 (1977), 35-37.</p>
<p>[Br1] M. Breen, Clear visibility, starshaped sets, and finitely starlike sets, J. of Geometry, 19 (1982), 183-196.</p>
<p>[Br2] M. Breen, Some Krasnoseleskii numbers for finitely starlike sets in the plane, J. of Geometry, 32 (1988), 1-12.</p>
<p>[Br3] M. Breen, Finitely starlike sets whose F-stars have positive measure, J. of Geometry, 35 (1989), pp.~19–25.</p>
<p>[K] M. A. Krasnoselskii, Sur un Critére pour Qu’un Domain Soit Étoilé, Math. Sb., 19 (1946), pp.309-310.</p>
<p>[P] B. Peterson, Is there a Krasnonselskii theorem for finitely starlike sets?, Convexity and Related Combinatorial Geometry, Marcel Dekker, New York, 1982, pp.81-84.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-10T11:17:30Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-10T11:17:30Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Convexity"/>
    <category term="Chaya Keller"/>
    <category term="Marilyn Breen"/>
    <category term="Mark Krasnoselskii"/>
    <category term="Micha A. Perles"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-4139075556580650905</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/4139075556580650905/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/12/shuffling-around.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/4139075556580650905" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/4139075556580650905" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/12/shuffling-around.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Shuffling Around</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In the fall of 1983 as a junior at Cornell I took CS 481, Introduction to the Theory of Computing, from Juris Hartmanis. Needless to say this was the course that changed my life and led me down a path that would have me teach a variation of this course myself more than twenty times.</p><p>For some reason one of the final exam questions is still stuck in my head.</p><blockquote style="border: none; margin: 0px 0px 0px 40px; padding: 0px; text-align: left;"><p>Let the permutation of a language L be the set of strings x such that there is a string y in L which is a permutation of the letters in x. For example perm({01},{001})={01,10,001,010,100}. </p><p>Are regular languages closed under permutations?</p></blockquote><p>There's a short and easy answer that's not so easy to find. Just in that P v NP spirit a Hartmanis test question should have. Give it a try before you read more.</p><p>If you <a href="https://www.chegg.com/homework-help/questions-and-answers/ll-shuffle-language-l-let-shuffle-l-following-language-w-x-elementof-l-w-x-w-permutation-l-q23260847">ask Chegg</a> you end up with </p><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://d2vlcm61l7u1fs.cloudfront.net/media%2F357%2F35711f1a-f8bc-490e-893d-cb13349ebfa3%2FphpMmxXRb.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="70" src="https://d2vlcm61l7u1fs.cloudfront.net/media%2F357%2F35711f1a-f8bc-490e-893d-cb13349ebfa3%2FphpMmxXRb.png" width="400"/></a></div><p>And for $15 you can get the answer. Back in 1983 we called that cheating.</p><p>The hint only works if there are regular languages whose permutations are not context free. Which is true in general but oddly enough the <a href="https://cs.stackexchange.com/questions/55507/proving-that-the-scramble-of-a-regular-language-is-context-free">permutation of every context-free language over a two-letter alphabet is context free</a>. The proof uses <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parikh%27s_theorem">Parikh's theorem</a> which implies that the permutation of any context-free language is the permutation of a regular language (over any alphabet size).</p><p>Some other fun permutation questions:</p><p/><ul style="text-align: left;"><li>Show that NP is closed under permutations.</li><li>Show that P is closed under permutations if and only if E = NE.</li><li>What about NL and L?</li></ul><div>Go ahead and chegg on those. </div><p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-09T17:55:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-09T17:55:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T14:59:23Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-12-08-a-simple-and-succinct-zero-knowledge-proof/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-12-08-a-simple-and-succinct-zero-knowledge-proof/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Simple and Succinct Zero Knowledge Proof</title>
    <summary>Many people have popularized the idea that succinct proofs and zero-knowledge proofs are a type of moon math. In this post, our goal is to present a simple proof system that can provide an introduction and intuition to this space. Perhaps surprisingly, the only tool we will use is the...</summary>
    <updated>2020-12-08T18:37:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-08T18:37:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T04:38:48Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/07/ram-and-vijay-shriram-data-science-fellows-at-stanford-apply-by-december-14-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/07/ram-and-vijay-shriram-data-science-fellows-at-stanford-apply-by-december-14-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Ram and Vijay Shriram Data Science Fellows at Stanford (apply by December 14, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Stanford Data Science offers postdoctoral fellow positions in interdisciplinary research with expertise in both Data Science AND its application in a domain of scholarship. Application requires research plan and identifying potential faculty collaborators. Hard application deadline. Website: https://datascience.stanford.edu/data-science-postdocs Email: datascience@stanford .edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Stanford Data Science offers postdoctoral fellow positions in interdisciplinary research with expertise in both Data Science AND its application in a domain of scholarship. Application requires research plan and identifying potential faculty collaborators.</p>
<p>Hard application deadline.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://datascience.stanford.edu/data-science-postdocs">https://datascience.stanford.edu/data-science-postdocs</a><br/>
Email: datascience@stanford .edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-07T17:25:26Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-07T17:25:26Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/07/tt-faculty-junior-and-senior-at-boston-university-apply-by-december-1-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/07/tt-faculty-junior-and-senior-at-boston-university-apply-by-december-1-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TT Faculty (junior and senior) at Boston University (apply by December 1, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Three searches in the new Faculty of Computational and Data Sciences (colocated with CS and Math/Stats), each with strong TCS components. Senior position in data science’s relations to societal goals, policy, ethics (in particular, accountability, fairness, trust, privacy). Junior positions related to algorithms, learning, AGT and economics, large-scale computing, human-centric computing, AI. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17169 Email: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Three searches in the new Faculty of Computational and Data Sciences (colocated with CS and Math/Stats), each with strong TCS components. Senior position in data science’s relations to societal goals, policy, ethics (in particular, accountability, fairness, trust, privacy). Junior positions related to algorithms, learning, AGT and economics, large-scale computing, human-centric computing, AI.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17169">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17169</a><br/>
Email: ads22@bu.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-07T16:50:01Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-07T16:50:01Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-16T19:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1444</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1444" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for November 2020</title>
    <summary>Highlights in property testing this month, include developments across the board. We have a nice potpourri of results which will catch your fancy. From a result which shows the tightness of quadratic gap between query complexities of adaptive vs non-adaptive testers for dense graph properties, to isoperimetric Talagrand-like inequalities for real valued functions over the […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Highlights in property testing this month, include developments across the board. We have a nice potpourri of results which will catch your fancy. From a result which shows the tightness of quadratic gap between query complexities of adaptive vs non-adaptive testers for dense graph properties, to isoperimetric Talagrand-like inequalities for real valued functions over the hypercube, to results which consider face off between quantum computing and distribution testing and more. Looks like the festive season came early for the PTReview readers.</p>



<p/>



<p><strong>Non-adaptive vs Adaptive Queries in the Dense Graph Testing Model</strong> (by Oded Goldreich and Avi Wigderson) (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/160/">ECCC</a>) It has been long established in the dense graph property testing literature that the query complexity of adaptive testers and non-adaptive testers are only a quadratic factor apart. This work asks: is this gap necessarily tight and answers in the affirmative. The main conceptual tool used in the paper is the notion of <em>robustly self-ordered graphs</em> and <em>local self-ordering procedures</em> for these graphs (which was developed by the same authors and was covered in our <a href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1420">September Post</a>). These results use these tools to port lower bounds on property testing problems for bit strings to graph properties.</p>



<p/>



<p><strong>Direct Sum and Partitionability Testing over General Groups </strong>(by Andrej Bogdanov and Gautam Prakriya) (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/164/">ECCC</a>)  In their celebrated work, Blum, Luby and Rubinfeld gave a four query test to determine whether a function \(f \colon \mathbb{F}_2^n \to \mathbb{F}_2\) is affine. This paper considers a generalization of the notion of affinity to functions \(f \colon \{0,1\}^n \to G\) where \(G\) is an Abelian group. The generalization sough asks: does \(f\) have the form \(f = \sum x_ig_i + g_0\) for group elements \(g_0, g_1, \cdots, g_n \in G\). In this setting, the BLR analysis does not apply as the domain and range are note equipped with the same group structure. This work presents a four query test for the above problem. In fact, the test is more general and can be used to decide whether a function \(f \colon D_1 \times D_2 \ldots \times D_n \to G\) from a product domain \(D_1 \times D_2 \ldots \times D_n\) to an Abelian group $G$ is a direct sum if it has the form \(f(x_1, x_2, \cdots, x_n) = \sum f_i(x_i)\) which resolves a conjecture of Dinur and Golubev. The work also presents results for testing whether a function \(f\) defined from a product domain to an Abelian group \(G\) is a direct product.</p>



<p/>



<p><strong>Isoperimetric Inequalities for Real-Valued Functions with Applications to Monotonicity Testing</strong> (by Hadley Black, Iden Kalemaj and Sofya Raskhodnikova) (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.09441.pdf">ArXiv</a>) This paper generalizes the celebrated isoperimetric inequalities of boolean functions over the hypercube to the setting of real valued functions. This generalized isoperimetry is then put to work to obtain a monotonicity tester for \(f \colon \{0,1\}^n \to \mathbb{R}\). The tester makes \(\min(\tilde{O}(r \sqrt n), O(n))\) non-adaptive queries (where \(r\) is the size of image of \(f\)) and has one-sided error. The authors generalize the KMS inequality by a Boolean decomposition theorem which allows them to represent any real valued function over the cube as a collection of Boolean functions over the cube which capture \(f\)’s distance to montonicity as well the structure of violations to monotonicity in \(f\). </p>



<p/>



<p><strong>Erasure-Resilient Sublinear-Time Graph Algorithms</strong> (by Amit Levi, Ramesh Krishnan S. Pallavoor, Sofya Raskhodnikova and Nithin Varma) (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.14291.pdf">ArXiv</a>) In a previous work, a subset of the authors explored how to equip property testers with the erasure-resilience for function properties. With graph properties, a different picture emerges. In the dense graph model, where you have query access to the adjacency matrix, the situation is <em>still</em> fine: adjacency matrices are functional representations of graphs: therefore, if you have a <em>black belt</em> in making property testers erasure resilient for function properties, you would be able to test properties of dense graphs too. However, if I give you query access to the graph through an adjacency list, the picture changes. These are non-functional representations of graphs and therefore need new conceptual tools. This paper begins the study of erasure resilience in the adjacency list model. It focuses on two computational tasks: testing connectivity and estimating average degree.  Let me showcase the results in the paper on testing connectivity. It is shown that you encounter a threshold phenomena in testing connectivity. As long as the fraction of erasures is small, you get testers which run in time independent of the size of the graph. But when the fraction of erasures exceeds a certain cutoff, it is shown that the tester needs a number of queries linear in the size of the adjacency list. </p>



<p><strong>Expander Random Walks: A Fourier Analytic Approach</strong> (by Gil Cohen, Noam Peri and Amnon Ta-Shma) (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/163/">ECCC</a>) While this is a not exactly a property testing paper, how can you not report a paper which proves a significant strengthening of the classic CLT for Markov Chains (alright, for random walks on expanders) with respect to the TV distance? Let us now unpack the above a little. So, consider the following setup: Suppose you have a \(d\)-regular expander \(G\). Now, imagine running the following process \(\textsf{(P)}\):</p>



<p>1) Label half the vertices in \(G\) as \(+1\) and the other half as \(-1\) arbitrarily.<br/>2) Take a \(t-1\) step random walk which involves \(t\) vertices: say \(v_1, v_2, \ldots v_t\).<br/>3) Finally, return the boolean label of all of the visited vertices. This gives a bit-vector \(x \in \{-1,1\}^t\).</p>



<p>Now, let us ask: Which class of functions get fooled by this process?</p>



<p>The main result of the paper shows that this process fools</p>



<p>1) Symmetric functions<br/>2) The class \(AC^0\)<br/>3) Functions \(f\) which are computable by low width read once branching programs.</p>



<p>In more detail, let \(f\) be a symmetric function and let \(G\) be a \(\lambda\)-spectral expander. For the process \(\textsf{(P)}\) defined above, it follows by the spectral expansion of \(G\), that \(discrepancy(f) = |E_{x \sim \textsf{(P)}} [f(x)] – E_{x \sim U_t} [f(x)]|\) is small.</p>



<p>Now note that the total variation distance is precisely equal to the maximum discrepancy you get over all symmetric functions \(f\). This leads to the connection that allows the authors to upgrade CLT for expander random walks as they are able to show a CLT for Markov Chains with respect to the TV distance (as opposed to the CLT with respect to the Kolmogorov Distance which is what was known from the work of Kipnis and Vadhan since 1986).</p>



<p/>



<p><strong>New Sublinear Algorithms and Lower Bounds for LIS Estimation</strong> (by Ilan Newman and Nithin Varma) (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2010.05805.pdf">ArXiv</a>) As the title suggests, this paper considers the task of estimating the length of the longest increasing sequence in an array. In particular, it gives a non-adaptive algorithm which estimates the LIS length within an additive error of \(\pm \varepsilon n\) in \(\tilde{O}\left(\frac{r}{\varepsilon^3}\right)\) queries (where \(r\) is the number of distinct elements in \(A\)). On the lower bound side, the paper presents a lower bound of \((\log n)^{\Omega(1/\varepsilon)}\) non-adaptive queries. The lower bound construction uses ideas from lower bound of Ben-Eliezer, Canonne, Letzter and Waingarten on testing monotone pattern freeness.</p>



<p/>



<p><strong>Stability and testability: equations in permutations</strong> (by Oren Becker, Alexander Lubotzky, AND Jonathan Mosheiff) (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.05234.pdf">ArXiv</a>) Consider the following question: Suppose I ask if two permuations \(A,B \in Sym(n)\). Suppose I want to decide whether these permutations commute or whether they are far from permutations which commute. Can this question be answered in time independent of \(n\)? The authors answer this question in the affirmative. They show a simple <em>Sample and Substitute</em> procedure which essentially does the following: take samples \(x_1, x_2, cdots x_k \sim [n]\). And accept <em>iff</em> \(ABx_i = BAx_i\) for each \(i\). The authors call this particular set of equations/constraints (checking whether \(AB = BA\)) stable: as it admits a Sample and Substitute style tester with query complexity independent of \([n]\).  This allows the authors to consider the group theoretic notion of stability as a property testing concept and allows them to examine the notion of stability from a computational standpoint.   </p>



<p/>



<p><strong>StoqMA meets distribution testing</strong> (by Yupan Liu) (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.05733.pdf">ArXiv</a>) This paper shows a containment result. A certain complexity class \(\textsf{eStoqMA}\) is shown to be a subset of \(\textsf{StoqMA}\). Let us informally define what these classes are. A language \(L \in \textsf{StoqMA}\) if there exists a verifier (which is a reversible quantum circuit) such that on input a string \(x\) such that for every \(x \in L\) there exists a witness quantum state which makes the verifier accept with probability at least \(2/3\). And in case \(x \not\in L\), for every quantum state the verifier rejects \(x\) with probability at least \(2/3\). The paper characterizes this class from a distribution testing point of view. And this connection allows the author to conclude that \(\textsf{eStoqMA} = \textsf{MA}\). Here, \(\textsf{eStoqMA}\) is a sub-class of \(\textsf{StoqMA}\) where all YES instances have an easy <em>witness</em>.</p>



<p/>



<p><strong>(Edit: <em>Added later</em>)</strong> We missed the following two papers. Thanks to our readers for pointing it out.</p>



<p/>



<p><strong>Near-Optimal Learning of Tree-Structured Distributions by Chow-Liu</strong> (by Arnab Bhattacharya, Sutanu Gayen, Eric Price and N.V. Vinodchandran) (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.04144.pdf">ArXiv</a>) Graphical models are a convenient way to describe high dimensional data in terms of its dependence structure. An important question in this area concerns learning/inferring the underlying graphical model from <em>iid</em> samples. This paper considers the problem when the underlying graph is in fact a tree. Thus, the challenge is to learn a tree structured distribution. The main result is that given sample access to a tree structured distribution, you can recover an \(\varepsilon\) <em>approximate</em> tree with good probability in \(O(n/\varepsilon)\).</p>



<p/>



<p><strong>Relaxed Locally Correctable Codes with Improved Parameters</strong> (by Vahid R. Asadi and Igor Shinkar) (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/142/">ECCC</a>) In their work on Robust PCPs of Proximity, Ben-Sasson et al. asked whether it is possible to obtain a \(q\)-query <em>(Relaxed)</em> Locally Decodable Code whose block length is strictly smaller than the best known bounds on block lengths for Locally Decodable Codes. Recall with relaxed LDCs you are allowed to abort outputting the \(i^{th}\) bit of the message should you detect that the received word is not a valid codeword. This paper makes progress on this problem and shows that you can actually construct an \(O(q)\)-query relaxed LDCs which encode a message of length \(k\) using \(O(k^{1 + 1/q})\) queries. This matches some of the known lower bounds for constant query LDCs which thus makes progress towards understanding the gap between LDCs and relaxed LDCs in the regime \(q = O(1)\).</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-07T16:29:50Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-07T16:29:50Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Akash</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2020-12-15T22:46:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
