<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-02-20T22:21:34Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?p=40</id>
    <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2020/02/08/icalp-and-lics-2020-relocation-and-extended-deadline/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>ICALP (and LICS) 2020 – Relocation and Extended Deadline</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the Wuhan coronavirus outbreak, the organizers of ICALP and LICS have made the difficult decision to relocate both (co-located) conferences from Beijing, China, to Saarbrücken, Germany. Speaking specifically about ICALP now (I do not have further information about LICS): As a result of previous uncertainty regarding the situation, the deadline has been extended … <a class="more-link" href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2020/02/08/icalp-and-lics-2020-relocation-and-extended-deadline/">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "ICALP (and LICS) 2020 – Relocation and Extended Deadline"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Due to the Wuhan coronavirus outbreak, the organizers of ICALP and LICS have made the difficult decision to relocate both (co-located) conferences from Beijing, China, to Saarbrücken, Germany. Speaking specifically about ICALP now (I do not have further information about LICS): As a result of previous uncertainty regarding the situation, the deadline has been extended by about six days, until Tuesday February 18, 2020, at 6 AM GMT. The dates of the conference remain (roughly) the same, July 8 – 11, 2020. <br/>The following is a more official message from ICALP Track A Chair, Artur Czumaj.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>The ICALP and the LICS steering committee have agreed together with the conference chairs in Beijing to relocate the two conferences.<br/>ICALP and LICS 2020 will take place in <strong>Saarbrücken</strong>, Germany, July 8 – 11 2020 (with satellite workshops on July 6 – 7 2020).<br/>The deadline is extended, see below.</p>



<p><strong>Call for Papers – ICALP 2020</strong><br/><strong>July 8 – 11 2020, Saarbrücken, Germany</strong></p>



<p><strong>NEW Paper submission deadline: Tuesday February 18, 2020, 6am GMT</strong><br/><a href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=icalp2020">https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=icalp2020</a></p>



<p>ICALP (International Colloquium on Automata, Languages and Programming) is the main European conference in Theoretical Computer Science and annual meeting of the European Association for Theoretical Computer Science (EATCS). ICALP 2020 will be hosted on the Saarland Informatics Campus in Saarbrücken, in co-location with LICS 2020 (ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science).</p>



<p><strong>Invited speakers:</strong><br/>Track A: Virginia Vassilevska (MIT), Robert Krauthgamer (Weizmann)<br/>Track B: Stefan Kiefer (Oxford)<br/>Joint ICALP-LICS: Andrew Yao (Tsinghua), Jérôme Leroux (Bordeaux)</p>



<p><strong>Submission Guidelines:</strong> see <a href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=icalp2020">https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=icalp2020</a></p>



<p><strong>NEW Paper submission deadline: February 18</strong>, 2020, 6am GMT<br/>notifications: April 15, 2020<br/>camera ready: April 28, 2020</p>



<p>Topics: ICALP 2020 will have the two traditional tracks<br/>A (Algorithms, Complexity and Games – including Algorithmic Game Theory, Distributed Algorithms and Parallel, Distributed and External Memory Computing) and<br/>B (Automata, Logic, Semantics and Theory of Programming).<br/><strong><em>    (Notice that the old tracks A and C have been merged into a single track A.)</em></strong><br/>Papers presenting original, unpublished research on all aspects of theoretical computer science are sought.</p>



<p>Typical, but not exclusive topics are:</p>



<p>Track A — Algorithmic Aspects of Networks and Networking, Algorithms for Computational Biology, Algorithmic Game Theory, Combinatorial Optimization, Combinatorics in Computer Science, Computational Complexity, Computational Geometry, Computational Learning Theory, Cryptography, Data Structures, Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Foundations of Machine Learning, Foundations of Privacy, Trust and Reputation in Network, Network Models for Distributed Computing, Network Economics and Incentive-Based Computing Related to Networks, Network Mining and Analysis, Parallel, Distributed and External Memory Computing, Quantum Computing, Randomness in Computation, Theory of Security in Networks</p>



<p>Track B — Algebraic and Categorical Models, Automata, Games, and Formal Languages, Emerging and Non-standard Models of Computation, Databases, Semi-Structured Data and Finite Model Theory, Formal and Logical Aspects of Learning, Logic in Computer Science, Theorem Proving and Model Checking, Models of Concurrent, Distributed, and Mobile Systems, Models of Reactive, Hybrid and Stochastic Systems, Principles and Semantics of Programming Languages, Program Analysis and Transformation, Specification, Verification and Synthesis, Type Systems and Theory, Typed Calculi</p>



<p><strong>PC Track A chair: Artur Czumaj</strong> (University  of Warwick)<br/><strong>PC Track B chair: Anuj Dawar</strong> (University of Cambridge)</p>



<p>Contact<br/>All questions about submissions should be emailed to the PC Track chairs:<br/>Artur Czumaj <a href="mailto:A.Czumaj@warwick.ac.uk">A.Czumaj@warwick.ac.uk&lt;mailto:A.Czumaj@warwick.ac.uk&gt;</a><br/>Anuj Dawar <a href="mailto:Anuj.Dawar@cl.cam.ac.uk">Anuj.Dawar@cl.cam.ac.uk&lt;mailto:Anuj.Dawar@cl.cam.ac.uk&gt;</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-02-08T15:01:28Z</updated>
    <published>2020-02-08T15:01:28Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://kamathematics.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Kamathematics</title>
      <updated>2020-02-20T22:21:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?p=34</id>
    <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/20/theory-and-practice-of-differential-privacy-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy 2019</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While I’m a relative newcomer to differential privacy (my first paper on it was only in 2017), I’ve found the community to be a pleasure to interact with: paradoxically, simultaneously tight-knit yet highly welcoming to newcomers. I partially credit this culture to the number of workshops and programs which bring people together, including, but not … <a class="more-link" href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/20/theory-and-practice-of-differential-privacy-2019/">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy 2019"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>While I’m a relative newcomer to differential privacy (my <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.10127">first paper</a> on it was only in 2017), I’ve found the community to be a pleasure to interact with: paradoxically, simultaneously tight-knit yet highly welcoming to newcomers. I partially credit this culture to the number of workshops and programs which bring people together, including, but not limited to, <a href="https://www.birs.ca/events/2018/5-day-workshops/18w5189">a BIRS workshop</a>, <a href="https://privacytools.seas.harvard.edu/">the Privacy Tools project at Harvard</a>, <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/programs/privacy2019">a semester at the Simons Institute</a>, <a href="https://shonan.nii.ac.jp/seminars/164/">the forthcoming Shonan workshop</a>, and <a href="https://tpdp.cse.buffalo.edu/">the Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy (TPDP) Workshop</a>.</p>



<p>I’m writing this post to draw attention to the imminent deadline of <a href="https://tpdp.cse.buffalo.edu/2019/">TPDP 2019</a>, co-located with CCS 2019 in London. I’ll spare you the full details (click the link for more information), but most pressing is the deadline tomorrow, June 21, 2019, anywhere on Earth (let me know if this presents hardship for you, and I can pass concerns on to the chair). Essentially anything related to the theory or practice of differential privacy is welcome. Submissions are limited to four pages in length and are lightly refereed, based on originality, relevance, interest, and clarity. There are no published proceedings, and previously published results are welcome. If you’ve been looking to get to know the community, consider either submitting or attending the workshop! </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-20T18:05:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-20T18:05:19Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://kamathematics.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Kamathematics</title>
      <updated>2020-02-20T22:21:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?p=23</id>
    <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/17/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hello World!</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Welcome to my blog! My name is Gautam Kamath, and I just started as an assistant professor in computer science at the University of Waterloo (for more info, see About). This blog will, broadly speaking, be about topics relevant to those interested in the the theory of computer science, statistics, and machine learning. Posts will … <a class="more-link" href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/17/hello-world/">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Hello World!"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Welcome to my blog! My name is Gautam Kamath, and I just started as an assistant professor in computer science at the University of Waterloo (for more info, see <a href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/about/">About</a>).</p>



<p>This blog will, broadly speaking, be about topics relevant to those interested in the the theory of computer science, statistics, and machine learning. Posts will range from technical, to informational, to meta (read: basically whatever I want to write about, but I’ll do my best to keep it topical). Stay tuned!</p>



<p>The unofficial theme song of this blog is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8Ir-zFC9nFE">“Mathematics” by Mos Def</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-17T23:42:13Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-17T23:42:13Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://kamathematics.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Kamathematics</title>
      <updated>2020-02-20T22:21:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?p=78</id>
    <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/2018/09/19/the-dynamics-of-lagrange-and-hamilton/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The dynamics of Lagrange and Hamilton</title>
    <summary>In 1788, Lagrange presented a set of equations of motion that, unlike Newtonian mechanics, are independent of the choice of coordinates of the physical system, and ultimately led to the formulation of general relativity. Hamilton came up with a different set of equations of motion in 1833 that arguably led to the development of quantum mechanics. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In 1788, Lagrange presented a set of equations of motion that, unlike Newtonian mechanics, are independent of the choice of coordinates of the physical system, and ultimately led to the formulation of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Einstein%E2%80%93Hilbert_action">general relativity</a>. Hamilton came up with a different set of equations of motion in 1833 that arguably led to the development of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamiltonian_(quantum_mechanics)">quantum mechanics</a>. Remarkably, in classical mechanics, these sets of equations turn out to be <em>equivalent</em> via a beautiful duality due to <strong>Legendre</strong>.</p>
<p><img alt="AduC_057_Legendre_(L.,_1756-1797)" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-82" src="https://nisheethvishnoi.files.wordpress.com/2018/09/aduc_057_legendre_l-_1756-1797.jpg?w=1008"/></p>
<p><span style="color: #999999;"><em>A portrait of Legendre by H. Rousseau, E. Thomas, Augustin Challamel, and Desire Lacroix via Wikimedia Commons</em></span></p>
<p>Lagrangian and Hamiltonian dynamics have inspired several promising optimization and sampling algorithms such as <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1603.04245.pdf">first-order methods in optimization</a>,  <a href="http://arogozhnikov.github.io/2016/12/19/markov_chain_monte_carlo.html">Hamiltonian Monte Carlo</a> (see also this <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1802.08898">paper</a> that will appear in NIPS 2018). Legendre duality also appears in convex optimization as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fenchel%27s_duality_theorem">Fenchel</a> <a href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/convex-optimization/">duality</a>.  <a href="https://nisheethvishnoi.files.wordpress.com/2018/09/lagrangehamiltonian.pdf" title="LagrangeHamiltonian">This</a> note, written primarily for optimization folks, introduces Lagrangian dynamics, Hamiltonian dynamics, and proves the duality that connects them.</p>
<p>I hope that these fundamental ideas inspire you as well to think about optimization from a physics perspective!</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2018-09-19T22:15:10Z</updated>
    <published>2018-09-19T22:15:10Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>nisheethvishnoi</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Algorithms, Nature, and Society</title>
      <updated>2020-02-20T22:21:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?p=63</id>
    <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/2018/09/16/fair-elections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://radiochablais.ch//podcast/mp3/info_12h_13062018.mp3" length="0" rel="enclosure" type="audio/mpeg"/>
    <link href="http://radiochablais.ch//podcast/mp3/info_12h_13062018.mp3" length="0" rel="enclosure" type="audio/mpeg"/>
    <title>Fair Elections</title>
    <summary>Elisa Celis and Nisheeth Vishnoi Elections are the nervous system of a democracy and, hence, issues related to their transparency and fairness are central to healthy societies. However, the number of controversial elections has exploded since 2000, and the more recent ones involve the use of the Internet and algorithms — a good excuse for computer […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center;"><em><a href="https://theory.epfl.ch/celis/HOME.html">Elisa Celis</a> and Nisheeth Vishnoi</em></p>
<p>Elections are the nervous system of a democracy and, hence, issues related to their transparency and fairness are central to healthy societies. However, the number of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_controversial_elections">controversial elections</a> has exploded since 2000, and the more recent ones involve the use of the Internet and algorithms — a good excuse for computer scientists to get involved in elections to save democracy!</p>
<p>Last year, the two of us and Lingxao Huang revisited the question of <em>fairness</em> in <em>multi-winner</em> elections<em>. </em>A multi-winner election is one where the objective is to select a committee from a set of candidates based on voter preferences. However, election systems for multi-winner elections have been shown to be <a href="https://www.representwomen.org/voting_rules_pose_barrier_for_women">biased against minorities</a> by giving preference to committees that under-represent their already-small numbers. When the candidates have certain sensitive attributes (such as gender), and different types (e.g., male, female and non-binary) we may instead wish to impose additional requirement so that the winning committee is <em>fair</em>. We considered the problem of finding the committee with the maximum number of votes, subject to such additional fairness requirements.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>But what does it mean to be fair?</em></p>
<p>Is a committee fair when types are equally represented? Or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proportional_representation">proportionally represented</a>? These questions have received more than a century’s worth of attention in social choice theory and are deeply entangled with culture and politics. In short, fairness means different things in different contexts and rather than addressing a specific instance of this question, we asked ourselves — <em>can we provide a framework in which a user can specify fairness constraints according to their needs and design algorithms that can compute the winning committee accordingly?</em></p>
<p>Because such a framework must handle general classes of constraints, the algorithmic task became more challenging than the usual unconstrained case. If you are interested in understanding our algorithmic and complexity results, they appear in our recent <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1710.10057.pdf">paper</a> that was presented at IJCAI-ECAI this year.</p>
<p>Clearly, however, there are real merits to providing such generality — earlier this year, our paper caught the eye of members of a <a href="https://appelcitoyen.ch/">people’s movement</a> from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canton_of_Valais">Valais</a> canton in Switzerland, who were in the process of rethinking elections in their region. They were happy to know that we had solved the exact problem they needed for a primary election and asked us if we would be willing to help them conduct their elections. We were, of course, thrilled!</p>
<p>After an intense collaboration for more than four months, 8 elections that used our framework concluded on September 9, 2018. For us, there were several eye-opening aspects of taking our algorithmic framework from theory to practice. Perhaps the most interesting one was coming up with an answer to:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Who decides what is fair?</em></p>
<p>In this case, it was the voters! Before voting on the committee, a vote to determine the fairness constraints was conducted in each of the eight districts. This vote was in mid-June and also checked if the voters agree to use our algorithmic framework. Since transparency was the key motivation, prior to this vote,  we were invited to a press conference to educate the people about the whole process that resulted in coverage in newspapers <a href="https://www.letemps.ch/suisse/listes-ideales-constituante-valaisanne?itm_source=homepage&amp;itm_medium=position-12">Le Temps</a>,  <a href="https://www.lenouvelliste.ch/articles/valais/canton/appel-citoyen-lance-sa-primaire-digitale-en-vue-de-la-constituante-les-passionnes-de-democratie-ont-jusqu-a-jeudi-pour-s-inscrire-763669">Le Nouvelliste</a>, TV channel <a href="https://www.google.com/url?q=http://canal9.ch/appel-citoyen-va-choisir-ses-candidats-pour-la-lassemblee-constituante-en-deux-etapes-et-par-internet/&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1537194868256000&amp;usg=AFQjCNGQkC-CmcI2n0iBfAAzxP4GWbiBzQ">Canal 9</a>, and radio channels <a href="http://www.rhonefm.ch/fr/podcasts/journal-du-soir-une-election-primaire-digitale--c-est-l-aventure-dans-laquelle-se-lance-le-mouvement-apolitique-appel-citoyen-en-premiere-mondiale-1107827">Rhone FM</a> and  <a href="http://radiochablais.ch//podcast/mp3/info_12h_13062018.mp3">Radio Chablais</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="20180612_142435" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-65" src="https://nisheethvishnoi.files.wordpress.com/2018/09/20180612_142435.jpg?w=1008"/></p>
<p><em>An image from the press conference in Sion on June 12, 2018. Elisa Celis (center), accompanied by members of Appel Citoyen.</em></p>
<p>In the end, the voters decided to place constraints on the gender balance, age demographics, and regions. While all districts approved these same three attributes, the specific constraints varied by district according to their demographics and pre-defined regions. This was a truly open and democratic way to determine the criteria by which the committee was to be balanced. The constraints not only ensured that the outcome would be fair (as defined by the voters) but also encouraged many more women to run for election than the party originally anticipated — in fact, in several districts there were more women than men contesting the election!</p>
<p><img alt="20180909_153659" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-64" src="https://nisheethvishnoi.files.wordpress.com/2018/09/20180909_153659.jpg?w=1008"/></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>Computing the winning committees in Sion on September 9, 2018. From L to R: Lingxiao Huang, Vijay Keswani, Elisa Celis, Florian Evequoz, Bernadette Morand-Aymon.</em></p>
<p>Everything about these elections, from votes, candidates, constraints, and code, to the output, is open for all to <a href="https://appelcitoyen.ch/blog/on-ouvre-les-urnes-donnees-brutes-de-la-primaire/">verify</a>. We have also made available a <a href="http://valais-elections.herokuapp.com/">demo</a> with pre-loaded constraints, candidate information, and votes for anyone to test and compute the results. To know more about the use of our algorithm in these elections, take a look at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X6M1fpcEBQE">this video</a>. A few links to the coverage of these elections can be found here: <a href="http://canal9.ch/constituante-appel-citoyen-a-designe-ses-96-candidats-une-primaire-digitale-realisee-grace-a-une-methode-concue-par-lepfl/">Canal 9</a>,  <a href="https://www.letemps.ch/suisse/valais-appel-citoyen-lance-primaire-constituante">Le Temps</a>, <a href="https://www.lenouvelliste.ch/dossiers/tout-savoir-sur-la-constituante/articles/constituante-la-primaire-numerique-d-appel-citoyen-a-rendu-son-verdict-782906">Le Nouvelliste</a>.</p>
<p>We feel fortunate that we were given this unique opportunity to take tools from computer science to the heart of a democratic process. It was an unparalleled learning experience for all of us and something that we increasingly look forward to in the future.</p>
<p><img alt="constraints" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-70" src="https://nisheethvishnoi.files.wordpress.com/2018/09/constraints.gif?w=1008"/></p>
<p><img alt="candidates" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-69" src="https://nisheethvishnoi.files.wordpress.com/2018/09/candidates.gif?w=1008"/></p>
<p>You can also use our <a href="https://theory.epfl.ch/bias/elections/">demo</a> to design your own elections and play around with our algorithms. This demo was developed with the help of Abhibhav Garg and Vijay Keswani and has limited functionality. If you are interested in using our full framework and/or working with us,  please feel free to <a href="https://theory.epfl.ch/bias/contact.html">contact us</a>.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2018-09-16T20:02:02Z</updated>
    <published>2018-09-16T20:02:02Z</published>
    <category term="AI and Society"/>
    <category term="Algorithms"/>
    <category term="Fairness"/>
    <author>
      <name>nisheethvishnoi</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Algorithms, Nature, and Society</title>
      <updated>2020-02-20T22:21:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?p=55</id>
    <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/2018/06/06/an-exposition-on-geodesic-convexity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Exposition on Geodesic Convexity</title>
    <summary>I arrived at the Institute for Advanced Study to attend a workshop on Optimization, Complexity and Invariant Theory organized by Avi Wigderson. The workshop has an incredibly diverse agenda, also reflected in the participants. I will talk about Geodesic Convexity: Sometimes, functions that are non-convex in the Euclidean space turn out to be convex if one introduces […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I arrived at the Institute for Advanced Study to attend a workshop on <a href="https://www.math.ias.edu/ocit2018/agenda">Optimization, Complexity and Invariant Theory</a> organized by Avi Wigderson. The workshop has an incredibly diverse agenda, also reflected in the participants.</p>
<p>I will talk about <em>Geodesic Convexity: </em>Sometimes, functions that are non-convex in the Euclidean space turn out to be convex if one introduces a suitable metric (or differential structure) and redefines convexity with respect to the induced straight lines — <em>geodesics</em>. Such a function is called <em>geodesically convex. </em>Unlike standard convexity,<em>  w</em>hen does a function have this property and how to optimize it, is not well-understood. My talk will focus on introducing geodesic convexity and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.04051">show</a> that the problem of computing the Brascamp-Lieb constant has a succinct geodesically convex formulation.</p>
<p>And, accompanying my talk are <a href="https://nisheethvishnoi.files.wordpress.com/2018/06/geodesicconvexity.pdf" title="GeodesicConvexity">these</a> self-contained and expository notes on differentiation on manifolds, geodesics, and geodesic convexity that are prepared with the help of my student Ozan Yildiz.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2018-06-06T10:40:23Z</updated>
    <published>2018-06-06T10:40:23Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>nisheethvishnoi</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Algorithms, Nature, and Society</title>
      <updated>2020-02-20T22:21:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?p=30</id>
    <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/2018/05/26/algorithms-for-convex-optimization/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Lecture Notes on Algorithms for Convex Optimization</title>
    <summary>I have been teaching convex optimization methods to students of computer science and machine learning over four years in various forms and styles. Finally, the notes are online here!</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I have been teaching convex optimization methods to students of computer science and machine learning over four years in various forms and styles. Finally, the notes are online <a href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/convex-optimization/">here</a>!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2018-05-26T11:12:52Z</updated>
    <published>2018-05-26T11:12:52Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>nisheethvishnoi</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Algorithms, Nature, and Society</title>
      <updated>2020-02-20T22:21:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
