<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2022-05-22T05:38:20Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/075</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/075" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-075 |  Vanishing Spaces of Random Sets and Applications to Reed-Muller Codes | 

	Prahladh Harsha, 

	Siddharth Bhandari, 

	Srikanth Srinivasan, 

	Ramprasad Saptharishi</title>
    <summary>We study the following natural question on random sets of points in $\mathbb{F}_2^m$:
    

Given a random set of $k$ points $Z=\{z_1, z_2, \dots, z_k\} \subseteq \mathbb{F}_2^m$, what is the dimension of the space of degree at most $r$ multilinear polynomials that vanish on all points in $Z$?


We show that, for $r \leq \gamma m$ (where $\gamma &gt; 0$ is a small, absolute constant) and $k = (1-\epsilon) \cdot {m \choose {\leq r}}$ for any constant $\epsilon &gt; 0$, the space of degree at most $r$ multilinear polynomials vanishing on a random set $Z = \{z_1,\ldots, z_k\}$ has dimension exactly ${m \choose {\leq r}} - k$ with probability $1 - o(1)$. This bound shows that random sets have a much smaller space of degree at most $r$ multilinear polynomials vanishing on them, compared to the worst-case bound (due to Wei (IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory, 1991)) of ${m \choose{\leq r}} - {{\log_2 k}\choose {\leq r}} \gg {m\choose{\leq r}} - k$. 

    Using this bound, we show that high-degree Reed-Muller codes ($\text{RM}(m,d)$ with $d &gt; (1-\gamma) m$) ``achieve capacity'' under the Binary Erasure Channel in the sense that, for any $\epsilon &gt; 0$, we can recover from $(1 - \epsilon) \cdot {m\choose {\leq m-d-1}}$ random erasures with probability $1 - o(1)$. This also implies that $\text{RM}(m,d)$ is also efficiently decodable from $\approx {m\choose {\leq m-(d/2)}}$ random errors for the same range of parameters.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-21T19:53:52Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-21T19:53:52Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/05/21/congratulations-dr-osegueda</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/05/21/congratulations-dr-osegueda.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Congratulations, Dr. Osegueda!</title>
    <summary>Martha Osegueda, one of Mike Goodrich’s students at UC Irvine, successfully defended her doctoral dissertation yesterday. Martha is originally Salvadorean, and came to UCI from an undergraduate degree at the University of Texas El Paso. Her research at UCI has spanned a wide variety of topics in graph drawing, phylogeny, computational geometry, and parallel query complexity:</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Martha Osegueda, one of Mike Goodrich’s students at UC Irvine, successfully defended her doctoral dissertation yesterday. Martha is originally Salvadorean, and came to UCI from an undergraduate degree at the University of Texas El Paso. Her research at UCI has spanned a wide variety of topics in graph drawing, phylogeny, computational geometry, and parallel query complexity:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>“Minimum-width drawings of phylogenetic trees” from <em>COCOA</em> 2019 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-36412-0_4">doi:10.1007/978-3-030-36412-0_4</a>) is about drawing evolutionary trees compactly. For the version of tree drawing they study, it turns out to be NP-hard when the order of the leaves is unconstrained but linear-time solvable for fixed leaf orderings.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Reconstructing binary trees in parallel” from <em>SPAA</em> 2020 (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.15259">arXiv:2006.15259</a>) involved the reconstruction of evolutionary trees from queries asking which pair of a triple of species is closest.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Concatenation arguments and their applications to polyominoes and polycubes”, in <em>CGTA</em> 2021 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.comgeo.2021.101790">doi:10.1016/j.comgeo.2021.101790</a>) and “On the number of compositions of two polycubes” from <em>EuroComb</em> 2021 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-83823-2_12">doi:10.1007/978-3-030-83823-2_12</a>) strengthen the known lower bounds on the growth rates of polyominoes and polycubes, using arguments based on counting ways of gluing pairs of smaller polyforms into larger ones.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Angles of arc-polygons and Lombardi drawings of cacti”, from <em>CCCG</em> 2021 (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.03615">arXiv:2107.03615</a>) is my only collaboration with Martha and one <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/07/10/angles-arc-triangles.html">I have posted about here</a>. It characterizes the vertex angles that are possible in triangles with circular-arc sides, and uses that characterization to prove the existence of a Lombardi drawing for any cactus graph.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Parallel network mapping algorithms” from <em>SPAA</em> 2021 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3409964.3461822">doi:10.1145/3409964.3461822</a>) and “Mapping Networks via parallel \(k\)th-hop traceroute queries” from <em>STACS</em> 2022 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.4230/LIPIcs.STACS.2022.4">doi:10.4230/LIPIcs.STACS.2022.4</a>) are on traceroute-like problems: mapping the structure of a computer communication network using a small number of parallel rounds of pings to determine distances from nodes on the network.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Taming the knight’s tour: Minimizing turns and crossings” from <em>FUN</em> 2021 and <em>TCS</em> 2022 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tcs.2021.12.002">doi:10.1016/j.tcs.2021.12.002</a>) shows how to move a chess knight around all of the squares of a chessboard, touching each square once, so that the number of times the knight’s path crosses itself or deviates from a straight path are both simultaneously approximately minimized.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Diamonds are forever in the blockchain: Geometric polyhedral point-set pattern matching” is her newest work, in submission. It studies problems of aligning a polyhedron to sample points from a similarly-shaped surface, motivated by an application in tracing the provenance of ethically sourced diamonds.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Despite all of these good publications, Mike tells me that it was difficult to persuade Martha that she had done enough for a doctorate. But she had, easily, and now she’s moving on to a position at Meta. Congratulations, Martha!</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108342653334960089">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-21T16:49:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-21T16:49:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T00:02:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09727</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09727" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Franz-Parisi Criterion and Computational Trade-offs in High Dimensional Statistics</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653091200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bandeira:Afonso_S=.html">Afonso S. Bandeira</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Alaoui:Ahmed_El.html">Ahmed El Alaoui</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hopkins:Samuel_B=.html">Samuel B. Hopkins</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schramm:Tselil.html">Tselil Schramm</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wein:Alexander_S=.html">Alexander S. Wein</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zadik:Ilias.html">Ilias Zadik</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09727">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Many high-dimensional statistical inference problems are believed to possess
inherent computational hardness. Various frameworks have been proposed to give
rigorous evidence for such hardness, including lower bounds against restricted
models of computation (such as low-degree functions), as well as methods rooted
in statistical physics that are based on free energy landscapes. This paper
aims to make a rigorous connection between the seemingly different low-degree
and free-energy based approaches. We define a free-energy based criterion for
hardness and formally connect it to the well-established notion of low-degree
hardness for a broad class of statistical problems, namely all Gaussian
additive models and certain models with a sparse planted signal. By leveraging
these rigorous connections we are able to: establish that for Gaussian additive
models the "algebraic" notion of low-degree hardness implies failure of
"geometric" local MCMC algorithms, and provide new low-degree lower bounds for
sparse linear regression which seem difficult to prove directly. These results
provide both conceptual insights into the connections between different notions
of hardness, as well as concrete technical tools such as new methods for
proving low-degree lower bounds.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09655</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09655" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Primrose: Selecting Container Data Types by their Properties</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653091200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/q/Qin:Xueying.html">Xueying Qin</a>, Liam O'Connor, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Steuwer:Michel.html">Michel Steuwer</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09655">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Container data types are ubiquitous in computer programming, enabling
developers to efficiently store and process collections of data with an
easy-to-use programming interface. Many programming languages offer a variety
of container implementations in their standard libraries based on data
structures offering different capabilities and performance characteristics.
Choosing the best container for an application is not straightforward, as
performance characteristics can change drastically in different scenarios, and
real-world performance is not always correlated to theoretical complexity. In
this paper, we present Primrose, a language-agnostic tool for selecting the
best performing valid container implementation from a set of container data
types that satisfy the given properties. Semantic properties allow application
developers to specify the expected behaviour of a container as a type
refinement, e.g., if the container should only contain unique values (such as a
set) or should satisfy the LIFO property of a stack. Semantic properties nicely
complement syntactic properties (i.e., traits, interfaces, or type classes),
allowing developers to specify a container's programming interface and
behaviour without committing to a concrete implementation. Primrose
automatically select the set of valid container implementations for which the
library specifications, written by the developers of container libraries,
satisfies the specified properties. Finally, Primrose ranks the valid library
implementations based on their runtime performance. We present our prototype
implementation of Primrose that preprocesses annotated Rust code, selecting the
best performing container implementation. Primrose is easy to integrate in
other programming languages. We encode properties and library specifications
into verification conditions in a SMT solver to determine the set of valid
container implementations.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-21T22:48:08Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09520</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09520" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dynamic SAFFRON: Disease Control Over Time Via Group Testing</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653091200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Arasli:Batuhan.html">Batuhan Arasli</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/u/Ulukus:Sennur.html">Sennur Ulukus</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09520">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the dynamic infection spread model that is based on the discrete
SIR model which assumes infections to be spread over time via infected and
non-isolated individuals. In our system, the main objective is not to minimize
the number of required tests to identify every infection, but instead, to
utilize the available, given testing capacity $T$ at each time instance to
efficiently control the infection spread. We introduce and study a novel
performance metric, which we coin as $\epsilon$-disease control time. This
metric can be used to measure how fast a given algorithm can control the spread
of a disease. We characterize the performance of dynamic individual testing
algorithm and introduce a novel dynamic SAFFRON based group testing algorithm.
We present theoretical results and implement the proposed algorithms to compare
their performances.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-21T22:38:26Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09245</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09245" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Deterministic Near-Optimal Distributed Listing of Cliques</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653091200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Censor=Hillel:Keren.html">Keren Censor-Hillel</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Leitersdorf:Dean.html">Dean Leitersdorf</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vulakh:David.html">David Vulakh</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09245">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The importance of classifying connections in large graphs has been the
motivation for a rich line of work on distributed subgraph finding that has led
to exciting recent breakthroughs. A crucial aspect that remained open was
whether deterministic algorithms can be as efficient as their randomized
counterparts, where the latter are known to be tight up to polylogarithmic
factors.
</p>
<p>We give deterministic distributed algorithms for listing cliques of size $p$
in $n^{1 - 2/p + o(1)}$ rounds in the \congest model. For triangles, our
$n^{1/3+o(1)}$ round complexity improves upon the previous state of the art of
$n^{2/3+o(1)}$ rounds [Chang and Saranurak, FOCS 2020]. For cliques of size $p
\geq 4$, ours are the first non-trivial deterministic distributed algorithms.
Given known lower bounds, for all values $p \geq 3$ our algorithms are tight up
to a $n^{o(1)}$ subpolynomial factor, which comes from the deterministic
routing procedure we use.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-21T22:48:58Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09243</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09243" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Frequency-Competitive Query Strategies to Maintain Low Congestion Potential Among Moving Entities</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653091200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Evans:William.html">William Evans</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kirkpatrick:David.html">David Kirkpatrick</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09243">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the problem of using location queries to monitor the congestion
potential among a collection of entities moving, with bounded speed but
otherwise unpredictably, in $d$-dimensional Euclidean space. Uncertainty in
entity locations due to potential motion between queries gives rise to a space
of possible entity configurations at each moment in time, with possibly very
different congestion properties. We define different measures of what we call
the congestion potential of such spaces, in terms of the (dynamic) intersection
graph of the uncertainty regions associated with entities, to describe the
congestion that might actually occur.
</p>
<p>Previous work [SoCG'13, EuroCG'14, SICOMP'16, SODA'19], in the same
uncertainty model, addressed the problem of minimizing congestion potential
using location queries of some bounded frequency. It was shown that it is
possible to design a query scheme that is $O(1)$-competitive, in terms of
worst-case congestion potential, with other, even clairvoyant query schemes
(that know the trajectories of all entities), subject to the same bound on
query frequency.
</p>
<p>In this paper we address the dual problem: how to guarantee a fixed bound on
congestion potential while minimizing the query frequency, measured in terms of
total number of queries or the minimum spacing between queries (granularity),
over any fixed time interval. This complementary objective necessitates quite
different algorithms and analyses. Nevertheless, our results parallel those of
the earlier papers, specifically tight competitive bounds on required query
frequency, with a few surprising differences.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09210</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.09210" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Reconfiguration of Digraph Homomorphisms</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653091200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/L=eacute=v=ecirc=que:Benjamin.html">Benjamin Lévêque</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/M=uuml=hlenthaler:Moritz.html">Moritz Mühlenthaler</a>, Thomas Suzan <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.09210">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>For a fixed graph H, the H-Recoloring problem asks whether for two given
homomorphisms from a graph G to H, we can transform one into the other by
changing the image of a single vertex of G in each step and maintaining a
homomorphism from G to H throughout. We extend an algorithm of Wrochna for
H-Recoloring where H is a square-free loopless undirected graph to the more
general setting of directed graphs. We obtain a polynomial-time algorithm for
H-Recoloring in this setting whenever H is a loopless digraph that does not
contain a 4-cycle of algebraic girth zero and whenever H is a reflexive digraph
that contains neither a 3-cycle of algebraic girth 1 nor a 4-cycle of algebraic
girth zero.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-21T22:46:03Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=22620</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/05/20/oliver-janzer-and-benny-sudakov-settled-the-erdos-sauer-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Oliver Janzer and  Benny Sudakov Settled the Erdős-Sauer Problem</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Norbert Sauer The news in brief:  In the new paper Resolution of the Erdős-Sauer problem on regular subgraphs Oliver Janzer and Benny Sudakov proved that any graph G with vertices and more than edges contains a k-regular subgraph. This bound … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/05/20/oliver-janzer-and-benny-sudakov-settled-the-erdos-sauer-problem/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img alt="Norbert-Sauer" class="alignnone  wp-image-22703" height="243" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/05/norbert-sauer.jpg?w=162&amp;h=243" width="162"/></p>
<p><a href="https://contacts.ucalgary.ca/info/math/profiles/101-152966">Norbert Sauer</a></p>
<p>The news in brief:  In the new paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12455">Resolution of the Erdős-Sauer problem on regular subgraphs</a> Oliver Janzer and Benny Sudakov proved <span class="abstract-full has-text-grey-dark mathjax" id="2204.12455v1-abstract-full"> that any graph G with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> vertices and more than <img alt="C_kn \log \log n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_kn+%5Clog+%5Clog+n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges contains a <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-12-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-52"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-53"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-54">k</span></span></span></span>-regular subgraph. This bound matches the lower bound of Pyber, Rödl and Szemerédi and thus completely resolved the well-known problem of Erdős and Sauer from 1975. The new bound </span><span class="abstract-full has-text-grey-dark mathjax" id="2204.12455v1-abstract-full">substantially improves an 1985 result of Pyber, who showed that <img alt="n \log n " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n+%5Clog+n+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-13-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-55"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-56"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-62"> edges</span></span></span></span> suffice.</span></p>
<h3>The history of the <span class="abstract-full has-text-grey-dark mathjax" id="2204.12455v1-abstract-full">Erdős -Sauer</span> problem 1975-2022</h3>
<p>Erdos and Sauer asked in 1975 how many edges (let’s denote the minimum number <img alt="f_k(n)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f_k%28n%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>) for an <em>n</em>-vertex graph guarantee a <em>k</em>-regular subgraph. In 1985 Laszlo Pyber proved that for some <img alt="C_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> every graph with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges and <img alt="C_kn \log n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_kn+%5Clog+n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges contains a <em>k</em>-regular graph. A few years later Pyber, Rodl and Szemeredi found a construction of a graph with<em> n</em> vertices and  <img alt="c n \log \log n " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=c+n+%5Clog+%5Clog+n+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges that contains no k-regular subgraph for every <img alt="k \ge 3" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k+%5Cge+3&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. (The paper appeared in 1995 but the result is from the late 80s.)</p>
<p>Paul <span class="abstract-full has-text-grey-dark mathjax" id="2204.12455v1-abstract-full">Erdős  mentioned the problem among his favorites in a famous paper in 1980 (Vol 1. Issue 1. of Combinatorica) and mentioned the results of Pyber and of Pyber, Rodl and Szemeredi in his 1989 paper.</span></p>
<p>Oliver and Benny proved an upper bound on the number of edges of k-regular free graphs that matches the Pyber, Rodl and Szemeredi lower bound. <span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>Congratulations!</strong></span></p>
<h3>AFK84 and the Berge-Sauer problem</h3>
<p><strong>Theorem: </strong>Every graph (or hypergraph) <em>G</em> with <em>n</em> vertices and <em>2n+1</em> edges contains a nontrivial subgraph <em>H</em> with all vertex-degrees divisible by 3.</p>
<p>This is a theorem of Noga Alon,  Shmuel Friedland, and me (AFK) from 1984.)</p>
<p><strong>Before the proof</strong>: If we want to get a subgraph with all vertex degrees even then we need<em> n</em> edges (or <em>n+1</em> edges for hypergraphs). This has a simple linear algebra proof which also gives an efficient algorithm.</p>
<p><strong>From-scratch proof scatch: </strong>Associate to every edge <em>e</em> of the graph a variable <img alt="x_e" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_e&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. Consider the two polynomial</p>
<p><em>P=</em> <img alt="\prod_{v \in V(G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cprod_%7Bv+%5Cin+V%28G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> <img alt="((\sum_{e: v \in e}x^2_e)^2-1)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28%28%5Csum_%7Be%3A+v+%5Cin+e%7Dx%5E2_e%29%5E2-1%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, and</p>
<p>Q=<img alt="\prod_{e\in E(G)}(x_e^2-1)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cprod_%7Be%5Cin+E%28G%29%7D%28x_e%5E2-1%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>If the theorem is false then <em>P-Q=0, </em>as polynomials over the field with three elements. This is impossible since P is a polynomial of degree <em>4n</em> while Q is a polynomial which has a monomial of degree <em>4n+2</em> with nonzero coefficient.</p>
<p>The theorem follows more directly from a theorem of Chevallay and even more directly from a theorem of Olson.</p>
<p>AFK84 was a necessary ingredients of Pyber 1985 upper bound as well as the Janzer-Sudakov new upper bound. It will be very nice to get rid of this ingredient. AFK84 came a little short of proving the Berge-Sauer conjecture that every 4-regular graph contains a 3-regular subgraph.  This conjecture was proved in a 1982 paper by Taskinov.</p>
<h3>Three problems</h3>
<p>A) Is it true that every graph with n vertices and 2n+1 edges with maximum degree 5 contains a 3-regular graph of type I? (Namely a 3-regular 3-edge colorable subgraph.)</p>
<p>B) How many edges for a 3-uniform hypergraph on n vertices guarantees a k-regular sub-hypergraph? (Here we refer to “3-regular hypergraph as a hypergraph so that every vertex belongs to three (or zero) edges. You can also demand that every pair of vertices belongs to three or zero edges.)</p>
<p>C) Is there a polynomial-time algorithm to find a<em> r</em>-regular subgraph for a graph with n vertices and <img alt="n^{1.01}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B1.01%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges.</p>
<h3>Climbing the Turan ladder</h3>
<p>Climbing the Turan ladder refers to unavoidable subgraphs of a graph of n vertices and m edges as m grows. (The Erdos-Renyi ladder is a similar notion for random graphs.)</p>
<p>Problem A) is related to the following:</p>
<p>When <img alt="m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is roughly <img alt="2n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p><strong>a)</strong> (for <img alt="m=2n-2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m%3D2n-2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>) you must have a subgraph with all degrees larger than 2</p>
<p><strong>b)</strong> (for <img alt="m= 2n+1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m%3D+2n%2B1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>) you must have a subgraph with all degrees divisible by 3 (AFK84), and</p>
<p><strong>c)</strong> (for <img alt="m=2n+1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m%3D2n%2B1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>) you also must have a subgraph <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> such that you can color its edges with three colors so that every (non-isolated) vertex have neighbors of the all color.</p>
<p>We don’t know what <img alt="m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> guarantees</p>
<p><strong>d)</strong> such an <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> so that for every vertex the number of edges of each color is the same modulo three.</p>
<p>Condition<strong> d)</strong> is stronger than both <strong>b)</strong> and <strong>c)</strong> and each of them is stronger than<strong> a)</strong>. Both<strong> a), b)</strong> and <strong>c)</strong> extend to hypergraphs.</p>
<h3>The relevance of Christos’s classes and the PME-conjecture.</h3>
<p>The <strong>Probabilistic Method is Efficient (PME)</strong> <strong>Conjecture</strong> asserts: Every mathematical proof based on the probabilistic method can be transformed into an efficient (randomized) algorithm.</p>
<p>This is a vague and controversial conjecture that I mentioned in the post <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2013/08/08/poznan-random-structures-and-algorithms-2013/" rel="bookmark">Poznań: Random Structures and Algorithms 2013</a>. (There I  referred to it as the Kalai-Spencer conjecture.) Now, if we can get rid of AFK84 and find a purely combinatorial/probabilistic  proof even just for the fact that every graph with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> vertices and <img alt="n^{1.01}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B1.01%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges contains a 3-regular subgraph, this would be nice on its own and may lead (especially for PME-believers) to an efficient algorithm. AFK84 is not supported by an efficient algorithm and, in fact it is related to one of Christos Papadimitriou’s classes describing the algorithmic difficulty for finding objects guarantees by mathematical proofs. See Papadimitriou’s  1994 paper: <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022000005800637" id="OT-8y8wGxeEJ"><span dir="ltr">On the complexity of the parity argument and other inefficient proofs of existence</span>‏.</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-20T13:00:53Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-20T13:00:53Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Benny Sudakov"/>
    <category term="Oliver Janzer"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:18Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/074</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/074" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-074 |  On Randomized Reductions to the Random Strings | 

	Michael Saks, 

	Rahul Santhanam</title>
    <summary>We study the power of randomized polynomial-time non-adaptive reductions to the problem of approximating Kolmogorov complexity and its polynomial-time bounded variants.

As our first main result, we give a sharp dichotomy for randomized non-adaptive reducibility to approximating Kolmogorov complexity. We show that any computable language $L$ that has a randomized polynomial-time non-adaptive reduction (satisfying a natural honesty condition) to $\omega(\log(n))$-approximating the Kolmogorov complexity is in AM $\cap$ coAM. On the other hand, using results of Hirahara [H20], it follows that every language in NEXP has a randomized polynomial-time non-adaptive reduction (satisfying the same honesty condition as before) to $O(\log(n))$-approximating the Kolmogorov complexity.

As our second main result, we give the first negative evidence against the NP-hardness of polynomial-time bounded Kolmogorov complexity with respect to randomized reductions. We show that for every polynomial t', there is a polynomial t such that if there is a randomized time t' non-adaptive reduction (satisfying a natural honesty condition) from SAT to $\omega(\log(n))$-approximating $K^t$ complexity, then either NE = coNE or E has sub-exponential size non-deterministic circuits infinitely often.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-20T10:27:57Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-20T10:27:57Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/073</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/073" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-073 |  Unbalanced Expanders from Multiplicity Codes | 

	Itay Kalev, 

	Amnon Ta-Shma</title>
    <summary>In 2007 Guruswami, Umans and Vadhan gave an explicit construction of a lossless condenser based on Parvaresh-Vardy codes. This lossless condenser is a basic building block in many constructions, and, in particular, is behind the state of the art extractor constructions.

We give an alternative construction that is based on Multiplicity codes. While the bottom-line result is similar to the GUV result, the analysis is very different. In GUV (and Parvaresh-Vardy codes) the polynomial ring is closed to a finite field, and every polynomial is associated with related elements in the finite field. In our construction a polynomial from the polynomial ring is associated with its iterated derivatives. Our analysis boils down to solving a differential equation over a finite field, and uses previous techniques, introduced by Kopparty for the list-decoding setting.
We also observe that these (and more general) questions were studied in differential algebra, and we use the terminology and result developed there.

We believe these techniques have the potential of getting better constructions and solving the current bottlenecks in the area.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-18T16:14:05Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-18T16:14:05Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=990</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2022/05/18/qa/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Q&amp;A</title>
    <summary>What led you to academia? Much to the shock of my fellow students, I have wanted to be a professor since my freshman year in Italy. The pursuit of knowledge and the lifestyle freedom really appealed to me. Naturally, I did not have a clue; but I would do it all over again, changing nothing… […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ol><li>What led you to academia?</li></ol>



<p>Much to the shock of my fellow students, I have wanted to be a professor since my freshman year in Italy. The pursuit of knowledge and the lifestyle freedom really appealed to me. Naturally, I did not have a clue; but I would do it all over again, changing nothing… alright, almost nothing.</p>



<ol start="2"><li>How did you become interested in theoretical computer science?</li></ol>



<p>I was totally hooked to computers since I was eight, and also worked on videogames in my early teens. In high school I didn’t mind math, but it was not my passion: It was mostly calculus which I thought was “only good for physics.” In college I had a first glimpse of theoretical computer science, and I was struck. The field was asking the right questions: What is a proof, what is knowledge, what is randomness, <em>when you are short on time?</em></p>



<ol start="3"><li>What are you currently working on?</li></ol>



<p>The most famous open problem in the field is the P vs. NP problem which can be phrased as asking to prove that <em>Super Mario</em> levels, properly constructed, are hard to beat. The general challenge is to exhibit problems that require a lot of time on computers. Much of my research concerns proving such limitations for restricted models of computers, for example computers with no memory. Even understanding such restricted models has proved enormously difficult, and a good reason for that is that they are extremely powerful, much more so than anyone anticipated.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-18T13:00:50Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-18T13:00:50Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="SpeakMemory"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1673</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2022/05/new-property-testing-book-by-arnab-bhattacharyya-and-yuichi-yoshida/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>New Property Testing book, by Arnab Bhattacharyya and Yuichi Yoshida</title>
    <summary>More great news: a new textbook on property testing, 📘 Property Testing: Problems and Techniques, by two experts in the field, Arnab Bhattacharyya and Yuichi Yoshida, is now available! As the overview below outlines (from the book’s website), the book covers a wide range of topics, and should give anyone interested a great overview of […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><strong>More great news:</strong> a new textbook on property testing, <img alt="&#x1F4D8;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/1f4d8.png" style="height: 1em;"/> <em><a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-981-16-8622-1">Property Testing: Problems and Techniques</a></em>, by two experts in the field,  <a href="https://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/~arnab/">Arnab Bhattacharyya</a> and <a href="http://research.nii.ac.jp/~yyoshida/">Yuichi Yoshida</a>, is now available!</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/book.jpg"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1674" height="406" src="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/book.jpg" width="306"/></a><em>Property Testing: Problems and Techniques</em> (Springer, 2022)</figure></div>



<p>As the overview below outlines (from <a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-981-16-8622-1">the book’s website</a>), the book covers a wide range of topics, and should give anyone interested a great overview of scope, techniques, and results in testing.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote has-text-align-left"><p>This book introduces important results and techniques in property testing, where the goal is to design algorithms that decide whether their input satisfies a predetermined property in sublinear time, or even in constant time – that is, time is independent of the input size.</p><p>This book consists of three parts. The first part provides an introduction to the foundations of property testing. The second part studies the testing of specific properties on strings, graphs, functions, and constraint satisfaction problems. Vectors and matrices over real numbers are also covered. The third part is more advanced and explains general conditions, including full characterizations, under which properties are constant-query testable.</p><p>The first and second parts of the book are intended for first-year graduate students in computer science. They should also be accessible to undergraduate students with the adequate background. The third part can be used by researchers or ambitious graduate students who want to gain a deeper theoretical understanding of property testing.</p><p/></blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-18T03:54:06Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-18T03:54:06Z</published>
    <category term="Announcement"/>
    <category term="Surveys and books"/>
    <author>
      <name>Clement Canonne</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2022-05-21T22:51:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?p=154</id>
    <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/2022/05/17/virtual-dimacs-workshop-on-entropy-and-optimization-on-may-18-19-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>(Virtual) DIMACS Workshop on Entropy and Optimization on May 18, 19, 2022</title>
    <summary>Mohit Singh and I are organizing a two-day virtual DIMACS Workshop on Entropy and Optimization that starts tomorrow — May 18, 19, 2022. We have a stellar lineup of speakers: Nima Anari (Stanford University), Alexander Barvinok (Michigan), Mark Braverman (Princeton), Sebastien Bubeck (Microsoft Research), Péter Csikvári (Alfred Renyi Institute of Mathematics), Zongchen Chen (MIT), Ronen […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p/>



<p>Mohit Singh and I are organizing a two-day virtual DIMACS Workshop on <strong>Entropy and Optimization</strong> that starts tomorrow — May 18, 19, 2022. </p>



<p>We have a stellar lineup of speakers:  </p>



<p><em>Nima Anari (Stanford University), Alexander Barvinok (Michigan), Mark Braverman (Princeton), Sebastien Bubeck (Microsoft Research), Péter Csikvári (Alfred Renyi Institute of Mathematics), Zongchen Chen (MIT), Ronen Eldan (Weizmann), Tali Kaufman (Bar-Ilan University), Jon Lee (Michigan), Shayan Oveis-Gharan (U Washington)</em></p>



<p>The goal of this workshop is to explore various connections between entropy, optimization, and sampling. Entropy-maximizing probability distributions have been recently used in interesting ways in applications such as algorithms for counting problems, algorithms for NP-hard optimization problems, and interior-point methods for convex programming</p>



<p>Attendance to the workshop is free but <strong>registration is required</strong>. To see the program of the workshop and register, visit <a href="http://dimacs.rutgers.edu/events/details?eID=318">here</a>.</p>



<p>Looking forward to seeing many of you there!</p>



<p/>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-17T21:01:47Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-17T21:01:47Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>nisheethvishnoi</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Algorithms, Nature, and Society</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:38:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20024</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/16/take-wing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Take Wing</title>
    <summary>It is a capital mistake to theorize before one has data—Sherlock Holmes Jeannette Wing is a Professor of Computer Science at Columbia University. She was recently appointed Executive VP for Research across all of Columbia’s campuses. She is also an adjunct Professor at Carnegie Mellon University. She stays busy. See this for her CV. Sixteen […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><i>It is a capital mistake to theorize before one has data—Sherlock Holmes</i></p>
<p>
Jeannette Wing is a Professor of Computer Science at Columbia University. She was recently <a href="https://president.columbia.edu/news/jeannette-wing-appointed-executive-vice-president-research">appointed</a> Executive VP for Research across all of Columbia’s campuses. She is also an adjunct Professor at Carnegie Mellon University. She stays busy. See <a href="https://www.cs.columbia.edu/~wing/">this</a> for her CV. </p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/16/take-wing/jw/" rel="attachment wp-att-20028"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-20028" height="225" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/jw.png?resize=225%2C225&amp;ssl=1" width="225"/></a></p>
<p>
Sixteen years ago she wrote a short <a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/afs/cs/usr/wing/www/publications/Wing06.pdf">position</a> paper for <em>Communications of the ACM</em> titled “Computational Thinking.” It begins:</p>
<p>
<em><br/>
 Computational thinking builds on the power and limits of computing processes, whether they are executed by a human or by a machine.<br/>
</em></p>
<p>
This is the first of sixteen sentences of the form “Computational thinking [verb]…,” plus one that follows a semicolon. The thirteenth prefaces six bulleted paragraphs giving characteristics of computational thinking. They fill page 3 of 3—the paper is shorter to read than this post. </p>
<p>
Her 2007 <a href="https://www.cs.cmu.edu/afs/cs/usr/wing/www/Computational_Thinking.pdf">talk</a> on “Computational Thinking” has oodles of things that aren’t in the paper: <em>pictures</em>. It also concludes by posing five questions that she put into another famous CACM paper.</p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Five Questions </b></p>
<p/><p>
This second <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2008/1/5481-five-deep-questions-in-computing/fulltext">paper</a> appeared in 2008 with the title “Five Deep Questions in Computing.” They are: </p>
<ol>
<li> P = NP?
</li><li> What is computable?
</li><li> What is intelligence?
</li><li> What is information?
</li><li> (How) can we build complex systems simply?
</li></ol>
<p>
The first is one of the basic questions of theory, of course. </p>
<p>
The next is about what are computations? This question complicates when one includes: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA_computing">DNA</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_computing">quantum</a> computers? Also what about man-machine joint computations? Given that humans and machines have different computing capability, now ask: What is computable? Pretty complex.</p>
<p>
Let’s skip what is intelligence for now.</p>
<p>
What is information? This is a perfect question: Information is not just <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>‘s and <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>‘s. DNA encodes information in a different way and with quantum computing, it’s not bits but qubits. Amazing. </p>
<p>
Finally we will also skip the last question. </p>
<p>
She ends with:<br/>
<em><br/>
I pose these questions to stimulate deep thinking and further discussion. What deep questions about computing would you want answered? In 50 years, how different will they and their answers be from what we ask and are able to answer today?<br/>
</em></p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Data Science </b></p>
<p/><p>
Wing is a leading expert of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_science">data science</a>. This field is traceable back to 1962 when <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Tukey">John Tukey</a> described an area he called “data analysis”. That is Tukey of Fast Fourier transform fame, who I knew when I was at Princeton. </p>
<p>
Data science combines the scientific method, math and statistics, specialized programming, advanced analytics, AI, and even storytelling to uncover and explain the business insights buried in data.</p>
<p>
Her current research interests are in trustworthy AI. Her areas of research expertise include security and privacy, formal methods, programming languages, and distributed and concurrent systems. She is widely recognized for her intellectual leadership in computer science, and more recently in data science. Wing’s seminal essay, titled “Computational Thinking,” was published more than a fifteen years ago and is credited with helping to establish the centrality of computer science to problem-solving in all other disciplines.</p>
<p>
Data can be precious for one of three reasons: the data set is expensive to collect; the data set contains a rare event (low signal-to-noise ratio); or the data set is artisanal—small, task-specific, and/or targets a limited audience. </p>
<ul>
<li> A good example of expensive data comes from large, one-off, expensive scientific instruments, for example, the Large Synoptic Survey Telescope, the Large Hadron Collider, and the IceCube Neutrino Detector at the South Pole.
</li><li> A good example of rare event data is data from sensors on physical infrastructure, such as bridges and tunnels; sensors produce a lot of raw data, but the disastrous event they are used to predict is (thankfully) rare. Rare data can also be expensive to collect.
</li><li> A good example of artisanal data is the tens of millions of court judgments that China has released online to the public since 2014.
</li></ul>
<p>
</p><p><b> Open Problems </b></p>
<p/><p>
Let’s take a cue from Wing: What other major aspects and objectives of computer science shall we put into crisp bullet points?</p>
<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-16T12:32:23Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-16T12:32:23Z</published>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6897620455238922302</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6897620455238922302/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/05/is-kamala-harris-our-first-female-prez.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6897620455238922302" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6897620455238922302" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/05/is-kamala-harris-our-first-female-prez.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Is Kamala Harris our first female PREZ? No. Do I have a theorem named after me. No. But in both cases...</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>On Nov 19, 2021 Joe Biden got a colonoscopy and hence the 25th amendment was used to make Kamala Harris the president temporarily (this source: <a href="https://nypost.com/2021/11/19/biden-returns-to-white-house-after-physical-colonoscopy/">here</a> says 85 minutes, though I thought I heard a few hours from other sources). </p><p>Does this make Kamala Harris our first female president?</p><p>I would say NO and I suspect you agree. A friend of mine suggested the phrasing <i>Kamala Harris is the</i> <i>first women to assume the powers of the president under the 25th amendment.  </i>True.  I don't think it means much. She tacked on the <i>under the 25th amendment </i>since Edith Wilson was essentially president when Woodrow Wilson had a stroke (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edith_Wilson#Increased_role_after_husband's_stroke">here</a>).</p><p><br/></p><p>A student asked me <i>Is there a theorem that is referred to as Gasarch's Theorem or something like that?</i></p><p>I will answer YES and NO, but really the answer is NO.</p><p>YES: In 1999 Gasarch and Kruskal had a paper in Mathematics Magazine: </p><p><a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/papers/dice.pdf">When can one load of Dice so that the sum is uniformly distributed</a>?<br/></p><p>In that paper we have a theorem that gives an exact condition on</p><p>(n_1,...,n_k) for when there is a loaded n_1-sided dice, n_2-sided dice,...,n_k-sided dice so that </p><p>the sums are all equally likely.</p><p>In 2018 Ian Morrison published a paper in the American Math Monthly:</p><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1411.2272">Sacks of dice with fair totals</a><br/></p><p>which used our work and referred to our main theorem as <b>The Gasarch-Kruskal Theorem.</b></p><p>Hence there is a theorem with my name on it!</p><p>NO: The Gasarch-Kruskal paper has only 8 citations (according to Google Scholar). This is more than I would have thought, but its not a lot. The fact that ONE person calls the main theorem THE GASARCH-KRUSKAL THEOREM hardly makes it a named theorem. </p><p>QUESTION: So what criteria can one use?</p><p>We could say that X has a theorem with their name on it if there is a Wikipedia entry about the theorem, using that name. That works to a point, but might fun afoul of Goodhart's law (if a measure becomes a target it stops being a measure) in that, for example, I could write a Wikipedia entry on The Gasarch-Kruskal Theorem. </p><p>We could say that 10 people need to refer to the theorem by the name of its authors. Why 10? Any number seems arbitrary. </p><p>CAVEAT: If someone asked Clyde Kruskal <i>is there a theorem that bears your name</i> that is trickier, since <i>The Kruskal Tree Theorem</i> bears his name.... but its not his theorem. Reminds me of the (fictional) scenario where a Alice steals  a Field's medal and tells Bob<i> I have a Field's Medal! </i>and Bob  thinks Alice is a world-class mathematician since she has a fields medal, rather than thinking Alice is a world class thief. See <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2018/08/how-valuable-is-fields-medal.html">here</a> for my post on that. </p><p>(I originally had Kruskal Three Theorem instead of Tree Theorem. I have corrected this but I hope it inspires Clyde to prove a theorem about the number Three so he can have a named theorem. And if he is lucky, over time, people will confuse it with the Kruskal Tree Theorem!) </p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><i><br/></i></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-16T04:41:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-16T04:41:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-05-21T22:15:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/072</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/072" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-072 |  Probabilistic Kolmogorov Complexity with Applications to Average-Case Complexity | 

	Zhenjian Lu, 

	Halley Goldberg, 

	Valentine Kabanets, 

	Igor Oliveira</title>
    <summary>Understanding the relationship between the worst-case and average-case complexities of $\mathrm{NP}$ and of other subclasses of $\mathrm{PH}$ is a long-standing problem in complexity theory. Over the last few years, much progress has been achieved in this front through the investigation of meta-complexity: the complexity of problems that refer to the complexity of the input string $x$ (e.g., given a string $x$, estimate its time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity). In particular, [Hir21] employed techniques from meta-complexity to show that if $\mathrm{DistNP} \subseteq \mathrm{AvgP}$ then $\mathrm{UP} \subseteq \mathrm{DTIME}[2^{O(n/\log n)}]$. While this and related results [HN21, CHV22] offer exciting progress after a long gap, they do not survive in the setting of ramdonmized computations: roughly speaking, "randomness" is the opposite of "structure", and upper bounding the amount of structure (time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity) of different objects is crucial in recent applications of meta-complexity. This limitation is significant, since randomized computations are ubiquitous in algorithm design and give rise to a more robust theory of average-case complexity [IL90].

In this work, we develop a probabilistic theory of meta-complexity, by incorporating randomness into the notion of complexity of a string $x$. This is achieved through a new probabilistic variant of time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity that we call $\mathrm{pK}^t$ complexity. Informally, $\mathrm{pK}^t(x)$ measures the complexity of $x$ when shared randomness is available to all parties involved in a computation. By porting key results from meta-complexity to the probabilistic domain of $\mathrm{pK}^t$ complexity and its variants, we are able to establish new connections between worst-case and average-case complexity in the important setting of probabilistic computations:

-  If $\mathrm{DistNP} \subseteq \mathrm{AvgBPP}$, then $\mathrm{UP}\subseteq\mathrm{RTIME}\!\left[2^{O(n/\log n)}\right]$. 

-  If $\mathrm{Dist\Sigma}^{\mathrm{P}}_{2} \subseteq \mathrm{AvgBPP}$, then $\mathrm{AM} \subseteq \mathrm{BPTIME}\!\left[2^{O(n/\log n)}\right]$. 

- In the fine-grained setting [CHV22], we get $\mathrm{UTIME}[2^{O(\sqrt{n\log n})}]\subseteq \mathrm{RTIME}[2^{O(\sqrt{n\log n})}]$ and $\mathrm{AMTIME}[2^{O(\sqrt{n\log n})}] \subseteq \mathrm{BPTIME}[2^{O(\sqrt{n\log n})}]$ from stronger average-case assumptions. 

- If $\mathrm{DistPH}\subseteq\mathrm{AvgBPP}$, then $\mathrm{PH}\subseteq\mathrm{BPTIME}\!\left[2^{O(n/\log n)}\right]$. Specifically, for any $\ell \geq 0$, if $\mathrm{Dist\Sigma}_{\ell+2}^{\mathrm{P}}\subseteq\mathrm{AvgBPP}$ then $\mathrm{\Sigma}_{\ell}^{\mathrm{P}}\subseteq\mathrm{BPTIME}\!\left[2^{O(n/\log n)}\right]$.

- Strengthening a result from [HN21], we show that if $\mathrm{DistNP}\subseteq\mathrm{AvgBPP}$ then polynomial size Boolean circuits can be agnostically PAC learned under any unknown $\mathrm{P}/\mathrm{poly}$-samplable distribution in polynomial time.

In some cases, our framework allows us to significantly simplify existing proofs, or to extend results to the more challenging probabilistic setting with little to no extra effort.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-16T01:12:32Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-16T01:12:32Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8332</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/15/information-theoretic-cryptography-22-guest-post-by-benny-applebaum/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Information Theoretic Cryptography 22: Guest post by Benny Applebaum</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear friends, The third information-theoretic cryptography conference (ITC) 2022 will be held in-person at MIT this year from July 5-7. We have an exciting program with 17 cool papers and 6 plenary talks by Yuval Ishai, Rafael Pass, David Zuckerman, Omri Ben-Eliezer, Dakshita Khurana and Yevgeniy Dodis on topics that span the breadth of information-theoretic cryptography (and … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/15/information-theoretic-cryptography-22-guest-post-by-benny-applebaum/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Information Theoretic Cryptography 22: Guest post by Benny Applebaum</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear friends,</p>



<p>The third information-theoretic cryptography conference (ITC) 2022 will be held in-person at MIT this year from July 5-7. We have an exciting program with 17 cool papers and 6 plenary talks by Yuval Ishai, Rafael Pass, David Zuckerman, Omri Ben-Eliezer, Dakshita Khurana and Yevgeniy Dodis on topics that span the breadth of information-theoretic cryptography (and beyond). </p>



<p>More information here: <a href="https://t.co/VhueMjajyf" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">itcrypto.github.io/2022/index.html</a></p>



<p>We hope to see many of you at the conference.</p>



<p>The organizers</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-15T17:05:29Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-15T17:05:29Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/05/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/05/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>A tutorial on how to use Inkscape to make nice mathematical diagrams quickly enough for real-time note-taking in mathematical lectures (\(\mathbb{M}\), via). It’s from 2019, so doesn’t take advantage of newer features of Inkscape released since then. I use Illustrator, but without a site license it’s expensive; the other free program many of our students use is Ipe, more oriented to PDF than SVG but with good TeX integration.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://castel.dev/post/lecture-notes-2/">A tutorial on how to use Inkscape to make nice mathematical diagrams quickly enough for real-time note-taking in mathematical lectures</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108228874974700230">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=31227940">via</a>). It’s from 2019, so doesn’t take advantage of newer features of Inkscape released since then. I use Illustrator, but without a site license it’s expensive; the other free program many of our students use is <a href="https://ipe.otfried.org/">Ipe</a>, more oriented to PDF than SVG but with good TeX integration.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cop-win_graph">Cop-win graph</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108235112878367692">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> now a Wikipedia Good Article. It was the last of my current nominations, so it may be a while until the next. These are graphs on which a cop can catch a robber in a game where they alternate moving on edges or staying put, <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2016/08/18/game-of-cop.html">as I discussed in an earlier post</a>. The GA reviewer made me take out as unsourced a statement that a recognition algorithm of <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016%2FS0166-218X%2803%2900295-6">Spinrad 2004</a> uses time \(O(mn/\log n)\), faster than the bound of \(O(n^3/\log n)\) from Spinrad’s paper. But I still think it’s true.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://chaoxuprime.com/posts/2019-01-12-lights-out-game.html">Lights out game on a grid</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@chao/108228363268882685">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> This is the puzzle where you have to turn out all of a given set of lights on a grid graph using switches that flip the state of any grid cell and all of its neighbors. It’s just solving sparse systems of linear equations over \(\mathbb{F}_2\), but Gaussian elimination is slow and the usual form of nested dissection requires full-rank matrices. Instead Chao Xu describes an \(O(n^3)\)-time algorithm.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/publiccommentsonthecmf/">Stanford mathematics professor Brian Conrad takes a deeper look at the proposed revisions to the California Math Framework for high school mathematics</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108247956356449281">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/02/brian-conrad-takes-down-the-cmf/">via</a>), finding an “abundance of false or misleading citations”, “misrepresentations of facts and evidence”, “guidance lacking  details essential for implementation or seeming to be opinions rather than evidence-based”, and “bias toward data science … based on misinformation and hype”.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://twistypuzzles.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=37692">A twisty mechanical puzzle with exponential solution length</a> inspires <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@henryseg/108194775453014602">Henry Segerman to ask: are superexponential puzzles possible?</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Progress in polyhedral combinatorics <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108259553485852087">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/04/29/joshua-hinman-proved-baranys-conjecture-on-face-numbers-of-polytopes-and-lei-xue-proved-a-lower-bound-conjecture-by-grunbaum/">via</a>): <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02568">convex polytopes cannot have fewer intermediate-dimensional faces than the smaller of their numbers of facets or vertices</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/202205/noti2468/noti2468.html">Steven Clontz reviews <em>Games for Your Mind</em></a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@StevenXClontz/108261574819754988">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> by Jason Rosenhouse, in <em>Notices of the AMS</em>. It’s about logic puzzles in the style of Lewis Carroll and Raymond Smullyan, but the review has a broader focus on puzzles and metapuzzles more generally.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://amandaghassaei.com/projects/digital_marbling/">Digital marbling</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108270841049246147">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span>  A recent physics-based simulation project for paper marbling, by Amanda Ghassaei, who was also responsible for an <a href="https://origamisimulator.org/">origami simulator</a> that I <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2018/02/28/linkage.html">linked with a different url</a> a few years ago.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://eiko-fried.com/welcome-to-hotel-elsevier-you-can-check-out-any-time-you-like-not/">The information Elsevier tracks and resells about the scientists who access its journals</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108278540265067636">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=31326672">via</a>). An EU GDPR personal information request reveals not just dates and times from journal paper reading, writing, and reviewing data but also user names, phone numbers, and bank account information, whether you read the emails from them, and a huge list of the spam newsletters that they subscribe you to.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2022/05/10/partially-specified-mathematical-objects-ambient-parameters-and-asymptotic-notation/">Terry Tao tries to make mathematical sense of notations like \(\pm\) or \(O(\dots)\)</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108280853102871738">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>)</span>  that specify something partially rather than exactly. It’s a long post, but I think much less technical than most of Tao’s posts.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2022/05/11/how-scholarly-meeting-became-superspreader-event">Pandemic at the conference</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108284204495257458">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span> ACM CHI, the annual conference in computer–human interaction, was held in a hybrid format with 1900 physical attendees in New Orleans a week ago. It became a coronavirus superspreader event, despite its vaccine and mask mandates.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://retractionwatch.com/2022/05/12/a-college-that-doesnt-exist-an-email-address-that-goes-dark-who-wrote-this-paper/">The mystery of who wrote a mathematics paper in a special issue, heavily based on the work of the highly-cited special issue editor</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108289912652816183">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> It’s by someone who doesn’t seem to exist at a college that doesn’t exist. But the special issue editor can show emails from the author, so that’s something. Searching MathSciNet for similarly-titled works produces confidence-inspiring journals like <em>Chaos, Solitons, and Fractals</em> and <em>Fuzzy Sets and Systems</em>, but this one isn’t indexed.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://may12.womeninmaths.org/">May 12th was chosen as a day to globally celebrate women in mathematics</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@JordiGH/108289993565001699">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span>  It was the birthday of Maryam Mirzakhani (1977–2017), the first and so far only woman to win the Fields Medal. The link lists celebration events continuing for a month or so.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://medium.com/swlh/polyomino-loops-fc8f6fc92c2f">Polyomino loops</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108304649157797618">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> Matthew Yuan wonders, if you play billiards in a polyomino and try shooting a ball diagonally from the midpoint of each of the polyomino edges, how to count the number of loops that these billiard paths will link up into. It’s somewhat related to the African lusona drawings that I <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/08/02/sona-enumeration.html">discussed in an earlier post</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://jeremykun.com/2022/05/14/practical-math-preview-collect-sensitive-survey-responses-privately/">Collecting sensitive survey responses privately</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@j2kun/108301309174075160">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> This excerpt by Jeremy Kun from his book-in-progress on practical programming techniques is about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randomized_response">randomized response</a>, a method for collecting accurate information from survey respondents on whether they may have participated in an illegal activity (like, say, abortion in the US in the 1960s) without revealing the identities of the participants to the data collectors. Similar ideas of preventing inferences about individuals in data sets also led to the development of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Differential_privacy">differential privacy</a>.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-15T16:11:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-15T16:11:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T00:02:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4630</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2022/05/14/the-first-xl-computer-scientist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The First XL Computer Scientist</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some time ago, I received a message to the effect that I was being considered for membership in the “Academy of the XL”, to which my reaction was, hey, we have all gone out of shape during the pandemic, and … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2022/05/14/the-first-xl-computer-scientist/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Some time ago, I received a message to the effect that I was being considered for membership in the “Academy of the XL”, to which my reaction was, hey, we have all gone out of shape during the pandemic, and body-shaming is never… then it was explained to me that, in this context, “XL” means “forty” and that the Academy of the Forty is Italy’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accademia_nazionale_delle_scienze">National Academy of Science</a>.</p>
<p>Italy has a wonderfully named, and well-known within the country, National Academy of Arts and Science, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accademia_dei_Lincei">Accademia dei Lincei</a>, which means something like academy of the “eagle-eyed” (literally, lynx-eyed), that is, people that can see far. The Accademia dei XL is much less well known, although it has a distinguished 240-year history, during which people like Guglielmo Marconi and Enrico Fermi were members. More recently, the much beloved Rita Levi-Montalcini, Holocaust survivor, Nobel Laureate, and Senator-for-life, was a member. Current members include Nobel Laureates Carlo Rubbia and Giorgio Parisi. Noted algebraist Corrado De Concini is the current president.</p>
<p>Be that as it may, the academicians did vote to make me a member, their first computer scientist ever. Next week, at the inauguration of their 240th academic year, I will speak to the other members about randomness and pseudorandomness in computation.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-14T15:07:57Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-14T15:07:57Z</published>
    <category term="Italy"/>
    <category term="theory"/>
    <category term="Pseudorandomness"/>
    <category term="things that are excellent"/>
    <category term="XL"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20013</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/14/rafail-is-no-secret/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Rafail Is No Secret</title>
    <summary>Never say anything in an electronic message that you wouldn’t want appearing, and attributed to you, in tomorrow morning’s front-page headline in the New York Times—Colonel David Russell. Rafail Ostrovsky is a professor of computer science at the UCLA Samueli School of Engineering. Ken and I have been friends with him for many years, long […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<i>Never say anything in an electronic message that you wouldn’t want appearing, and attributed to you, in tomorrow morning’s front-page headline in the New York Times—Colonel David Russell.</i></p>
<p>
Rafail Ostrovsky is a professor of computer science at the UCLA Samueli School of Engineering. Ken and I have been friends with him for many years, long before he moved to UCLA. He is one of the world experts in security theory and practice. And he is especially strong at seeing new attacks and then finding defenses for them. See his web <a href="http://web.cs.ucla.edu/~rafail/">home</a> site for some details. </p>
<p>
Rafail was just awarded the 2022 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/W._Wallace_McDowell_Award">McDowell award</a>.  For visionary contributions to computer security theory and practice, including foreseeing new cloud vulnerabilities and then pioneering corresponding novel solutions. </p>
<p>
Again first seeing attacks, then inventing defenses. </p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/14/rafail-is-no-secret/ro/" rel="attachment wp-att-20016"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-20016" height="300" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/ro.jpg?resize=208%2C300&amp;ssl=1" width="208"/></a></p>
<p>
</p><p><b> A Key Result </b></p>
<p/><p>
One of Rafail’s neat results is how to create strong keys from biological data. This is joint work with Yevgeniy Dodis, Leonid Reyzin, and Adam Smith and is <a href="http://web.cs.ucla.edu/~rafail/PUBLIC/89.pdf">Fuzzy Extractors:</a> How to Generate Strong Keys from Biometrics and Other Noisy Data. </p>
<p>
Rather than try and generate keys from silly to generate patterns such as: 	 	my name + 3.14159 	 the idea is to use your own biological data. This paper unlike traditional cryptographic keys, is (1) not reproducible precisely and (2) not distributed uniformly. Yet it allows strong keys.</p>
<p>
</p><p><b> A Non-Typical Result </b></p>
<p/><p>
Rafail has a <a href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2020/997.pdf">paper</a> that is titled Alibi: A Flaw in Cuckoo-Hashing based Hierarchical ORAM Schemes and a Solution and is joint with Brett Hemenway Falk and Daniel Noble both of University of Pennsylvania. Their paper solves a nice problem, but we believe is unique for its abstract:  </p>
<p>
There once was a table of hashes <br/>
 That held extra items in stashes <br/>
 It all seemed like bliss <br/>
 But things went amiss <br/>
 When the stashes were stored in the caches </p>
<p>
</p><p><b> More Results </b></p>
<p/><p>
Here is another of Rafail’s results that demonstrates his many abilities. The <a href="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007/978-3-540-24676-3_30.pdf">paper</a> is titled Public Key Encryption with Keyword Search and is joint with Dan Boneh, Giovanni Di Crescenzo, and Giuseppe Persiano.  Consider a mail server that stores various messages publicly encrypted for Alice by others. Using our mechanism Alice can send the mail server a key that will enable the server to identify all messages containing some specific keyword, but learn nothing else. We define the concept of public key encryption with keyword search and give several constructions. </p>
<p>
This result is interesting in that Rafail creates a problem that allows security to be partial. The full text is safe but it is still possible to search the text for certain keywords. This allows the security to be weaken, but not to be weaken all the way. </p>
<p>
It is surprising that security can be weaken partially, but not all the way. It might seem likely that this weaken notation of security could be too dangerous. One of the advantages of precise security models is that such results can be safely defined and shown to be safe. This is the fundamental advantage of modern formal definitions for security. </p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Open Problems </b></p>
<p/><p>
Rafail is one of the top researchers in security in the broadest sense. He is one of the best at defining new types of security and then showing that such notions are actually safe.</p>
<p>
Congrats to him for the McDowell award.</p>
<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-14T13:05:19Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-14T13:05:19Z</published>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/071</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/071" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-071 |  Robustly Separating the Arithmetic Monotone Hierarchy Via Graph Inner-Product | 

	Utsab Ghosal, 

	Arkadev Chattopadhyay, 

	Partha Mukhopadhyay</title>
    <summary>We establish an $\epsilon$-sensitive hierarchy separation for monotone arithmetic computations. The notion of $\epsilon$-sensitive monotone lower bounds was recently introduced by Hrubes [Computational Complexity'20]. We show the following:
   
(1) There exists a monotone polynomial over $n$ variables in VNP that cannot be computed by $2^{o(n)}$ size monotone circuits in an $\epsilon$-sensitive way as long as $\epsilon \ge 2^{-\Omega(n)}$.

(2) There exists a polynomial over $n$ variables that can be computed by polynomial size monotone circuits but cannot be computed by any monotone arithmetic branching program (ABP) of $n^{o(\log n)}$ size, even in an $\epsilon$-sensitive fashion as long as $\epsilon \ge n^{-\Omega(\log n)}$.

(3) There exists a polynomial over $n$ variables that can be computed by polynomial size monotone ABP but cannot be computed in $n^{o(\log n)}$ size by monotone formulas even in an $\epsilon$-sensitive way, when $\epsilon \ge n^{-\Omega(\log n)}$.

(4) There exists a polynomial over $n$ variables that can be computed by width-$4$  polynomial size monotone arithmetic branching programs (ABPs) but cannot be computed in $2^{o(n^{1/d})}$ size by monotone, unbounded fan-in formulas of product depth $d$ even in an $\epsilon$-sensitive way, when $\epsilon \ge 2^{-\Omega(n^{1/d})}$. This yields an $\epsilon$-sensitive separation of constant-depth monotone formulas and constant-width monotone ABPs. It seems that even an ordinary separation of the two classes was not known.   

An interesting feature of our separations is that in each case the polynomial exhibited is obtained from a graph inner-product polynomial by choosing an appropriate graph topology. The closely related graph inner-product Boolean function for expander graphs was invented by Hayes [DM &amp; TCS'11], also independently by Pitassi [2009], in the context of best-partition multiparty communication complexity.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-13T15:36:48Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-13T15:36:48Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8329</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/12/workshop-on-local-algorithm-22-guest-post-by-clement-canonne/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Workshop on Local Algorithm 22: Guest post by Clément Canonne</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After two years online, the 🔎 Workshop on Local Algorithms (WOLA) is back in person, and will be held in Warsaw from June 25th to June 27th. Come and discuss local algorithms of all kinds — sublinear-time, distributed, streaming, (massively) parallel, as well as graphical models and much more; and exchange ideas, techniques, and insights with others from … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/12/workshop-on-local-algorithm-22-guest-post-by-clement-canonne/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Workshop on Local Algorithm 22: Guest post by Clément Canonne</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>After two years online, the <img alt="&#x1F50E;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f50e.png" style="height: 1em;"/> <strong>Workshop on Local Algorithms (WOLA)</strong> is back in person, and will be held in Warsaw from June 25th to June 27th. Come and discuss local algorithms of all kinds — sublinear-time, distributed, streaming, (massively) parallel, as well as graphical models and much more; and exchange ideas, techniques, and insights with others from various research communities.</p>



<p>The workshop will feature talks from a range of exciting speakers, social events, poster sessions, and local (!) outings: to stay up to date on the schedule, and register, please head to <a href="https://ideas-ncbr.pl/en/wola/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://ideas-ncbr.pl/en/wola/</a></p>



<p>Looking forward to seeing you at WOLA!</p>



<p>PS: online attendance is also possible, for those who cannot attend in person. Streaming, after all, is on-topic <img alt="&#x1F642;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f642.png" style="height: 1em;"/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-12T14:05:40Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-12T14:05:40Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=622</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2022/05/12/tcs-talk-wednesday-may-18-thatchaphol-saranurak-university-of-michigan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, May 18 — Thatchaphol Saranurak, University of Michigan</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, May 18th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). Thatchaphol Saranurak from University of Michigan will speak about “All-pairs minimum cuts in nearly quadratic time: a tutorial ” (abstract below). You can reserve a spot as an […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, May 18th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/thsaranurak/"><strong>Thatchaphol Saranurak</strong></a> from University of Michigan will speak about “<em>All-pairs minimum cuts in nearly quadratic time: a tutorial </em>” (abstract below).</p>
<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/next-tcs-talk">the online form</a>. Registration is <em>not</em> required to attend the interactive talk, and the link will be posted on the website the day prior to the talk; however, by registering in the form, you will receive a reminder, along with the link. (The recorded talk will also be posted <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/past-talks">on our website</a> afterwards) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/suggest-a-talk">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/">the website</a>.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Abstract: We recently showed an algorithm for computing all-pairs minimum cuts (or, more precisely, the Gomory-Hu tree) in ~O(n^2) time in weighted graphs and even almost-linear time in unweighted graphs. For weighted graphs, this is the first improvement over the 60-year-old algorithm by Gomory and Hu. Thus, surprisingly, computing all-pairs minimum cuts seems to be strictly easier than computing all-pairs shortest paths, which is conjectured to require n^{3-o(1)} time.</p>
<p>I will give a tutorial on the techniques behind our new result, one of which is called “isolating cuts”. Then, I will survey recent progress in fast minimum cut algorithms and discuss open problems.</p>
<p>Joint work with Amir Abboud, Robert Krauthgamer, Jason Li, Debmalya Panigrahi, and Ohad Trabelsi.</p></blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-12T07:31:06Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-12T07:31:06Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:54Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20001</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/11/differential-privacy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Differential Privacy</title>
    <summary>I’m low-key. I like my privacy—Kemba Walker. Avrim Blum, Irit Dinur, Cynthia Dwork, Frank McSherry, Kobbi Nissim, and Adam Smith, received the ACM 2021 Paris Kanellakis Theory and Practice Award. They worked on and studied the notion of differential privacy. Privacy One of the key advances of modern cryptography is its ability to define new […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<i>I’m low-key. I like my privacy—Kemba Walker.</i></p>
<p>
Avrim Blum, Irit Dinur, Cynthia Dwork, Frank McSherry, Kobbi Nissim, and Adam Smith, received the ACM 2021 Paris Kanellakis Theory and Practice <a href="https://awards.acm.org/kanellakis">Award</a>. They worked on and studied the notion of <a href="https://privacytools.seas.harvard.edu/differential-privacy">differential privacy</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/11/differential-privacy/all-12/" rel="attachment wp-att-20004"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-20004" height="338" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/all.png?resize=600%2C338&amp;ssl=1" width="600"/></a></p>
<p><b> Privacy </b></p>
<p/><p>
One of the key advances of modern cryptography is its ability to define new types of security. One can be pretty naive in defining simple notions of security. For example, it is not too hard to get correct the notion: Given the encrypted message <img alt="{E_K(M)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BE_K%28M%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> one cannot easily determine <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> without knowing the key <img alt="{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. However, things are much more complex when we wish to define more complex notions. </p>
<p>
This happens with notions of privacy. Differential privacy is a framework for reasoning about statistical databases. Imagine you have two otherwise identical databases, one with your personal information in it, and one without it. Differential Privacy ensures that the probability that a statistical query will produce a given result is (nearly) the same whether it’s conducted on the first or second database. </p>
<p>
Perhaps a concrete question will help: <i>How can we use data to learn about a population, without learning about specific individuals within the population?</i> Consider these two questions: </p>
<ol>
<li> “How many people live in Vermont?”
</li><li> “How many people named Joe Smith live in Vermont?”
</li></ol>
<p>
The first reveals a property of the whole population, while the second reveals information about one person. We need to be able to learn about trends in the population while preventing the ability to learn anything new about a particular individual. This is the goal of many statistical analyses of data, such as the statistics published by the U.S. Census Bureau. This is what differential privacy is all about. </p>
<p>
</p><p><b> The Award </b></p>
<p/><p>
From the award citation:</p>
<p>
<em><br/>
Differential privacy is a definition and framework for reasoning about privacy in statistical databases. While the privacy of individuals contributing to a dataset has been a long-standing concern, prior to the Kanellakis recipients’ work, computer scientists only knew how to mitigate several specific privacy attacks via a disparate set of techniques. The foundation for differential privacy emerged in the early 2000’s from several key papers. At the ACM Symposium on the Principles of Database Systems (PODS 2003) Dinur and Nissim presented a paper which showed that any technique that allows reasonably accurate answers to a large number of queries is inherently non-private.</em></p><em>
</em><p><em>
Later, a sequence of papers by Dwork and Nissim at the International Conference on Cryptology (Crypto 2004); as well as Blum, Dwork, McSherry, and Nissim at the ACM Symposium on the Principles of Database Systems (PODS 2005); and Dwork, McSherry, Nissim, and Smith at the Theory of Cryptology Conference (TCC 2006) further defined and studied the notion of differential privacy.</em> </p>
<p>
Look at <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/understanding-differential-privacy-85ce191e198a">the article</a> for more discussion of what it is all about. </p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Open Problems </b></p>
<p/><p>
We wish Avrim, Irit, Cynthia, Frank, Kobbi, and Adam congrats on their well deserved award. </p>
<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-11T20:20:18Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-11T20:20:18Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-5898963605660384340</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/5898963605660384340/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/05/queen-elizabeth-is-3rd-longest-reigning.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/5898963605660384340" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/5898963605660384340" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/05/queen-elizabeth-is-3rd-longest-reigning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Queen Elizabeth is the 3rd longest reigning monarch; The problem with definitions</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> A few days ago Queen Elizabeth passed Johann II of Liechtenstein to be the third longest reigning monarch (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_longest-reigning_monarchs">here</a>). </p><p>A summary of the top 4:</p><p><br/></p><p>4) Johann II, Liechtenstein ruled from Nov 12 1858 until his death on Feb 11, 1929. When he became King he was 18. He was king for 70 years, 91 days. </p><p>3) Queen Elizabeth II (thats a two, not an eleven) ruled from Feb 2, 1952 until now. When she became Queen she was  25. I am writing this on May 10 at which time she ruled 70 years, 94 days. </p><p>2) Bhumibol Adulyadej (Thailand) ruled from June 9, 1946 until Oct 13, 2016. When he became King he was 19. He was king for 70 years, 126 days. </p><p>1) Louis XIV ruled from May 14, 1643 until Sept 1, 1715. When he became King he was 4 years and 8 months. He was king for 72 years, 110 days. </p><p><br/></p><p>Johann, Elizabeth, and Bhumibol started their reigns a bit young (they would have to to have ruled so long) but their first day of their reign they knew what the job was, what they are supposed to do etc. </p><p>Here is my complaint: Louis XIV being king at the age of 4 years 8 months should not count (someone who proofread this post wondered if 4 years 9 months would count. No.) Shouldn't we define the reign of a king as the point at which he can make real decisions as king? Or something like that. </p><p>For the record of the longest marriage there is a similar problem. The three longest marriages are legit in that the people got married at a reasonable age (I think all were married after they were 17). The fourth longest marriage of all time involved two people that were married when they were 5. That should not count (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_long_marriages">here</a>).</p><p>Is there a way to define monarch's reigns and also marriage length so that it corresponds to our intuitions? </p><p>In Math we can use rigorous definitions but in English its harder. </p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-11T03:39:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-11T03:39:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-05-21T22:15:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://gradientscience.org/datamodels-2/</id>
    <link href="https://gradientscience.org/datamodels-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Uncovering Brittleness with Datamodels</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a class="bbutton" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.00622" style="float: left; width: 45%;">
<i class="fas fa-file-pdf"/>
    Paper
</a>
<a class="bbutton" href="https://github.com/MadryLab/datamodels-data" style="float: left; width: 45%;">
<i class="fab fa-github"/>
   Data
</a>
<br/></p>

<p>In this blog post we use datamodels to identify and study a new form of model <em>brittleness.</em></p>

<h2 id="recap-datamodels">Recap: Datamodels</h2>

<p>In our <a href="https://gradientscience.org/datamodels-1/">last post</a>, we introduced datamodels: a framework for studying how models use training data to make predictions. While we summarize datamodels in short below, if you haven’t yet read about datamodels we recommend reading our <a href="https://gradientscience.org/datamodels-1/">last post</a> for the full picture.</p>

<p>Consider a training set $S$ (e.g., a set of images and labels from a computer vision dataset), a learning algorithm $\mathcal{A}$ (e.g., training a deep neural network from scratch with SGD), and a target example $x$ (e.g., a test image and label from the same dataset). A <em>datamodel</em> for the target example $x$ is a parameterized function that takes as input a subset $S’$ of the original training set $S$, and predicts the outcome of training a model on $S’$ (using $\mathcal{A}$) and evaluating on $x$. In other words, a datamodel predicts how the choice of a specific training subset changes the final model prediction.</p>

<p><img alt="A graphic showing a test image and a training set. Some of the training images are greyed out to indicate a subset S-prime of the training set. There is an arrow from the training set to a question asking, &quot;if i train a model on examples # 1, 3, 5, etc., how will the model behave on the given target example?&quot; This question is fed to the datamodel, which returns an estimate of what the output (e.g. loss) of a model trained on S-prime and evaluated on x would be." src="https://gradientscience.org/images/datamodels/datamodel_blogpost_figures.001.png"/></p>

<p>Our <a href="https://gradientscience.org/datamodels-1/">last post</a> focused on constructing <em>linear</em> datamodels (one for each CIFAR-10 test image) that accurately predict the outcome of training a deep neural network from scratch on subsets of the CIFAR-10 training set.</p>

<p>Today, we’ll use datamodels to investigate deep neural networks’ predictions. Specifically, we’ll introduce and measure <em>data-level brittleness</em>: how sensitive are model predictions to removing a small number of training set points?</p>

<h2 id="data-level-brittleness-a-motivating-example">Data-level brittleness: a motivating example</h2>

<p>Consider this image of a boat from the <a href="https://www.cs.toronto.edu/~kriz/cifar.html">CIFAR-10</a> test set:</p>

<p><img alt="An image of a boat from the CIFAR-10 test set" src="https://gradientscience.org/images/datamodels/Untitled.png" width="120px"/></p>

<p>A deep neural network (ResNet-9) trained on CIFAR-10 correctly classifies this example as a boat with <strong>71%</strong> (softmax) confidence. The classification is also “robust” in the sense that over different training runs (each with a different random initialization of the network, batch ordering, data augmentation, etc.), the trained model classifies this example correctly <strong>84%</strong> of the time.</p>

<p>It turns out, however, that if we remove just the following nine images from the CIFAR-10 training set…</p>

<p><img alt="Nine images from the CIFAR-10 training set that, when removed, induce misclassification of the boat example above." src="https://gradientscience.org/images/datamodels/datamodel_blogpost_figures.001%201.png"/></p>

<p>…models trained with the exact same training procedure (applied to the remaining 49,991 images in the training set) correctly classify the boat only <strong>35%</strong> of the time! Furthermore, when we remove only 11 additional training images, the probability of correct classification decreases to merely <strong>10%</strong> (the accuracy of a <em>random</em> classifier!).</p>

<p>Model behavior on this boat image exemplifies <em>data-level brittleness.</em> Models confidently and consistently output correct predictions, but these predictions hinge on a very small set of training examples. (One might hypothesize that in this case, brittleness stems from the fact that there are very few training examples of boats on land or grass.)</p>

<h2 id="quantifying-brittleness-with-datamodels">Quantifying brittleness with datamodels</h2>

<p>How do we actually measure data-level brittleness? In the example above, models misclassified the boat after we removed nine images. These were nine <em>specifically chosen</em> images, however: removing nine <em>randomly chosen</em> training images of boats does not at all degrade models’ probability of correctly classifying the boat image. Even removing the nine most <em>similar</em> training examples to the boat image (e.g., in terms of representation space distance) degrades this probability by only 4%.</p>

<p>So, how do we find the “right” images to remove? Specifically, what we’re looking for is the smallest subset of the training set whose removal induces misclassification on average, i.e.,</p>

<p>\begin{align}
\tag{1}
\label{eq:origobj}
\min_{R \subset S} |R’|, \text{ such that }\mathbb{E}[\text{margin of a model
trained on } S \setminus R \text{ on } x] \leq 0.
\end{align}</p>

<p>Unfortunately, problems like this (optimizing a black-box function over the space of all possible subsets of a large set) are computationally challenging to solve. In the worst case, to find the smallest set satisfying the above condition we would have to train several models for each possible training subset.</p>

<p>This is where datamodels come in. Recall that for a target example $x$ (e.g., our  boat example from before), we can construct (read our <a href="https://gradientscience.org/datamodels-1/">previous post</a> to see how) a <em>datamodel</em> $g$ that, for any subset of the training set $S’$, returns an estimate:</p>

<p>\begin{align}
g(S’) \approx \mathbb{E}[\text{margin of a classifier trained on $S’$ when
evaluated on $x$}].
\end{align}</p>

<p>(Here, the expectation is taken over training non-determinism.) Datamodel estimates can be highly accurate. For example, see the following graph of predicted average margin $g(S’)$ against true average margin (the RHS above) from our last post:</p>

<p><img alt="A graph comparing true and datamodel-predicted outcomes of model training." src="https://gradientscience.org/images/datamodels/Untitled%201.png"/></p>

<p>Datamodel predictiveness means we can (approximately) solve our earlier optimization problem (\eqref{eq:origobj}) by optimizing instead the <em>surrogate objective</em>:</p>

<p>\begin{align}
\tag{2}
\label{eq:surrogate1}
\min_{R \subset S} \vert R \vert \text{ such that } g(S \backslash R) \leq 0
\end{align}</p>

<p>Since $g(\cdot)$ is a simple (linear) function (see the drop-down below for more details), this new optimization problem is computationally easy to solve (and doesn’t involve training additional models).</p>

<section class="container">
<div>
<div class="checkboxdiv">
<input id="ac-1" name="accordion-1" type="checkbox"/>
<label for="ac-1"><span class="fas fa-chevron-right" id="titlespan"/><strong> Why is it easy to solve?</strong> (Click to expand)</label>
<article class="small">
In our last post, we showed that for deep neural networks, datamodels that are linear with respect to the <em>presence</em> of each training image can suffice to accurately predict model behavior. In the linear datamodel regime, we parameterize our datamodel $g(\cdot)$ for a target example $x$ with a weight vector $w \in \mathbb{R}^{50,000}$ (where $50,000$ is the size of the training set), and the datamodel prediction $g(S’)$ is precisely:
    
\begin{align}
    g(S’) = \mathbf{1}_{S’}^\top w,
\end{align}

where $\mathbf{1}_{S'}$ is a 50,000-dimensional indicator vector of $S'$ (i.e., taking on a value of one at index $i$ if the $i$-th training image is in $S'$, and zero otherwise).

Here, solving the optimization problem \(\eqref{eq:surrogate1}\) corresponds to choosing $R$ as the training images that correspond to the largest indices of $w_i$.
</article>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<p><br/></p>

<p>After finding a subset $R$ that minimizes the surrogate objective above, we can verify that $R$ is an upper bound on the objective above by training a collection of models on the remaining training images $S \setminus R$, and checking to see that the target example is misclassified on average. We can <em>ensure</em> we actually get an upper bound on the size of the minimum $R$ by solving</p>

<p>\begin{align}
\min_{R \subset S} \vert R \vert \text{ such that } g(S \setminus R) \leq C,
\end{align}</p>

<p>where $C&lt;0$ is a threshold that we (very coarsely) search for using the verification procedure—if the image isn’t misclassified on average, we can decrease $C$.</p>

<h2 id="looking-at-brittleness-in-aggregate">Looking at brittleness in aggregate</h2>

<p>So far in this post, we’ve seen an example of data-level brittleness, and provided a datamodel-based method for estimating the brittleness of any given prediction. How brittle are model predictions as a whole?</p>

<p>We use our datamodel-based approach to estimate the data-level brittleness of each image in (a random sample of) the CIFAR-10 test set. Specifically, for each test image, we estimate (and bound) the number of training images one would need to remove in order to flip models’ predictions on the test image. We plot the <em>cumulative distribution</em> of these estimates below: a point $(x, y)$ on the blue line below indicates that a $y$ fraction of test set predictions are brittle to the removal of at most $x$ training images.</p>

<p><img alt="CDF of data-level brittleness" src="https://gradientscience.org/images/datamodels/cifar_brittleness_combined_withflips_False.svg"/></p>

<p>It turns out that our motivating boat example is not so unusual. In fact, for around 20% of the CIFAR-10 test images it suffices to remove fewer than 60 training images to induce misclassification! Also, for around half of the test examples, it suffices to remove fewer than 250 training images (still only 0.5% of the training set).</p>

<p>The other lines in the graph above illustrate just how hard it is to identify prediction brittleness via other means. Each one represents a different heuristic: a point $(x, y)$ on the line indicates that for a $y$-fraction of the test set, removing the $x$ most similar images to the target example (according to the corresponding heuristic) is necessary to flip models’ predictions. (See Appendix F.2 in our <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.00622">paper</a> for more details on these baselines!)</p>

<h2 id="bonus-label-flipping-attacks">Bonus: Label-flipping attacks</h2>

<p>One immediate consequence of the techniques we discovered in this blog post is the existence of strong <em>label-flipping</em> attacks. So far, we’ve looked exclusively at the result of removing training images—if we use the exact same technique but instead just flip the labels of the images we would have removed, we find more severe brittleness:</p>

<p><img alt="flipping.png" src="https://gradientscience.org/images/datamodels/cifar_brittleness_combined_withflips_True_True.svg"/></p>

<p>The dashed line above is the same as the blue line from earlier—the new solid blue line shows that for over half of the CIFAR-10 test images, we are able to induce misclassification by relabeling just 35 (target-specific) images!</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>In this post, we introduced a new notion of model brittleness, examined how to quantify it with datamodels, and demonstrated that a large fraction of predictions on the CIFAR-10 test set are quite brittle.</p>

<p>Our results demonstrate one of many ways in which datamodels can be a useful proxy for end-to-end training. More broadly (and as we’ll see in our upcoming posts!), datamodels open the door to many other fine-grained analyses of model predictions.</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://gradientscience.org/</id>
      <author>
        <name>Gradient Science</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://gradientscience.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gradientscience.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Research highlights and perspectives on machine learning and optimization from MadryLab.</subtitle>
      <title>gradient science</title>
      <updated>2022-05-21T22:51:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/05/10/postdoc-in-tcs-and-or-combinatorial-optimization-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-june-29-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/05/10/postdoc-in-tcs-and-or-combinatorial-optimization-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-june-29-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc in TCS and/or combinatorial optimization at University of Copenhagen (apply by June 29, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for postdoc positions in TCS and/or combinatorial optimization. The application deadline is June 29. See http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-220629.html for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jn@di.ku.dk. Website: https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=156468 Email: jn@di.ku.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for postdoc positions in TCS and/or combinatorial optimization. The application deadline is June 29. See <a href="http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-220629.html">http://www.jakobnordstrom.se/openings/Postdoc-UCPH-220629.html</a> for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jn@di.ku.dk.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=156468">https://employment.ku.dk/faculty/?show=156468</a><br/>
Email: jn@di.ku.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-10T22:12:21Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-10T22:12:21Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:22Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2022/05/10/ideal-workshop-on-algorithms-for-massive-data-sets/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2022/05/10/ideal-workshop-on-algorithms-for-massive-data-sets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>IDEAL Workshop on Algorithms for Massive Data Sets</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">May 13, 2022 Northwestern University and Zoom https://www.ideal.northwestern.edu/events/massive-data-sets/ We are inviting you to attend the IDEAL Workshop on Algorithms for Massive Data Sets. The workshop will take place at Northwestern University on Friday, May 13. It will be in a hybrid format. If you are interested in participating in the workshop (in-person or remotely), please … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2022/05/10/ideal-workshop-on-algorithms-for-massive-data-sets/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">IDEAL Workshop on Algorithms for Massive Data Sets</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-10T16:07:55Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-10T16:07:55Z</published>
    <category term="workshop"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19987</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/10/peters-face/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Peter’s Face</title>
    <summary>Mathematics is not about numbers, equations, computations, or algorithms: it is about understanding—Bill Thurston. Peter Weinberger is a computer scientist who is famous for many things—including his face. His name “Peter” alone stands for “rock or stone”. He did great work at Bell Labs, where he was part of the team that created the AWK […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<i>Mathematics is not about numbers, equations, computations, or algorithms: it is about understanding—Bill Thurston.</i></p>
<p>
Peter Weinberger is a computer scientist who is famous for many things—including his <a href="http://spinroot.com/pico/pjw.html">face</a>. His name “Peter” alone stands for “rock or stone”. He did great work at Bell Labs, where he was part of the team that created the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AWK">AWK</a> Programming Language: the others were Alfred Aho and Brian Kernighan. </p>
<p>
I just saw him, after a few years, at Bob <a href="https://wordpress.com/read/feeds/115529253/posts/3992043808">Sedgewick’s</a> retirement event in Princeton. </p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/10/peters-face/pw/" rel="attachment wp-att-19990"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-19990" height="300" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/pw.jpg?resize=252%2C300&amp;ssl=1" width="252"/></a></p>
<p>
</p><p><b> His Face </b></p>
<p/><p>
Peter’s face comes up in Bell Lab’s lure:  For some reason, the <a href="http://spinroot.com/pico/pjw.html">portrait</a> of Peter Weinberger has always been our most popular target for picture editing experiments. It started a few years ago when Peter was raised to the rank of department head and was careless enough to leave a portrait of himself floating around. On a goofy Saturday evening at the lab, Rob Pike and I started making photocopies and, to emphasize Peter’s rise in the managerial hierarchy, prepared a chart of the Bell Labs Cabinet with his picture stuck in every available slot. Peter must have realized that the best he could do was not to react at all, if at least he wanted to avoid seeing his face 10 feet high on a watertower. Nevertheless, Peter’s picture appeared and reappeared in the most unlikely places in the lab. </p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Experiments </b></p>
<p/><p>
Peter’s research over the years has been, I believe, an interesting mixture of theory and practice. Early on he did experimental work in deep number theory. For example his paper with Daniel Shanks <a href="http://matwbn.icm.edu.pl/ksiazki/aa/aa21/aa21139.pdf">refuted</a> an open conjecture. This work is an interesting blend of computations and theory. One of the surprises of deep number theory is that shocks abound in the fine structure of number fields. This structure is not always straightforward and often depends on examples and counterexamples. </p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Crypto </b></p>
<p/><p>
Peter also worked with the US government in classified ways. He is part of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JASON_(advisory_group)">Jason’s</a> group. For example you can see some of his work on the evaluation of research directions: </p>
<ol>
<li> <a href="https://irp.fas.org/agency/dod/jason/dna.pdf">DNA</a>: one of my favorite.
</li><li> <a href="https://irp.fas.org/agency/dod/jason/qc.pdf">Quantum</a>.
</li><li> <a href="https://irp.fas.org/agency/dod/jason/medimag.pdf">Medical Imaging</a>.
</li></ol>
<p>
Other parts of it are classified and <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Renaissance and Google </b></p>
<p/><p>
Renaissance Technologies is an American hedge fund based on Long Island. The firm is regarded as the most successful hedge fund in the world. Weinberger was the chief technology officer at Renaissance until he left for Google in 2003. This exit made sense since Peter seems to love problems in infrastructure and security. Working to solve infrastructure problems at the global scale at Google was clearly a compelling opportunity for him. </p>
<p>
Below is an excerpt from a <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?arnumber=1514393">talk</a> with Peter and Laurianne Mclaughlin:</p>
<div class="wp-caption aligncenter" id="attachment_19992" style="width: 250px;"><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/10/peters-face/peter-weinberger/" rel="attachment wp-att-19992"><img alt="" class="size-medium wp-image-19992" height="300" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/pw2.jpg?resize=240%2C300&amp;ssl=1" width="240"/></a><p class="wp-caption-text" id="caption-attachment-19992">Peter Weinberger, New York City, 2015</p></div>
<p>
<b>Weinberger</b>: I’m a software engineer. I write programs, infrastructure stuff mostly. I’m working on tools for processing various kinds of logs created by internal software. I’m not working on security directly, but a lot of what we do is affected by security and privacy concerns. As a result of the Sarbanes-Oxley Act, most companies now create a lot of logs to verify what code they’re running, and [show] how people work with internal data.</p>
<p>
Also, I spend a lot of time reading code. At Google, you can’t check in code without it being reviewed and approved by a peer, so if you work with productive people, there’s a lot of code to review.</p>
<p>
<b>LM</b>: What are the biggest technology challenges for Google today?</p>
<p>
<b>Weinberger</b>: Scale is the problem. Our business grows rapidly. That means every year, a lot of the technology decisions made a year ago don’t look so good any more. Exponential growth is a very pleasant problem but requires a lot of work.</p>
<p>
<b>LM</b>: What are your technology pet peeves?</p>
<p>
<b>Weinberger</b>: I’m sure I’ve got dozens. Password management. Sometimes people, like auditors, think users should regularly change passwords. I think this just encourages people to use crummy passwords—because either they have to write the passwords down, or they need a sequence of passwords that are very similar.</p>
<p>
One of my other pet peeves here is curious error messages. A lot of them are still awful. They start with the word “abort” but the program continues. We have a lot of legacy software, and you end up with these situations where an error message pops up, but the computer keeps on going. Deep in the software something went wrong, and reports it, but you’re seven levels of abstraction away, and it’s just useless noise.</p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Open Problems </b></p>
<p/><p>
Peter is still working on his problems. We wish him well on solving them and on all he is doing.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-10T13:48:43Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-10T13:48:43Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4626</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2022/05/10/stoc-2022-and-other-theory-events/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>STOC 2022, and other theory events</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Below is the call for participation to STOC 2022, which will take place in Rome in the third week of June. If you would like to come to Italy a few days in advance, Alon Rosen and I are organizing … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2022/05/10/stoc-2022-and-other-theory-events/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Below is the call for participation to STOC 2022, which will take place in Rome in the third week of June. </p>



<p>If you would like to come to Italy a few days in advance, Alon Rosen and I are organizing two co-locating workshops on graph algorithms and on cryptography in Milan on June 15-18 (details forthcoming). If you want to stay longer, I am organizing a <a href="https://lucatrevisan.github.io/fai.html">mini-workshop on fairness in AI </a>in Milan on June 27 (more details about it in a few days). Registration will be free for both events. There are several high-speed trains every day between Rome and Milan, taking about 3 hours.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p><strong>Call for Participation </strong></p>



<p><a href="https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=http%3A%2F%2Facm-stoc.org%2Fstoc2022%2F&amp;data=05%7C01%7Cl.trevisan%40unibocconi.it%7C1414e8ebe6c84cb1feab08da26d30a66%7C6bf3b57a9fb447c29ada51156518f52f%7C1%7C0%7C637864985669532280%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=IvAE0knKAOaU1M8xFhHlk%2B2JkbKCmitWJ7L0DdL7lq0%3D&amp;reserved=0" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"><strong>54th ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC 2022) – Theory Fest </strong></a></p>



<p><strong>June 20-24, 2022 </strong></p>



<p><strong>Rome, Italy </strong></p>



<p>The 54th ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC 2022) is sponsored by the ACM Special Interest Group on Algorithms and Computation Theory and will be held in Rome, Italy, Monday June 20 – Friday, June 24, 2022.</p>



<p>STOC 2022 – Theory Fest will feature technical talk sessions, <a href="https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=http%3A%2F%2Facm-stoc.org%2Fstoc2022%2Fworkshops.html&amp;data=05%7C01%7Cl.trevisan%40unibocconi.it%7C1414e8ebe6c84cb1feab08da26d30a66%7C6bf3b57a9fb447c29ada51156518f52f%7C1%7C0%7C637864985669532280%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=0IwoFBH2nZ9G4OVQYIeErR0tFrjqnJ1FSUXO1DAMflI%3D&amp;reserved=0" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">6 workshops</a> with introductory tutorials, poster sessions, social events, and a special joint session with “<a href="https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.lincei.it%2Fen&amp;data=05%7C01%7Cl.trevisan%40unibocconi.it%7C1414e8ebe6c84cb1feab08da26d30a66%7C6bf3b57a9fb447c29ada51156518f52f%7C1%7C0%7C637864985669532280%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=VdbRq7JdfE3gww0LXDyBGsFUmSFyhJzzTB6nT4JAqSc%3D&amp;reserved=0" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Accademia Nazionale dei Lincei</a>”, the oldest and most prestigious Italian academic institution, followed by a reception and a concert at the <a href="https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.lincei.it%2Fen%2Fcorsini-palace&amp;data=05%7C01%7Cl.trevisan%40unibocconi.it%7C1414e8ebe6c84cb1feab08da26d30a66%7C6bf3b57a9fb447c29ada51156518f52f%7C1%7C0%7C637864985669688516%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=Qg8fp6EggGzAqdlfCV54DG%2FxEIWk2ZrOUbpy2NMhOy0%3D&amp;reserved=0" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Academy historic site</a>. </p>



<p><strong>Registration</strong></p>



<p>STOC 2022 registration is available <a href="https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=http%3A%2F%2Facm-stoc.org%2Fstoc2022%2Fregistration.html&amp;data=05%7C01%7Cl.trevisan%40unibocconi.it%7C1414e8ebe6c84cb1feab08da26d30a66%7C6bf3b57a9fb447c29ada51156518f52f%7C1%7C0%7C637864985669688516%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=0p5rN4YqvT7g3qlE9x7X5A%2FiSCLAZ6slKQIVrm94iQw%3D&amp;reserved=0" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Early registration deadline: April 30th. </strong></p>



<p>STOC 2022 is sponsored by Algorand, Amazon, Apple, Google, IOHK, Microsoft, Sapienza University of Rome. </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-10T12:17:42Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-10T12:17:42Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1667</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2022/05/2022-voila-wola/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>2022: Voilà, WOLA!</title>
    <summary>Good news, everyone! WOLA, the Workshop on Local Algorithms, is coming back this year, with WOLA 2022 taking place in person* in Warsaw on June 25–27. Exciting speakers, events and outings are being planned! Keep track of updates by visiting the website, and register at https://ideas-ncbr.pl/en/wola/registration/ (even if you intend to attend remotely). * Virtual […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Good news, everyone! WOLA, the Workshop on Local Algorithms, is coming back this year, with <a href="https://ideas-ncbr.pl/en/wola/">WOLA 2022</a> taking place <strong>in person</strong>* in Warsaw on June 25–27. Exciting speakers, events and outings are being planned!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><a href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/6fgrkl.jpg"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1668" height="469" src="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/6fgrkl.jpg" width="620"/></a></figure>



<p>Keep track of updates by visiting <a href="https://ideas-ncbr.pl/en/wola/">the website</a>, and <strong>register</strong> at <a href="https://ideas-ncbr.pl/en/wola/registration/">https://ideas-ncbr.pl/en/wola/registration/</a>  (even if you intend to attend remotely).</p>



<p>* Virtual participation is also possible.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-09T13:04:56Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-09T13:04:56Z</published>
    <category term="Announcement"/>
    <author>
      <name>Clement Canonne</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2022-05-21T22:51:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=22634</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/05/09/past-and-future-events/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Past and Future Events</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quick announcements of past (recorded) and future events 1) Shachar Lovett was the Erdos Speaker for 2022 and his great talks are recorded. (Lecture 1, Tensor ranks and their applications lecture 2, The monomial structure of Boolean functions, lecture 3, … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/05/09/past-and-future-events/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><h3>Quick announcements of past (recorded) and future events</h3>
<p>1) Shachar Lovett was the <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/node/3086257">Erdos Speaker for 2022</a> and his great talks are recorded. (<a href="https://huji.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=77834b4f-4050-495b-afd1-ae610069bb22">Lecture 1</a>, <strong>Tensor ranks and their applications</strong> <a href="https://huji.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=e511cae0-b0ed-4024-8b56-ae670062fb01&amp;instance=HUJI21">lecture 2</a>, <strong>The monomial structure of Boolean functions</strong>, <a href="https://huji.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=424913ee-0af1-4496-b66d-ae67005ed4c5">lecture 3</a>, <strong>Point location: an interface between geometry, machine learning and complexity.</strong>)</p>
<p>2) Two weeks ago there was a wonderful <a href="https://math.nyu.edu/faculty/pollack/seminar/spring22/DCGDay22.html">workshop in memory of Eli Goodman and Ricky Pollack</a> The speakers were Andreas Holmsen, Micha Sharir (Tel Aviv University), Esther Ezra, Xavier Goaoc, Andrew Suk, and Sylvain Cappell. The lectures are recorded, <a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLl18CMjwy1yZmhwbMW6THPbu8vluKDrEz">here is the playlist</a> on the computational geometry <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC8bRNi3tJX-tfR_RMtyWR7w/videos">you tube channel</a>.</p>
<p>3) This week I give the <a href="https://secfac.wisc.edu/awards-lectures/hilldale-lecture-series/current-lectures/#physical-sciences">Hilldale <span class="d2edcug0 hpfvmrgz qv66sw1b c1et5uql lr9zc1uh a8c37x1j fe6kdd0r mau55g9w c8b282yb keod5gw0 nxhoafnm aigsh9s9 d3f4x2em iv3no6db jq4qci2q a3bd9o3v b1v8xokw oo9gr5id hzawbc8m" dir="auto">Distinguished Lectures in Physical Sciences at the University of Wisconsin-Madison</span></a>. (The link contains the zoom address.) The topic is quantum computing. Lecture I (Tuesday, May 10, 12:00 CST) is on <strong>The Argument Against Quantum Computers</strong> and lecture II (Thursday, May 12, 12:00 CST) is on <strong>Quantum Computers, Predictability and Free Will.  </strong><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/05/fwhilldale-blog.docx" title="FWHilldale-blog">Text for lecture</a><strong><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/05/fwhilldale-blog.docx" title="FWHilldale-blog"> 2</a></strong>.</p>
<p>4) This year I also give the Turàn memorial lectures in Budapest. The first talk <strong>Discrete Geometry – When Combinatorics Meets Convexity</strong> was given by zoom and <a href="https://video.renyi.hu/video/recent-progress-in-combinatorial-questions-in-convexity-408">here is a link to the recording.</a>  The two remaining talks, one devoted to probabilistic combinatorics and one devoted to extremal combinatorics will take place live (but in a hybrid setting) on June in Budapest.</p>
<p>5) The Simons Center at Berkeley celebrates on May 25-27 its <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/workshops/simons-institute-10th-anniversary-symposium" rel="noopener" target="_blank">10th Anniversary Symposium</a> (I plan to devote to it a special post).</p>
<p>6) <a href="https://vinberg.combgeo.org/igor-pak/">Igor Pak gave the Vinberg lecture</a> <strong>Combinatorial inequalities</strong> on Wednesday May 4. (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLU5TmElGttj2Edo_4KGOBaLXge3ZVRePU">This You Tube channel</a> is devoted to Vinberg’s talks and I will add a link to Igor’s talk here when it will be available.)</p>
<p>7) Remote lectures open up new opportunities. This summer I was invited to give a lecture in Indonesia and last fall I gave a lecture at Lahore, Pakistan.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/05/hilldale.png"><img alt="Hilldale" class="alignnone  wp-image-22647" height="426" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/05/hilldale.png?w=332&amp;h=426" width="332"/></a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-09T06:03:47Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-09T06:03:47Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Conferences"/>
    <category term="Convexity"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <category term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:18Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/070</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/070" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-070 |  On Solving Sparse Polynomial Factorization Related Problems | 

	Ilya Volkovich, 

	Pranav Bisht</title>
    <summary>In a recent result of Bhargava, Saraf and Volkovich [FOCS’18; JACM’20], the first sparsity bound for constant individual degree polynomials was shown. In particular, it was shown that any factor of a polynomial with at most $s$ terms and individual degree bounded by $d$ can itself have at most $s^{O(d^2\log n)}$ terms. It is conjectured, though, that the "true" sparsity bound should be polynomial (i.e. $s^{poly(d)}$). In this paper we provide supporting evidence for this conjecture by presenting polynomial-time algorithms for several problems that would be implied by a polynomial-size sparsity bound. In particular, we give an efficient (deterministic) identity testing algorithms for $\Sigma^{[2]}\Pi\Sigma\Pi^{[\deg_{x_i} \leq d]}$ circuits and testing if a sparse polynomial is an exact power. Hence, our algorithms rely on different techniques.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-09T04:31:19Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-09T04:31:19Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1651</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2022/05/news-for-april-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for April 2022</title>
    <summary>We have…I don’t know, I’ve lost count of the number of papers this month. It’s a big bonanza. Sublinear algorithms for edit distance, planar graphs, distributions, bipartite graphs, groups, error correcting codes, Bayesian nets, polynomials… Let’s proceed with the spread. Improved Sublinear-Time Edit Distance for Preprocessed Strings by Karl Bringmann, Alejandro Cassis, Nick Fischer, and […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We have…I don’t know, I’ve lost count of the number of papers this month. It’s a big bonanza. Sublinear algorithms for edit distance, planar graphs, distributions, bipartite graphs, groups, error correcting codes, Bayesian nets, polynomials…</p>



<p>Let’s proceed with the spread.</p>



<p><strong>Improved Sublinear-Time Edit Distance for Preprocessed Strings</strong> by Karl Bringmann, Alejandro Cassis, Nick Fischer, and Vasileios Nakos (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.14137">arXiv</a>). The edit distance between strings is a classic and important problem in algorithms. You might recall that classic \(O(n^2)\) algorithm to compute the edit distance between strings of length \(n\). It has been show that getting a \(O(n^{2-\delta})\) time algorithm is SETH-hard. But what can be done in sublinear time? This paper considers the preprocessed version: suppose we can perform near-linear preprocessing on the strings. We now want to distinguish between edit distance between \(\leq k\) and \(\geq k\cdot n^{o(1)}\). This paper shows that with near-linear preprocessing on strings, one can solve this problem in \(k \cdot n^{o(1)}\) time. </p>



<p><strong>Optimal Closeness Testing of Discrete Distributions Made <s>Complex</s> Simple</strong> by (our own) Clément L. Canonne and Yucheng Sun (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12640">arXiv</a>). Given two distributions \(p, q\) over support \([k]\), the aim is to distinguish between (i) the distributions being equal, and (ii) the total variation distance between \(p, q\) being at least \(\epsilon\). The tester should has a failure probability of at most \(\delta\). A recent work nails down the sample complexity with respect to all parameters. This paper gives a simpler proof of the main result. Earlier proofs used Poissonization tricks and fairly clever arguments about Poisson random variables. This proof is much more transparent, and uses an identity that relates the expectation of a random variable to its characteristic function. A nice feature of this proof is that it works directly with the multinomial distribution, which means a fixed number of samples (rather than choosing the number of samples from a distribution).</p>



<p><strong>Tolerant Bipartiteness Testing in Dense Graphs</strong> by Arijit Ghosh, Gopinath Mishra, Rahul Raychaudhury, and Sayantan Sen (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12397">arXiv</a>). Testing bipartiteness of dense graphs is about as a classic as it gets. We wish to distinguish a bipartite graph from one that requires \(\varepsilon n^2\) edge removals to make it bipartite. Readers of this blog should know that there is a \(\widetilde{O}(\varepsilon^{-2})\)-query property tester for this problem. (Ok, so now you know.) This paper studies the tolerant version of bipartiteness testing. Note that this is equivalent to approximating the maxcut, up to additive error \(\varepsilon n^2\). Classic approximation algorithms show that the latter can be done in \(\widetilde{O}(\varepsilon^{-6})\) queries and \(\exp(\widetilde{O}(\varepsilon^{-2}))\) time. This paper considers the easier problem of distinguishing whether the distance to bipartiteness is at most \(\varepsilon\) or at least \(2 \varepsilon\). This problem is solved in \(\widetilde{O}(\varepsilon^{-3})\) queries and \(\exp(\widetilde{O}(\varepsilon^{-1}))\). </p>



<p><strong>Properly learning monotone functions via local reconstruction</strong> by Jane Lange, Ronitt Rubinfeld, Arsen Vasilyan (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.11894">arXiv</a>). Ah yes, monotone functions. An ongoing love (obsession? interest?) for property testing people. This paper studies the problem of proper learning of Boolean valued monotone functions over the Boolean hypercube. Given access to uniform random evaluations of a monotone function \(f:\{0,1\}^n \to \{0,1\}\), we wish to compute a monotone function \(g\) that approximates the original function. Classic results from Fourier analysis show that an approximation  can be learned using \(\exp(\sqrt{n}/\varepsilon)\) queries. But this approximation function might not be monotone, and only yields improper learning. This paper gives a proper learner that outputs a monotone approximation, in roughly the same query complexity. This result directly gives a constant tolerance monotonicity tester for Boolean functions. The paper uses recent results from distributed algorithms and local computation. It also leads to tolerant testers for monotonicity over posets with small diameter.</p>



<p><strong>Massively Parallel Computation and Sublinear-Time Algorithms for Embedded Planar Graphs</strong> by Jacob Holm and Jakub Tětek (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.09035">arXiv</a>). Sublinear algorithms for planar graphs is another ongoing love (at least for me). This paper considers a new take of this problem: suppose we have access to a geometric embedding of a planar graph \(G\). Can we get sublinear algorithms for a variety of problems? This paper first shows how to construct a convenient decomposition, called an \(r\)-division, in sublinear time. This division can be used to approximate Lipschitz graph parameters, such as maximum matching sizes, maximum independent set, etc. The paper also shows how to compute an \(r\)-division in the MPC model, which solves many classic graph  problems (connected components, matchings, etc.) in \(O(1)\) rounds. There is a (conditional) lower bound showing that, without an embedding, it is not possible to solve such problems in \(O(1)\) rounds (and sublinear space per processor).</p>



<p><strong>Independence Testing for Bounded Degree Bayesian Network</strong> by Arnab Bhattacharyya, Clément L. Canonne (again, our own), and Joy Qiping Yang (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.08690">arXiv</a>). Given a distribution \(\mathcal{P}\) on the Boolean hypercube \(\{0,1\}^n\), the problem is to determine whether \(\mathcal{P}\) is a product distribution. In general, this problem requires \(\Omega(2^n)\) samples. Suppose \(\mathcal{P}\) has a sparse, “efficient” description. Can we do better? This paper shows that when \(\mathcal{P}\) is generated by a Bayesian network (with bounded indegree), then the independence testing problem can be solved with a \(\widetilde{O}(n/\varepsilon^2)\) samples. Think of a Bayesian network as a DAG, where each vertex generates a Bernoulli random variable. The variable at a vertex depends only the outcomes at its neighborhood.</p>



<p><strong>Low Degree Testing over the Reals </strong>by Vipul Arora, Arnab Bhattacharyya, Noah Fleming, Esty Kelman, and Yuichi Yoshida (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.08404">arXiv</a>, <a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/051/">ECCC</a>). The problem testing low degree polynomials goes back to the birth of property testing. This paper studies real valued polynomials, in the distribution free setting. Formally, we have query access to a function \(f: \mathbb{R}^d \to \mathbb{R}\). The distance is measured with respect to an unknown distribution \(\mathcal{D}\) over the domain. This paper shows that the real low degree testing problem can be solved in \(poly(d\varepsilon^{-1})\) queries (under some reasonableness conditions on the distribution). The approach is go to via the “self-correct and test” approach: try to compute a low degree polynomial that fits some sampled data, and then check how far the self-corrected version is from another sample.</p>



<p><strong>Testing distributional assumptions of learning algorithms</strong> by Ronitt Rubinfeld and Arsen Vasilyan (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2204.07196.pdf">arXiv</a>). Consider the problem of learning a halfspace over \(\mathbb{R}^n\). If the underlying distribution is Gaussian, then this class can be learned in \(n^{poly(\varepsilon^{-1})}\) samples. If the distribution is arbitrary, no \(2^{o(n)}\) algorithm is known despite much research. This paper introduces the notion of having a <em>tester-learner</em> pair. The tester first checks if the input distribution is “well-behaved” (Gaussian-like). If the tester passes, then we run the learner. Indeed, this perspective goes back to some of the original motivations for property testing (when is testing faster than learning). The intriguing aspect of this problem is that we do not have efficient testers for determining if an input distribution is Gaussian. This paper circumvents that problem by estimating certain moments of the distribution. If these moments agree with the moments of a Gaussian, then the learner is guaranteed to succeed. We get the best of both worlds: if the input distribution is Gaussian, the learning is done correctly. If the learner succeeds, then then output (hypothesis) is guaranteed to be correct, regardless of the input distribution.</p>



<p><strong>Testability in group theory</strong> by Oren Becker, Alexander Lubotzky, and Jonathan Mosheiff (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.04539">arXiv</a>). This paper is the journal version of a result of the authors, and it gives a group theoretic presentation of a property testing result. Consider the following problem. The input is a pair permutations \((\sigma_1, \sigma_2)\) over \([n]\). The aim is to test whether they commute: \(\sigma_1 \sigma_2 = \sigma_2 \sigma_1\). Another result of the authors gives a tester that makes \(O(\varepsilon^{-1})\) queries. They refer to this problem as “testing the relation” \(XY = YX\). This paper gives a grand generalization of that result, best explained by another example. Consider another relation/property denoted \(\{XZ = ZX, YZ = ZY\}\). This property consists of all triples of permutations \((\sigma_1, \sigma_2, \sigma_3)\), where \(\sigma_3\) commutes with the other two. A consequence of the main theorem is that this property is not testable with query complexity independent of \(n\). The main result of this paper is a characterization of testable relations, which goes via studying the expansion of an infinite graph associated with the relation.</p>



<p><strong>Testing Positive Semidefiniteness Using Linear Measurements</strong> by Deanna Needell, William Swartworth, and David P. Woodruff (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.03782">arXiv</a>). The input is a \(d \times d\) real, symmetric matrix \(M\) and we wish to determine if it is positive semidefinite (all eigenvalues are positive). For the testing problem, we reject when the minimum eigenvalue is at most \(-\varepsilon \|M\|_2\). (The paper also considers general Schatten \(p\)-norms.) This paper gives a list of results for non-adaptive vs adaptive, and one-sided vs two-sided testers. There are two access models considered: a single query consists of either a (i) matrix-vector product \(Mx\) or (ii) vector-matrix-vector product \(y^TMx\). Typical models that query entries of the matrix require strong bounds on the entries, which is less reasonable in practical situations. An interesting discovery is that the non-adaptive, one-sided complexity is \(\Theta(\sqrt{d}\varepsilon^{-1})\) while the two-sided bound is independent of \(d\).</p>



<p><strong>Relaxed Locally Decodable and Correctable Codes: Beyond Tensoring</strong> by Gil Cohen and Tal Yankovitz (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/045/">ECCC</a>). Locally decodable and correctable codes are a fundamental object of study in property testing (and TCS in general). Consider a locally correctable code (LCC). Given a string \(x\), the decoder/corrector makes \(q\) queries to \(x\), and outputs a symbol. We can think of the output collectively as a string \(y\). If \(x\) is a codeword, then \(y = x\). Otherwise, \(dist(y,z) \leq \varepsilon\), where \(z\) is some codeword close to \(x\). In the relaxed version, the corrector is allowed to output \(\bot\), denoting that it has discovered corruption. The distance is only measured in the coordinates where the corrector does not output \(\bot\). Thus, the corrector gets a “free pass” if it outputs \(\bot\). But note that when \(x\) is a codeword, the output must be exactly \(x\). This paper gives a Relaxed LCC with query complexity \((\log n)^{O(\log\log\log n)}\), a significant improvement over the previous best \((\log n)^{O(\log\log n)}\). It is know from previous work that the query complexity must be \(\Omega(\sqrt{\log n})\).</p>



<p><strong>Verifying The Unseen: Interactive Proofs for Label-Invariant Distribution Properties</strong> by Tal Herman and Guy Rothblum (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/052/">arXiv</a>). This paper considers the distribution testing problem in the context of interactive proofs. The verifier, who wishes to test a property of a distribution \(\mathcal{P}\), interacts with a prover who knows the distribution. The guarantee required is the standard one for interactive proof systems: in the YES case, an honest prover should be able to convince the verifier. In the NO case, no prover can convince the verifier with high probability. There are two important parameters of interest: the sample complexity of the verifier, and the communication complexity of the messages. It is useful to consider the two extremes. In one extreme, the verifier can simply solve the problem herself, ignoring the prover. This could require \(\Theta(n/\log n)\) queries (for the hardest properties like entropy and support size). Another extreme is for the honest prover to simply send an approximate description of the distribution, which takes \(O(n)\) bits. The prover can just test equality to the prover message, which only takes \(\Theta(\sqrt{n})\) queries. This paper shows a 2-round protocol for any (label-invariant) property where both the communication and the sample complexity can be made \(\Theta(\sqrt{n})\). This result shows the power of interaction for distribution testing problems.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-06T21:38:15Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-06T21:38:15Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Seshadhri</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2022-05-21T22:51:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-1290268660743913623</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/1290268660743913623/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=1290268660743913623" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/1290268660743913623" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/1290268660743913623" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2022/05/halg-2022-call-for-participation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>HALG 2022: Call for participation</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am posting this call for participation on behalf of<strong> </strong>Keren Censor-Hillel, PC chair for HALG 2022. I expect that many colleagues from the Track A community will attend that event<span style="color: #0000ee;"><u> </u>and enjoy its mouth-watering scientific programme.<u> </u></span><strong/><div style="text-align: left;"><p><strong> </strong></p><p style="text-align: center;"><strong>7th Highlights of Algorithms conference (HALG 2022)<br/></strong>The London School of Economics and Political Science, June 1-3, 2022<br/><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022</a></p>   <p><br/>The Highlights of Algorithms conference is a forum for presenting  the highlights of recent developments in algorithms and for discussing  potential further advances in this area. The conference will provide a  broad picture of the latest research in algorithms through a series of  invited talks, as well as the possibility for all researchers and  students to present their recent results through a series of short talks  and poster presentations. Attending the Highlights of Algorithms  conference will also be an opportunity for networking and meeting  leading researchers in algorithms.</p>   <p>For local information, visa information, or information about registration, please contact Tugkan Batu <a href="mailto:t.batu@lse.ac.uk" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">t.batu@lse.ac.uk</a>.—<br/> </p><p><b>PROGRAM </b></p>   <p>A detailed schedule and a list of all accepted short contributions is available at <a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022/programme/Programme" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022/programme/Programme</a><br/><br/><strong>REGISTRATION</strong></p>   <p><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022/registration/Registration" rel="nofollow">https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022/registration/Registration</a></p>   <p><strong/></p>   <p style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;"><strong>Early registration (by 20th May 2022)</strong></p><div style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;">   </div><p style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;">Students: £100<br class=""/>Non-students: £150</p><div style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;">   </div><p style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;"><strong>Late registration (from 21st May 2022)</strong><br class=""/>Students: £175<br class=""/>Non-students: £225</p>   <p>Registration includes the lunches provided, coffee breaks, and the conference reception.</p>   <p>There are some funds from conference sponsors to subsidise student  registration fees. Students can apply for a fee waiver by sending an  email to Enfale Farooq (<a href="mailto:e.farooq@lse.ac.uk" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">e.farooq@lse.ac.uk</a>) by <strong>15th May 2022</strong>.  Those students presenting a contributed talk will be given priority in  allocation of these funds. The applicants will be notified of the  outcome by 17th May 2022.<br/></p>   <p><strong>INVITED SPEAKERS</strong></p>   <p style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;">Survey speakers:</p><div style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;">   </div><p style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;">Amir Abboud (Weizmann Institute of Science) <br/>Julia Chuzhoy (Toyota Technological Institute at Chicago)<br/>Martin Grohe (RWTH Aachen University)<br/>Anna Karlin (University of Washington)<br/>Richard Peng (Georgia Institute of Technology)<br/>Thatchaphol Saranurak (University of Michigan)</p><div style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;">   </div><p style="margin-left: 40px; text-align: left;">Invited talks:<br class=""/><strong><br class=""/></strong>Peyman Afshani (Aarhus University)  <br class=""/>Soheil Behnezhad (Stanford University)  <br class=""/>Sayan Bhattacharya (University of Warwick)<br class=""/>Guy Blelloch (Carnegie Mellon University)<br class=""/>Greg Bodwin (University of Michigan)<br class=""/>Mahsa Eftekhari (University of California, Davis)<br class=""/>John Kallaugher (Sandia National Laboratories)<br class=""/>William Kuszmaul (Massachusetts Institute of Technology)<br class=""/>Jason Li (Carnegie Mellon University)<br class=""/>Joseph Mitchell (SUNY, Stony Brook)<br class=""/>Shay Moran (Technion)<br class=""/>Merav Parter (Weizmann Institute of Science)<br class=""/>Aviad Rubinstein (Stanford University)<br class=""/>Rahul Savani (University of Liverpool)<br class=""/>Mehtaab Sawhney (Massachusetts Institute of Technology)<br class=""/>Jakub Tetek (University of Copenhagen)<br class=""/>Vera Traub (ETH Zurich)<br class=""/>Jan Vondrak (Stanford University)<br class=""/>Yelena Yuditsky (Université Libre de Bruxelles) </p></div><p/><p/><p/><p/><p/><p/><p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-06T15:01:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-06T15:01:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2022-05-14T21:18:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8325</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/06/halg-22-call-for-participation-guest-post-by-keren-censor-hillel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>HALG ’22 Call for Participation (Guest post by Keren Censor-Hillel)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">7th Highlights of Algorithms conference (HALG 2022)The London School of Economics and Political Science, June 1-3, 2022https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022 The Highlights of Algorithms conference is a forum for presenting the highlights of recent developments in algorithms and for discussing potential further advances in this area. The conference will provide a broad picture of the latest research in algorithms through a … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/06/halg-22-call-for-participation-guest-post-by-keren-censor-hillel/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">HALG ’22 Call for Participation (Guest post by Keren Censor-Hillel)</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><strong>7th Highlights of Algorithms conference (HALG 2022)<br/></strong>The London School of Economics and Political Science, June 1-3, 2022<br/><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022</a></p>



<p><br/>The Highlights of Algorithms conference is a forum for presenting the highlights of recent developments in algorithms and for discussing potential further advances in this area. The conference will provide a broad picture of the latest research in algorithms through a series of invited talks, as well as the possibility for all researchers and students to present their recent results through a series of short talks and poster presentations. Attending the Highlights of Algorithms conference will also be an opportunity for networking and meeting leading researchers in algorithms.</p>



<p>For local information, visa information, or information about registration, please contact Tugkan Batu <a href="mailto:t.batu@lse.ac.uk" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">t.batu@lse.ac.uk</a>.—<br/>PROGRAM: </p>



<p>A detailed schedule and a list of all accepted short contributions is available at:<a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022/programme/Programme" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022/programme/Programme</a><br/>—<br/><strong>REGISTRATION</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022/registration/Registration" rel="nofollow">https://www.lse.ac.uk/HALG-2022/registration/Registration</a></p>



<p><strong/></p>



<p><strong>Early registration (by 20th May 2022)</strong></p>



<p>Students: £100<br class=""/>Non-students: £150</p>



<p><strong>Late registration (from 21st May 2022)</strong><br class=""/>Students: £175<br class=""/>Non-students: £225</p>



<p>Registration includes the lunches provided, coffee breaks, and the conference reception.</p>



<p>There are some funds from conference sponsors to subsidise student registration fees. Students can apply for a fee waiver by sending an email to Enfale Farooq (<a href="mailto:e.farooq@lse.ac.uk" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">e.farooq@lse.ac.uk</a>) by <strong>15th May 2022</strong>. Those students presenting a contributed talk will be given priority in allocation of these funds. The applicants will be notified of the outcome by 17th May 2022.—<br/></p>



<p><strong>INVITED SPEAKERS</strong></p>



<p>Survey speakers:</p>



<p>Amir Abboud (Weizmann Institute of Science) <br/>Julia Chuzhoy (Toyota Technological Institute at Chicago)<br/>Martin Grohe (RWTH Aachen University)<br/>Anna Karlin (University of Washington)<br/>Richard Peng (Georgia Institute of Technology)<br/>Thatchaphol Saranurak (University of Michigan)</p>



<p>Invited talks:<br class=""/><strong><br class=""/></strong>Peyman Afshani (Aarhus University)  <br class=""/>Soheil Behnezhad (Stanford University)  <br class=""/>Sayan Bhattacharya (University of Warwick)<br class=""/>Guy Blelloch (Carnegie Mellon University)<br class=""/>Greg Bodwin (University of Michigan)<br class=""/>Mahsa Eftekhari (University of California, Davis)<br class=""/>John Kallaugher (Sandia National Laboratories)<br class=""/>William Kuszmaul (Massachusetts Institute of Technology)<br class=""/>Jason Li (Carnegie Mellon University)<br class=""/>Joseph Mitchell (SUNY, Stony Brook)<br class=""/>Shay Moran (Technion)<br class=""/>Merav Parter (Weizmann Institute of Science)<br class=""/>Aviad Rubinstein (Stanford University)<br class=""/>Rahul Savani (University of Liverpool)<br class=""/>Mehtaab Sawhney (Massachusetts Institute of Technology)<br class=""/>Jakub Tetek (University of Copenhagen)<br class=""/>Vera Traub (ETH Zurich)<br class=""/>Jan Vondrak (Stanford University)<br class=""/>Yelena Yuditsky (Université libre de Bruxelles) </p>



<p/>



<p>Best regards,</p>



<p>Keren Censor-Hillel</p>



<p>PC chair for HALG 2022</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-06T14:43:24Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-06T14:43:24Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://dstheory.wordpress.com/?p=131</id>
    <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2022/05/06/wednesday-may-11th-2022-sebastien-bubeck-from-microsoft-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Wednesday May 11th 2022 — Sébastien Bubeck from Microsoft Research</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The next Foundations of Data Science virtual talk of this year will take place on Wednesday, March 11th at 1:00 PM Pacific Time (16:00 Eastern Time, 22:00 Central European Time, 20:00 UTC). Sébastien Bubeck from Microsoft Research will speak about “Set Chasing, with an application to online shortest path.” Please register here to join the<a class="more-link" href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2022/05/06/wednesday-may-11th-2022-sebastien-bubeck-from-microsoft-research/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">"Wednesday May 11th 2022 — Sébastien Bubeck from Microsoft Research"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory/home" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Foundations of Data Science</a> virtual talk of this year will take place on <strong>Wednesday, March 11th</strong> at <strong>1:00 PM Pacific Time</strong> (16:00 Eastern Time, 22:00 Central European Time, 20:00 UTC). <a href="http://sbubeck.com/">Sébastien Bubeck</a> from<strong> Microsoft Research</strong> will speak about “Set Chasing, with an application to online shortest path.<em>”</em></p>



<p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Please register here to join the virtual talk.</a></p>



<p><strong>Abstract</strong>:  Since the late 19th century, mathematicians have realized the importance and generality of selection problems: given a collection of sets, select an element in each set, possibly in a “nice” way. Of particular importance in computer science is the scenario where the ground set is a metric space, in which case it is natural to ask for <strong>Lipschitz</strong> selection. In this talk I will describe a far-reaching extension of this classical Lipschitz selection problem to an *online* setting, where sets are streaming to the selector. I will show how Riemannian gradient descent (aka mirror descent) can be used to approach this type of problems. I will illustrate the power of the framework by solving a long-standing problem in online shortest path known as layered graph traversal (introduced by Papadimitriou and Yannakakis in 1989).</p>



<p> The series is supported by the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1934846&amp;HistoricalAwards=false">NSF HDR TRIPODS Grant 1934846</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-06T02:40:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-06T02:40:00Z</published>
    <category term="Announcement"/>
    <author>
      <name>dstheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://dstheory.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Foundation of Data Science – Virtual Talk Series</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:38:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/069</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/069" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-069 |  List-Decoding Random Walk XOR Codes Near the Johnson Bound | 

	Silas Richelson, 

	Sourya Roy</title>
    <summary>In a breakthrough result, Ta-Shma described an explicit construction of an almost optimal binary code (STOC 2017).  Ta-Shma's code has distance $\frac{1-\varepsilon}{2}$ and rate $\Omega\bigl(\varepsilon^{2+o(1)}\bigr)$ and thus it almost achieves the Gilbert-Varshamov bound, except for the $o(1)$ term in the exponent.  The prior best list-decoding algorithm for (a variant of) Ta-Shma's code achieves is due to Alev et al (STOC 2021).  This algorithm makes use of SDP hierarchies, and is able to recover from a $\frac{1-\rho}{2}-$fraction of errors as long as $\rho\geq2^{\log(1/\varepsilon)^{1/6}}$.  In this work we give an improved analysis of a similar list-decoding algorithm.  Our algorithm works for Ta-Shma's original code, and it is able to list-decode almost all the way to the Johnson bound: it can recover from a $\frac{1-\rho}{2}-$fraction of errors as long as $\rho\geq2\sqrt{\varepsilon}$.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-05T13:45:01Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-05T13:45:01Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/068</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/068" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-068 |  Sketching Approximability of (Weak) Monarchy Predicates | 

	Santhoshini Velusamy, 

	Chi-Ning  Chou, 

	Madhu Sudan, 

	Alexander Golovnev, 

	Amirbehshad Shahrasbi</title>
    <summary>We analyze the sketching approximability of constraint satisfaction problems on Boolean domains, where the constraints are balanced linear threshold functions applied to literals. In particular, we explore the approximability of monarchy-like functions where the value of the function is determined by a weighted combination of the vote of the first variable (the president) and the sum of the votes of all remaining variables. The pure version of this function is when the president can only be overruled by when all remaining variables agree. For every $k \geq 5$, we show that CSPs where the underlying predicate is a pure monarchy function on $k$ variables have no non-trivial sketching approximation algorithm in $o(\sqrt{n})$ space. We also show infinitely many weaker monarchy functions for which CSPs using such constraints are non-trivially approximable by $O(\log(n))$ space sketching algorithms. Moreover, we give the first example of sketching approximable asymmetric Boolean CSPs. Our results work within the framework of Chou, Golovnev, Sudan, and Velusamy (FOCS 2021) that characterizes the sketching approximability of all CSPs. Their framework can be applied naturally to get a computer-aided analysis of the approximability of any specific constraint satisfaction problem. The novelty of our work is in using their work to get an analysis that applies to infinitely many problems simultaneously.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-05T13:43:24Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-05T13:43:24Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T05:37:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
