<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-01-16T09:28:19Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04975</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04975" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Existence of cube terms in finite finitely generated clones</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547596800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kazda:Alexandr.html">Alexandr Kazda</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhuk:Dmitriy.html">Dmitriy Zhuk</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04975">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the problem of whether a given finite clone generated by finitely
many operations contains a cube term and give both structural and algorithmic
results. We show that if such a clone has a cube term then it has a cube term
of dimension at most $N$, where the number $N$ depends on the arities of the
generators of the clone and the size of the basic set. For idempotent clones we
give a tight bound on $N$ that matches an earlier result of K. Kearnes and A.
Szendrei. On the algorithmic side, we show that deciding the existence of cube
terms is in P for idempotent clones and in EXPTIME in general.
</p>
<p>Since a clone contains a $k$-ary near unanimity operation if and only if it
contains a cube term and a chain of J\'onsson terms, our results can also be
also used to decide whether a given finite algebra has a near unanimity
operation.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T02:20:45Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04944</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04944" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Computational Fluid Dynamics on 3D Point Set Surfaces</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547596800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bouchiba:Hassan.html">Hassan Bouchiba</a>, Simon Santoso, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Deschaud:Jean=Emmanuel.html">Jean-Emmanuel Deschaud</a>, Luisa Rocha-Da-Silva, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Goulette:Fran=ccedil=ois.html">François Goulette</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Coupez:Thierry.html">Thierry Coupez</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04944">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Computational fluid dynamics (CFD) in many cases requires designing 3D models
manually, which is a tedious task that requires specific skills. In this paper,
we present a novel method for performing CFD directly on scanned 3D point
clouds. The proposed method builds an anisotropic volumetric tetrahedral mesh
adapted around a point-sampled surface, without an explicit surface
reconstruction step. The surface is represented by a new extended implicit
moving least squares (EIMLS) scalar representation that extends the definition
of the function to the entire computational domain, which makes it possible for
use in immersed boundary flow simulations. The workflow we present allows us to
compute flows around point-sampled geometries automatically. It also gives a
better control of the precision around the surface with a limited number of
computational nodes, which is a critical issue in CFD.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T02:38:46Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04934</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04934" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Algorithm for Bounding the Probability of r-core Formation in k-uniform Random Hypergraphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547596800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bissias:George.html">George Bissias</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04934">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present an algorithm for bounding the probability of r-core formation in
k-uniform hypergraphs. Understanding the probability of core formation is
useful in numerous applications including bounds on the failure rate of
Invertible Bloom Lookup Tables (IBLTs) and the probability that a boolean
formula is satisfiable.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T02:22:39Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04911</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04911" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Unconstrained Church-Turing thesis cannot possibly be true</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547596800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gurevich:Yuri.html">Yuri Gurevich</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04911">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Church-Turing thesis asserts that if a partial strings-to-strings
function is effectively computable then it is computable by a Turing machine.
</p>
<p>In the 1930s, when Church and Turing worked on their versions of the thesis,
there was a robust notion of algorithm. These traditional algorithms are known
also as classical or sequential. In the original thesis, effectively computable
meant computable by an effective classical algorithm. Based on an earlier
axiomatization of classical algorithms, the original thesis was proven in 2008.
</p>
<p>Since the 1930s, the notion of algorithm has changed dramatically. New
species of algorithms have been and are being introduced. We argue that the
generalization of the original thesis, where effectively computable means
computable by an effective algorithm of any species, cannot possibly be true.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T02:20:56Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04738</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04738" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Efficient Algorithms to Test Digital Convexity</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547596800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Crombez:Lo=iuml=c.html">Loïc Crombez</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fonseca:Guilherme_D=_da.html">Guilherme D. da Fonseca</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/G=eacute=rard:Yan.html">Yan Gérard</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04738">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A set $S \subset \mathbb{Z}^d$ is digital convex if $conv(S) \cap
\mathbb{Z}^d = S$, where $conv(S)$ denotes the convex hull of $S$. In this
paper, we consider the algorithmic problem of testing whether a given set $S$
of $n$ lattice points is digital convex. Although convex hull computation
requires $\Omega(n \log n)$ time even for dimension $d = 2$, we provide an
algorithm for testing the digital convexity of $S\subset \mathbb{Z}^2$ in $O(n
+ h \log r)$ time, where $h$ is the number of edges of the convex hull and $r$
is the diameter of $S$. This main result is obtained by proving that if $S$ is
digital convex, then the well-known quickhull algorithm computes the convex
hull of $S$ in linear time. In fixed dimension $d$, we present the first
polynomial algorithm to test digital convexity, as well as a simpler and more
practical algorithm whose running time may not be polynomial in $n$ for certain
inputs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T02:39:12Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04628</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04628" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A constant parameterized approximation for hard-capacitated k-means</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547596800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xu:Yicheng.html">Yicheng Xu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Yong.html">Yong Zhang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zou:Yifei.html">Yifei Zou</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04628">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Hard-capacitated k-means (HCKM) is one of the remaining fundamental problems
for which if there exist polynomial time constant factor approximation is not
clear. But what we know is that it is at least APX-hard. Most of the existing
as well as the state-of-the-art constant-factor results for hard-capacitated
min-sum k-clusterings are pseudo-approximations that violate either the
capacity or the cardinality constraints. In this paper, we propose an FPT
approximation for HCKM without violating any hard constraints whose running
time is $2^{O(k\log k)}n^{O(1)}$ and performance guarantee is $69+\epsilon$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T02:22:58Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04583</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04583" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Platoon Forming Algorithms for Intelligent Street Intersections</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547596800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>R. W. Timmerman, M. A. A. Boon <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04583">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study intersection access control for autonomous vehicles. Platoon forming
algorithms, which aim to organize individual vehicles in platoons, are very
promising. To create those platoons, we slow down vehicles before the actual
arrival at the intersection in such a way that each vehicle can traverse the
intersection at high speed. This increases the capacity of the intersection
significantly, offering huge potential savings with respect to travel time in
nowadays traffic.
</p>
<p>We propose several new platoon forming algorithms and provide an approximate
mean delay analysis for our algorithms. A comparison between the current day
practice at intersections (through a case study in SUMO) and our proposed
algorithms is provided. Simulation results for fairness are obtained as well,
showing that platoon forming algorithms with a low mean delay sometimes are
relatively unfair, indicating a potential need for balancing mean delay and
fairness.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T02:38:39Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04576</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04576" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On geometric complexity theory: Multiplicity obstructions are stronger than occurrence obstructions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547596800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Julian Dörfler, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Ikenmeyer:Christian.html">Christian Ikenmeyer</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Panova:Greta.html">Greta Panova</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04576">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Geometric Complexity Theory as initiated by Mulmuley and Sohoni in two papers
(SIAM J Comput 2001, 2008) aims to separate algebraic complexity classes via
representation theoretic multiplicities in coordinate rings of specific group
varieties. The papers also conjecture that the vanishing behavior of these
multiplicities would be sufficient to separate complexity classes (so-called
occurrence obstructions). The existence of such strong occurrence obstructions
has been recently disproven in 2016 in two successive papers, Ikenmeyer-Panova
(Adv. Math.) and B\"urgisser-Ikenmeyer-Panova (J. AMS). This raises the
question whether separating group varieties via representation theoretic
multiplicities is stronger than separating them via occurrences. This paper
provides for the first time a setting where separating with multiplicities can
be achieved, while the separation with occurrences is provably impossible. Our
setting is surprisingly simple and natural: We study the variety of products of
homogeneous linear forms (the so-called Chow variety) and the variety of
polynomials of bounded border Waring rank (i.e. a higher secant variety of the
Veronese variety). As a side result we prove a slight generalization of
Hermite's reciprocity theorem, which proves Foulkes' conjecture for a new
infinite family of cases.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T02:20:20Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1809.06474</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1809.06474" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Zeroth-order Nonconvex Stochastic Optimization: Handling Constraints, High-Dimensionality and Saddle-Points</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547596800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Balasubramanian:Krishnakumar.html">Krishnakumar Balasubramanian</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Ghadimi:Saeed.html">Saeed Ghadimi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1809.06474">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we propose and analyze zeroth-order stochastic approximation
algorithms for nonconvex and convex optimization, with a focus on addressing
constrained optimization, high-dimensional setting and saddle-point avoiding.
To handle constrained optimization, we first propose generalizations of the
conditional gradient algorithm achieving rates similar to the standard
stochastic gradient algorithm using only zeroth-order information. To
facilitate zeroth-order optimization in high-dimensions, we explore the
advantages of structural sparsity assumptions. Specifically, (i) we highlight
an implicit regularization phenomenon where the standard stochastic gradient
algorithm with zeroth-order information adapts to the sparsity of the problem
at hand by just varying the step-size and (ii) propose a truncated stochastic
gradient algorithm with zeroth-order information, whose rate of convergence
depends only poly-logarithmically on the dimensionality. We next focus on
avoiding saddle-points in non-convex setting. Towards that, we interpret the
Gaussian smoothing technique for estimating gradient based on zeroth-order
information as an instantiation of first-order Stein's identity. Based on this,
we provide a novel linear-(in dimension) time estimator of the Hessian matrix
of a function using only zeroth-order information, which is based on
second-order Stein's identity. We then provide an algorithm for avoiding
saddle-points, which is based on a zeroth-order cubic regularization Newton's
method and discuss its convergence rates.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T02:22:46Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/9th-phd-summer-school-in-discrete-mathematics/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/9th-phd-summer-school-in-discrete-mathematics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>9th PhD Summer School in Discrete Mathematics</title>
    <summary>June 30 – July 6, 2019 Rogla, Slovenia https://conferences.famnit.upr.si/event/12/ The summer school will offer two mini-courses: “Combinatorial limits and their applications in extremal combinatorics” and “Coxeter groups”, as well as invited talks and student talks</summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:09:50Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T23:09:50Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:22:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/5th-algorithmic-and-enumerative-combinatorics-summer-school-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/5th-algorithmic-and-enumerative-combinatorics-summer-school-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>5th Algorithmic and Enumerative Combinatorics Summer School 2019</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">July 29 – August 2, 2019 Hagenberg, Austria https://www3.risc.jku.at/conferences/aec2019/index.html n the spirit of the AEC2014, AEC2015, AEC2016 and AEC2018, the goal of this summer school is to put forward the interplay between the fields of Enumerative Combinatorics, Analytic Combinatorics, and Algorithmics. This is a very active research area, which, aside from the three fields fueling … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/5th-algorithmic-and-enumerative-combinatorics-summer-school-2019/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">5th Algorithmic and Enumerative Combinatorics Summer School 2019</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:09:30Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T23:09:30Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:22:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/spring-school-and-workshop-on-polytopes/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/spring-school-and-workshop-on-polytopes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Spring School and Workshop on Polytopes</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">March 11-15, 2019 Bochum, Germany https://www.rub.de/polytopes2019/ Registration deadline: February 11, 2019 The Spring School is designed for advanced bachelor, master and PhD students. The aim is to prepare the participants in such a way that they can follow the lectures of the subsequent workshop. It consists of three crash courses: Geometry of Polytopes, Monday (2x2h) … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/spring-school-and-workshop-on-polytopes/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Spring School and Workshop on Polytopes</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:08:56Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T23:08:56Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:22:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>For the new year, I’ve decided to try to get back into taking photos more frequently, and to make it lower-overhead I’m making individual Mastodon posts for some of them rather than writing a longer blog post for every batch of photos. So that’s why you see a couple of those images inline here.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>For the new year, I’ve decided to try to get back into taking photos more frequently, and to make it lower-overhead I’m making individual Mastodon posts for some of them rather than writing a longer blog post for every batch of photos. So that’s why you see a couple of those images inline here.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://community.wolfram.com/groups/-/m/t/1579272">Fitting in</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@shonk/101320172170027222"/>). Animated GIF of 124 disks packed (supposedly optimally) on a sphere and then steregraphically projected to the plane, by Clayton Shonkwiler.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://twitter.com/BrunoLevy01/status/1080085027210309632">More animated GIFs of fluids with splashy frothy surfaces</a> by Bruno Levy (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101349213452607605"/>). The fluids are modeled as power diagrams of systems of discrete points and simulated using methods from <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1605.00568">arXiv:1605.00568</a>.
See follow-up tweets for source code and long explanatory video.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/help/stats/2018_by_area/index">Lots of charts and plots of the growth of arXiv.org through 2018</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101355877277070622"/>). In the area I moderate (cs.DS, algorithms and data structures) the number of preprints grew from 1597 in 2017 to 1767 in 2018, but this was a little below the 14% growth rate for arXiv overall, and was far outpaced by the rapid growth in cs.CV (computer vision), cs.LG (machine learning), and cs.CL (natural language processing).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.fortbraggalleywayart.org/the-fish-mural.html">Matsya And The Great Deluge</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101361278765845519"/>). Street art from Fort Bragg illustrating an ancient Indian folk tale.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/mfb/MatsyaAndTheGreatDeluge.html"><img alt="&quot;Matsya And The Great Deluge&quot; street art in Fort Bragg, California" src="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/mfb/MatsyaAndTheGreatDeluge-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;"/></a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.metafilter.com/178580/Orange-Peels-and-Fresnel-Integrals-Train-Sets-The-Urinal-Problem">Orange peels and fresnel integrals! Train sets! The urinal problem!</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101366435174480182"/>). Metafilter discovers <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@esoterica">Interesting Esoterica</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/1.9781611975482"><em>Proceedings of the Thirtieth Annual ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA 2019)</em></a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101373871420970067"/>). My favorite talk from the first day of SODA was “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/1.9781611975482.27">Extremal and probabilistic results for order types</a>” (Jie Han, Yoshiharu Kohayakawa, Marcelo T. Sales, and Henrique Stagni).
Its main results are
    <ol>
      <li>the probability that a random point set has a specific order type is upper and lower bounded by functions of the smallest size of a grid containing the order type, and</li>
      <li>every nontrivial hereditary property of point sets has probability  of being true of random point sets.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-iran-demographer-arrests-20190107-story.html">Iran arrests demographers, the latest target amid an escalating crackdown on academics and activists</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101379517186873559"/>). One of the two arrestees is an Iranian-Australian dual citizen; the other is director of the Iranian National Institute of Population Research. The apparent reason for the arrest is that their research contradicted a political narrative of Iranian hardliners according to which Iran is suffering a population crash and must increase fertility.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The first sighting of one of my Wikipedia illustrations in a SODA talk goes to Michał Włodarczyk’s “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/1.9781611975482.104">Losing treewidth by separating subsets</a>” (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101389040748549759"/>). It concerns removing few graph vertices to reach a subgraph with some desired property. If the optimal solution removes  vertices and graphs with the property have treewidth , then his solution removes  vertices and takes the same time as exactly solving  subproblems of size .</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2019/01/analco-sosa-soda-post.html">Michael Mitzenmacher blogs about SODA, SOSA, ALENEX, and ANALCO</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101390458273110460"/>).
Michael was PC co-chair of <a href="https://simplicityinalgorithms.com/">SOSA</a>, which I was skeptical about (shouldn’t all the best algorithms be simple?), but the session I attended favorably impressed me. Here’s an example, a simple algorithm for <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1501.07460">2-approximating maximum genus oriented graph embedding</a>: greedily remove 2-edge paths while preserving connectivity. .</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pubs/EppRee-SODA-19-slides.pdf">My SODA talk slides on finding laminar 3-vertex separators</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101396845733518307"/>). At the talk, someone asked about finding a maximum set of laminar 3-separators. It’s NP-complete: use Uehara’s “<a href="https://www.jaist.ac.jp/~uehara/pdf/triangle.pdf">NP-complete problems on a 3-connected cubic graph and their applications</a>” to find cubic planar graphs whose -separators are vertex neighborhoods (so laminar separators = neighbors of independent vertices) in which maximum independent set is hard.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Spotted on the Cambridge University Press display table at SODA (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101402305412043483"/>):</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/soda-books/index.html"><img alt="Forbidden Configurations in Discrete Geometry on display alongside other Cambridge University Press books" src="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/soda-books/books-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;"/></a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://codeparade.itch.io/marblemarcher">Marble Marcher</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101407478247456589"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=18805717">via</a>). A game of guiding a marble across a dynamically changing fractal surface. The key is to use the recursive structure of the fractal to make a data structure that can handle the interactions between the marble and the fractal surface quickly enough to run in realtime.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://thehighergeometer.wordpress.com/2019/01/13/some-serious-open-access-journals-in-mathematics/">A list of (respectable) open access journals in mathematics</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101410796814360458"/>). <a href="http://jgaa.info/">JGAA</a> and <a href="http://jocg.org/">JoCG</a> not yet listed but maybe soon?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.metafilter.com/178755/Space-filling-curves-the-hard-way">Wacław Szpakowski’s space-filling curve art</a> (<a href="https://mastodon.social/@joshmillard/101415993062003559"/>).</p>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_Bruijn%E2%80%93Erd%C5%91s_theorem_(graph_theory)">The De Bruijn–Erdős theorem</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101421411362488773"/>): when all finite subgraphs of an infinite graph are -colorable, so is the whole graph. Now a Good Article on Wikipedia.</li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-15T22:07:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T22:07:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:11:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4048</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4048" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4048#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4048" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">The Winding Road to Quantum Supremacy</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Greetings from QIP’2019 in Boulder, Colorado! Obvious highlights of the conference include Urmila Mahadev’s opening plenary talk on her verification protocol for quantum computation (which I blogged about here), and Avishay Tal’s upcoming plenary on his and Ran Raz’s oracle separation between BQP and PH (which I blogged about here). If you care, here are […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Greetings from <a href="https://jila.colorado.edu/qip2019/">QIP’2019</a> in Boulder, Colorado!  Obvious highlights of the conference include Urmila Mahadev’s opening plenary talk on her verification protocol for quantum computation (which I blogged about <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3697">here</a>), and Avishay Tal’s upcoming plenary on his and Ran Raz’s oracle separation between BQP and PH (which I blogged about <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3827">here</a>).  If you care, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/talks/online.ppt">here</a> are the slides for the talk I just gave, on the paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1802.09025">“Online Learning of Quantum States”</a> by me, Xinyi Chen, Elad Hazan, Satyen Kale, and Ashwin Nayak.  Feel free to ask in the comments about what else is going on.</p>



<p>I returned a few days ago from my whirlwind Australia tour, which included Melbourne and Sydney; a Persian wedding that happened to be held next to a pirate ship (the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MY_Steve_Irwin">Steve Irwin</a>, used to harass whalers and adorned with a huge Jolly Roger); meetings and lectures graciously arranged by friends at <a href="https://www.uts.edu.au/">UTS</a>; a quantum computing lab tour personally conducted by 2018 “Australian of the Year” <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michelle_Simmons">Michelle Simmons</a>; three meetups with readers of this blog (or more often, readers of the <em>other</em> Scott A’s blog who graciously settled for the discount Scott A); and an excursion to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grampians_National_Park">Grampians National Park</a> to see wild kangaroos, wallabies, koalas, and emus.</p>



<p>But the thing that happened in Australia that provided the actual occassion for this post is this: I was interviewed by Adam Ford in Carlton Gardens in Melbourne, about quantum supremacy, AI risk, Integrated Information Theory, whether the universe is discrete or continuous, and to be honest I don’t remember what else.  You can watch the first segment, the one about the prospects for quantum supremacy, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=1&amp;v=BvVciA5iXH4">here on YouTube</a>.  My only complaint is that Adam’s video camera <em>somehow</em> made me look like an out-of-shape slob who needs to hit the gym or something.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-15T18:51:16Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T18:51:16Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T18:51:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-4806966094683791166</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/4806966094683791166/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/do-we-ever-only-care-about-decision.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/4806966094683791166" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/4806966094683791166" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/do-we-ever-only-care-about-decision.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>do we ever only care about the decision problem? I know of only one case of that</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(I had been thinking of this for a post then Lance's post on <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/search-versus-decision.html">search versus decision</a> inspired me to write up these thoughts.)<br/>
<br/>
When teaching NP-completeness we often say<br/>
<br/>
<i>The problem we really care about is, for example, given a weighted graph and two vertices s and t, find the optimal way to go from s to t while hitting every node. But its cleaner mathematically to look at the decision problem:</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
<i>{ (G,s,t,C) : there is a Ham Path from s to t that costs \le C }</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
<i>The search and decision are poly time equivalent, so its fine to just look at the decision. Indeed- if our interest in in lower bounds then clearly if Decision is hard then Find is Hard.</i><br/>
<br/>
But here are some questions about search vs decision in general, not just with regard to P vs NP.<br/>
<br/>
1) Is there ever a case where the real world actually cares about the decision version? I can think of just one- given a number is it PRIME is used in Crypto. The real world does not need the witness that its prime (or similar).  They  just want a prime.  Any other cases?<br/>
<br/>
2) How far apart can search and decision be? NP-decision and NP-search they are poly equivalent. In other domains can they be very far apart? For example, is FINDING a k-clique or k-ind set in a graph on 2^{2k} vertices require roughly n^k steps (go through all k-sets) or can we do much better? I suspect this is unknown but would be delighted if a commenter tells me otherwise.<br/>
<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-15T16:21:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T16:21:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>https://plus.google.com/101693130490639305932</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T02:52:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://bit-player.org/?p=2108</id>
    <link href="http://bit-player.org/2019/glaubers-dynamics" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://bit-player.org/2019/glaubers-dynamics#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://bit-player.org/2019/glaubers-dynamics/feed/atom" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Glauber’s dynamics</title>
    <summary type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Roy J. Glauber, Harvard physics professor for 65 years, longtime Keeper of the Broom at the annual Ig Nobel ceremony, and winner of a non-Ig Nobel, has died at age 93. Glauber is known for his work in quantum optics; … <a href="http://bit-player.org/2019/glaubers-dynamics">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Roy J. Glauber, Harvard physics professor for 65 years, longtime Keeper of the Broom at the annual <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ig_Nobel_Prize">Ig Nobel</a> ceremony, and winner of a non-Ig Nobel, has died at age 93. Glauber is known for his work in quantum optics; roughly speaking, he developed a mathematical theory of the laser at about the same time that device was invented, circa 1960. His two main papers on the subject, published in <em>Physical Review</em> in 1963, did not meet with instant acclaim; the Nobel committee’s recognition of their worth came more than 40 years later, in 2005. A third paper from 1963, titled “<a href="https://aip.scitation.org/doi/10.1063/1.1703954">Time-dependent statistics of the Ising model</a>,” also had a delayed impact. It is the basis of a modeling algorithm now called Glauber dynamics, which is well known in the cloistered community of statistical mechanics but deserves wider recognition.</p>
<p>Before digging into the dynamics, however, let us pause for a few words about the man himself, drawn largely from the obituaries in the <em><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/08/obituaries/roy-j-glauber-dead.html">New York Times</a></em> and the <a href="https://www.thecrimson.com/article/2019/1/3/roy-glauber-harvard-professor-obituary/"><em>Harvard Crimson</em></a>.</p>
<p>Glauber was a member of the first class to graduate from the Bronx High School of Science, in 1941. From there he went to Harvard, but left in his sophomore year, at age 18, to work in the theory division at Los Alamos, where he helped calculate the critical mass of fissile material needed for a bomb. After the war he finished his degree at Harvard and went on to complete a PhD under Julian Schwinger. After a few brief adventures in Princeton and Pasadena, he was back at Harvard in 1952 and never left. A poignant aspect of his life is mentioned briefly in a <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3149897/">2009 interview</a>, where Glauber discusses the challenge of sustaining an academic career while raising two children as a single parent.</p>
<hr/>
<p>Here’s a glimpse of Glauber dynamics in action. Click the <em>Go</em> button, then try fiddling with the slider.</p>
<div id="glauber-viz" style="width: 600px; margin: 15px auto;">
	<canvas height="600px" id="glauber-canvas" width="600px"/><p/>
<div id="glauber-controls" style="display: flex; margin: auto;">
		<output class="slider-output" for="glauber-slider" id="glauber-temp" style="font-family: sans-serif; font-style: bold; margin: auto 10px;">3.00</output><br/>
		<input id="glauber-slider" max="5.0" min="0.01" step="0.01" style="width: 300px; margin: auto 10px;" type="range" value="3.00"/><br/>
		<button id="glauber-go-button" style="width: 50px; margin: 10px;">Go</button>
	</div>
</div>
<p class="indent">In the computer program that drives this animation, the slider controls a variable representing temperature. At high temperature (slide the control all the way to the right), you’ll see a roiling, seething mass of colored squares, switching rapidly and randomly between light and dark shades. There are no large-scale or long-lived structures. Occasionally the end point is not a monochromatic field. Instead the panel is divided into broad stripes—horizontal, vertical, or diagonal. This is an artifact of the finite size of the lattice and the use of wraparound boundary conditions. On an infinite lattice, the stripes would not occur.At low temperature (slide to the left), the tableau congeals into a few writhing blobs of contrasting color. Then the minority blobs are likely to evaporate, and you’ll be left with an unchanging, monochromatic panel. Between these extremes there’s some interesting behavior. Adjust the slider to a temperature near 2.27 and you can expect to see persistent fluctuations at all possible scales, from isolated individual blocks to patterns that span the entire array.</p>
<p>What we’re looking at here is a simulation of a model of a ferromagnet—the kind of magnet that sticks to the refrigerator. The model was introduced almost 100 years ago by Wilhelm Lenz and his student Ernst Ising. They were trying to understand the thermal behavior of ferromagnetic materials such as iron. If you heat a block of magnetized iron above a certain temperature, called the Curie point, it loses all traces of magnetization. Slow cooling below the Curie point allows it to spontaneously magnetize again, perhaps with the poles in a different orientation. The onset of ferromagnetism at the Curie point is an abrupt phase transition.</p>
<p>Lenz and Ising created a <a href="http://bit-player.org/bph-publications/AmSci-2000-09-Hayes-Ising.pdf">stripped-down model of a ferromagnet</a>. In the two-dimensional version shown here, each of the small squares represents the spin vector of an unpaired electron in an iron atom. The vector can point in either of two directions, conventionally called <em>up</em> and <em>down</em>, which for graphic convenience are represented by two contrasting colors. There are \(100 \times 100 = 10{,}000\) spins in the array. This would be a minute sample of a real ferromagnet. On the other hand, the system has \(2^{10{,}000}\) possible states—quite an enormous number.</p>
<p>The essence of ferromagnetism is that adjacent spins “prefer” to point in the same direction. To put that  more formally: The energy of neighboring spins is lower when they are parallel, rather than antiparallel. <img alt="four possible orientations of two spins (up up, up down, down up, down down), with their corresponding energies" border="0" class="alignright" height="111" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Ising-spin-pairs.png" style="margin-bottom: 0px;" width="262"/>For the array as a whole, the energy is minimized if all the spins point the same way, either up or down. Each spin contributes a tiny magnetic moment. When the spins are parallel, all the moments add up and the system is fully magnetized.</p>
<p>If energy were the only consideration, the Ising model would always settle into a magnetized configuration, but there is a countervailing influence: Heat tends to randomize the spin directions. At infinite temperature, thermal fluctuations completely overwhelm the spins’ tendency to align, and all states are equally likely. Because the vast majority of those \(2^{10{,}000}\) configurations have nearly equal numbers of <em>up</em> and <em>down</em> spins, the magnetization is negligible. At zero temperature, nothing prevents the system from condensing into the fully magnetized state. The interval between these limits is a battleground where energy and entropy contend for supremacy. Clearly, there must be a transition of some kind. For Lenz and Ising in the 1920s, the crucial question was whether the transition comes at a sharply defined critical temperature, as it does in real ferromagnets. A more gradual progression from one regime to the other would signal the model’s failure to capture important aspects of ferromagnet physics.</p>
<p>In his doctoral dissertation Ising investigated the one-dimensional version of the model—a chain or ring of spins, each one holding hands with its two nearest neighbors. The result was a disappointment: He found no abrupt phase transition. And he speculated that the negative result would also hold in higher dimensions. The Ising model seemed to be dead on arrival.</p>
<p>It was revived a decade later by Rudolf Peierls, who gave suggestive evidence for a sharp transition in the two-dimensional lattice. Then in 1944 Lars Onsager “solved” the two-dimensional model, showing that the phase transition does exist. The phase diagram looks like this:</p>
<p><img alt="Graph of the gagnetization v temperature phase diagram for the Ising model." border="0" class="centered" height="566" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/magnetization-v-temperature.png" width="640"/></p>
<p>As the system cools, the salt-and-pepper chaos of infinite temperature evolves into a structure with larger blobs of color, but the <em>up</em> and <em>down</em> spins remain balanced on average (implying zero magnetization) down to the critical temperature \(T_C\). At that point there is a sudden bifurcation, and the system will follow one branch or the other to full magnetization at zero temperature.</p>
<hr/>
<p>If a model is classified as <em>solved</em>, is there anything more to say about it? In this case, I believe the answer is yes. The solution to the two-dimensional Ising model gives us a prescription for calculating the probability of seeing any given configuration at any given temperature. That’s a major accomplishment, and yet it leaves much of the model’s behavior unspecified. The solution defines the probability distribution at equilibrium—after the system has had time to settle into a statistically stable configuration. It doesn’t tell us anything about how the lattice of spins reaches that equilibrium when it starts from an arbitrary initial state, or how the system evolves when the temperature changes rapidly.</p>
<p>It’s not just the solution to the model that has a few vague spots. When you look at the finer details of how spins interact, the model itself leaves much to the imagination. When a spin reacts to the influence of its nearest neighbors, and those neighbors are also reacting to one another, does everything happen all at once? Suppose two antiparallel spins both decide to flip at the same time; they will be left in a configuration that is still antiparallel. It’s hard to see how they’ll escape repeating the same dance over and over, like people who meet head-on in a corridor and keep making mirror-image evasive maneuvers. This kind of standoff can be avoided if the spins act sequentially rather than simultaneously. But if they take turns, how do they decide who goes first?</p>
<p>Within the intellectual traditions of physics and mathematics, these questions can be dismissed as foolish or misguided. After all, when we look at the procession of the planets orbiting the sun, or at the colliding molecules in a gas, we don’t ask who takes the first step; the bodies are all in continuous and simultaneous motion. Newton gave us a tool, calculus, for understanding such situations. If you make the steps small enough, you don’t have to worry so much about the sequence of marching orders.</p>
<p>However, if you want to write a computer program simulating a ferromagnet (or simulating planetary motions, for that matter), questions of sequence and synchrony cannot be swept aside. With conventional computer hardware, “let everything happen at once” is not an option. The program must consider each spin, one at a time, survey the surrounding neighborhood, apply an update rule that’s based on both the state of the neighbors and the temperature, and then decide whether or not to flip. Thus the program must choose a sequence in which to visit the lattice sites, as well as a sequence in which to visit the neighbors of each site, and those choices can make a difference in the outcome of the simulation. So can other details of implementation. Do we look at all the sites, calculate their new spin states, and then update all those that need to be flipped? Or do we update each spin as we go along, so that spins later in the sequence will see an array already modified by earlier actions? The original definition of the Ising model is silent on such matters, but the programmer must make a commitment one way or another.</p>
<p>This is where Glauber dynamics enters the story. Glauber presented a version of the Ising model that’s somewhat more explicit about how spins interact with one another and with the “heat bath” that represents the influence of temperature. It’s a theory of Ising <em>dynamics</em> because he describes the spin system not just at equilibrium but also during transitional stages. I don’t know if Glauber was the first to offer an account of Ising dynamics, but the notion was certainly not commonplace in 1963.</p>
<hr/>
<p>There’s no evidence Glauber was  thinking of his method as an algorithm suitable for computer implementation. The subject of simulation doesn’t come up in his 1963 paper, where his primary aim is to find analytic expressions for the distribution of <em>up</em> and <em>down</em> spins as a function of time. (He did this only for the one-dimensional model.) Nevertheless, Glauber dynamics offers an elegant approach to programming an interactive version of the Ising model. Assume we have a lattice of \(N\) spins. Each spin \(\sigma\) is indexed by its coordinates \(x, y\) and takes on one of the two values \(+1\) and \(-1\). Thus flipping a spin is a matter of multiplying \(\sigma\) by \(-1\). The algorithm for a updating the lattice looks like this:</p>
<blockquote><p class="undent">Repeat \(N\) times:</p>
<ol style="margin-bottom: 0px;">
<li>Choose a spin \(\sigma_{x, y}\) at random.</li>
<li>Sum the values of the four neighboring spins, \(S = \sigma_{x+1, y} + \sigma_{x-1, y} + \sigma_{x, y+1} + \sigma_{x, y-1}\). The possible values of \(S\) are \(\{-4, -2, 0, +2, +4\}\).</li>
<li>Calculate \(\Delta E = 2 \, \sigma_{x, y} \, S\), the change in interaction energy if \(\sigma_{x, y}\) were to flip.</li>
<li>If \(\Delta E \lt 0\), set \(\sigma_{x, y} = -\sigma_{x, y}\).</li>
<li>Otherwise, set \(\sigma_{x, y} = -\sigma_{x, y}\) with probability \(\exp(-\Delta E/T)\), where \(T\) is the temperature.</li>
</ol>
<p class="undent">Display the updated lattice.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Step 4 says: If flipping a spin will reduce the overall energy of the system, flip it. Step 5 says: Even if flipping a spin raises the energy, go ahead and flip it in a randomly selected fraction of the cases. The probability of such spin flips is the Boltzmann factor \(\exp(-\Delta E/T)\). This quantity goes to \(0\) as the temperature \(T\) falls to \(0\), so that energetically unfavorable flips are unlikely in a cold lattice. The probability approaches \(1\) as \(T\) goes to infinity, which is why the model is such a seething mass of fluctuations at high temperature.</p>
<p>(If you’d like to take a look at real code rather than pseudocode—namely the JavaScript program running the simulation above—it’s <a href="https://github.com/bit-player/glauber">on GitHub</a>.)</p>
<p>Glauber dynamics belongs to a family of methods called Markov chain Monte Carlo algorithms (MCMC). The <a href="http://bit-player.org/bph-publications/AmSci-2013-03-Hayes-Markov.pdf">idea of Markov chains</a> was an innovation in probability theory in the early years of the 20th century, extending classical probability to situations where the the next event depends on the current state of the system. <a href="http://bit-player.org/bph-publications/AmSci-1993-03-Hayes-random-numbers.pdf">Monte Carlo algorithms</a> emerged at post-war Los Alamos, not long after Glauber left there to resume his undergraduate curriculum. He clearly kept up with the work of Stanislaw Ulam and other former colleagues in the Manhattan Project.</p>
<p>Within the MCMC family, the distinctive feature of Glauber dynamics is choosing spins at random. The obvious alternative is to march methodically through the lattice by columns and rows, examining every spin in turn. <img alt="Blinking checkerboard" border="0" class="alignleft" height="" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/blinking-checkerboard.png" style="margin-bottom: 0px;" width="210"/>That procedure can certainly be made to work, but it requires care in implementation. At low temperature the Ising process is very nearly deterministic, since unfavorable flips are extremely rare. When you combine a deterministic flip rule with a deterministic path through the lattice, it’s easy to get trapped in recurrent patterns. For example, a subtle bug yields the same configuration of spins on every step, shifted left by a single lattice site, so that the pattern seems to slide across the screen. Another spectacular failure gives rise to a blinking checkerboard, where every spin is surrounded by four opposite spins and flips on every time step. Avoiding these errors requires much fussy attention to algorithmic details. (My personal experience is that the first attempt is never right.)</p>
<p>Choosing spins by throwing random darts at the lattice turns out to be less susceptible to clumsy mistakes. Yet, at first glance, the random procedure seems to have hazards of its own. In particular, choosing 10,000 spins at random from a lattice of 10,000 sites does <em>not</em> guarantee that every site will be visited once. On the contrary, a few sites will be sampled six or seven times, and you can expect that 3,679 sites (that’s \(1/e \times 10{,}000)\) will not be visited at all. Doesn’t that bias distort the outcome of the simulation? No, it doesn’t. After many iterations, all the sites will get equal attention.</p>
<p>The nasty bit in all Ising simulation algorithms is updating pairs of adjacent sites, where each spin is the neighbor of the other. Which one goes first, or do you try to handle them simultaneously? The column-and-row ordering maximizes exposure to this problem: Every spin is a member of such a pair. Other sequential algorithms—for example, visiting all the black squares of a checkerboard followed by all the white squares—avoid these confrontations altogether, never considering two adjacent spins in succession. Glauber dynamics is the Goldilocks solution. Pairs of adjacent spins do turn up as successive elements in the random sequence, but they are rare events. Decisions about how to handle them have no discernible influence on the outcome.</p>
<hr/>
<p>Years ago, I had several opportunities to meet Roy Glauber. Regrettably, I failed to take advantage of them. Glauber’s office at Harvard was in the Lyman Laboratory of Physics, a small isthmus building connecting two larger halls. In the 1970s I was a frequent visitor there, pestering people to write articles for <em>Scientific American</em>. It was fertile territory; for a few years, the magazine found more authors per square meter in Lyman Lab than anywhere else in the world. But I never knocked on Glauber’s door. Perhaps it’s just as well. I was not yet equipped to appreciate what he had to say.</p>
<p>Now I can let him have the last word. This is from the introduction to the paper that introduced Glauber dynamics:</p>
<blockquote><p>If the mathematical problems of equilibrium statistical mechanics are great, they are at least relatively well-defined. The situation is quite otherwise in dealing with systems which undergo large-scale changes with time. The principles of nonequilibrium statistical mechanics remain in largest measure unformulated. While this lack persists, it may be useful to have in hand whatever precise statements can be made about the time-dependent hehavior of statistical systems, however simple they may be.</p></blockquote>
<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-15T12:30:26Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T12:30:26Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://bit-player.org" term="computing"/>
    <category scheme="http://bit-player.org" term="physics"/>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Hayes</name>
      <uri>http://bit-player.org</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://bit-player.org/feed/atom</id>
      <link href="http://bit-player.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://bit-player.org/feed/atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">An amateur's outlook on computation and mathematics</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">bit-player</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T12:32:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/15/faculty-positions-at-all-levels-at-tu-eindhoven-apply-by-march-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/15/faculty-positions-at-all-levels-at-tu-eindhoven-apply-by-march-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>faculty positions (at all levels) at TU Eindhoven (apply by March 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Mathematics and Computer Science at TU Eindhoven is looking for new faculty members to expand its academic staff. We welcome applications in all areas of computer science and at all levels, ranging from (tenure-track) assistant professor to full professor. Website: https://jobs.tue.nl/en/vacancy/faculty-members-computer-science-assistant-associate-and-full-professor-level-418993.html Email: M.T.d.Berg@tue.nl</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Mathematics and Computer Science at TU Eindhoven is looking for new faculty members to expand its academic staff. We welcome applications in all areas of computer science and at all levels, ranging from (tenure-track) assistant professor to full professor.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://jobs.tue.nl/en/vacancy/faculty-members-computer-science-assistant-associate-and-full-professor-level-418993.html">https://jobs.tue.nl/en/vacancy/faculty-members-computer-science-assistant-associate-and-full-professor-level-418993.html</a><br/>
Email: M.T.d.Berg@tue.nl</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-15T08:57:36Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T08:57:36Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:21:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04377</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04377" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Lower bounds for multilinear bounded order ABPs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547510400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ramya:C=.html">C. Ramya</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rao:B=_V=_Raghavendra.html">B. V. Raghavendra Rao</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04377">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Proving super-polynomial size lower bounds for syntactic multilinear
Algebraic Branching Programs(smABPs) computing an explicit polynomial is a
challenging problem in Algebraic Complexity Theory. The order in which
variables in $\{x_1,\ldots,x_n\}$ appear along source to sink paths in any
smABP can be viewed as a permutation in $S_n$. In this article, we consider the
following special classes of smABPs where the order of occurrence of variables
along a source to sink path is restricted:
</p>
<p>Strict circular-interval ABPs: For every subprogram the index set of
variables occurring in it is contained in some circular interval of
$\{1,\ldots,n\}$.
</p>
<p>L-ordered ABPs: There is a set of L permutations of variables such that every
source to sink path in the ABP reads variables in one of the L orders.
</p>
<p>We prove exponential lower bound for the size of a strict circular-interval
ABP computing an explicit n-variate multilinear polynomial in VP. For the same
polynomial, we show that any sum of L-ordered ABPs of small size will require
exponential ($2^{n^{\Omega(1)}}$) many summands, when $L \leq
2^{n^{1/2-\epsilon}}, \epsilon&gt;0$. At the heart of above lower bound arguments
is a new decomposition theorem for smABPs: We show that any polynomial
computable by an smABP of size S can be written as a sum of O(S) many
multilinear polynomials where each summand is a product of two polynomials in
at most 2n/3 variables computable by smABPs. As a corollary, we obtain a low
bottom fan-in version of the depth reduction by Tavenas [MFCS 2013] in the case
of smABPs. In particular, we show that a polynomial having size S smABPs can be
expressed as a sum of products of multilinear polynomials on $O(\sqrt{n})$
variables, where the total number of summands is bounded by $2^{O(\sqrt{n}\log
n \log S)}$. Additionally, we show that L-ordered ABPs can be transformed into
L-pass smABPs with a polynomial blowup in size.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:20:50Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04372</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04372" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Online Inventory Management with Application to Energy Procurement in Data Centers</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547510400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yang:Lin.html">Lin Yang</a>, Mohammad H. Hajiesmaili, Ramesh Sitaraman, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mallada:Enrique.html">Enrique Mallada</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wong:Wing_S=.html">Wing S. Wong</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wierman:Adam.html">Adam Wierman</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04372">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Motivated by the application of energy storage management in electricity
markets, this paper considers the problem of online linear programming with
inventory management constraints. Specifically, a decision maker should satisfy
some units of an asset as her demand, either form a market with time-varying
price or from her own inventory. The decision maker is presented a price in
slot-by-slot manner, and must immediately decide the purchased amount with the
current price to cover the demand or to store in inventory for covering the
future demand. The inventory has a limited capacity and its critical role is to
buy and store assets at low price and use the stored assets to cover the demand
at high price. The ultimate goal of the decision maker is to cover the demands
while minimizing the cost of buying assets from the market. We propose BatMan,
an online algorithm for simple inventory models, and BatManRate, an extended
version for the case with rate constraints. Both BatMan and BatManRate achieve
optimal competitive ratios, meaning that no other online algorithm can achieve
a better theoretical guarantee. To illustrate the results, we use the proposed
algorithms to design and evaluate energy procurement and storage management
strategies for data centers with a portfolio of energy sources including the
electric grid, local renewable generation, and energy storage systems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:22:38Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04358</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04358" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quotient Hash Tables - Efficiently Detecting Duplicates in Streaming Data</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547510400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/G=eacute=raud:R=eacute=mi.html">Rémi Géraud</a>, Marius Lombard-Platet, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Naccache:David.html">David Naccache</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04358">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This article presents the Quotient Hash Table (QHT) a new data structure for
duplicate detection in unbounded streams. QHTs stem from a corrected analysis
of streaming quotient filters (SQFs), resulting in a 33\% reduction in memory
usage for equal performance. We provide a new and thorough analysis of both
algorithms, with results of interest to other existing constructions.
</p>
<p>We also introduce an optimised version of our new data structure dubbed
Queued QHT with Duplicates (QQHTD).
</p>
<p>Finally we discuss the effect of adversarial inputs for hash-based duplicate
filters similar to QHT.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:34:42Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04237</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04237" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Topology is relevant (in the infinite-domain dichotomy conjecture for constraint satisfaction problems)</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547510400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bodirsky:Manuel.html">Manuel Bodirsky</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mottet:Antoine.html">Antoine Mottet</a>, Miroslav Olšák, Jakub Opršal, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pinsker:Michael.html">Michael Pinsker</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Willard:Ross.html">Ross Willard</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04237">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The algebraic dichotomy conjecture for Constraint Satisfaction Problems
(CSPs) of reducts of (infinite) finitely bounded homogeneous structures states
that such CSPs are polynomial-time tractable when the model-complete core of
the template has a pseudo-Siggers polymorphism, and NP-complete otherwise.
</p>
<p>One of the important questions related to this conjecture is whether,
similarly to the case of finite structures, the condition of having a
pseudo-Siggers polymorphism can be replaced by the condition of having
polymorphisms satisfying a fixed set of identities of height 1, i.e.,
identities which do not contain any nesting of functional symbols. We provide a
negative answer to this question by constructing for each non-trivial set of
height 1 identities a structure whose polymorphisms do not satisfy these
identities, but whose CSP is tractable nevertheless.
</p>
<p>An equivalent formulation of the dichotomy conjecture characterizes
tractability of the CSP via the local satisfaction of non-trivial height 1
identities by polymorphisms of the structure. We show that local satisfaction
and global satisfaction of non-trivial height 1 identities differ for
$\omega$-categorical structures with less than double exponential orbit growth,
thereby resolving one of the main open problems in the algebraic theory of such
structures.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:21:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04068</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04068" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Longest Common Subsequence on Weighted Sequences</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547510400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Evangelos Kipouridis, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tsichlas:Kostas.html">Kostas Tsichlas</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04068">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the general problem of the Longest Common Subsequence (LCS) on
weighted sequences. Weighted sequences are an extension of classical strings,
where in each position every letter of the alphabet may occur with some
probability. In this paper we provide faster algorithms and prove a series of
hardness results for more general variants of the problem. In particular, we
provide an NP-Completeness result on the general variant of the problem instead
of the log-probability version used in earlier papers, already for alphabets of
size 2. Furthermore, we design an EPTAS for bounded alphabets, which is also an
improved, compared to previous results, PTAS for unbounded alphabets. These are
in a sense optimal, since it is known that there is no FPTAS for bounded
alphabets, while we prove that there is no EPTAS for unbounded alphabets.
Finally, we provide a matching conditional (under the Exponential Time
Hypothesis) lower bound for any PTAS. As a side note, we prove that it is
sufficient to work with only one threshold in the general variant of the
problem.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04008</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.04008" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fast and Simple Deterministic Algorithms for Highly-Dynamic Networks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547510400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Censor=Hillel:Keren.html">Keren Censor-Hillel</a>, Neta Dafni, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kolobov:Victor_I=.html">Victor I. Kolobov</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Paz:Ami.html">Ami Paz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schwartzman:Gregory.html">Gregory Schwartzman</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.04008">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper provides a surprisingly simple method for obtaining fast (constant
amortized time) deterministic distributed algorithms for a highly-dynamic
setting, in which arbitrarily many edge changes may occur in each round. Among
the implications of our results are deterministic algorithms that maintain
solutions to many problems, including $(degree+1)$-coloring, maximal matching,
maximal independent set and the seemingly unrelated problem of a
2-approximation for minimum weight vertex cover (2-MWVC).
</p>
<p>These significantly improve upon prior work in various aspects, such as
having $O(1)$ amortized round complexity, using message of logarithmic size
only, handling arbitrarily many concurrent topology changes, being
deterministic, having correctness guarantees for intermediate rounds, and more.
</p>
<p>The core of our work is in defining a subclass of locally-checkable labelings
which we call locally-fixable labelings (LFLs). Very roughly speaking, these
are labelings that allow a node to fix its neighborhood based solely on their
old labels. We present a simple algorithm for LFLs with small labels, which
handles multiple edge insertions/deletions while keeping the amortized round
complexity at a small constant. We then extend it, for specific tasks, to
handle the insertion and deletion of nodes. Moreover, we show that the same
approach can also fix labeling with large labels, given that they can be made
to behave as small labels.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:34:05Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.03931</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.03931" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Joint Placement and Allocation of Virtual Network Functions with Budget and Capacity Constraints</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547510400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sallam:Gamal.html">Gamal Sallam</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Ji:Bo.html">Bo Ji</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.03931">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>With the advent of Network Function Virtualization (NFV), network services
that traditionally run on proprietary dedicated hardware can now be realized
using Virtual Network Functions (VNFs) that are hosted on general-purpose
commodity hardware. This new network paradigm offers a great flexibility to
Internet service providers (ISPs) for efficiently operating their networks
(collecting network statistics, enforcing management policies, etc.). However,
introducing NFV requires an investment to deploy VNFs at certain network nodes
(called VNF-nodes), which has to account for practical constraints such as the
deployment budget and the VNF-node capacity. To that end, it is important to
design a joint VNF-nodes placement and capacity allocation algorithm that can
maximize the total amount of network flows that are fully processed by the
VNF-nodes while respecting such practical constraints. In contrast to most
prior work that often neglects either the budget constraint or the capacity
constraint, we explicitly consider both of them. We prove that accounting for
these constraints introduces several new challenges. Specifically, we prove
that the studied problem is not only NP-hard but also non-submodular. To
address these challenges, we introduce a novel relaxation method such that the
objective function of the relaxed placement subproblem becomes submodular.
Leveraging this useful submodular property, we propose two algorithms that
achieve an approximation ratio of $\frac{1}{2}(1-1/e)$ and $\frac{1}{3}(1-1/e)$
for the original non-relaxed problem, respectively. Finally, we corroborate the
effectiveness of the proposed algorithms through extensive evaluations using
both trace-driven simulations and simulations based on synthesized network
settings.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:37:17Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.03783</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.03783" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On Huang and Wong's Algorithm for Generalized Binary Split Trees</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547510400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chrobak:Marek.html">Marek Chrobak</a>, Mordecai Golin, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Munro:J=_Ian.html">J. Ian Munro</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Young:Neal_E=.html">Neal E. Young</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.03783">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Huang and Wong [5] proposed a polynomial-time dynamic-programming algorithm
for computing optimal generalized binary split trees. We show that their
algorithm is incorrect. Thus, it remains open whether such trees can be
computed in polynomial time. Spuler [11, 12] proposed modifying Huang and
Wong's algorithm to obtain an algorithm for a different problem: computing
optimal two-way-comparison search trees. We show that the dynamic program
underlying Spuler's algorithm is not valid, in that it does not satisfy the
necessary optimal-substructure property and its proposed recurrence relation is
incorrect. It remains unknown whether the algorithm is guaranteed to compute a
correct overall solution.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:37:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.03744</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.03744" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Exponentially Faster Massively Parallel Maximal Matching</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547510400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Behnezhad:Soheil.html">Soheil Behnezhad</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hajiaghayi:MohammadTaghi.html">MohammadTaghi Hajiaghayi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Harris:David_G=.html">David G. Harris</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.03744">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The study of graph problems in the Massively Parallel Computations (MPC)
model has recently seen a burst of breakthroughs. Czumaj et al. [STOC'18],
Assadi et al. [SODA'19], and Ghaffari et al. [PODC'18], gave algorithms for
finding a $1+\varepsilon$ approximate maximum matching in $O(\log \log n)$
rounds using $\widetilde{O}(n)$ memory per machine. Despite this progress, we
still have a far more limited understanding of the central symmetry-breaking
problem of maximal matching. The round complexity of all these algorithms blows
up to $\Omega(\log n)$ in this case, which is considered inefficient. In fact,
the only known subpolylogarithmic round algorithm remains to be that of
Lattanzi et al. [SPAA'11] which undesirably requires a strictly super-linear
space of $n^{1+\Omega(1)}$ per machine.
</p>
<p>We resolve this shortcoming by providing exponentially faster algorithms for
maximal matching. Perhaps more importantly, we obtain this by analyzing an
extremely simple and natural algorithm. The algorithm edge-samples the graph,
partitions the vertices at random, and finds a greedy maximal matching within
each partition. We show that this algorithm drastically reduces the vertex
degrees. This, among some other results, leads to an $O(\log \log \Delta)$
round algorithm for maximal matching with $O(n)$ space. The space can be
further improved to mildly sublinear in $n$ by standard techniques.
</p>
<p>As an immediate corollary, we get a $2$ approximation for minimum vertex
cover in essentially the same rounds and space. This is the best possible
approximation factor under standard assumptions, culminating a long line of
research. Other corollaries include more efficient algorithms for $1 +
\varepsilon$ approximate matching and $2 + \varepsilon$ approximate weighted
matching. All these results can also be implemented in the congested clique
model within $O(\log \log \Delta)$ rounds.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:30:40Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1804.02075</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1804.02075" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Framework for Searching in Graphs in the Presence of Errors</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1547510400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dereniowski:Dariusz.html">Dariusz Dereniowski</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tiegel:Stefan.html">Stefan Tiegel</a>, Przemysław Uznański, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wolleb=Graf:Daniel.html">Daniel Wolleb-Graf</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1804.02075">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the problem of searching for an unknown target vertex $t$ in a
(possibly edge-weighted) graph. Each \emph{vertex-query} points to a vertex $v$
and the response either admits $v$ is the target or provides any neighbor
$s\not=v$ that lies on a shortest path from $v$ to $t$. This model has been
introduced for trees by Onak and Parys [FOCS 2006] and for general graphs by
Emamjomeh-Zadeh et al. [STOC 2016]. In the latter, the authors provide
algorithms for the error-less case and for the independent noise model (where
each query independently receives an erroneous answer with known probability
$p&lt;1/2$ and a correct one with probability $1-p$).
</p>
<p>We study this problem in both adversarial errors and independent noise
models. First, we show an algorithm that needs $\frac{\log_2 n}{1 - H(r)}$
queries against \emph{adversarial} errors, where adversary is bounded with its
rate of errors by a known constant $r&lt;1/2$. Our algorithm is in fact a
simplification of previous work, and our refinement lies in invoking
amortization argument. We then show that our algorithm coupled with Chernoff
bound argument leads to an algorithm for independent noise that is simpler and
with a query complexity that is both simpler and asymptotically better to one
of Emamjomeh-Zadeh et al. [STOC 2016].
</p>
<p>Our approach has a wide range of applications. First, it improves and
simplifies Robust Interactive Learning framework proposed by Emamjomeh-Zadeh et
al. [NIPS 2017]. Secondly, performing analogous analysis for
\emph{edge-queries} (where query to edge $e$ returns its endpoint that is
closer to target) we actually recover (as a special case) noisy binary search
algorithm that is asymptotically optimal, matching the complexity of Feige et
al. [SIAM J. Comput. 1994]. Thirdly, we improve and simplify upon existing
algorithm for searching of \emph{unbounded} domains due to Aslam and Dhagat
[STOC 1991].
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:30:15Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/14/summer-school-on-geometric-and-algebraic-combinatorics/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/14/summer-school-on-geometric-and-algebraic-combinatorics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Summer School on Geometric and Algebraic Combinatorics</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">June 17-28, 2019 Paris, France http://gac-school.imj-prg.fr/ Submission deadline: March 27, 2019 Registration deadline: March 27, 2019 This two-week summer school will present an overview of a selection of topics in the crossroads between geometry, algebra, and combinatorics. It will consist of four one-week mini-courses given by leading experts, complemented with supervised exercise sessions, lectures by … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/14/summer-school-on-geometric-and-algebraic-combinatorics/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Summer School on Geometric and Algebraic Combinatorics</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-14T14:09:57Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-14T14:09:57Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:22:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-6137751989330501107</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/6137751989330501107/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=6137751989330501107" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/6137751989330501107" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/6137751989330501107" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2019/01/one-postdoc-position-available-at.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>One postdoc position available at Reykjavik University</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div style="background-color: white; color: #222222; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small; font-style: normal; font-weight: 400; letter-spacing: normal; text-align: center; text-indent: 0px; white-space: normal;"><b><br class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-Apple-interchange-newline"/>Open Problems in the Equational Logic of Processes</b></div><span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-m_2410624989205033738im" style="background-color: white; color: #222222; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: x-small; font-style: normal; font-weight: 400; letter-spacing: normal; text-align: start; text-indent: 0px; white-space: normal;"><div style="text-align: center;"><br/><b>School of Computer Science, <span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-il">Reykjavik</span> <span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-il">University</span></b><br/><br/><b>One Postdoc</b><b> </b><b>Position</b></div><br/>Applications are invited for one post-doctoral position at the School of Computer Science, <span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-il">Reykjavik</span> <span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-il">University</span>.   The position is part of a three-year research project funded by the  Icelandic Research Fund, under the direction of Luca Aceto (Gran Sasso  Science Institute and <span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-il">Reykjavik</span> <span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-il">University</span>) <span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-il"/>and Anna Ingolfsdottir (<span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-il">Reykjavik</span> <span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-il">University</span>) in cooperation with Bas Luttik (TU Eindhoven) and Alexandra Silva (University C<span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-m_2410624989205033738im">ollege London)</span>.  The overarching goal of this project is to solve some of the  challenging open problems in the equational axiomatization of  behavioural equivalences over process calculi. Interested applicants can  contact Luca Aceto (email: <a href="mailto:luca@ru.is" style="color: #1155cc;" target="_blank">luca@ru.is</a>) for further details on the research proposal.</span><span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-m_2410624989205033738im" style="background-color: white; color: #222222; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: x-small; font-style: normal; font-weight: 400; letter-spacing: normal; text-align: start; text-indent: 0px; white-space: normal;"/><div><span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-m_2410624989205033738im"><div style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small;"><br/>The  successful candidate will benefit from, and contribute to, the research  environment at the Icelandic Centre of Excellence in Theoretical  Computer Science (ICE-TCS). For information about ICE-TCS and its  activities, see<br/><br/><div style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.icetcs.ru.is/" style="color: #1155cc;" target="_blank">http://www.icetcs.ru.is/</a>.</div></div><div style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small;">Moreover,  she/he will cooperate with Bas Luttik and Alexandra Silva  during the  project work and will benefit from the interaction with their research  groups at TU Eindhoven and University College London. The postdoc will  also have a chance to interact with Clemens Grabmayer and the CS group  at the Gran Sasso Science Institute (<a href="http://cs.gssi.it/" style="color: #1155cc;" target="_blank">http://cs.gssi.it/</a>), L'Aquila, Italy. </div><br/><b style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small;">Qualification requirements</b><span style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: x-small;"><span lang="IS" style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 10pt;"/><b><span lang="IS" style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 10pt;"/></b><b><span lang="IS" style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 10pt;"/></b><span lang="IS" style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 10pt;"><br/></span></span>Applicants  for the postdoctoral position should have, or be about to hold, a PhD  degree in Computer Science or closely related fields. Previous knowledge  of at least one of concurrency theory, process calculi, (structural)  operational semantics and logic in computer science is highly desirable.</span></div><div style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small;"><span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-m_2410624989205033738im"><br/><b>Remuneration</b><span><span lang="IS" style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 10pt;"><br/></span></span>The wage for the postdoctoral position is </span>530,000 ISK (roughly 3,830  € at the present exchange rate) per month before taxes. (See <a href="http://payroll.is/en/" target="_blank">http://payroll.is/en/</a> for information on what the wage will be after taxes.)<span> </span>The position is  for two years, starting as soon as possible, and is renewable for  another year, based on good performance and mutual satisfaction.</div><div><span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-m_2410624989205033738im"><br/><b style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small;">Application details</b><br/><br/>Interested  applicants should send their CV, including a list of publications, in  PDF to all the addresses below, together with a statement outlining  their suitability for the project and the names of at least two  referees.<br/><br/>Luca Aceto<br/>email: <a href="mailto:luca@ru.is" style="color: #1155cc; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small;" target="_blank">luca@ru.is</a><br/><br/>Anna Ingolfsdottir<br/>email: <a href="mailto:annai@ru.is" style="color: #1155cc; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small;" target="_blank">annai@ru.is</a></span></div><div style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small;"><br/></div><div style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: small;"><span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-m_2410624989205033738im"/></div><span class="m_1631593900696185630gmail-m_5141331556671273973gmail-m_-7043862561460987118gmail-m_2410624989205033738im">We  will start reviewing applications as soon as they arrive and will  continue to accept applications until the position is filled. We  strongly encourage interested applicants to send their applications as  soon as possible<span> and no later than 8 February 2019. </span></span></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-14T10:10:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-14T10:10:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2019-01-14T12:54:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/004</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/004" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-004 |  UG-hardness to NP-hardness by Losing Half | 

	Amey Bhangale, 

	Subhash Khot</title>
    <summary>The $2$-to-$2$ Games Theorem of [KMS-1, DKKMS-1, DKKMS-2, KMS-2] implies that it is NP-hard to distinguish between Unique Games instances with assignment satisfying at least  $(\frac{1}{2}-\varepsilon)$ fraction of the constraints $vs.$ no assignment satisfying more than $\varepsilon$ fraction of the constraints, for every constant $\varepsilon&gt;0$. We show that the reduction can be transformed in a non-trivial way to give a stronger guarantee in the completeness case: For at least $(\frac{1}{2}-\varepsilon)$ fraction of the vertices on one side, all the constraints associated with them in the Unique Games instance can be satisfied. 


We use this guarantee to convert the known UG-hardness results to NP-hardness. We show:

1. Tight inapproximability of approximating independent sets in a degree $d$ graphs within a factor of $\Omega\left(\frac{d}{\log^2 d}\right)$, where $d$ is a constant. 
2. NP-hardness of approximate Maximum Acyclic Subgraph problem within a factor of $\frac{2}{3}+\varepsilon$, improving the previous ratio of $\frac{14}{15}+\varepsilon$ by Austrin et al.[AMW15].
3. For any predicate $P^{-1}(1) \subseteq [q]^k$ supporting balanced pairwise independent distribution, given a $P$-CSP instance with value at least $\frac{1}{2}-\varepsilon$, it is NP-hard to satisfy more than $\frac{|P^{-1}(1)|}{q^k}+\varepsilon$ fraction of constraints.</summary>
    <updated>2019-01-13T07:45:37Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-13T07:45:37Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T09:21:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=15570</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/01/13/jean-bourgain-1954-2018-and-michael-atiyah-1929-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Jean Bourgain 1954–2018 and Michael Atiyah 1929–2019</title>
    <summary>A tribute to two premier analysts From Flanders Today src1 and Ryle Trust Lecture src2 Baron Jean Bourgain and Sir Michael Atiyah passed away within the past three weeks. They became mathematical nobility by winning the Fields Medal, Atiyah in 1966 and Bourgain in 1994. Bourgain was created Baron by King Philippe of Belgium in […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>A tribute to two premier analysts</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/01/bourgainatiyah.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-15571" height="165" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/01/bourgainatiyah.png?w=240&amp;h=165" width="240"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">From Flanders Today <a href="http://www.flanderstoday.eu/innovation/face-flanders-jean-bourgain">src1</a> and Ryle Trust Lecture <a href="http://www.sgr.org.uk/events/islam-and-west-personal-perspective">src2</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Baron Jean Bourgain and Sir Michael Atiyah passed away within the past three weeks. They became mathematical nobility by winning the Fields Medal, Atiyah in 1966 and Bourgain in 1994. Bourgain was created Baron by King Philippe of Belgium in 2015. Atiyah’s knighthood did not confer nobility, but he held the dynastic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_Merit">Order of Merit</a>, which is limited to 24 living members and has had fewer than 200 total since its inception in 1902. Atiyah had been #2 by length of tenure after Prince Philip and ahead of Prince Charles. </p>
<p>
Today we discuss how they ennobled mathematics by their wide contributions.</p>
<p>
Bourgain was affiliated to IAS by the IBM John von Neumann Professorship. He had been battling cancer for a long time. Here is the middle section of the coat of arms he created for his 2015 investiture:</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/01/bourgainarmsmiddle.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-15581" height="165" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/01/bourgainarmsmiddle.png?w=300&amp;h=165" width="300"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Detail from IAS <a href="https://www.ias.edu/ideas/jean-bourgain%E2%80%99s-coat-arms">source</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
The shield shows the beginning of an Apollonian circle <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apollonian_gasket">packing</a>, in which every radius is the reciprocal of an integer. This property continues as circles are recursively inscribed in the curvilinear regions—see this 2000 <a href="http://www.math.ucsd.edu/~ronspubs/03_02_appolonian.pdf">survey</a> for a proof. To quote Bourgain’s <a href="https://www.ias.edu/ideas/jean-bourgain's-coat-arms">words</a> accompanying his design:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> The theory of these [packings] is today a rich mathematical research area, at the interface of hyperbolic geometry, dynamics, and number theory. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Bourgain’s affinity to topics we hold dear in computing theory is shown by this 2009 <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xMWlv_1DqyM">talk</a> titled, “The Search for Randomness.” It covers not only PRNGs and crypto but also expander graphs and <em>succinctness</em> in quantum computing. He has been hailed for diversity in other mathematical areas and editorships of many journals. We will talk about a problem in analysis which he helped solve not by analytical means but by connecting the problem to additive combinatorics.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> From Analysis to Combinatorics </h2><p/>
<p>
</p><p>
Sōichi Kakeya posed the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kakeya_set">problem</a> of the minimum size of a subset of <img alt="{\mathbb{R}^{2}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5E%7B2%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{R}^{2}}"/> in which a unit-length needle can be rotated through 360 degrees. Abram Besicovitch showed in 1928 that such sets can have Lebesgue measure <img alt="{\epsilon}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon}"/> for any <img alt="{\epsilon &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon &gt; 0}"/>. He had already shown that one can achieve measure zero with a weaker property, which he had used to show a strong failure of Fubini’s theorem for Riemann integrals:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> For all <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/> there is a measure-zero subset of <img alt="{\mathbb{R}^d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5Ed%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{R}^d}"/> that contains a unit line segment in every direction. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The surprise to many of us is that such strange sets would have important further consequences in analysis. A 2008 <a href="http://www.ams.org/journals/bull/2008-45-01/S0273-0979-07-01189-5/S0273-0979-07-01189-5.pdf">survey</a> in the <em>AMS Bulletin</em> by Izabella Łaba, titled “From Harmonic Analysis to Arithmetic Combinatorics,” brings out breakthrough contributions by Bourgain to conjectures and problems that involve further properties of these sets, which seem to retain Kakeya’s name: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <b>Conjecture:</b> A Kakeya set in <img alt="{R^{d}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR%5E%7Bd%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R^{d}}"/> must have Hausdorff dimension <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This and the formally weaker conjecture that the set must have Minkowski dimension <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/> are proved in <img alt="{\mathbb{R}^2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5E2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{R}^2}"/> but open for all <img alt="{d \geq 3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd+%5Cgeq+3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d \geq 3}"/>. Bourgain first proved that the <em>restriction conjecture</em> of Elias Stein, which is about extensions of the Fourier transform from certain subspaces of functions from <img alt="{\mathbb{R}^d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5Ed%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{R}^d}"/> to <img alt="{\mathbb{C}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BC%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{C}}"/> to operators from <img alt="{L^q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%5Eq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L^q}"/> to <img alt="{L^p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%5Ep%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L^p}"/> functions on <img alt="{\mathbb{R}^d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5Ed%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{R}^d}"/>, implies the Kakeya conjecture. It is likewise open for <img alt="{d,p \geq 3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%2Cp+%5Cgeq+3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d,p \geq 3}"/>. As Łaba writes, associated estimates “with <img alt="{p &gt; 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp+%3E+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p &gt; 2}"/> require deeper geometrical information, and this is where we find Kakeya sets lurking under the surface.” </p>
<p>
What Bourgain showed is that the restriction estimates place constraints on sets of lower Hausdorff dimension that force them to align “tubes” along discrete directions that can be approximated via integer lattices. This led to the following “key lemma”:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Lemma 1</b> <em> Consider subsets <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S}"/> of <img alt="{A \times B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA+%5Ctimes+B%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A \times B}"/>, where <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> and <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> are finite subsets of <img alt="{\mathbb{Z}^d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Ed%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{Z}^d}"/>, and define </em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  S^{+} = \{a+b: (a,b) \in S\}, \qquad S^{-} = \{a - b: (a,b) \in S\}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++S%5E%7B%2B%7D+%3D+%5C%7Ba%2Bb%3A+%28a%2Cb%29+%5Cin+S%5C%7D%2C+%5Cqquad+S%5E%7B-%7D+%3D+%5C%7Ba+-+b%3A+%28a%2Cb%29+%5Cin+S%5C%7D.+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  S^{+} = \{a+b: (a,b) \in S\}, \qquad S^{-} = \{a - b: (a,b) \in S\}. "/></p>
</em><p><em>For every <img alt="{C &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{C &gt; 0}"/> there is <img alt="{C' &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC%27+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{C' &gt; 0}"/> such that whenever <img alt="{|S^{+}| \leq Cn}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CS%5E%7B%2B%7D%7C+%5Cleq+Cn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{|S^{+}| \leq Cn}"/>, where <img alt="{n = \max\{|A|,|B|\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn+%3D+%5Cmax%5C%7B%7CA%7C%2C%7CB%7C%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n = \max\{|A|,|B|\}}"/>, we have <img alt="{|S^{-}| \leq C'n^{2 - \frac{1}{13}}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CS%5E%7B-%7D%7C+%5Cleq+C%27n%5E%7B2+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B13%7D%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{|S^{-}| \leq C'n^{2 - \frac{1}{13}}}"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
To quote Łaba: “Bourgain’s approach, however, provided a way out. Effectively, it said that our hypothetical set would have <em>structure</em>, to the extent that many of its lines would have to be parallel instead of pointing in different directions. <em>Not a Kakeya set, after all.</em>” She further says:</p>
<p>
</p><blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Bourgain’s argument was, to this author’s knowledge, the first application of additive number theory to Euclidean harmonic analysis. It was significant, not only because it improved Kakeya bounds, but perhaps even more so because it introduced many harmonic analysts to additive number theory, including [Terence] Tao who contributed so much to the subject later on, and jump-started interaction and communication between the two communities. The Green-Tao theorem [on primes] and many other developments might have never happened, were it not for Bourgain’s brilliant leap of thought in 1998. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Among <a href="https://www.ias.edu/press-releases/2019/jean-bourgain-obituary">many</a> <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/01/02/jean/">sources</a>, note this <a href="http://www.math.ucsd.edu/~fan/reading/ross/">seminar</a> sponsored by Fan Chung and links from Tao’s own memorial <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2018/12/29/jean-bourgain/">post</a>.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Michael Atiyah </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Michael Atiyah was also much more than an analyst—indeed, he was first a topologist and algebraic geometer. He was also a theoretical physicist. Besides all these scientific hats, he engaged with society at large. After heading Britain’s Royal Society from 1990 to 1995, he became president of the <a href="https://pugwash.org/">Pugwash</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pugwash_Conferences_on_Science_and_World_Affairs">Conferences</a> on Science and World Affairs. This organization was founded by Joseph Rotblat and Bertrand Russell in the 1950s to avert nuclear war and misuse of science, and won the 1995 Nobel Peace Prize.</p>
<p>
The “misuse of science” aspect comes out separately in Atiyah’s 1999 <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1127049/">article</a> in the <em>British Medical Journal</em> titled, “Science for evil: the scientist’s dilemma.” It lays out a wider scope of ethical and procedural concerns than the original anti-war purpose. This is furthered in his 1999 <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/304691079_The_Social_Responsibility_of_Scientists">book</a> <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1057/9780230508606_15">chapter</a>, “The Social Responsibility of Scientists,” which laid out six points including:</p>
<ul>
<li>
First there is the argument of moral responsibility. If you create something you should be concerned with its consequences. This should apply as much to making scientific discoveries as to having children. <p/>
</li><li>
Scientists will understand the technical problems better than the average politician or citizen and knowledge brings responsibility. <p/>
</li><li>
[T]here is need to prevent a public backlash against science. Self-interest requires that scientists must be fully involved in public debate and must not be seen as “enemies of the people.”
</li></ul>
<p>
As he says in its abstract:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> In my own case, after many years of quiet mathematical research, working out of the limelight, a major change occurred when unexpectedly I found myself president of the Royal Society, in a very public position, and expected to act as a general spokesman for the whole of science. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Within physics and mathematics, he also ventured into a debate that comes closer to the theory-as-social-process topic we <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2011/12/21/proofs-proofs-and-proofs/">have</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2010/01/11/why-do-we-need-cyber-security/">discussed</a> on this blog. In 1994 he led a collection of community <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/math/9404229">responses</a> to a 1993 <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/math/9307227">article</a> by Arthur Jaffe and Frank Quinn that began with the question, “Is speculative mathematics dangerous?” Atiyah replied by saying he agreed with many of their points, especially the need to distinguish between results based on rigorous proofs and heuristic arguments,</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> …But if mathematics is to rejuvenate itself and break exciting new ground it will have to allow for the exploration of new ideas and techniques which, in their creative phase, are likely to be as dubious as in some of the great eras of the past. …[I]n the early stages of new developments, we must be prepared to act in more buccaneering style. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Now we cannot help recalling his <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/17NBICP6OcUSucrXKNWvzLmrQpfUrEKuY/view">claim</a> last September of heuristic arguments that will build a proof of the Riemann Hypothesis, which we <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/09/26/reading-into-atiyahs-proof/">covered</a> in <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/09/23/preview-of-the-atiyah-talk/">several</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/09/21/the-specter-of-simpler-proofs/">posts</a>. As we stated in our New Year’s <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/01/06/predictions-for-2019/">post</a>, nothing more of substance has come to our attention. We do not know how much more work was done on the promised longer paper. We will move toward discussing briefly how his most famous work is starting to matter in algorithms and complexity.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Indexes and Invariants </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We will not try to go into even as much detail as we did for Kakeya sets about Atiyah’s signature contributions to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Topological_K-theory">topological</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K-theory">K-theory</a>, physical <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Atiyah#Gauge_theory_(1977-1985)">gauge</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gauge_theory">theory</a>, his celebrated <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atiyah-Singer_index_theorem">index theorem</a> with Isadore Singer, and much else. But we can evoke reasons for us to be interested in the last. We start with the simple statement from the <a href="http://www.abelprize.no/c53865/binfil/download.php?tid=53804">essay</a> by John Rognes of Oslo that accompanied the 2004 Abel Prize award to Atiyah and Singer:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 2</b> <em> Let <img alt="{P(f) = 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP%28f%29+%3D+0%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P(f) = 0}"/> be a system of differential equations. Then </em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \text{analytical index}(P) = \text{topological index}(P). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Ctext%7Banalytical+index%7D%28P%29+%3D+%5Ctext%7Btopological+index%7D%28P%29.+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \text{analytical index}(P) = \text{topological index}(P). "/></p>
</em><p><em/>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Here the <em>analytical index</em> equals the dimension <img alt="{d_k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd_k%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d_k}"/> of the kernel of <img alt="{P}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P}"/> minus the dimension <img alt="{d_c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd_c%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d_c}"/> of the co-kernel of <img alt="{P}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P}"/>, which (again quoting Rognes) “is equal to the number of parameters needed to describe all the solutions of the equation, minus the number of relations there are between the expressions <img alt="{P(f)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP%28f%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P(f)}"/>.” The <em>topological index</em> has a longer laundry list of items in its definition, but the point is, <em>those items are usually all easily calculable</em>. It is further remarkable that in many cases we can get <img alt="{d_k - d_c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd_k+-+d_c%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d_k - d_c}"/> without knowing how to compute <img alt="{d_k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd_k%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d_k}"/> and <img alt="{d_c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd_c%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d_c}"/> individually. The New York Times <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/11/obituaries/michael-atiyah-dead.html">obituary</a> quotes Atiyah from 2015:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> It’s a bit of black magic to figure things out about differential equations even though you can’t solve them. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
One thing it helps figure out is satisfiability. Besides cases where knowing the number of solutions does help in finding them, there are many theorems that needed only information about the number and the parameterization. </p>
<p>
We have an analogous situation in complexity theory with the lower bound theorem of Walter Baur and Volker Strassen, which we covered in this <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2010/08/19/projections-can-be-tricky/">post</a>: The number of multiplication gates needed to compute an arithmetical function <img alt="{f}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f}"/> is bounded below by a known constant times the log-base-2 of the maximum number of solutions to a system formed from the partial derivatives of <img alt="{f}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f}"/> and a certain number of linear equations, over cases where that number is finite. Furthermore, both theorems front on algebraic geometry and geometric invariant theory, whose rapid ascent in our field was witnessed by a workshop at IAS that we <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/06/06/princeton-is-invariant/">covered</a> last June. That workshop mentioned not only Atiyah but also the further work in algebraic geometry by his student Frances Kirwan, who was contemporaneous with Ken while at Oxford. Thus we may see more of the kind of connections in which Atiyah delighted, as noted in <a href="https://www.maths.ox.ac.uk/node/31190">current</a> <a href="https://www.heidelberg-laureate-forum.org/blog/laureate/sir-michael-francis-atiyah/">tributes</a> and the “<a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/04/mathematical-matchmaker-michael-atiyah-dreams-quantum-union/">matchmaker</a>” label which was <a href="https://www.facebook.com/ICM2018/posts/1023543974470240">promoted</a> at last August’s ICM.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Our condolences go out to their families and colleagues.</p>
<p>
[more tribute links]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-13T06:11:28Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-13T06:11:28Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="index theorem"/>
    <category term="Jean Bourgain"/>
    <category term="Kakeya sets"/>
    <category term="memorial"/>
    <category term="Michael Atiyah"/>
    <category term="science and society"/>
    <category term="sphere packings"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:21:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/11/postdoc-position-at-duke-university-apply-by-february-28-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/11/postdoc-position-at-duke-university-apply-by-february-28-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc position at Duke University (apply by February 28, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The algorithms and computational economics research groups at Duke University invite applications for one or potentially more postdoctoral positions, starting on or after July 1, 2019. The AcademicJobsOnline URL has full details as well as online application form. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/13114 Email: kamesh@cs.duke.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The algorithms and computational economics research groups at Duke University invite applications for one or potentially more postdoctoral positions, starting on or after July 1, 2019. The AcademicJobsOnline URL has full details as well as online application form.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/13114">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/13114</a><br/>
Email: kamesh@cs.duke.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-11T20:32:25Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-11T20:32:25Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:21:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:typepad.com,2003:post-6a00d83452383469e2022ad3cdb3fe200b</id>
    <link href="https://3dpancakes.typepad.com/ernie/2019/01/im-a-bit-disappointed-that-michael-describes-al-nayrizis-and-perigals-families-of-simple-perfect-squarings-of-the-fla.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://3dpancakes.typepad.com/ernie/2019/01/im-a-bit-disappointed-that-michael-describes-al-nayrizis-and-perigals-families-of-simple-perfect-squarings-of-the-fla.html" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <title/>
    <summary>I'm a bit disappointed that Michael describes al-Nayrizi's and Perigal's (families of) simple perfect squarings of the (flat square) torus as different. They are, in fact, identical—not just “congruent” or “equivalent” or “isomorphic”, but actually indistinguishable. They only look different...</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div><p><br/>
</p><p class="asset asset-video"><br/>
	<br/>
</p><br/>
I'm a bit disappointed that Michael describes al-Nayrizi's and Perigal's (families of) simple perfect squarings of the (flat square) torus as different. They are, in fact, identical—not just “congruent” or “equivalent” or “isomorphic”, but actually indistinguishable. They only look different because al-Nayrizi and Perigal cut the torus into a square in two different ways.<p/></div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-11T13:13:51Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-11T13:13:51Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Erickson</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:typepad.com,2003:weblog-6686</id>
      <link href="https://3dpancakes.typepad.com/ernie/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://3dpancakes.typepad.com/ernie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Let Σ be a combinatorial surface with n vertices, genus g, and b boundaries.  Amen.</subtitle>
      <title>Ernie's 3D Pancakes</title>
      <updated>2019-01-11T13:13:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3373</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/01/11/sigecom-dissertation-award-call/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>SIGecom Dissertation Award call</title>
    <summary>Please consider nominating graduating Ph.D. students for the SIGecom Dissertation Award.  If you are a graduating student, consider asking your adviser or other senior mentor to nominate you. Nominations are due on February 28, 2019.  This award is given to a student who defended a thesis in 2018.  It is a prestigious award and is […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div>Please consider nominating graduating Ph.D. students for the SIGecom Dissertation Award.  If you are a graduating student, consider asking your adviser or other senior mentor to nominate you.</div>
<div/>
<div>Nominations are due on February 28, 2019.  This award is given to a student who defended a thesis in 2018.  It is a prestigious award and is accompanied by a $1500 prize.  In the past, the grand prize has been awarded to:</div>
<div/>
<div>2017: Aviad Rubinstein, “Hardness of Approximation Between P and NP”</div>
<div>2016: Peng Shi, “Prediction and Optimization in School Choice”</div>
<div>2015: Inbal Talgam-Cohen, “Robust Market Design: Information and Computation “</div>
<div>2014: S. Matthew Weinberg, “Algorithms for Strategic Agents”</div>
<div>2013: Balasubramanian Sivan, “Prior Robust Optimization”</div>
<div/>
<div>And the award has had seven runner-ups: Rachel Cummings, Christos Tzamos, Bo Waggoner, James Wright, Xi (Alice) Gao, Yang Cai, and Sigal Oren.  You can find detailed information about the nomination process at: <a href="http://www.sigecom.org/awardd.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">http://www.sigecom.org/awardd.html</a>. We look forward to reading your nominations!</div>
<div/>
<div>Your Award Committee,</div>
<div/>
<div>Renato Paes Leme</div>
<div>Aaron Roth (Chair)</div>
<div>Inbal Talgam-Cohen</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-11T03:27:39Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-11T03:27:39Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Kevin Leyton-Brown</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:20:56Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-25562705.post-2366077530752985091</id>
    <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/feeds/2366077530752985091/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=25562705&amp;postID=2366077530752985091" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default/2366077530752985091" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default/2366077530752985091" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/2019/01/dear-all-please-consider-nominating.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>2019 SIGecom Dissertation Award: Call for Nominations</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div class="MsoNormal" style="margin: 0px;">Dear all,<br/><br/>Please consider nominating graduating Ph.D. students for the SIGecom Dissertation Award.  If you are a graduating student, consider asking your adviser or other senior mentor to nominate you.<br/><br/>Nominations are due on February 28, 2019.  This award is given to a student who defended a thesis in 2018.  It is a prestigious award and is accompanied by a $1500 prize.  In the past, the grand prize has been awarded to:<br/><br/>2017: Aviad Rubinstein, "Hardness of Approximation Between P and NP"<br/>2016: Peng Shi, "Prediction and Optimization in School Choice"<br/>2015: Inbal Talgam-Cohen, "Robust Market Design: Information and Computation "<br/>2014: S. Matthew Weinberg, "Algorithms for Strategic Agents"<br/>2013: Balasubramanian Sivan, "Prior Robust Optimization"<br/><br/><br/>And the award has had seven runner-ups: Rachel Cummings, Christos Tzamos, Bo Waggoner, James Wright, Xi (Alice) Gao, Yang Cai, and Sigal Oren.  You can find detailed information about the nomination process at: <a href="http://www.sigecom.org/awardd.html">http://www.sigecom.org/awardd.html</a>. We look forward to reading your nominations!<br/><br/><br/>Your Award Committee,<br/><b><br/></b><b>Renato Paes Leme</b><br/><b>Aaron Roth</b> (Chair)<br/><b>Inbal Talgam-Cohen</b></div><div class="m_-6389343170732676329gmail-adL" style="background-color: white; color: #222222; font-size: small;"><span class="m_-6389343170732676329gmail-im" style="color: #500050;"/><br/><div style="font-family: arial, helvetica, sans-serif;"/></div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-10T20:26:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-10T20:26:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Aaron Roth</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>https://plus.google.com/111805394598997130229</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-25562705</id>
      <category term="game theory"/>
      <category term="news"/>
      <author>
        <name>Aaron Roth</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      </author>
      <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Adventures in Computation</title>
      <updated>2019-01-14T10:58:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204.post-4590649641895956020</id>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/4590649641895956020/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=4590649641895956020" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/4590649641895956020" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/4590649641895956020" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2019/01/analco-sosa-soda-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>ANALCO, SOSA, SODA post</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I spent the last few days at SODA-ANALCO-ALENEX-SOSA in San Diego.  (Nice location choice, I'd say!)  Here's some news.<br/><br/>This will be the last ANALCO (Analytic Algorithms and Combinatorics).  Apparently submissions have been decreasing, so they've decided it will halt and the work on these topics will go into SODA and other conferences.  I'm not sure how to think of it -- I think we as a community have far too many conferences/workshops generally, but I think the SODA model of having ANALCO and ALENEX (and now SOSA, I imagine) folded in cleanly into the main conference is an excellent model.  I also like the ANALCO topics.  But I can understand the time may have come to do something else.  Thanks to everyone who worked to organize ANALCO and keep it going these many years.<br/><br/>It looks like SOSA (Symposium on Simplicity in Algorithms) will be taking its place in the SODA lineup.  I co-chaired the symposium with Jeremy Fineman this year, the second for the symposium.  I was surprised by the high quality of the submissions, and was then further surprised by the strong turnout at SODA.  The room was quite full for the Tuesday afternoon sessions, and there were easily 75+ people at several of the talks.  I do think there's a need for SOSA -- no other workshop/conference hits the theme of simplicity in our area, and it's a really nice fit with the rest of SODA.  I'm hoping it will last, and in particular that they'll continue to have a good number of high quality submissions, but that depends on all of you.  Ideally, there will be a positive feedback loop here -- now that there's a good home for this type of work (besides notes on the arxiv), people will be more inclined to write up and submit things to SOSA.  For Tuesday's talks, I'll call out Josh Alman's great presentation on "An Illuminating Algorithm for the Light Bulb Problem" as my favorite for the day.<br/><br/>With ANALCO exiting, though, I think there's more room for additional satellite events at SODA, so hopefully some people will get creative.<br/><br/>If I had thought about it I should have live-blogged the business meeting.  I'd say as highlights, first, Sandy Irani presented the report of the ad hoc committee to combat harassment and discrimination in the theory of computing community.   (See <a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~irani/safetoc.html">here</a> for the report.)  There was an overwhelming vote to adopt their recommendations going forward.  It's good to see progress in addressing these community concerns.  Second, Shuchi Chawla will be the next PC chair, and she brought forward a plan to have SODA PC members be allowed to submit papers (with a higher bar) that was voted on favorably as well.<br/><br/>I suppose the last note is that Jon Kleinberg's invited talk was the conference highlight you expect a Jon Kleinberg talk to be, with interesting results and models related to fairness and implicit bias.<br/><br/>Thanks to SIAM and all the organizers for their hard work.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-09T22:25:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-09T22:25:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/02161161032642563814</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204</id>
      <category term="conferences"/>
      <category term="research"/>
      <category term="society"/>
      <category term="algorithms"/>
      <category term="administration"/>
      <category term="teaching"/>
      <category term="Harvard"/>
      <category term="papers"/>
      <category term="graduate students"/>
      <category term="funding"/>
      <category term="talks"/>
      <category term="blogs"/>
      <category term="codes"/>
      <category term="jobs"/>
      <category term="reviews"/>
      <category term="personal"/>
      <category term="travel"/>
      <category term="undergraduate students"/>
      <category term="books"/>
      <category term="open problems"/>
      <category term="PCs"/>
      <category term="consulting"/>
      <category term="randomness"/>
      <category term="CCC"/>
      <category term="blog book project"/>
      <category term="research labs"/>
      <category term="ISIT"/>
      <category term="tenure"/>
      <category term="comments"/>
      <category term="recommendations"/>
      <category term="outreach"/>
      <category term="students"/>
      <author>
        <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06738274256402616703</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">My take on computer science -- <br/> 
algorithms, networking, information theory -- <br/> 
and related items.</div>
      </subtitle>
      <title>My Biased Coin</title>
      <updated>2019-01-09T22:25:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/09/mixed-integer-nonlinear-optimization-meets-data-science/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/09/mixed-integer-nonlinear-optimization-meets-data-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Mixed-Integer Nonlinear Optimization meets Data Science</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">June 25, 2018 – June 28, 2019 Ischia, Italy http://www.iasi.cnr.it/minoa/big-data-school/ CNR-IASI, as part of the MINOA project, announces the school for PhD students and post-docs on the theme Mixed Integer Non linear Optimization meets Data Science. The school will cover the following topics: Deep learning for AI Clustering for Big Data Machine Learning for Combinatorial … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/09/mixed-integer-nonlinear-optimization-meets-data-science/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Mixed-Integer Nonlinear Optimization meets Data Science</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-09T20:51:39Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-09T20:51:39Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:22:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/?p=5374</id>
    <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/2019/01/09/the-baruch-distinguished-mathematics-lecture-series/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Baruch Distinguished Mathematics Lecture Series</title>
    <summary>I am happy to announce the beginning of the Baruch Distinguished Mathematics Lecture Series. In this series we will bring established mathematicians to give talks to a general mathematical audience. Our first Distinguished Lecture, by Bjorn Poonen, will be “Undecidability in Number Theory”. Click here for the full details. The talk is open to everyone, […]</summary>
    <updated>2019-01-09T20:43:09Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-09T20:43:09Z</published>
    <category term="Math events"/>
    <author>
      <name>Adam Sheffer</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Discrete geometry and other typos</subtitle>
      <title>Some Plane Truths</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:22:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/?p=1350</id>
    <link href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/01/09/nemirovskis-acceleration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Nemirovski’s acceleration</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I will describe here the very first (to my knowledge) acceleration algorithm for smooth convex optimization, which is due to Arkadi Nemirovski (dating back to the end of the 70’s). The algorithm relies on a -dimensional plane-search subroutine (which, in … <a href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/01/09/nemirovskis-acceleration/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I will describe here the very first (to my knowledge) acceleration algorithm for smooth convex optimization, which is due to <a class="liinternal" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arkadi_Nemirovski" rel="nofollow">Arkadi Nemirovski</a> (dating back to the end of the 70’s). The algorithm relies on a <img alt="2" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="12" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-bc2da46d9824359f6ac8d33c5fb882dd_l3.png?resize=8%2C12&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="8"/>-dimensional plane-search subroutine (which, in theory, can be implemented in <img alt="\log(1/\epsilon)" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="19" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-38bfa3c1131fbae41cb358b8b685dc56_l3.png?resize=61%2C19&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="61"/> calls to a first-order oracle). He later improved it to only require a <img alt="1" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="13" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-21b5b4cbe9a10b6d847eeb4265b99898_l3.png?resize=7%2C13&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="7"/>-dimensional line-search in 1981, but of course the breakthrough that everyone knows about came a year after with the famous 1982 paper by <a class="liinternal" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yurii_Nesterov" rel="nofollow">Nesterov</a> that gets rid of this extraneous logarithmic term altogether (and in addition is based on the <a class="liinternal" href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2018/11/21/a-short-proof-for-nesterovs-momentum/">deep insight</a> of modifying Polyak’s momentum).</p>
<p>Let <img alt="f" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="16" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-c7d97b919a3b73617cf2fbb375fff3b1_l3.png?resize=10%2C16&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="10"/> be a <img alt="1" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="13" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-21b5b4cbe9a10b6d847eeb4265b99898_l3.png?resize=7%2C13&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="7"/>-smooth function. Denote <img alt="x^{+} = x - \nabla f(x)" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="19" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-d69559ebcb4e4ecdf7454cab91bf526b_l3.png?resize=125%2C19&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="125"/>. Fix a sequence <img alt="(\lambda_t)_{t \in \N}" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="18" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-ba9ca1ebe088d1befda0acb3c4644727_l3.png?resize=43%2C18&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="43"/>, to be optimized later. We consider the “conjugate” point <img alt="\sum_{s =1}^t \lambda_s \nabla f(x_s)" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="23" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-d22daf1993fbb2397de0b21ab0ea87ee_l3.png?resize=119%2C23&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="119"/>. The algorithm simply returns the optimal combination of the conjugate point and the gradient descent point, that is:</p>
<p class="ql-center-displayed-equation" style="line-height: 54px;"><span class="ql-right-eqno">   </span><span class="ql-left-eqno">   </span><img alt="\[ x_{t+1} = \mathrm{argmin}_{x \in P_t} f(x) \, \text{where} \, P_t = \mathrm{span}\left(x_t^+, \sum_{s =1}^t \lambda_s \nabla f(x_s)\right) \,. \]" class="ql-img-displayed-equation " height="54" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-81d8ed71d897fa020844a53ecc9a5cc8_l3.png?resize=479%2C54&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="479"/></p>
<p>Let us denote <img alt="g_s = \nabla f(x_s)" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="18" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-e614d7a76c02a9a308f9898af91df8ff_l3.png?resize=95%2C18&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="95"/> and <img alt="\delta_s = f(x_s) - f(x^*)" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="18" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-629dcf91ea83c14ea854c74de1069acd_l3.png?resize=143%2C18&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="143"/> for shorthand. The key point is that <img alt="g_{t+1} \in P_t^{\perp}" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="20" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-9d21b904e2ccc5df54959aa117a37b98_l3.png?resize=77%2C20&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="77"/>, and in particular <img alt="\|\sum_{s \leq t} \lambda_s g_s\|^2 = \sum_{s \leq t} \lambda_s^2 \|g_s\|^2" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="22" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-4e57279bc2d0342e42087a51af61fb76_l3.png?resize=231%2C22&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="231"/>. Now recognize that <img alt="\|g_s\|^2" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="20" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-b728147d95760e42ef7cdbb706a8cfd1_l3.png?resize=38%2C20&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="38"/> is a lower bound on the improvement <img alt="\delta_s - \delta_{s+1}" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="17" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-0808cda8024eb11ab7ce37176832a9fe_l3.png?resize=68%2C17&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="68"/> (here we use that <img alt="x_{s+1}" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="13" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-b0878f455a78407f8618e726e941aea6_l3.png?resize=33%2C13&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="33"/> is better than <img alt="x_s^+" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="19" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-5acc4c663fcf2f647eb177ebb24bc154_l3.png?resize=20%2C19&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="20"/>). Thus we get:</p>
<p class="ql-center-displayed-equation" style="line-height: 40px;"><span class="ql-right-eqno">   </span><span class="ql-left-eqno">   </span><img alt="\[ \|\sum_{s \leq t} \lambda_s g_s\|^2 \leq \sum_{s \leq t} \lambda_s^2 (\delta_s - \delta_{s+1}) \leq \sum_{s \leq t} \delta_s (\lambda_s^2 - \lambda_{s-1}^2) \,. \]" class="ql-img-displayed-equation " height="40" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-a12bda17f9c1f0f0e13ef03c9a1c9d2c_l3.png?resize=404%2C40&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="404"/></p>
<p>In other words if the sequence <img alt="\lambda" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="12" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-ab48baf331239642a00255b86324280a_l3.png?resize=10%2C12&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="10"/> is chosen such that <img alt="\lambda_s = \lambda_s^2 - \lambda_{s-1}^2" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="21" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-2f241a8315da6dd3f7735135d1d2b7ae_l3.png?resize=114%2C21&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="114"/> then we get</p>
<p class="ql-center-displayed-equation" style="line-height: 40px;"><span class="ql-right-eqno">   </span><span class="ql-left-eqno">   </span><img alt="\[ \|\sum_{s \leq t} \lambda_s g_s\|^2 \leq \sum_{s \leq t} \lambda_s \delta_s \,. \]" class="ql-img-displayed-equation " height="40" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-8e959561f27eec9096b81bd7148a4a75_l3.png?resize=180%2C40&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="180"/></p>
<p>This is good because roughly the reverse inequality also holds true by convexity (and the fact that <img alt="x_s \in P_s" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="15" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-212cae06b1b9b8b6af498b589bb15865_l3.png?resize=56%2C15&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="56"/> so <img alt="g_s \cdot x_s = 0" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="16" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-cf91835fdc91be361d1c7e89f867c5db_l3.png?resize=78%2C16&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="78"/>):</p>
<p class="ql-center-displayed-equation" style="line-height: 40px;"><span class="ql-right-eqno">   </span><span class="ql-left-eqno">   </span><img alt="\[ \sum_{s \leq t} \lambda_s \delta_s \leq \sum_{s \leq t} \lambda_s g_s \cdot (x_s - x^*) \leq \|x^*\| \cdot \| \sum_{s \leq t} \lambda_s g_s\| \,. \]" class="ql-img-displayed-equation " height="40" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-9d1ee450c97dfc04bca3a123fb68daa8_l3.png?resize=391%2C40&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="391"/></p>
<p>So finally we get <img alt="\sum_{s \leq t} \lambda_s \delta_s \leq \|x^*\|^2" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="22" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-d58dea2404181d7f1751fcf8e68ad024_l3.png?resize=143%2C22&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="143"/>, and it just remains to realize that <img alt="\lambda_s" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="15" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-f100f89f751713a1814b3938a510009b_l3.png?resize=16%2C15&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="16"/> is of order <img alt="s" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="8" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-3bcfb3f0b6b04be3b598743cd774dd78_l3.png?resize=8%2C8&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="8"/> so that <img alt="\delta_t \leq \|x^*\|^2 / t^2" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="20" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-3ff4a3e78d1ced5a05f33eb077194504_l3.png?resize=103%2C20&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="103"/>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-09T18:51:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-09T18:51:19Z</published>
    <category term="Optimization"/>
    <author>
      <name>Sebastien Bubeck</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit</id>
      <link href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Random topics in optimization, probability, and statistics. By Sébastien Bubeck</subtitle>
      <title>I’m a bandit</title>
      <updated>2019-01-15T23:43:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=606</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2019/01/09/my-last-3-5-years/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>My last 3.5 years</title>
    <summary>I haven’t breathed (freely) since 3.5 years ago.  Precisely since the day before I left my Cambridge flat, when the Pods guy told me he couldn’t park. I had to vacate within 24 hours, had no place to put all the stuff I had never used since moving there in 2008, and also happened to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: justify;">I haven’t breathed (freely) since 3.5 years ago.  Precisely since the day before I left my Cambridge flat, when the Pods guy told me he couldn’t park. I had to vacate within 24 hours, had no place to put all the stuff I had never used since moving there in 2008, and also happened to have a 3-hour CPR course planned long ago, starting in minutes.  I took that life-saving course on the edge of the seat, each 5-minute break dashing out to call movers who might have had an unlikely last minute cancellation in the busiest day of the year (August 31).</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Oh the times I wished that the fireproof storage where the things eventually went burned down to the ground.  Instead I was going to have to move my never used belongings a million times up and down stairs.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Anyway, after Cambridge I went to the <a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2015/11/16/from-the-simons-institute/">Simons institute</a>. Even with all the help from the staff, finding housing was atrocious, and I had to change it during the semester. I didn’t have a place to come back, and from Berkeley I eventually found a short-term rental in Needham, MA.  The idea was to buy a house in that short term.  This proved <a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2015/12/15/how-to-buy-a-house/">impossible</a>.  So we had to find another rental.  In the process, I was discriminated against three times.  One time the landlord rejected in writing my application claiming that they did not want to rent to families. The other two times the landlord simply rejected my application, and then lowered the price. I thought these moves made them dumb, but maybe they are actually much smarter than me, because after toying with the idea I did not, in fact, sue.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Eventually we found another longer-term rental.  From there, with more excruciating difficulties I <a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2017/12/19/how-to-buy-a-house-ii/">wrote about earlier</a>, I bought a house, which however required 1 year of renovations (not exactly cosmetic — more about this later).  These were completed just in time to store my useless stuff there: I left for another semester at the Simons institute.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">My second visit to the institute was also great.  In fact I enjoyed it even more than the semester on fine-grained: I was there for the program on lower bounds, which are exactly the problems I went into computer science to study. I had the best time, and lots of research exchanges.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">But again, the housing situation in Berkeley was desperate.  Twice I lost a house for 1 hour. Meaning, the landlord called to make the deal, I couldn’t pick up the phone, and when I called back 1 hour later the place was gone.  I still think it would be better if the institute bought a block of houses, and also provided computers.  Even better if they make it easier to print, rather than having to stand in a corner or go through a complicated set up.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Another interesting pattern is that during my first visit there was a heat wave and the AC broke, and it was hot.  This time there was a rather serious wildfire, causing very unhealthy conditions in the bay area, and at times they couldn’t run the heating systems to avoid sucking in the smoke, and it was cold.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Berkeley isn’t Princeton, but it’s hard for me not to compare the logistics of my visits to Simons and the IAS in Princeton.  In the latter I was put in a house steps from the Institute, with minimal effort and at a fraction of the price.  In my office there was already a working computer, connected to a printer.</p>
<p>Here’s the meaning of cloud computing, remote desktop, telnet, etc in 2019, here’s the progress, the sustainability, the sharing economy: everybody brings their own laptop.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Back from Simons, I can’t help but be surprised that I still have an office.  In fact this happens every time I go up the stairs, turn the corner and see my name on the tag, and it says “Professor”. Really? Under <em>my name</em>? I have a startle each time.  I know this feeling is irrational, but is there.  Coming back from California, the feeling is intense.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Back to business, I am now teaching algorithms.  I am running an online section, for which I am making videos on my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UChbOQ1Q8Fv44LbrQMvTPoEQ">youtube channel</a>. It’s the future.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-09T16:36:12Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-09T16:36:12Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Emanuele</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>By Emanuele Viola</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2019-01-16T06:22:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
