<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-02-24T02:29:34Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09472</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09472" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Geometric rank of tensors and subrank of matrix multiplication</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kopparty:Swastik.html">Swastik Kopparty</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Moshkovitz:Guy.html">Guy Moshkovitz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zuiddam:Jeroen.html">Jeroen Zuiddam</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09472">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Motivated by problems in algebraic complexity theory (e.g., matrix
multiplication) and extremal combinatorics (e.g., the cap set problem and the
sunflower problem), we introduce the geometric rank as a new tool in the study
of tensors and hypergraphs. We prove that the geometric rank is an upper bound
on the subrank of tensors and the independence number of hypergraphs. We prove
that the geometric rank is smaller than the slice rank of Tao, and relate
geometric rank to the analytic rank of Gowers and Wolf in an asymptotic
fashion. As a first application, we use geometric rank to prove a tight upper
bound on the (border) subrank of the matrix multiplication tensors, matching
Strassen's well-known lower bound from 1987.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T02:21:09Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09465</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09465" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Locally Private Hypothesis Selection</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gopi:Sivakanth.html">Sivakanth Gopi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kamath:Gautam.html">Gautam Kamath</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kulkarni:Janardhan.html">Janardhan Kulkarni</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nikolov:Aleksandar.html">Aleksandar Nikolov</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wu:Zhiwei_Steven.html">Zhiwei Steven Wu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Huanyu.html">Huanyu Zhang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09465">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We initiate the study of hypothesis selection under local differential
privacy. Given samples from an unknown probability distribution $p$ and a set
of $k$ probability distributions $\mathcal{Q}$, we aim to output, under the
constraints of $\varepsilon$-local differential privacy, a distribution from
$\mathcal{Q}$ whose total variation distance to $p$ is comparable to the best
such distribution. This is a generalization of the classic problem of $k$-wise
simple hypothesis testing, which corresponds to when $p \in \mathcal{Q}$, and
we wish to identify $p$. Absent privacy constraints, this problem requires
$O(\log k)$ samples from $p$, and it was recently shown that the same
complexity is achievable under (central) differential privacy. However, the
naive approach to this problem under local differential privacy would require
$\tilde O(k^2)$ samples.
</p>
<p>We first show that the constraint of local differential privacy incurs an
exponential increase in cost: any algorithm for this problem requires at least
$\Omega(k)$ samples. Second, for the special case of $k$-wise simple hypothesis
testing, we provide a non-interactive algorithm which nearly matches this
bound, requiring $\tilde O(k)$ samples. Finally, we provide sequentially
interactive algorithms for the general case, requiring $\tilde O(k)$ samples
and only $O(\log \log k)$ rounds of interactivity. Our algorithms are achieved
through a reduction to maximum selection with adversarial comparators, a
problem of independent interest for which we initiate study in the parallel
setting. For this problem, we provide a family of algorithms for each number of
allowed rounds of interaction $t$, as well as lower bounds showing that they
are near-optimal for every $t$. Notably, our algorithms result in exponential
improvements on the round complexity of previous methods.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09464</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09464" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Private Mean Estimation of Heavy-Tailed Distributions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kamath:Gautam.html">Gautam Kamath</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Singhal:Vikrant.html">Vikrant Singhal</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/u/Ullman:Jonathan.html">Jonathan Ullman</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09464">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We give new upper and lower bounds on the minimax sample complexity of
differentially private mean estimation of distributions with bounded $k$-th
moments. Roughly speaking, in the univariate case, we show that $n =
\Theta\left(\frac{1}{\alpha^2} +
\frac{1}{\alpha^{\frac{k}{k-1}}\varepsilon}\right)$ samples are necessary and
sufficient to estimate the mean to $\alpha$-accuracy under
$\varepsilon$-differential privacy, or any of its common relaxations. This
result demonstrates a qualitatively different behavior compared to estimation
absent privacy constraints, for which the sample complexity is identical for
all $k \geq 2$. We also give algorithms for the multivariate setting whose
sample complexity is a factor of $O(d)$ larger than the univariate case.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09463</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09463" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Privately Learning Markov Random Fields</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Huanyu.html">Huanyu Zhang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kamath:Gautam.html">Gautam Kamath</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kulkarni:Janardhan.html">Janardhan Kulkarni</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wu:Zhiwei_Steven.html">Zhiwei Steven Wu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09463">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the problem of learning Markov Random Fields (including the
prototypical example, the Ising model) under the constraint of differential
privacy. Our learning goals include both structure learning, where we try to
estimate the underlying graph structure of the model, as well as the harder
goal of parameter learning, in which we additionally estimate the parameter on
each edge. We provide algorithms and lower bounds for both problems under a
variety of privacy constraints -- namely pure, concentrated, and approximate
differential privacy. While non-privately, both learning goals enjoy roughly
the same complexity, we show that this is not the case under differential
privacy. In particular, only structure learning under approximate differential
privacy maintains the non-private logarithmic dependence on the dimensionality
of the data, while a change in either the learning goal or the privacy notion
would necessitate a polynomial dependence. As a result, we show that the
privacy constraint imposes a strong separation between these two learning
problems in the high-dimensional data regime.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09460</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09460" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Parameterized Objectives and Algorithms for Clustering Bipartite Graphs and Hypergraphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Veldt:Nate.html">Nate Veldt</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wirth:Anthony.html">Anthony Wirth</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gleich:David_F=.html">David F. Gleich</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09460">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Graph clustering objective functions with tunable resolution parameters make
it possible to detect different types of clustering structure in the same
graph. These objectives also provide a unifying view of other non-parametric
objectives, which often can be captured as special cases. Previous research has
largely focused on parametric objectives for standard graphs, in which all
nodes are of the same type, and edges model pairwise relationships. In our
work, we introduced parameterized objective functions and approximation
algorithms specifically for clustering bipartite graphs and hypergraphs, based
on correlation clustering. This enables us to develop principled approaches for
clustering datasets with different node types (bipartite graphs) or multiway
relationships (hypergraphs). Our hypergraph objective is related to
higher-order notions of modularity and normalized cut, and is amenable to
approximation algorithms via hypergraph expansion techniques. Our bipartite
objective generalizes standard bipartite correlation clustering, and in a
certain parameter regime is equivalent to bicluster deletion, i.e., removing a
minimum number of edges to separate a bipartite graph into disjoint bicliques.
The problem in general is NP-hard, but we show that in a certain parameter
regime it is equivalent to a bipartite matching problem, meaning that it is
polynomial time solvable in this regime. For other regimes, we provide
approximation guarantees based on LP-rounding. Our results include the first
constant factor approximation algorithm for bicluster deletion. We illustrate
the flexibility of our framework in several experiments. This includes
clustering a food web and an email network based on higher-order motif
structure, detecting clusters of retail products in product review hypergraph,
and evaluating our algorithms across a range of parameter settings on several
real world bipartite graphs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09458</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09458" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Ranking an Assortment of Products via Sequential Submodular Optimization</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Asadpour:Arash.html">Arash Asadpour</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Niazadeh:Rad.html">Rad Niazadeh</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saberi:Amin.html">Amin Saberi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Shameli:Ali.html">Ali Shameli</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09458">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study an optimization problem capturing a core operational question for
online retailing platforms. Given models for the users' preferences over
products as well as the number of items they are willing to observe before
clicking on one or abandoning the search, what is the best way to rank the
relevant products in response to a search query?
</p>
<p>In order to capture both popularity and diversity effects, we model the
probability that a user clicks on an element from a subset of products as a
monotone submodular function of this set. We also assume that the patience
level of the users, or the number of items they are willing to observe before
clicking on one or abandoning the search, is a given random variable. Under
those assumptions, the objective functions capturing user engagement or
platform revenue can be written as a new family of submodular optimization
problems over a sequence of elements.
</p>
<p>We call this family of natural optimization problems sequential submodular
optimization. By building on and extending the literature on submodular
maximization subject to matroid constraints, we derive a (1-1/e) optimal
approximation algorithm for maximizing user engagement and a bi-criteria
approximation algorithm for maximizing revenue subject to a lower bound on user
engagement.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09451</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09451" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Temporal Constraint Satisfaction Problems in Fixed-Point Logic</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bodirsky:Manuel.html">Manuel Bodirsky</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pakusa:Wied.html">Wied Pakusa</a>, Jakub Rydval <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09451">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Finite-domain constraint satisfaction problems are either solvable by
Datalog, or not even expressible in fixed-point logic with counting. The border
between the two regimes coincides with an important dichotomy in universal
algebra; in particular, the border can be described by a strong height-one
Maltsev condition. For infinite-domain CSPs the situation is more complicated
even if the template structure of the CSP is model-theoretically tame. We prove
that there is no Maltsev condition that characterises Datalog already for the
CSPs of first-order reducts of (Q;&lt;); such CSPs are called temporal CSPs and
are of fundamental importance in infinite-domain constraint satisfaction. Our
main result is a complete classification of temporal CSPs that can be solved in
Datalog, and that can be solved in fixed point logic (with or without
counting); the classification shows that many of the equivalent conditions in
the finite fail to capture expressibility in any of these formalisms already
for temporal CSPs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T02:21:42Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09441</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09441" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Localized Flow-Based Clustering in Hypergraphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Veldt:Nate.html">Nate Veldt</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Benson:Austin_R=.html">Austin R. Benson</a>, Jon Kleinberg <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09441">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Local graph clustering algorithms are designed to efficiently detect small
clusters of nodes that are biased to a localized region of a large graph.
Although many techniques have been developed for local clustering in graphs,
very few algorithms have been designed to detect local clusters in hypergraphs,
which better model complex systems involving multiway relationships between
data objects. In this paper we present a framework for local clustering in
hypergraphs based on minimum cuts and maximum flows. Our approach extends
previous research on flow-based local graph clustering, but has been
generalized in a number of key ways. First of all, we demonstrate how to
incorporate recent results on generalized hypergraph $s$-$t$ cut problems. This
allows us to accommodate a wide range of different hypergraph cut functions,
which can assign different penalties based on how each hyperedge is split
across different clusters. Furthermore, our algorithm comes with a number of
attractive theoretical properties in terms of recovering nodes sets with low
hypergraph conductance and hypergraph normalized cut scores. Finally, and most
importantly, our method is strongly-local, meaning that its runtime depends
only on the size of an input set. In practice this allows our method to quickly
find localized clusters without exploring an entire input hypergraph. We
demonstrate the power of our method in local cluster detection experiments on
an Amazon product hypergraph and a Stack Overflow question hypergraph. Although
both datasets involve millions of nodes, millions of edges, and a large average
hyperedge size, we are able to detect local clusters in a matter of a few
seconds or a few minutes, depending on the size of the cluster.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09264</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09264" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Practical Estimation of Renyi Entropy</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Skorski:Maciej.html">Maciej Skorski</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09264">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Entropy Estimation is an important problem with many applications in
cryptography, statistic,machine learning. Although the estimators optimal with
respect to the sample complexity have beenrecently developed, there are still
some challenges we address in this paper.The contribution is a novel estimator
which is built directly on the birthday paradox. Theanalysis turns out to be
considerably simpler and offer superior confidence bounds with
explicitconstants. We also discuss how streaming algorithm can be used to
massively improve memoryconsumption. Last but not least, we study the problem
of estimation in low or moderate regimes,adapting the estimator and proving
rigorus bounds.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09180</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09180" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A symmetric alternating minimization algorithm for total variation minimization</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lei:Yuan.html">Yuan Lei</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xie:Jiaxin.html">Jiaxin Xie</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09180">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we propose a novel symmetric alternating minimization
algorithm to solve a broad class of total variation (TV) regularization
problems. Unlike the usual $z^k\to x^k$ Gauss-Seidel cycle, the proposed
algorithm performs the special $\overline{x}^{k}\to z^k\to x^k$ cycle. The main
idea for our setting is the recent symmetric Gauss-Seidel (sGS) technique which
is developed for solving the multi-block convex composite problem. This idea
also enables us to build the equivalence between the proposed method and the
well-known accelerated proximal gradient (APG) method. The faster convergence
rate of the proposed algorithm can be directly obtained from the APG framework
and numerical results including image denoising, image deblurring, and analysis
sparse recovery problem demonstrate the effectiveness of the new algorithm.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09130</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09130" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A polynomial lower bound on adaptive complexity of submodular maximization</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Wenzheng.html">Wenzheng Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Paul.html">Paul Liu</a>, Jan Vondrak <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09130">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In large-data applications, it is desirable to design algorithms with a high
degree of parallelization. In the context of submodular optimization, adaptive
complexity has become a widely-used measure of an algorithm's "sequentiality".
Algorithms in the adaptive model proceed in rounds, and can issue polynomially
many queries to a function $f$ in each round. The queries in each round must be
independent, produced by a computation that depends only on query results
obtained in previous rounds.
</p>
<p>In this work, we examine two fundamental variants of submodular maximization
in the adaptive complexity model: cardinality-constrained monotone
maximization, and unconstrained non-monotone maximization. Our main result is
that an $r$-round algorithm for cardinality-constrained monotone maximization
cannot achieve a factor better than $1 - 1/e - \Omega(\min \{ \frac{1}{r},
\frac{\log^2 n}{r^3} \})$, for any $r &lt; n^c$ (where $c&gt;0$ is some constant).
This is the first result showing that the number of rounds must blow up
polynomially large as we approach the optimal factor of $1-1/e$.
</p>
<p>For the unconstrained non-monotone maximization problem, we show a positive
result: For every instance, and every $\delta&gt;0$, either we obtain a
$(1/2-\delta)$-approximation in $1$ round, or a
$(1/2+\Omega(\delta^2))$-approximation in $O(1/\delta^2)$ rounds. In particular
(in contrast to the cardinality-constrained case), there cannot be an instance
where (i) it is impossible to achieve a factor better than $1/2$ regardless of
the number of rounds, and (ii) it takes $r$ rounds to achieve a factor of
$1/2-O(1/r)$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09067</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09067" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Incremental Sampling Without Replacement for Sequence Models</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Shi:Kensen.html">Kensen Shi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bieber:David.html">David Bieber</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sutton:Charles.html">Charles Sutton</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09067">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Sampling is a fundamental technique, and sampling without replacement is
often desirable when duplicate samples are not beneficial. Within machine
learning, sampling is useful for generating diverse outputs from a trained
model. We present an elegant procedure for sampling without replacement from a
broad class of randomized programs, including generative neural models that
construct outputs sequentially. Our procedure is efficient even for
exponentially-large output spaces. Unlike prior work, our approach is
incremental, i.e., samples can be drawn one at a time, allowing for increased
flexibility. We also present a new estimator for computing expectations from
samples drawn without replacement. We show that incremental sampling without
replacement is applicable to many domains, e.g., program synthesis and
combinatorial optimization.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09041</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09041" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Compressed Data Structures for Binary Relations in Practice</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/q/Quijada=Fuentes:Carlos.html">Carlos Quijada-Fuentes</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Penabad:Miguel_R=.html">Miguel R. Penabad</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Ladra:Susana.html">Susana Ladra</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Guti=eacute=rrez:Gilberto.html">Gilberto Gutiérrez</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09041">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Binary relations are commonly used in Computer Science for modeling data. In
addition to classical representations using matrices or lists, some compressed
data structures have recently been proposed to represent binary relations in
compact space, such as the $k^2$-tree and the Binary Relation Wavelet Tree
(BRWT). Knowing their storage needs, supported operations and time performance
is key for enabling an appropriate choice of data representation given a domain
or application, its data distribution and typical operations that are computed
over the data.
</p>
<p>In this work, we present an empirical comparison among several compressed
representations for binary relations. We analyze their space usage and the
speed of their operations using different (synthetic and real) data
distributions. We include both neighborhood and set operations, also proposing
algorithms for set operations for the BRWT, which were not presented before in
the literature. We conclude that there is not a clear choice that outperforms
the rest, but we give some recommendations of usage of each compact
representation depending on the data distribution and types of operations
performed over the data. We also include a scalability study of the data
representations.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09028</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09028" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A general kernelization technique for domination and independence problems in sparse classes</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Einarson:Carl.html">Carl Einarson</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Reidl:Felix.html">Felix Reidl</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.09028">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We unify and extend previous kernelization techniques in sparse classes [5,
16] by defining a structure we call water lilies and show how it can be used in
bounded expansion classes to construct linear bikernels for $(r, c)$-DOMINATING
SET, $(r, c)$-SCATTERED SET, TOTAL $r$-DOMINATION, r-Roman Domination, and a
problem we call $(r, [{\lambda}, {\mu}])$-DOMINATION (implying a bikernel for
r-PERFECT CODE). At the cost of slightly changing the output graph class these
bikernels can be turned into into kernels. Finally, we demonstrate how these
constructions can be combined to create 'multikernels', meaning graphs who
represent kernels for multiple problems at once. Concretely, we show that
$r$-DOMINATING SET, TOTAL $r$-DOMINATION, and $r$-ROMAN DOMINATION admit a
multikernel; as well as $r$-DOMINATING SET and $2r$-INDEPENDENT SET for
multiple values of $r$ at once.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08992</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08992" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Total tessellation cover and quantum walk</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Alexandre Abreu, Luís Cunha, Celina de Figueiredo, Franklin Marquezino, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Posner:Daniel.html">Daniel Posner</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Portugal:Renato.html">Renato Portugal</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08992">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We propose the total staggered quantum walk model and the total tessellation
cover of a graph. This model uses the concept of total tessellation cover to
describe the motion of the walker who is allowed to hop both to vertices and
edges of the graph, in contrast with previous models in which the walker hops
either to vertices or edges. We establish bounds on $T_t(G)$, which is the
smallest number of tessellations required in a total tessellation cover of $G$.
We highlight two of these lower bounds $T_t(G) \geq \omega(G)$ and $T_t(G)\geq
is(G)+1$, where $\omega(G)$ is the size of a maximum clique and $is(G)$ is the
number of edges of a maximum induced star subgraph. Using these bounds, we
define the good total tessellable graphs with either $T_t(G)=\omega(G)$ or
$T_t(G)=is(G)+1$. The $k$-total tessellability problem aims to decide whether a
given graph $G$ has $T_t(G) \leq k$. We show that $k$-total tessellability is
in $\mathcal{P}$ for good total tessellable graphs. We establish the
$\mathcal{NP}$-completeness of the following problems when restricted to the
following classes: ($is(G)+1$)-total tessellability for graphs with $\omega(G)
= 2$; $\omega(G)$-total tessellability for graphs $G$ with $is(G)+1 = 3$;
$k$-total tessellability for graphs $G$ with $\max\{\omega(G), is(G)+1\}$ far
from $k$; and $4$-total tessellability for graphs $G$ with $\omega(G) = is(G)+1
= 4$. As a consequence, we establish hardness results for bipartite graphs,
line graphs of triangle-free graphs, universal graphs, planar graphs, and
$(2,1)$-chordal graphs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T02:20:33Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08894</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08894" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On rectangle-decomposable 2-parameter persistence modules</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Botnan:Magnus_Bakke.html">Magnus Bakke Botnan</a>, Vadim Lebovici, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Oudot:Steve.html">Steve Oudot</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08894">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper addresses two questions: (1) can we identify a sensible class of
2-parameter persistence modules on which the rank invariant is complete? (2)
can we determine efficiently whether a given 2-parameter persistence module
belongs to this class? We provide positive answers to both questions, and our
class of interest is that of rectangle-decomposable modules. Our contributions
include: (a) a proof that the rank invariant is complete on
rectangle-decomposable modules, together with an inclusion-exclusion formula
for counting the multiplicities of the summands; (b) algorithms to check
whether a module induced in homology by a bifiltration is
rectangle-decomposable, and to decompose it in the affirmative, with a better
complexity than state-of-the-art decomposition methods for general 2-parameter
persistence modules. Our algorithms are backed up by a new structure theorem,
whereby a 2-parameter persistence module is rectangle-decomposable if, and only
if, its restrictions to squares are. This local condition is key to the
efficiency of our algorithms, and it generalizes previous conditions from the
class of block-decomposable modules to the larger one of rectangle-decomposable
modules. It also admits an algebraic formulation that turns out to be a weaker
version of the one for block-decomposability. Our analysis focuses on the case
of modules indexed over finite grids, the more general cases are left as future
work.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08693</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08693" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Weighted Epsilon-Nets</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bertschinger:Daniel.html">Daniel Bertschinger</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schnider:Patrick.html">Patrick Schnider</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08693">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Motivated by recent work of Bukh and Nivasch on one-sided
$\varepsilon$-approximants, we introduce the notion of \emph{weighted
$\varepsilon$-nets}. It is a geometric notion of approximation for point sets
in $\mathbb{R}^d$ similar to $\varepsilon$-nets and
$\varepsilon$-approximations, where it is stronger than the former and weaker
than the latter. The main idea is that small sets can contain many points,
whereas large sets must contain many points of the weighted $\varepsilon$-net.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we analyze weak weighted $\varepsilon$-nets with respect to
convex sets and axis-parallel boxes and give upper and lower bounds on
$\varepsilon$ for weighted $\varepsilon$-nets of size two and three. Some of
these bounds apply to classical $\varepsilon$-nets as well.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.13008</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.13008" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximating Gromov-Hausdorff Distance in Euclidean Space</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582502400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Majhi:Sushovan.html">Sushovan Majhi</a>, Jeffrey Vitter, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wenk:Carola.html">Carola Wenk</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.13008">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Gromov-Hausdorff distance $(d_{GH})$ proves to be a useful distance
measure between shapes. In order to approximate $d_{GH}$ for compact subsets
$X,Y\subset\mathbb{R}^d$, we look into its relationship with $d_{H,iso}$, the
infimum Hausdorff distance under Euclidean isometries. As already known for
dimension $d\geq 2$, the $d_{H,iso}$ cannot be bounded above by a constant
factor times $d_{GH}$. For $d=1$, however, we prove that
$d_{H,iso}\leq\frac{5}{4}d_{GH}$. We also show that the bound is tight. In
effect, this gives rise to an $O(n\log{n})$-time algorithm to approximate
$d_{GH}$ with an approximation factor of $\left(1+\frac{1}{4}\right)$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-24T02:27:50Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/02/23/postdoc-at-university-of-chicago-apply-by-march-15-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/02/23/postdoc-at-university-of-chicago-apply-by-march-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at University of Chicago (apply by March 15, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Econometrics and Statistics group at the Booth School of Business of the University of Chicago invites applications for a postdoctoral researcher working with Prof. Bryon Aragam. Potential candidates should have a background in statistics and machine learning, for example nonconvex optimization, nonparametric statistics, and/or learning theory. Website: https://uchicago.wd5.myworkdayjobs.com/External/job/Hyde-Park-Campus/Principal-Researcher_JR07406 Email: bryon@chicagobooth.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Econometrics and Statistics group at the Booth School of Business of the University of Chicago invites applications for a postdoctoral researcher working with Prof. Bryon Aragam. Potential candidates should have a background in statistics and machine learning, for example nonconvex optimization, nonparametric statistics, and/or learning theory.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://uchicago.wd5.myworkdayjobs.com/External/job/Hyde-Park-Campus/Principal-Researcher_JR07406">https://uchicago.wd5.myworkdayjobs.com/External/job/Hyde-Park-Campus/Principal-Researcher_JR07406</a><br/>
Email: bryon@chicagobooth.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-02-23T18:01:23Z</updated>
    <published>2020-02-23T18:01:23Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T02:28:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/023</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/023" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-023 |  Non-Malleability against Polynomial Tampering | 

	Eshan Chattopadhyay, 

	Jyun-Jie Liao, 

	Marshall Ball, 

	Tal Malkin, 

	Li-Yang Tan</title>
    <summary>We present the first explicit construction of a  non-malleable code that can handle tampering functions that are bounded-degree polynomials. 

Prior to our work, this was only known  for  degree-1 polynomials (affine tampering functions), due to  Chattopadhyay and Li (STOC 2017). As a direct corollary, we obtain an explicit non-malleable code that is secure against tampering by bounded-size arithmetic circuits.

We show applications of our non-malleable code in constructing   non-malleable secret sharing schemes that are robust against bounded-degree polynomial tampering. In fact our result is stronger: we can handle adversaries that can adaptively choose the polynomial tampering function based on initial leakage of a bounded number of shares.

Our results are derived from explicit constructions of  seedless non-malleable extractors that can handle bounded-degree polynomial tampering functions. Prior to our work, no such result was known even for degree-2 (quadratic) polynomials.</summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T05:37:13Z</updated>
    <published>2020-02-23T05:37:13Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T02:28:14Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08944</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08944" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum Time-Space Tradeoffs by Recording Queries</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hamoudi:Yassine.html">Yassine Hamoudi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Magniez:Fr=eacute=d=eacute=ric.html">Frédéric Magniez</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08944">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We use the recording queries technique of Zhandry [Zha19] to prove lower
bounds in the exponentially small success probability regime, with applications
to time-space tradeoffs. We first extend the recording technique to the case of
non-uniform input distributions and we describe a new simple framework for
using it. Then, as an application, we prove strong direct product theorems for
$K$-Search under a natural product distribution not considered in previous
works, and for finding $K$ distinct collisions in a uniform random function.
Finally, we use the latter result to obtain the first quantum time-space
tradeoff that is not based on a reduction to $K$-Search. Namely, we demonstrate
that any $T$-query algorithm using $S$ qubits of memory must satisfy a tradeoff
of $T^3 S \geq \Omega(N^4)$ for finding $\Theta(N)$ collisions in a random
function. We conjecture that this result can be improved to $T^2 S \geq
\Omega(N^3)$, and we show that it would imply a $T^2 S \geq
\tilde{\Omega}(N^2)$ tradeoff for Element Distinctness.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08892</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08892" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Reliable Distributed Clustering with Redundant Data Assignment</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gandikota:Venkata.html">Venkata Gandikota</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mazumdar:Arya.html">Arya Mazumdar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rawat:Ankit_Singh.html">Ankit Singh Rawat</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08892">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we present distributed generalized clustering algorithms that
can handle large scale data across multiple machines in spite of straggling or
unreliable machines. We propose a novel data assignment scheme that enables us
to obtain global information about the entire data even when some machines fail
to respond with the results of the assigned local computations. The assignment
scheme leads to distributed algorithms with good approximation guarantees for a
variety of clustering and dimensionality reduction problems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08872</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08872" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Halpern Iteration for Near-Optimal and Parameter-Free Monotone Inclusion and Strong Solutions to Variational Inequalities</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Diakonikolas:Jelena.html">Jelena Diakonikolas</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08872">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We leverage the connections between nonexpansive maps, monotone Lipschitz
operators, and proximal mappings to obtain near-optimal (i.e., optimal up to
poly-log factors in terms of iteration complexity) and parameter-free methods
for solving monotone inclusion problems. These results immediately translate
into near-optimal guarantees for approximating strong solutions to variational
inequality problems, approximating convex-concave min-max optimization
problems, and minimizing the norm of the gradient in min-max optimization
problems. Our analysis is based on a novel and simple potential-based proof of
convergence of Halpern iteration, a classical iteration for finding fixed
points of nonexpansive maps. Additionally, we provide a series of algorithmic
reductions that highlight connections between different problem classes and
lead to lower bounds that certify near-optimality of the studied methods.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08825</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08825" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On quasipolynomial multicut-mimicking networks and kernelization of multiway cut problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wahlstr=ouml=m:Magnus.html">Magnus Wahlström</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08825">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We show the existence of an exact mimicking network of $k^{O(\log k)}$ edges
for minimum multicuts over a set of terminals in an undirected graph, where $k$
is the total capacity of the terminals. Furthermore, if Small Set Expansion has
an approximation algorithm with a ratio slightly better than $\Theta(\log n)$,
then a mimicking network of quasipolynomial size can be computed in polynomial
time. As a consequence of the latter, several problems would have
quasipolynomial kernels, including Edge Multiway Cut, Group Feedback Edge Set
for an arbitrary group, 0-Extension for integer-weighted metrics, and Edge
Multicut parameterized by the solution and the number of cut requests. The
result works via a combination of the matroid-based irrelevant edge approach
used in the kernel for $s$-Multiway Cut with a recursive decomposition and
sparsification of the graph along sparse cuts. The main technical contribution
is a matroid-based marking procedure that we can show will mark all
non-irrelevant edges, assuming that the graph is sufficiently densely
connected. The only part of the result that is not currently constructive and
polynomial-time computable is the detection of such sparse cuts. This is the
first progress on the kernelization of Multiway Cut problems since the kernel
for $s$-Multiway Cut for constant value of $s$ (Kratsch and Wahlstr\"om, FOCS
2012).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08730</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08730" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Cutting Corners</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Salo:Ville.html">Ville Salo</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08730">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We define and study a class of subshifts of finite type (SFTs) defined by a
family of allowed patterns of the same shape where, for any contents of the
shape minus a corner, the number of ways to fill in the corner is the same. The
main results are that for such an SFT, a locally legal pattern of convex shape
is globally legal, and there is a measure that samples uniformly on all convex
sets. Under suitable computability assumptions, this measure can be sampled,
and legal configurations counted and enumerated, effectively and efficiently.
Our approach to convexity is axiomatic, and only requires an abstract convex
geometry that is "midpointed with respect to the shape". We construct such
convex geometries on several groups, in particular all strongly polycyclic
groups and free groups. We also show some other methods for sampling finite
patterns, one based on orderings and one based on contructing new "independent
sets" from old. We also show a link to conjectures of Gottshalk and Kaplansky.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08659</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08659" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Maximum Edge-Colorable Subgraph and Strong Triadic Closure Parameterized by Distance to Low-Degree Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gr=uuml=ttemeier:Niels.html">Niels Grüttemeier</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Komusiewicz:Christian.html">Christian Komusiewicz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Morawietz:Nils.html">Nils Morawietz</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08659">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given an undirected graph $G$ and integers $c$ and $k$, the Maximum
Edge-Colorable Subgraph problem asks whether we can delete at most $k$ edges in
$G$ to obtain a graph that has a proper edge coloring with at most $c$ colors.
We show that Maximum Edge-Colorable Subgraph admits, for every fixed $c$, a
linear-size problem kernel when parameterized by the edge deletion distance of
$G$ to a graph with maximum degree $c-1$. This parameterization measures the
distance to instances that, due to Vizing's famous theorem, are trivial
yes-instances. For $c\le 4$, we also provide a linear-size kernel for the same
parameterization for Multi Strong Triadic Closure, a related edge coloring
problem with applications in social network analysis. We provide further
results for Maximum Edge-Colorable Subgraph parameterized by the vertex
deletion distance to graphs where every component has order at most $c$ and for
the list-colored versions of both problems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08634</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08634" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Even faster algorithms for CSAT over~supernilpotent algebras</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Piotr Kawałek, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Krzaczkowski:Jacek.html">Jacek Krzaczkowski</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08634">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper two algorithms solving circuit satisfiability problem over
supernilpotent algebras are presented. The first one is deterministic and is
faster than fastest previous algorithm presented by Aichinger. The second one
is probabilistic with linear time complexity. Application of the former
algorithm to finite groups provides time complexity that is usually lower than
in previously best (given by F\"oldv\'ari) and application of the latter leads
to corollary, that circuit satisfiability problem for group G is either
tractable in probabilistic linear time if G is nilpotent or is NP-complete if G
fails to be nilpotent. The results are obtained, by translating equations
between polynomials over supernilpotent algebras to bounded degree polynomial
equations over finite fields.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08626</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08626" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Intermediate problems in modular circuits satisfiability</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Paweł M. Idziak, Piotr Kawałek, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Krzaczkowski:Jacek.html">Jacek Krzaczkowski</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08626">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In <a href="http://export.arxiv.org/abs/1710.08163">arXiv:1710.08163</a> a generalization of Boolean circuits to arbitrary finite
algebras had been introduced and applied to sketch P versus NP-complete
borderline for circuits satisfiability over algebras from congruence modular
varieties. However the problem for nilpotent (which had not been shown to be
NP-hard) but not supernilpotent algebras (which had been shown to be polynomial
time) remained open.
</p>
<p>In this paper we provide a broad class of examples, lying in this grey area,
and show that, under the Exponential Time Hypothesis and Strong Exponential
Size Hypothesis (saying that Boolean circuits need exponentially many modular
counting gates to produce boolean conjunctions of any arity), satisfiability
over these algebras have intermediate complexity between $\Omega(2^{c\log^{h-1}
n})$ and $O(2^{c\log^h n})$, where $h$ measures how much a nilpotent algebra
fails to be supernilpotent. We also sketch how these examples could be used as
paradigms to fill the nilpotent versus supernilpotent gap in general.
</p>
<p>Our examples are striking in view of the natural strong connections between
circuits satisfiability and Constraint Satisfaction Problem for which the
dichotomy had been shown by Bulatov and Zhuk.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08580</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08580" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The (Generalized) Orthogonality Dimension of (Generalized) Kneser Graphs: Bounds and Applications</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Golovnev:Alexander.html">Alexander Golovnev</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Haviv:Ishay.html">Ishay Haviv</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08580">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The orthogonality dimension of a graph $G=(V,E)$ over a field $\mathbb{F}$ is
the smallest integer $t$ for which there exists an assignment of a vector $u_v
\in \mathbb{F}^t$ with $\langle u_v,u_v \rangle \neq 0$ to every vertex $v \in
V$, such that $\langle u_v, u_{v'} \rangle = 0$ whenever $v$ and $v'$ are
adjacent vertices in $G$. The study of the orthogonality dimension of graphs is
motivated by various application in information theory and in theoretical
computer science. The contribution of the present work is two-folded.
</p>
<p>First, we prove that there exists a constant $c$ such that for every
sufficiently large integer $t$, it is $\mathsf{NP}$-hard to decide whether the
orthogonality dimension of an input graph over $\mathbb{R}$ is at most $t$ or
at least $3t/2-c$. At the heart of the proof lies a geometric result, which
might be of independent interest, on a generalization of the orthogonality
dimension parameter for the family of Kneser graphs, analogously to a
long-standing conjecture of Stahl (J. Comb. Theo. Ser. B, 1976).
</p>
<p>Second, we study the smallest possible orthogonality dimension over finite
fields of the complement of graphs that do not contain certain fixed subgraphs.
In particular, we provide an explicit construction of triangle-free $n$-vertex
graphs whose complement has orthogonality dimension over the binary field at
most $n^{1-\delta}$ for some constant $\delta &gt;0$. Our results involve
constructions from the family of generalized Kneser graphs and they are
motivated by the rigidity approach to circuit lower bounds. We use them to
answer a couple of questions raised by Codenotti, Pudl\'{a}k, and Resta (Theor.
Comput. Sci., 2000), and in particular, to disprove their Odd Alternating Cycle
Conjecture over every finite field.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08533</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08533" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Algorithms and Lower Bounds for de Morgan Formulas of Low-Communication Leaf Gates</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kabanets:Valentine.html">Valentine Kabanets</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Koroth:Sajin.html">Sajin Koroth</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lu:Zhenjian.html">Zhenjian Lu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Myrisiotis:Dimitrios.html">Dimitrios Myrisiotis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Oliveira:Igor.html">Igor Oliveira</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08533">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The class $FORMULA[s] \circ \mathcal{G}$ consists of Boolean functions
computable by size-$s$ de Morgan formulas whose leaves are any Boolean
functions from a class $\mathcal{G}$. We give lower bounds and (SAT, Learning,
and PRG) algorithms for $FORMULA[n^{1.99}]\circ \mathcal{G}$, for classes
$\mathcal{G}$ of functions with low communication complexity. Let
$R^{(k)}(\mathcal{G})$ be the maximum $k$-party NOF randomized communication
complexity of $\mathcal{G}$. We show:
</p>
<p>(1) The Generalized Inner Product function $GIP^k_n$ cannot be computed in
$FORMULA[s]\circ \mathcal{G}$ on more than $1/2+\varepsilon$ fraction of inputs
for $$ s = o \! \left ( \frac{n^2}{ \left(k \cdot 4^k \cdot
{R}^{(k)}(\mathcal{G}) \cdot \log (n/\varepsilon) \cdot \log(1/\varepsilon)
\right)^{2}} \right).$$ As a corollary, we get an average-case lower bound for
$GIP^k_n$ against $FORMULA[n^{1.99}]\circ PTF^{k-1}$.
</p>
<p>(2) There is a PRG of seed length $n/2 + O\left(\sqrt{s} \cdot
R^{(2)}(\mathcal{G}) \cdot\log(s/\varepsilon) \cdot \log (1/\varepsilon)
\right)$ that $\varepsilon$-fools $FORMULA[s] \circ \mathcal{G}$. For
$FORMULA[s] \circ LTF$, we get the better seed length $O\left(n^{1/2}\cdot
s^{1/4}\cdot \log(n)\cdot \log(n/\varepsilon)\right)$. This gives the first
non-trivial PRG (with seed length $o(n)$) for intersections of $n$ half-spaces
in the regime where $\varepsilon \leq 1/n$.
</p>
<p>(3) There is a randomized $2^{n-t}$-time $\#$SAT algorithm for $FORMULA[s]
\circ \mathcal{G}$, where $$t=\Omega\left(\frac{n}{\sqrt{s}\cdot\log^2(s)\cdot
R^{(2)}(\mathcal{G})}\right)^{1/2}.$$ In particular, this implies a nontrivial
#SAT algorithm for $FORMULA[n^{1.99}]\circ LTF$.
</p>
<p>(4) The Minimum Circuit Size Problem is not in $FORMULA[n^{1.99}]\circ XOR$.
On the algorithmic side, we show that $FORMULA[n^{1.99}] \circ XOR$ can be
PAC-learned in time $2^{O(n/\log n)}$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08498</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08498" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Space Efficient Deterministic Approximation of String Measures</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cheng:Kuan.html">Kuan Cheng</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jin:Zhengzhong.html">Zhengzhong Jin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Xin.html">Xin Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zheng:Yu.html">Yu Zheng</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08498">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study approximation algorithms for the following three string measures
that are widely used in practice: edit distance, longest common subsequence,
and longest increasing sequence.\ All three problems can be solved exactly by
standard algorithms that run in polynomial time with roughly $O(n)$ space,
where $n$ is the input length, and our goal is to design deterministic
approximation algorithms that run in polynomial time with significantly smaller
space. Towards this, we design several algorithms that achieve $1+\epsilon$ or
$1-\epsilon$ approximation for all three problems, where $\epsilon&gt;0$ can be
any constant. Our algorithms use space $n^{\delta}$ for any constant $\delta&gt;0$
and have running time essentially the same as or slightly more than the
standard algorithms. Our algorithms significantly improve previous results in
terms of space complexity, where all known results need to use space at least
$\Omega(\sqrt{n})$. Some of our algorithms can also be adapted to work in the
asymmetric streaming model \cite{saks2013space}, and output the corresponding
sequence.
</p>
<p>Our algorithms are based on the idea of using recursion as in Savitch's
theorem \cite{Savitch70}, and a careful modification of previous techniques to
make the recursion work. Along the way we also give a new logspace reduction
from longest common subsequence to longest increasing sequence, which may be of
independent interest.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T23:24:14Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08495</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08495" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Eccentricity terrain of $\delta$-hyperbolic graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dragan:Feodor_F=.html">Feodor F. Dragan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Guarnera:Heather_M=.html">Heather M. Guarnera</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08495">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A graph $G=(V,E)$ is $\delta$-hyperbolic if for any four vertices $u,v,w,x$,
the two larger of the three distance sums $d(u,v)+d(w,x)$, $d(u,w)+d(v,x)$, and
$d(u,x)+d(v,w)$ differ by at most $2\delta \geq 0$. Recent work shows that many
real-world graphs have small hyperbolicity $\delta$. This paper describes the
eccentricity terrain of a $\delta$-hyperbolic graph. The eccentricity function
$e_G(v)=\max\{d(v,u) : u \in V\}$ partitions the vertex set of $G$ into
eccentricity layers $C_{k}(G) = \{v \in V : e(v)=rad(G)+k\}$, $k \in
\mathbb{N}$, where $rad(G)=\min\{e_G(v): v\in V\}$ is the radius of $G$. The
paper studies the eccentricity layers of vertices along shortest paths,
identifying such terrain features as hills, plains, valleys, terraces, and
plateaus. It introduces the notion of $\beta$-pseudoconvexity, which implies
Gromov's $\epsilon$-quasiconvexity, and illustrates the abundance of
pseudoconvex sets in $\delta$-hyperbolic graphs. In particular, it shows that
all sets $C_{\leq k}(G)=\{v\in V : e_G(v) \leq rad(G) + k\}$, $k\in
\mathbb{N}$, are $(2\delta-1)$-pseudoconvex. Additionally, several bounds on
the eccentricity of a vertex are obtained which yield a few approaches to
efficiently approximating all eccentricities. An $O(\delta |E|)$ time
eccentricity approximation $\hat{e}(v)$, for all $v\in V$, is presented that
uses distances to two mutually distant vertices and satisfies $e_G(v)-2\delta
\leq \hat{e}(v) \leq {e_G}(v)$. It also shows existence of two eccentricity
approximating spanning trees $T$, one constructible in $O(\delta |E|)$ time and
the other in $O(|E|)$ time, which satisfy ${e}_G(v) \leq e_T(v) \leq
{e}_G(v)+4\delta+1$ and ${e}_G(v) \leq e_T(v) \leq {e}_G(v)+6\delta$,
respectively. Thus, the eccentricity terrain of a tree gives a good
approximation (up-to an additive error $O(\delta))$ of the eccentricity terrain
of a $\delta$-hyperbolic graph.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08475</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08475" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fast Multi-Subset Transform and Weighted Sums Over Acyclic Digraphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Koivisto:Mikko.html">Mikko Koivisto</a>, Antti Röyskö Department of Computer Science, University of Helsinki, Finland) <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08475">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The zeta and Moebius transforms over the subset lattice of $n$ elements and
the so-called subset convolution are examples of unary and binary operations on
set functions. While their direct computation requires $O(3^n)$ arithmetic
operations, less naive algorithms only use $2^n \mathrm{poly}(n)$ operations,
nearly linear in the input size. Here, we investigate a related $n$-ary
operation that takes $n$ set functions as input and maps them to a new set
function. This operation, we call multi-subset transform, is the core
ingredient in the known inclusion--exclusion recurrence for weighted sums over
acyclic digraphs, which extends Robinson's recurrence for the number of
labelled acyclic digraphs. Prior to this work the best known complexity bound
was the direct $O(3^n)$. By reducing the task to multiple instances of
rectangular matrix multiplication, we improve the complexity to $O(2.985^n)$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08474</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08474" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Online Policies for Efficient Volunteer Crowdsourcing</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Vahideh Manshadi, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rodilitz:Scott.html">Scott Rodilitz</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08474">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Nonprofit crowdsourcing platforms such as food recovery organizations rely on
volunteers to perform time-sensitive tasks. To encourage volunteers to complete
a task, platforms use nudging mechanisms to notify a subset of volunteers with
the hope that at least one of them responds positively. However, since
excessive notifications may reduce volunteer engagement, the platform faces a
trade-off between notifying more volunteers for the current task and saving
them for future ones. Motivated by these applications, we introduce the online
volunteer notification problem, a generalization of online stochastic bipartite
matching where tasks arrive following a known time-varying distribution over
task types. Upon arrival of a task, the platform notifies a subset of
volunteers with the objective of minimizing the number of missed tasks. To
capture each volunteer's adverse reaction to excessive notifications, we assume
that a notification triggers a random period of inactivity, during which she
will ignore all notifications. However, if a volunteer is active and notified,
she will perform the task with a given pair-specific match probability that
captures her preference for the task. We develop two online randomized policies
that achieve constant-factor guarantees close to the upper bounds we establish
for the performance of any online policy. Our policies as well as hardness
results are parameterized by the minimum discrete hazard rate of the
inter-activity time distribution. The design of our policies relies on two
modifications of an ex-ante feasible solution: properly scaling down the
notification probability prescribed by the ex-ante solution, and sparsifying
that solution. Further, in collaboration with Food Rescue U.S., a
volunteer-based food recovery platform, we demonstrate the effectiveness of our
policies by testing them on the platform's data from various locations across
the U.S.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08428</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08428" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Storage Space Allocation Strategy for Digital Data with Message Importance</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Shanyun.html">Shanyun Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/She:Rui.html">Rui She</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhu:Zheqi.html">Zheqi Zhu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fan:Pingyi.html">Pingyi Fan</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08428">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper mainly focuses on the problem of lossy compression storage from
the perspective of message importance when the reconstructed data pursues the
least distortion within limited total storage size. For this purpose, we
transform this problem to an optimization by means of the importance-weighted
reconstruction error in data reconstruction. Based on it, this paper puts
forward an optimal allocation strategy in the storage of digital data by a kind
of restrictive water-filling. That is, it is a high efficient adaptive
compression strategy since it can make rational use of all the storage space.
It also characterizes the trade-off between the relative weighted
reconstruction error and the available storage size. Furthermore, this paper
also presents that both the users' preferences and the special characteristic
of data distribution can trigger the small-probability event scenarios where
only a fraction of data can cover the vast majority of users' interests.
Whether it is for one of the reasons above, the data with highly clustered
message importance is beneficial to compression storage. In contrast, the data
with uniform information distribution is incompressible, which is consistent
with that in information theory.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08389</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08389" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Improved Approximate Degree Bounds For k-distinctness</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mande:Nikhil_S=.html">Nikhil S. Mande</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Thaler:Justin.html">Justin Thaler</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhu:Shuchen.html">Shuchen Zhu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.08389">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>An open problem that is widely regarded as one of the most important in
quantum query complexity is to resolve the quantum query complexity of the
k-distinctness function on inputs of size N. While the case of k=2 (also called
Element Distinctness) is well-understood, there is a polynomial gap between the
known upper and lower bounds for all constants k&gt;2. Specifically, the best
known upper bound is O(N^{(3/4)-1/(2^{k+2}-4)}) (Belovs, FOCS 2012), while the
best known lower bound for k &gt;= 2 is Omega(N^{2/3} + N^{(3/4)-1/(2k)})
(Aaronson and Shi, J.~ACM 2004; Bun, Kothari, and Thaler, STOC 2018).
</p>
<p>For any constant k &gt;= 4, we improve the lower bound to
Omega(N^{(3/4)-1/(4k)}). This yields, for example, the first proof that
4-distinctness is strictly harder than Element Distinctness. Our lower bound
applies more generally to approximate degree.
</p>
<p>As a secondary result, we give a simple construction of an approximating
polynomial of degree O(N^{3/4}) that applies whenever k &lt;= polylog(N).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.05160</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2002.05160" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal Multiple Stopping Rule for Warm-Starting Sequential Selection</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1582416000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fekom:Mathilde.html">Mathilde Fekom</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vayatis:Nicolas.html">Nicolas Vayatis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kalogeratos:Argyris.html">Argyris Kalogeratos</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2002.05160">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper we present the Warm-starting Dynamic Thresholding algorithm,
developed using dynamic programming, for a variant of the standard online
selection problem. The problem allows job positions to be either free or
already occupied at the beginning of the process. Throughout the selection
process, the decision maker interviews one after the other the new candidates
and reveals a quality score for each of them. Based on that information, she
can (re)assign each job at most once by taking immediate and irrevocable
decisions. We relax the hard requirement of the class of dynamic programming
algorithms to perfectly know the distribution from which the scores of
candidates are drawn, by presenting extensions for the partial and
no-information cases, in which the decision maker can learn the underlying
score distribution sequentially while interviewing candidates.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-02-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/02/22/applications-maximum-matching</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/02/22/applications-maximum-matching.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Two applications of maximum matching</title>
    <summary>This quarter I’m teaching a course on graph algorithms (an upper-division elective, so only around 200 students; our required classes are much bigger) and we’ve reached the part of the course where we discuss matching. Motivating bipartite matching, perfect matching, weighted matching, and stable matching are all easy enough but I wanted a few more examples of applications of non-bipartite maximum-cardinality matching, so I asked my colleague Vijay Vazirani who responded with two cute ones that I wasn’t already familiar with.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This quarter I’m teaching a course on graph algorithms (an upper-division elective, so only around 200 students; our required classes are much bigger) and we’ve reached the part of the course where we discuss <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matching_(graph_theory)">matching</a>. Motivating bipartite matching, perfect matching, weighted matching, and stable matching are all easy enough but I wanted a few more examples of applications of non-bipartite <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/02/22/Maximum cardinality matching">maximum-cardinality matching</a>, so I asked my colleague Vijay Vazirani who responded with two cute ones that I wasn’t already familiar with.</p>

<p>His first suggestion was two-processor scheduling. To keep things simple and concrete let’s assume that we have a collection of equal-length tasks, with a partial ordering (or DAG) describing their timing constraints. If we have one processor to perform them on (or one person to perform them), the obvious solution is to schedule them according to a linear extension of the partial order (a topological ordering of the DAG), allowing them to all be performed with no delays, in total time equal to the number of tasks. But now suppose that there are two processors or people performing the tasks, so we can process two tasks at a time and, ideally, finish twice as quickly. We would like to find a schedule with as many compatible pairs of tasks as we can, saving as many time slots as there are pairs. Two tasks are compatible if they are incomparable in the partial order (there is no path between them in the DAG), so it looks like we simply need to find a maximum matching in the incomparability graph of the partial order. This doesn’t quite work because two matched pairs can “cross”,
unable to both be used in the same schedule because each pair contains an element constrained to be earlier than an element of the other pair. But when this happens, it’s possible to uncross them and get another matching that’s at least as good, eventually reaching a matching without any crossings that can be topologically ordered to give an optimal schedule. The connection between this scheduling problem and matching appears to come from Fujii, Kasami, and Ninamiya, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/0117070">Optimal sequencing of two equivalent processors</a>”, <em>SIAM J. Appl. Math.</em> 1969; for fast algorithms for this special case of matching see H. Gabow, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/322326.322335">An almost-linear algorithm for two-processor scheduling</a>”, <em>JACM</em> 1982.</p>

<p>Another application, closer to the real world, comes from a problem of matching kidney donors to kidney donor recipients. But we don’t use the obvious bipartite graph of donors and recipients. Most kidney transplant recipients enter the matching process paired up already with a friend or relative who is willing to donote one of their kidneys, because otherwise there wouldn’t be enough kidneys to go around. But usually these donor-recipient pairs are incompatible with each other, so they need to find another donor-recipient pair such that the donors from each pair are compatible with the recipients from the other pair. Then, all four people get together at the same hospital and trade kidneys. More complicated exchanges of three or more pairs are not done, because that would require simultaneous operations with six or more people and significantly greater chances that one of them will back out at the last minute. So to save as many lives as possible, we need a maximum matching on a graph whose vertices are donor-recipient pairs and whose edges represent double compatibility of pairs. There’s a big literature on kidney exchange but the source for the connection to maximum matching appears to be A. E. Roth, T. Sönmez, and M. U. Ünver, “<a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w10698.pdf">Pairwise kidney exchange</a>”, <em>J. Econ. Th.</em> 2005.
If pairwise compatibility is an equivalence relation then the matching part is trivial (it’s just matching in a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cluster_graph">disjoint union of cliques</a>) but this framework is flexible enough to handle arbitrary non-transitive compatibility relations.</p>

<p>I learned of the kidney donor matching application a little too late to incorporate it into my introductory lecture on matching, so I used the other one. But next time I’ll be prepared with both!</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103705828147671738">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-02-22T17:55:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-02-22T17:55:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-02-23T02:36:56Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/022</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/022" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-022 |  Interactive Error Resilience Beyond $\frac{2}{7}$ | 

	Klim Efremenko, 

	Gillat Kol, 

	Raghuvansh Saxena</title>
    <summary>Interactive error correcting codes can protect interactive communication protocols against a constant fraction of adversarial errors, while incurring only a constant multiplicative overhead in the total communication. What is the maximum fraction of errors that such codes can protect against? 

For the non-adaptive channel, where the parties must agree in advance on the order in which they communicate, Braverman and Rao prove that the maximum error resilience is~$\frac{1}{4}$ (STOC, 2011). Ghaffari, Haeupler, and Sudan (STOC, 2014) consider the {\em adaptive} channel, where the order in which the parties communicate may not be fixed, and give a clever protocol that is resilient to a $\frac{2}{7}$ fraction of errors. This was believed to be optimal. 

We revisit this result, and show how to overcome the $\frac{2}{7}$ barrier. Specifically, we show that, over the adaptive channel, every two-party communication protocol can be converted to a protocol that is resilient to $\frac{7}{24} &gt; \frac{2}{7}$ fraction of errors with only a constant multiplicative overhead to the total communication. The protocol is obtained by a novel implementation of a feedback mechanism over the adaptive channel.</summary>
    <updated>2020-02-22T02:29:22Z</updated>
    <published>2020-02-22T02:29:22Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T02:28:14Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/02/21/tenure-track-faculty-all-levels-at-boston-university-apply-by-february-21-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/02/21/tenure-track-faculty-all-levels-at-boston-university-apply-by-february-21-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure-track faculty, all levels at Boston University (apply by February 21, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Faculty of Computing &amp; Data Sciences invites applications for multiple tenured and tenure-track faculty positions at all ranks. Founded in 2019, the Faculty of Computing &amp; Data Sciences is a new university-wide, degree-granting academic unit. Consideration and review of applications will be on a rolling basis. See the full ad for more information. Website: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Faculty of Computing &amp; Data Sciences invites applications for multiple tenured and tenure-track faculty positions at all ranks. Founded in 2019, the Faculty of Computing &amp; Data Sciences is a new university-wide, degree-granting academic unit. Consideration and review of applications will be on a rolling basis. See the full ad for more information.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.bu.edu/cds-faculty/join-us/">https://www.bu.edu/cds-faculty/join-us/</a><br/>
Email: ads22@bu.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-02-21T19:56:13Z</updated>
    <published>2020-02-21T19:56:13Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-02-24T02:28:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
