<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-06-21T05:23:07Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08656</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08656" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Stochastic One-Sided Full-Information Bandit</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1561075200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhao:Haoyu.html">Haoyu Zhao</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Wei.html">Wei Chen</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08656">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we study the stochastic version of the one-sided full
information bandit problem, where we have $K$ arms $[K] = \{1, 2, \ldots, K\}$,
and playing arm $i$ would gain reward from an unknown distribution for arm $i$
while obtaining reward feedback for all arms $j \ge i$. One-sided full
information bandit can model the online repeated second-price auctions, where
the auctioneer could select the reserved price in each round and the bidders
only reveal their bids when their bids are higher than the reserved price. In
this paper, we present an elimination-based algorithm to solve the problem. Our
elimination based algorithm achieves distribution independent regret upper
bound $O(\sqrt{T\cdot\log (TK)})$, and distribution dependent bound $O((\log T
+ \log K)f(\Delta))$, where $T$ is the time horizon, $\Delta$ is a vector of
gaps between the mean reward of arms and the mean reward of the best arm, and
$f(\Delta)$ is a formula depending on the gap vector that we will specify in
detail. Our algorithm has the best theoretical regret upper bound so far. We
also validate our algorithm empirically against other possible alternatives.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-21T01:25:17Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08484</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08484" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Coresets for Clustering with Fairness Constraints</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1561075200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Huang:Lingxiao.html">Lingxiao Huang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jiang:Shaofeng_H==C=.html">Shaofeng H.-C. Jiang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vishnoi:Nisheeth_K=.html">Nisheeth K. Vishnoi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08484">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In a recent work, Chierichetti et al. studied the following "fair" variants
of classical clustering problems such as $k$-means and $k$-median: given a set
of $n$ data points in $\mathbb{R}^d$ and a binary type associated to each data
point, the goal is to cluster the points while ensuring that the proportion of
each type in each cluster is roughly the same as its underlying proportion.
Subsequent work has focused on either extending this setting to when each data
point has multiple, non-disjoint sensitive types such as race and gender, or to
address the problem that the clustering algorithms in the above work do not
scale well. The main contribution of this paper is an approach to clustering
with fairness constraints that involve multiple, non-disjoint types, that is
{\em also scalable}. Our approach is based on novel constructions of coresets:
for the $k$-median objective, we construct an $\varepsilon$-coreset of size
$O(\Gamma k^2 \varepsilon^{-d})$ where $\Gamma$ is the number of distinct
collections of groups that a point may belong to, and for the $k$-means
objective, we show how to construct an $\varepsilon$-coreset of size $O(\Gamma
k^3\varepsilon^{-d-1})$. The former result is the first known coreset
construction for the fair clustering problem with the $k$-median objective, and
the latter result removes the dependence on the size of the full dataset as in
Schmidt et al. and generalizes it to multiple, non-disjoint types. Plugging our
coresets into existing algorithms for fair clustering such as Backurs et al.
results in the fastest algorithms for several cases. Empirically, we assess our
approach over the Adult and Bank dataset, and show that the coreset sizes are
much smaller than the full dataset; applying coresets indeed accelerates the
running time of computing the fair clustering objective while ensuring that the
resulting objective difference is small.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08455</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08455" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Push-pull direct CAD modeling with movable neighboring faces for preserving G^1 connections</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1561075200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zou:Qiang.html">Qiang Zou</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Feng:Hsi=Yung.html">Hsi-Yung Feng</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08455">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>B-rep model editing plays an essential role in CAD and motivates the very
recent direct modeling CAD paradigm, which features intuitive push-pull
manipulation of the model geometry. Boundary faces in a B-rep model could be
connected in a smooth manner, typically G1 continuous, for functional,
manufacturing or aesthetic reasons. Quite often, it is desirable to preserve
such smooth connections during push-pull moves. This is, however, no trivial
matter and introduces additional challenges. To preserve the G1 connections,
neighboring faces of push-pulled faces need to be made movable, but their
motions are not known explicitly. Consequently, it becomes challenging to track
the geometry-topology inconsistency caused by these movable faces and to attain
a robust update for push-pulled solid models. No effective ways exist in the
literature to deal with the challenges; the industrial state of the art has
implemented this function, but the challenges are not addressed satisfactorily
and robustness issues are observed. This paper proposes a novel reverse
tracking method to solve the above challenges, and then, based on it, presents
a systematic method for push-pull direct modeling while preserving G1
connections. The developed method has been validated with a series of case
studies.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-21T01:53:35Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08448</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08448" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Extensions of Self-Improving Sorters</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1561075200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cheng:Siu=Wing.html">Siu-Wing Cheng</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jin:Kai.html">Kai Jin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yan:Lie.html">Lie Yan</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08448">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Ailon et al. (SICOMP 2011) proposed a self-improving sorter that tunes its
performance to an unknown input distribution in a training phase. The input
numbers $x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_n$ come from a product distribution, that is, each
$x_i$ is drawn independently from an arbitrary distribution ${\cal D}_i$. We
study two relaxations of this requirement. The first extension models hidden
classes in the input. We consider the case that numbers in the same class are
governed by linear functions of the same hidden random parameter. The second
extension considers a hidden mixture of product distributions.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-21T01:51:20Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08433</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08433" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A decision-support method for information inconsistency resolution in direct modeling of CAD models</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1561075200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zou:Qiang.html">Qiang Zou</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Feng:Hsi=Yung.html">Hsi-Yung Feng</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08433">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Direct modeling is a very recent CAD paradigm that can provide unprecedented
modeling flexibility. It, however, lacks the parametric capability, which is
indispensable to modern CAD systems. For direct modeling to have this
capability, an additional associativity information layer in the form of
geometric constraint systems needs to be incorporated into direct modeling.
This is no trivial matter due to the possible inconsistencies between the
associativity information and geometry information in a model after direct
edits. The major issue of resolving such inconsistencies is that there often
exist many resolution options. The challenge lies in avoiding invalid
resolution options and prioritizing valid ones. This paper presents an
effective method to support the user in making decisions among the resolution
options. In particular, the method can provide automatic information
inconsistency reasoning, avoid invalid resolution options completely, and guide
the choice among valid resolution options. Case studies and comparisons have
been conducted to demonstrate the effectiveness of the method.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-21T01:54:02Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08371</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08371" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fine-grained complexity of graph homomorphism problem for bounded-treewidth graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1561075200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Okrasa:Karolina.html">Karolina Okrasa</a>, Paweł Rzążewski <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08371">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>For graphs $G$ and $H$, a \emph{homomorphism} from $G$ to $H$ is an
edge-preserving mapping from the vertex set of $G$ to the vertex set of $H$.
For a fixed graph $H$, by \textsc{Hom($H$)} we denote the computational problem
which asks whether a given graph $G$ admits a homomorphism to $H$. If $H$ is a
complete graph with $k$ vertices, then \textsc{Hom($H$)} is equivalent to the
$k$-\textsc{Coloring} problem, so graph homomorphisms can be seen as
generalizations of colorings. It is known that \textsc{Hom($H$)} is
polynomial-time solvable if $H$ is bipartite or has a vertex with a loop, and
NP-complete otherwise [Hell and Ne\v{s}et\v{r}il, JCTB 1990].
</p>
<p>In this paper we are interested in the complexity of the problem,
parameterized by the treewidth of the input graph $G$. If $G$ has $n$ vertices
and is given along with its tree decomposition of width $\mathrm{tw}(G)$, then
the problem can be solved in time $|V(H)|^{\mathrm{tw}(G)} \cdot
n^{\mathcal{O}(1)}$, using a straightforward dynamic programming. We explore
whether this bound can be improved. We show that if $H$ is a \emph{projective
core}, then the existence of such a faster algorithm is unlikely: assuming the
Strong Exponential Time Hypothesis (SETH), the \homo{H} problem cannot be
solved in time $(|V(H)|-\epsilon)^{\mathrm{tw}(G)} \cdot n^{\mathcal{O}(1)}$,
for any $\epsilon &gt; 0$. This result provides a full complexity characterization
for a large class of graphs $H$, as almost all graphs are projective cores.
</p>
<p>We also notice that the naive algorithm can be improved for some graphs $H$,
and show a complexity classification for all graphs $H$, assuming two
conjectures from algebraic graph theory. In particular, there are no known
graphs $H$ which are not covered by our result.
</p>
<p>In order to prove our results, we bring together some tools and techniques
from algebra and from fine-grained complexity.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08320</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08320" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Scalable and Differentially Private Distributed Aggregation in the Shuffled Model</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1561075200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Ghazi:Badih.html">Badih Ghazi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pagh:Rasmus.html">Rasmus Pagh</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Velingker:Ameya.html">Ameya Velingker</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08320">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Federated learning promises to make machine learning feasible on distributed,
private datasets by implementing gradient descent using secure aggregation
methods. The idea is to compute a global weight update without revealing the
contributions of individual users.
</p>
<p>Current practical protocols for secure aggregation work in an "honest but
curious" setting where a curious adversary observing all communication to and
from the server cannot learn any private information assuming the server is
honest and follows the protocol.
</p>
<p>A more scalable and robust primitive for privacy-preserving protocols is
shuffling of user data, so as to hide the origin of each data item. Highly
scalable and secure protocols for shuffling, so-called mixnets, have been
proposed as a primitive for privacy-preserving analytics in the
Encode-Shuffle-Analyze framework by Bittau et al. Recent papers by Cheu et al.
and Balle et al. have formalized the "shuffled model" and suggested protocols
for secure aggregation that achieve differential privacy guarantees. Their
protocols come at a cost, though: Either the expected aggregation error or the
amount of communication per user scales as a polynomial $n^{\Omega(1)}$ in the
number of users $n$.
</p>
<p>In this paper we propose simple and more efficient protocol for aggregation
in the shuffled model, where communication as well as error increases only
polylogarithmically in $n$. Our new technique is a conceptual "invisibility
cloak" that makes users' data almost indistinguishable from random noise while
introducing zero distortion on the sum.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-21T01:50:28Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08308</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08308" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Complexity of Online Bribery in Sequential Elections</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1561075200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hemaspaandra:Edith.html">Edith Hemaspaandra</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hemaspaandra:Lane_A=.html">Lane A. Hemaspaandra</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rothe:Joerg.html">Joerg Rothe</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08308">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Prior work on the complexity of bribery assumes that the bribery happens
simultaneously, and that the briber has full knowledge of all voters' votes.
But neither of those assumptions always holds. In many real-world settings,
votes come in sequentially, and the briber may have a use-it-or-lose-it moment
to decide whether to bribe/alter a given vote, and at the time of making that
decision, the briber may not know what votes remaining voters are planning on
casting.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we introduce a model for, and initiate the study of, bribery
in such an online, sequential setting. We show that even for election systems
whose winner-determination problem is polynomial-time computable, an online,
sequential setting may vastly increase the complexity of bribery, in fact
jumping the problem up to completeness for high levels of the polynomial
hierarchy or even PSPACE. On the other hand, we show that for some natural,
important election systems, such a dramatic complexity increase does not occur,
and we pinpoint the complexity of their bribery problems in the online,
sequential setting.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-21T01:20:29Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08256</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08256" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Jaccard Filtration and Stable Paths in the Mapper</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1561075200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Dustin L. Arendt, Matthew Broussard, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Krishnamoorthy:Bala.html">Bala Krishnamoorthy</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saul:Nathaniel.html">Nathaniel Saul</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08256">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The contributions of this paper are two-fold. We define a new filtration
called the cover filtration built from a single cover based on a generalized
Jaccard distance. We provide stability results for the cover filtration and
show how the construction is equivalent to the Cech filtration under certain
settings. We then develop a language and theory for stable paths within this
filtration, inspired by ideas of persistent homology. We demonstrate how the
filtration and paths can be applied to a variety of applications in which
defining a metric is not obvious but a cover is readily available.
</p>
<p>We demonstrate the usefulness of this construction by employing it in the
context of recommendation systems and explainable machine learning. We
demonstrate a new perspective for modeling recommendation system data sets that
does not require manufacturing a bespoke metric. This extends work on
graph-based recommendation systems, allowing a topological perspective. For an
explicit example, we look at a movies data set and we find the stable paths
identified in our framework represent a sequence of movies constituting a
gentle transition and ordering from one genre to another.
</p>
<p>For explainable machine learning, we apply the Mapper for model induction,
providing explanations in the form of paths between subpopulations or
observations. Our framework provides an alternative way of building a
filtration from a single mapper that is then used to explore stable paths. As a
direct illustration, we build a mapper from a supervised machine learning model
trained on the FashionMNIST data set. We show that the stable paths in the
cover filtration provide improved explanations of relationships between
subpopulations of images.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-21T01:53:47Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/?p=1373</id>
    <link href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/06/20/optimal-bound-for-stochastic-bandits-with-corruption/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal bound for stochastic bandits with corruption</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Guest post by Mark Sellke. In the comments of the previous blog post we asked if the new viewpoint on best of both worlds can be used to get clean “interpolation” results. The context is as follows: in a STOC … <a href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/06/20/optimal-bound-for-stochastic-bandits-with-corruption/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>Guest post by <a class="liexternal" href="http://web.stanford.edu/~msellke/main">Mark Sellke</a>.</em></p>
<p>In the <a class="liinternal" href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/06/10/amazing-progress-in-adversarially-robust-stochastic-multi-armed-bandits/#comments">comments</a> of the previous blog post we asked if the new viewpoint on best of both worlds can be used to get clean “interpolation” results. The context is as follows: in a <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.09353">STOC 2018 paper</a> followed by a <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.08647">COLT 2019 paper</a>, the following corruption model was discussed: stochastic bandits, except for <img alt="C" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="12" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-eda88fce4ab12a676aa4baf036291115_l3.png?resize=14%2C12&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="14"/> rounds which are adversarial. The state of the art bounds were of the form: optimal (or almost optimal) stochastic term plus <img alt="K C" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="12" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-189063850ed2dd251e3453bcdf72bb1f_l3.png?resize=30%2C12&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="30"/>, and it was mentioned as an open problem whether <img alt="KC" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="12" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-a11b6676b92ebe2d33985ebf5d9107fe_l3.png?resize=30%2C12&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="30"/> could be improved to <img alt="C" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="12" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-eda88fce4ab12a676aa4baf036291115_l3.png?resize=14%2C12&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="14"/> (there is a lower bound showing that <img alt="C" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="12" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-eda88fce4ab12a676aa4baf036291115_l3.png?resize=14%2C12&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="14"/> is necessary — when <img alt="C = O(\sqrt{T})" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="20" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-7a63a8eb07aa9c2f39df62272d6a867e_l3.png?resize=92%2C20&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="92"/>). As was discussed in the comment section, it seemed that indeed this clean best of both worlds approach should certainly shed light on the corruption model. It turns out that this is indeed the case, and a one-line calculation resolves positively the open problem from the COLT paper. The formal result is as follows (recall the notation/definitions from <a class="liinternal" href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/06/10/amazing-progress-in-adversarially-robust-stochastic-multi-armed-bandits/">the previous blog post</a>):</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Lemma:</strong> Consider a strategy whose regret with respect to the optimal action <img alt="i^*" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="13" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-9af0b76a90462b68c1d83fca9cc6604d_l3.png?resize=12%2C13&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="12"/> is upper bounded by</p>
<p class="ql-center-displayed-equation" style="line-height: 56px;"><span class="ql-right-eqno"> (1) </span><span class="ql-left-eqno">   </span><img alt="\begin{equation*} c \sum_{t=1}^T \sum_{i \neq i^*} \sqrt{\frac{x_{i,t}}{t}} \,. \end{equation*}" class="ql-img-displayed-equation " height="56" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-2ed2f41c6df060684cac5f6b54464432_l3.png?resize=122%2C56&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="122"/></p>
<p>Then in the <img alt="C" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="12" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-eda88fce4ab12a676aa4baf036291115_l3.png?resize=14%2C12&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="14"/>-corruption stochastic bandit model one has that the regret is bounded by:</p>
<p class="ql-center-displayed-equation" style="line-height: 50px;"><span class="ql-right-eqno">   </span><span class="ql-left-eqno">   </span><img alt="\[ C + 2 c \sqrt{K C} + c^2 \sum_{i \neq i^*} \frac{\log(T)}{\Delta_i} \]" class="ql-img-displayed-equation " height="50" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-c48324ec76e014154981894b80b05577_l3.png?resize=219%2C50&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="219"/></p>
<p> </p></blockquote>
<p>Note that by the previous blog post we know strategies that satisfy (1) with <img alt="c=10" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="13" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-ac5b38b4377a6b37c2b5319ca167d4c1_l3.png?resize=49%2C13&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="49"/> (see Lemma 2 in the <a class="liinternal" href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/06/10/amazing-progress-in-adversarially-robust-stochastic-multi-armed-bandits/">previous post</a>).</p>
<p><em>Proof: In equation (1) let us apply Jensen over the corrupt rounds, this yields a term <img alt="c \sqrt{K C}" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="18" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-aec148c42036e82bad7bbc28ce4df79f_l3.png?resize=53%2C18&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="53"/>. For the non-corrupt rounds, let us use that</em></p>
<p class="ql-center-displayed-equation" style="line-height: 45px;"><span class="ql-right-eqno">   </span><span class="ql-left-eqno">   </span><img alt="\[ c \sqrt{\frac{x_{i,t}}{t}} \leq \frac{1}{2} \left( \Delta_i x_{i,t} + \frac{c^2}{t \Delta_i} \right) \]" class="ql-img-displayed-equation " height="45" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-85bba8f5ccf6308ab72f723bb5aa19b6_l3.png?resize=213%2C45&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="213"/></p>
<p>The sum of the second term on the right hand side is upper bounded by <img alt="c^2 \sum_{i \neq i^*} \frac{\log(T)}{2 \Delta_i}" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="28" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-b9e1680c083d81bc4a40e096a27bda7b_l3.png?resize=109%2C28&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="109"/>. On the other hand the sum (over non-corrupt rounds) of the first term is equal to <img alt="1/2" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="18" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-1c652ece8cc629e4e659c41eeed4d410_l3.png?resize=25%2C18&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="25"/> of the regret over the non-corrupt rounds, which is certainly smaller than <img alt="1/2" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="18" src="https://i1.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-1c652ece8cc629e4e659c41eeed4d410_l3.png?resize=25%2C18&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="25"/> of the total regret plus <img alt="C" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="12" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-eda88fce4ab12a676aa4baf036291115_l3.png?resize=14%2C12&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="14"/>. Thus we obtain (denoting <img alt="R" class="ql-img-inline-formula " height="12" src="https://i2.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-dfd80738ac64385be5b381ea59d7fe55_l3.png?resize=14%2C12&amp;ssl=1" style="vertical-align: 0px;" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="14"/> for the total regret):</p>
<p class="ql-center-displayed-equation" style="line-height: 50px;"><span class="ql-right-eqno">   </span><span class="ql-left-eqno">   </span><img alt="\[ R \leq c \sqrt{K C} + c^2 \sum_{i \neq i^*} \frac{\log(T)}{2 \Delta_i} + \frac{C}{2} + \frac{R}{2} \]" class="ql-img-displayed-equation " height="50" src="https://i0.wp.com/blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/wp-content/ql-cache/quicklatex.com-936baa25f1189bd3993ce4dba58242c5_l3.png?resize=290%2C50&amp;ssl=1" title="Rendered by QuickLaTeX.com" width="290"/></p>
<p>which concludes the proof.</p>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-20T18:43:39Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-20T18:43:39Z</published>
    <category term="Machine learning"/>
    <category term="Optimization"/>
    <category term="Theoretical Computer Science"/>
    <author>
      <name>Sebastien Bubeck</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit</id>
      <link href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Random topics in optimization, probability, and statistics. By Sébastien Bubeck</subtitle>
      <title>I’m a bandit</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T23:31:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?p=34</id>
    <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/20/theory-and-practice-of-differential-privacy-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy 2019</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While I’m a relative newcomer to differential privacy (my first paper on it was only in 2017), I’ve found the community to be a pleasure to interact with: paradoxically, simultaneously tight-knit yet highly welcoming to newcomers. I partially credit this culture to the number of workshops and programs which bring people together, including, but not … <a class="more-link" href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/20/theory-and-practice-of-differential-privacy-2019/">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy 2019"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>While I’m a relative newcomer to differential privacy (my <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.10127">first paper</a> on it was only in 2017), I’ve found the community to be a pleasure to interact with: paradoxically, simultaneously tight-knit yet highly welcoming to newcomers. I partially credit this culture to the number of workshops and programs which bring people together, including, but not limited to, <a href="https://www.birs.ca/events/2018/5-day-workshops/18w5189">a BIRS workshop</a>, <a href="https://privacytools.seas.harvard.edu/">the Privacy Tools project at Harvard</a>, <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/programs/privacy2019">a semester at the Simons Institute</a>, <a href="https://shonan.nii.ac.jp/seminars/164/">the forthcoming Shonan workshop</a>, and <a href="https://tpdp.cse.buffalo.edu/">the Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy (TPDP) Workshop</a>.</p>



<p>I’m writing this post to draw attention to the imminent deadline of <a href="https://tpdp.cse.buffalo.edu/2019/">TPDP 2019</a>, co-located with CCS 2019 in London. I’ll spare you the full details (click the link for more information), but most pressing is the deadline tomorrow, June 21, 2019, anywhere on Earth (let me know if this presents hardship for you, and I can pass concerns on to the chair). Essentially anything related to the theory or practice of differential privacy is welcome. Submissions are limited to four pages in length and are lightly refereed, based on originality, relevance, interest, and clarity. There are no published proceedings, and previously published results are welcome. If you’ve been looking to get to know the community, consider either submitting or attending the workshop! </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-20T18:05:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-20T18:05:19Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://kamathematics.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Kamathematics</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:23:07Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/06/20/portland-street-art</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/06/20/portland-street-art.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Portland street art</title>
    <summary>I’ve been in Portland, Oregon this week for Computational Geometry Week. Here are a few photos of local street art, the first set I’ve taken with my new Pixel 3 XL cellphone (I neglected to bring an actual camera for this trip):</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I’ve been in Portland, Oregon this week for <a href="http://eecs.oregonstate.edu/socg19/">Computational Geometry Week</a>. Here are a few photos of local street art, the first set I’ve taken with my new Pixel 3 XL cellphone
(I neglected to bring an actual camera for this trip):</p>

<div><table style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
<tbody><tr style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">
<td style="padding: 10px;"><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/portland/Clay-2nd-1.html"><img alt="Portland Oregon Street art: Clay &amp; 2nd" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/portland/Clay-2nd-1-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="400"/></a></td>
<td style="padding: 10px;"><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/portland/Clay-2nd-2.html"><img alt="Portland Oregon Street art: Clay &amp; 2nd" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/portland/Clay-2nd-2-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="382"/></a></td>
</tr><tr style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">
<td style="padding: 10px;"><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/portland/Hall-5th-2.html"><img alt="Portland Oregon Street art: Hall &amp; 5th" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/portland/Hall-5th-2-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="335"/></a></td>
<td style="padding: 10px;"><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/portland/College-4th.html"><img alt="Portland Oregon Street art: College &amp; 4th" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/portland/College-4th-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="382"/></a></td>
</tr></tbody></table></div>

<p><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/portland/index.html">Here are the rest of my photos</a>.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102306697775168322">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-20T17:04:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-20T17:04:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T00:20:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4207</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4207" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4207#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4207" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Quanta of Solace</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">In Quanta magazine, Kevin Hartnett has a recent article entitled A New Law to Describe Quantum Computing’s Rise? The article discusses “Neven’s Law”—a conjecture, by Hartmut Neven (head of Google’s quantum computing effort), that the number of integrated qubits is now increasing exponentially with time, so that the difficulty of simulating a state-of-the-art QC on […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In <em>Quanta</em> magazine, Kevin Hartnett has a recent article entitled <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/does-nevens-law-describe-quantum-computings-rise-20190618/">A New Law to Describe Quantum Computing’s Rise?</a>  The article discusses “Neven’s Law”—a conjecture, by Hartmut Neven (head of Google’s quantum computing effort), that the number of integrated qubits is now increasing exponentially with time, so that the difficulty of simulating a state-of-the-art QC on a fixed classical computer is increasing <em>doubly</em> exponentially with time.  (Jonathan Dowling tells me that he expressed the same thought years ago.)</p>



<p>Near the end, the <em>Quanta</em> piece quotes some UT Austin professor whose surname starts with a bunch of A’s as follows:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“I think the undeniable reality of this progress puts the ball firmly in the court of those who believe scalable quantum computing can’t work.   They’re the ones who need to articulate where and why the progress will stop.”</p></blockquote>



<p>The quote is perfectly accurate, but in context, it might give the impression that I’m endorsing Neven’s Law.  In reality, I’m reluctant to fit a polynomial or an exponential or any other curve through a set of numbers that so far hasn’t exceeded about 50.  I say only that, regardless of what anyone believes is the ultimate rate of progress in QC, what’s already happened today puts the ball firmly in the skeptics’ court.</p>



<p>Also in <em>Quanta</em>, Anil Ananthaswamy has a new article out on <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/how-to-turn-a-quantum-computer-into-the-ultimate-randomness-generator-20190619/">How to Turn a Quantum Computer Into the Ultimate Randomness Generator</a>.  This piece covers two schemes for using a quantum computer to generate “certified random bits”—that is, bits you can <em>prove</em> are random to a faraway skeptic.  one due to me, the other due to <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.00640">Brakerski et al</a>.  The one issue is that the article cites my <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.05903">paper with Lijie Chen</a> as showing that my scheme is sound (i.e., that under a suitable computational assumption, the QC is forced to generate a lot of entropy).  Unfortunately, my paper with Lijie shows nothing of the kind—it’s only about arguing that the results of such a test would be hard to spoof using a classical computer, not that they’re <em>random</em>.  The randomness aspect will be addressed in a paper that I’m currently writing; for now, see <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/talks/certrand2.ppt">these slides</a>.</p>



<p>As long as I’m linking to interesting recent <em>Quanta</em> articles, Erica Klarreich has <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematician-disproves-hedetniemis-graph-theory-conjecture-20190617/">A 53-Year-Old Network Coloring Conjecture is Disproved</a>.  Briefly, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hedetniemi%27s_conjecture">Hedetniemi’s Conjecture</a> stated that, given any two finite, undirected graphs G and H, the chromatic number of the tensor product G⊗H is just the minimum of the chromatic numbers of G and H themselves.  For more, see also <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/05/10/sansation-in-the-morning-news-yaroslav-shitov-counterexamples-to-hedetniemis-conjecture/">this post by Gil Kalai</a>—who appears here <em>not</em> in his capacity as a quantum computing skeptic.</p>



<p>In interesting math news beyond <em>Quanta</em> magazine, the Berkeley alumni magazine has a piece about the crucial, neglected topic of <a href="https://alumni.berkeley.edu/california-magazine/just-in/2019-06-14/chalk-market-where-mathematicians-go-get-good-stuff">mathematicians’ love for Hagoromo-brand chalk</a> (hat tip: Peter Woit).  I can personally vouch for this.  When I moved to UT Austin three years ago, most offices in CS had whiteboards, but I deliberately chose one with a blackboard.  I figured that chalk has its problems—it breaks, the dust gets all over—but I could live with them, much more than I could live with the Fundamental Whiteboard Difficulty, of all the available markers always being dry whenever you want to explain anything.  With the Hagoromo brand, though, you pretty much get all the benefits of chalk with none of the downsides, so it just strictly dominates whiteboards.</p>



<p>Jan Kulveit asked me to advertise the <a href="https://espr-camp.org/">European Summer Program on Rationality</a> (ESPR), which will take place this August 13-23, and which is aimed at students ages 16-19.  I’ve <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=2410">lectured</a> both at ESPR and at a similar summer program that ESPR was modeled after (called SPARC)—and while I was never there as a student, it looked to me like a phenomenal experience.   So if you’re a 16-to-19-year-old who reads this blog, please consider applying!</p>



<p>I’m now at the end of my annual family trip to Tel Aviv, returning to the Eastern US tonight, and then on to <a href="http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2019/stocprogram.html">STOC’2019</a> at the <a href="https://fcrc.acm.org/">ACM Federated Computing Research Conference</a> in Phoenix (which I can blog about if anyone wants me to).  It was a good trip, although marred by my two-year-old son Daniel falling onto sun-heated metal and suffering a second-degree burn on his leg, and then by the doctor botching the treatment.  Fortunately Daniel’s now healing nicely.  For future reference, whenever bandaging a burn wound, <em>be sure</em> to apply lots of Vaseline to prevent the bandage from drying out, and also to change the bandage daily.  Accept no fancy-sounding substitute.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-20T15:54:37Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-20T15:54:37Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T17:03:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7528</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/06/20/tcs-women-at-stoc-guest-post-by-virginia-williams/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS Women at STOC (guest post by Virginia Williams)</title>
    <summary>[Guest post by Virgi Vassilevska Williams on the TCS women program at STOC. In particular the TCS Women Spotlight workshop has a great program and is open to all. –Boaz] Dear all, The TCS Women 2019 program is finalized: https://sigact.org/tcswomen/tcs-women-2019/. Here are some details: On June 23rd, we have our TCS Women Spotlight workshop from 2 […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div><em>[Guest post by Virgi Vassilevska Williams on the TCS women program at STOC. In particular the TCS Women Spotlight workshop has a great program and is open to all. –Boaz]</em></div>
<div/>
<div>Dear all,</div>
<div/>
<div>The TCS Women 2019 program is finalized: <a href="https://sigact.org/tcswomen/tcs-women-2019/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">https://sigact.org/tcswomen/tcs-women-2019/</a>. Here are some details:</div>
<div/>
<div>On June 23rd, we have our TCS Women Spotlight workshop from 2 pm to 5 pm. This will feature an inspirational talk by Ronitt Rubinfeld (MIT &amp; Tel Aviv University)–“Comedy of Errors”, and rising stars talks by Naama Ben-David (CMU), Debarati Das (Charles University), Andrea Lincoln (MIT) and Oxana <span style="color: #000000;">Poburinnaya (Boston University). The workshop is open to all and we would love to see you all there.</span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;">On June 24th, we have the TCS Women lunch and panel of distinguished researchers from academia and industries. This year’s panelists include Shuchi Chawla (University of Wisconsin), Julia Chuzhoy (TTIC), Edith Cohen (Google), Faith Ellen (University of Toronto), Rachel Lin (University of Washington) and Nutan Limaye (Indian Institute of Technology, Mumbai). The event is open to all women participants of FCRC.</span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;">In addition to these, there will be a TCS Women poster session held jointly with the STOC poster session on June 24th. Fourteen women researchers will be presenting posters on their research. More information is available on our website. All are welcome. </span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;">We are providing travel scholarships to more than forty women students this year to attend STOC and FCRC. We secured funding from the NSF, Akamai, Amazon, Google and Microsoft. Thank you!<br/>
</span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;">Looking forward to seeing you soon!</span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;"> </span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;">Best wishes,</span></div>
<div><span style="color: #000000;">The TCS Women organizers</span></div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-20T14:33:12Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-20T14:33:12Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8718880846893877693</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/8718880846893877693/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/06/the-urbanrural-collegiality-divide.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8718880846893877693" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8718880846893877693" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/06/the-urbanrural-collegiality-divide.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Urban/Rural Collegiality Divide</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div>
Just a reminder that Grigory Yaroslavtsev has <a href="http://grigory.us/blog/theory-jobs-2019/">taken over</a> the <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Oegc0quwv2PqoR_pzZlUIrPw4rFsZ4FKoKkUvmLBTHM/edit?usp=sharing">Theory Jobs Spreadsheet</a>. Check out who is moving where and let everyone know where you will continue your research career.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
In 1999 when I considered leaving the University of Chicago for NEC Research I had a conversation with Bob Zimmer, then VP of Research and current U of C President. Zimmer said it was a shame I didn't live in Hyde Park, the Chicago South Side neighborhood where the university resides, and thus not fully connected with the school. At the time I didn't fully understand his point and did leave for NEC, only to return in 2003 and leave again in 2008. I never did live in Hyde Park.<br/>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
Recently I served on a review committee for a computer science department in a rural college town. You couldn't help but notice the great collegiality among the faculty. Someone told me their theory that you generally get more faculty collegiality in rural versus urban locations. Why?</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
In urban locations faculty tend to live further from campus, to get bigger homes and better schools, and face more traffic. They are likely to have more connections with people unconnected with the university. There are more consulting opportunities in large cities, a larger variety of coffee houses to hang out in and better connected airports make leaving town easier. Particularly in computer science, where you can do most of your research remotely, faculty will find themselves less likely to come in every day and you lose those constant informal connections with the rest of the faculty. </div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
This is a recent phenomenon, even going back to when I was a young faculty you needed to come to the office for access to research papers, better computers to write papers, good printers. Interactions with students and colleagues is always better in person but in the past the methods of electronic communication proved more limiting.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
The University of Chicago helped create and promote its own neighborhood and ran a very strong private school with reduced tuition for faculty children. Maybe my life would have been different had I immersed myself in that lifestyle. </div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
Or maybe we should go the other extreme. If we can find great ways to do on-line meetings and teaching, why do we need the physical university at all?</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-20T13:18:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-20T13:18:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T20:40:23Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-778501013924768672</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/778501013924768672/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=778501013924768672" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/778501013924768672" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/778501013924768672" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2019/06/postdoc-position-at-gssi-in-algorithms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc position at the GSSI in algorithms for modern networks, formal methods for reactive systems and model-based software engineering</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><span style="font-size: medium;"><b id="m_2299630027166989820gmail-m_-1686136991101628107gmail-docs-internal-guid-fe2365bd-7fff-efca-8269-ca7515fa84d9" style="font-weight: normal;"/></span><br/><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;"><span style="font-size: medium;"><b id="m_2299630027166989820gmail-m_-1686136991101628107gmail-docs-internal-guid-fe2365bd-7fff-efca-8269-ca7515fa84d9" style="font-weight: normal;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"><span style="font-size: medium;"><b id="m_2299630027166989820gmail-m_-1686136991101628107gmail-docs-internal-guid-fe2365bd-7fff-efca-8269-ca7515fa84d9" style="font-weight: normal;"/></span></span></b></span></div><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;"><span style="font-size: medium;"><b id="m_2299630027166989820gmail-m_-1686136991101628107gmail-docs-internal-guid-fe2365bd-7fff-efca-8269-ca7515fa84d9" style="font-weight: normal;"><span style="font-size: medium;"><b id="m_2299630027166989820gmail-m_-1686136991101628107gmail-docs-internal-guid-fe2365bd-7fff-efca-8269-ca7515fa84d9" style="font-weight: normal;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 700; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Postdoctoral position financed by the <a href="http://www.gssi.it/">GSSI</a></span></b></span></b></span></div><span style="font-size: medium;"><b id="m_2299630027166989820gmail-m_-1686136991101628107gmail-docs-internal-guid-fe2365bd-7fff-efca-8269-ca7515fa84d9" style="font-weight: normal;"><span style="font-size: medium;"><b id="m_2299630027166989820gmail-m_-1686136991101628107gmail-docs-internal-guid-fe2365bd-7fff-efca-8269-ca7515fa84d9" style="font-weight: normal;"><br/><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;"><span style="background-color: white; color: #222222; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"><b>Scientific profile:</b> The successful candidate will have a strong research record in one or more of the research areas within the <a href="https://sites.google.com/gssi.it/csgssi">Computer Science group at the GSSI,</a> namely algorithms for modern networks, formal methods for reactive systems and model-based software engineering. We welcome applications in any of those areas. </span></div></b></span><br/><br/><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The position is for two years (</span><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"><span style="font-size: medium;"><b id="m_2299630027166989820gmail-m_-1686136991101628107gmail-docs-internal-guid-fe2365bd-7fff-efca-8269-ca7515fa84d9" style="font-weight: normal;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">renewable for a third year, if this is mutually agreeable)</span></b></span> and the salary is 36,000€ per year before taxes. </span></div><br/><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 700; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">How to apply: </span><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">The application must be submitted through the online form available at</span><a href="https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/" style="text-decoration: none;" target="_blank"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> </span><span style="background-color: transparent; color: #1155cc; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: underline; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/</span></a><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> by </span><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 700; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Thursday, 11 July 2019 at 6 p.m. (Central European Time)</span><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">. For more information, please consult the Call for Applications at</span><a href="https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/" style="text-decoration: none;" target="_blank"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> </span><span style="background-color: transparent; color: #1155cc; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: underline; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/</span></a><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">. </span></div><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> </span></div><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt; text-align: justify;"><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 700; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;">Requirements:</span><span style="background-color: transparent; color: black; font-family: Arial; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: 400; text-decoration: none; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;"> Candidates are expected to have a PhD degree in Computer Science or related disciplines. </span></div><br/></b></span></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-20T10:36:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-20T10:36:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T10:36:22Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-2613037482816339108</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/2613037482816339108/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=2613037482816339108" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/2613037482816339108" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/2613037482816339108" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2019/06/postdoctoral-position-at-gssi-within.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral position at the GSSI within the project “ALGADIMAR: Algorithms, Games, and Digital Markets”</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Computer Science group at the Gran Sasso Science Institute (GSSI, <a href="http://cs.gssi.it/">http://cs.gssi.it</a>) --- an international PhD school and centre for advanced studies located in L’Aquila, Italy --- has one available postdoctoral position  in the context of the PRIN projects  “ALGADIMAR: Algorithms, Games, and Digital Markets” (Gianlorenzo D’Angelo, PI at GSSI),  funded by the Italian Ministry for University and Research.<br/><br/>The position is briefly described below. It is for two years and the salary is 36,000€ per year before taxes. The position is renewable for a third year, if this is mutually agreeable.<br/><br/><b>How to apply:</b> The application must be submitted through the online form available at <a href="https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/">https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/</a> by Thursday, 11 July 2019 at 6 p.m. (Central European Time). For more information, please consult the Call for Applications at <a href="https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/">https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/</a> or write an email to <a href="http://www.gssi.it/people/professors/lectures-computer-science/item/456-d-angelo-gianlorenzo">Gianlorenzo D’Angelo</a>.<br/><br/><b>Requirements:</b> Candidates are expected to have a PhD degree in Computer Science or related disciplines. Preference will be given to applicants who have previous research experience on topics related to the theme of the project.<br/><br/><b>Postdoctoral position within the project “ALGADIMAR: Algorithms, Games, and Digital Markets”, supervised by <a href="http://www.gssi.it/people/professors/lectures-computer-science/item/456-d-angelo-gianlorenzo">Gianlorenzo D’Angelo</a>. </b><br/><br/>Brief description of the project: Digital markets form an increasingly important component of the global economy. The Internet has enabled new markets with previously unknown features (e-commerce, web-based advertisement, viral marketing, sharing economy, real-time trading), and algorithms play a central role in many decision processes involved in these markets. For example, algorithms run electronic auctions, adjust prices dynamically, trade stocks, harvest big data to decide market strategies and to provide recommendations to customers. The focus of the proposal ALGADIMAR is on the development of new methods and tools in research areas that are critical to the understanding of digital markets: algorithmic game theory, market and mechanism design, machine learning, algorithmic data analysis, optimization in strategic settings. We plan to apply these methods so as to solve fundamental algorithmic problems motivated by Internet advertisement, sharing economy, mechanism design for social good, security games. While our research is focused on foundational work —with rigorous design and analysis of algorithms, mechanisms and games— it will also include empirical validation on large-scale datasets from real-world applications.<br/><br/>Main activities:  The research activity will be on one or more of the following topics: design and analysis of algorithms; algorithms and data structures for big data; approximation algorithms; combinatorial optimization; algorithms for graphs and networks; autonomous agents and mobile computing; distributed algorithms; algorithmic game theory, algorithmic aspects of internet and social networks.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-20T10:07:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-20T10:07:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T10:36:22Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08141</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.08141" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Rock Climber Distance: Frogs versus Dogs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1560988800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Akitaya:Hugo_A=.html">Hugo A. Akitaya</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ryvkin:Leonie.html">Leonie Ryvkin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/T=oacute=th:Csaba_D=.html">Csaba D. Tóth</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08141">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The classical measure of similarity between two polygonal chains in Euclidean
space is the Fr\'echet distance, which corresponds to the coordinated motion of
two mobile agents along the chains while minimizing their maximum distance. As
computing the Fr\'echet distance takes near-quadratic time under the Strong
Exponential Time Hypothesis (SETH), we explore two new distance measures,
called rock climber distance and $k$-station distance, in which the agents move
alternately in their coordinated motion that traverses the polygonal chains. We
show that the new variants are equivalent to the Fr\'echet or the Hausdorff
distance if the number of moves is unlimited. When the number of moves is
limited to a given parameter $k$, we show that it is NP-hard to determine the
distance between two curves. We also describe a 2-approximation algorithm to
find the minimum $k$ for which the distance drops below a given threshold.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-20T23:28:28Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07919</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07919" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Existence of a Convex Polyhedron with Respect to the Given Radii</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1560988800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chaidee:Supanut.html">Supanut Chaidee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sugihara:Kokichi.html">Kokichi Sugihara</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.07919">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a set of radii measured from a fixed point, the existence of a convex
configuration with respect to the set of distinct radii in the two-dimensional
case is proved when radii are distinct or repeated at most four points.
However, we proved that there always exists a convex configuration in the
three-dimensional case. In the application, we can imply the existence of the
non-empty spherical Laguerre Voronoi diagram.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-20T23:27:50Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07887</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07887" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tutorial on algebraic deletion correction codes</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1560988800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tatwawadi:Kedar.html">Kedar Tatwawadi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chandak:Shubham.html">Shubham Chandak</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.07887">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The deletion channel is known to be a notoriously diffcult channel to design
error-correction codes for. In spite of this difficulty, there are some
beautiful code constructions which give some intuition about the channel and
about what good deletion codes look like. In this tutorial we will take a look
at some of them. This document is a transcript of my talk at the coding theory
reading group on some interesting works on deletion channel. It is not intended
to be an exhaustive survey of works on deletion channel, but more as a tutorial
to some of the important and cute ideas in this area. For a comprehensive
survey, we refer the reader to the cited sources and surveys.
</p>
<p>We also provide an implementation of VT codes that correct single
insertion/deletion errors for general alphabets at
https://github.com/shubhamchandak94/VT_codes/.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-20T23:26:20Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07874</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07874" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Space Efficient Algorithms for Breadth-Depth Search</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1560988800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chakraborty:Sankardeep.html">Sankardeep Chakraborty</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mukherjee:Anish.html">Anish Mukherjee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Satti:Srinivasa_Rao.html">Srinivasa Rao Satti</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.07874">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Continuing the recent trend, in this article we design several
space-efficient algorithms for two well-known graph search methods. Both these
search methods share the same name {\it breadth-depth search} (henceforth {\sf
BDS}), although they work entirely in different fashion. The classical
implementation for these graph search methods takes $O(m+n)$ time and $O(n \lg
n)$ bits of space in the standard word RAM model (with word size being
$\Theta(\lg n)$ bits), where $m$ and $n$ denotes the number of edges and
vertices of the input graph respectively. Our goal here is to beat the space
bound of the classical implementations, and design $o(n \lg n)$ space
algorithms for these search methods by paying little to no penalty in the
running time. Note that our space bounds (i.e., with $o(n \lg n)$ bits of
space) do not even allow us to explicitly store the required information to
implement the classical algorithms, yet our algorithms visits and reports all
the vertices of the input graph in correct order.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-20T23:26:29Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07871</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07871" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Indexing Graph Search Trees and Applications</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1560988800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chakraborty:Sankardeep.html">Sankardeep Chakraborty</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sadakane:Kunihiko.html">Kunihiko Sadakane</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.07871">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the problem of compactly representing the Depth First Search
(DFS) tree of a given undirected or directed graph having $n$ vertices and $m$
edges while supporting various DFS related queries efficiently in the RAM with
logarithmic word size. We study this problem in two well-known models: {\it
indexing} and {\it encoding} models. While most of these queries can be
supported easily in constant time using $O(n \lg n)$ bits\footnote{We use $\lg$
to denote logarithm to the base $2$.} of extra space, our goal here is, more
specifically, to beat this trivial $O(n \lg n)$ bit space bound, yet not
compromise too much on the running time of these queries. In the {\it indexing}
model, the space bound of our solution involves the quantity $m$, hence, we
obtain different bounds for sparse and dense graphs respectively. In the {\it
encoding} model, we first give a space lower bound, followed by an almost
optimal data structure with extremely fast query time. Central to our algorithm
is a partitioning of the DFS tree into connected subtrees, and a compact way to
store these connections. Finally, we also apply these techniques to compactly
index the shortest path structure, biconnectivity structures among others.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-20T23:27:05Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07813</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07813" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Inverse Kinematics of Some General 6R/P Manipulators</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1560988800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Capco:Jose.html">Jose Capco</a>, Manuel Joseph C. Loquias, Saraleen Mae M. Manongsong, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nemenzo:Fidel_R=.html">Fidel R. Nemenzo</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.07813">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We develop an algorithm that solves the inverse kinematics of general serial
2RP3R, 2R2P2R, 3RP2R and 6R manipulators based on the HuPf algorithm. We
identify the workspaces of the 3-subchains of the manipulator with a
quasi-projective variety in $\mathbb{P}^7$ via dual quaternions. This allows us
to compute linear forms that describe linear spaces containing the workspaces
of these 3-subchains. We present numerical examples that illustrate the
algorithm and show the real solutions.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-20T23:30:24Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07781</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07781" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Convergence of the Non-Uniform Directed Physarum Model</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1560988800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Facca:Enrico.html">Enrico Facca</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Karrenbauer:Andreas.html">Andreas Karrenbauer</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kolev:Pavel.html">Pavel Kolev</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mehlhorn:Kurt.html">Kurt Mehlhorn</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.07781">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The directed Physarum dynamics is known to solve positive linear programs:
minimize $c^T x$ subject to $Ax = b$ and $x \ge 0$ for a positive cost vector
$c$. The directed Physarum dynamics evolves a positive vector $x$ according to
the dynamics $\dot{x} = q(x) - x$. Here $q(x)$ is the solution to $Af = b$ that
minimizes the "energy" $\sum_i c_i f_i^2/x_i$.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we study the non-uniform directed dynamics $\dot{x} = D(q(x) -
x)$, where $D$ is a positive diagonal matrix. The non-uniform dynamics is more
complex than the uniform dynamics (with $D$ being the identity matrix), as it
allows each component of $x$ to react with different speed to the differences
between $q(x)$ and $x$. Our contribution is to show that the non-uniform
directed dynamics solves positive linear programs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-20T23:21:19Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07754</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.07754" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the Constrained Least-cost Tour Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1560988800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Patrick O'Hara, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ramanujan:M=_S=.html">M. S. Ramanujan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Damoulas:Theodoros.html">Theodoros Damoulas</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.07754">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We introduce the Constrained Least-cost Tour (CLT) problem: given an
undirected graph with weight and cost functions on the edges, minimise the
total cost of a tour rooted at a start vertex such that the total weight lies
within a given range. CLT is related to the family of Travelling Salesman
Problems with Profits, but differs by defining the weight function on edges
instead of vertices, and by requiring the total weight to be within a range
instead of being at least some quota. We prove CLT is $\mathcal{NP}$-hard, even
in the simple case when the input graph is a path. We derive an informative
lower bound by relaxing the integrality of edges and propose a heuristic
motivated by this relaxation. For the case that requires the tour to be a
simple cycle, we develop two heuristics which exploit Suurballe's algorithm to
find low-cost, weight-feasible cycles. We demonstrate our algorithms by
addressing a real-world problem that affects urban populations: finding routes
that minimise air pollution exposure for walking, running and cycling in the
city of London.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-20T23:20:35Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16021</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/06/19/diophantine-equations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Diophantine Equations</title>
    <summary>Complexity of solving polynomial equations [ Jeff ] Jeff Lagarias is a mathematician or a professor at the University of Michigan. Today I wish to discuss Diophantine equations. Note, the “or” is a poor joke: For mathematicians is true also when both and are true. Jeff has a paper titled Complexity of Diophantine Equations and […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Complexity of solving polynomial equations</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/06/19/diophantine-equations/jeff/" rel="attachment wp-att-16022"><img alt="" class="alignright  wp-image-16022" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/jeff.jpg?w=240" width="240"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">[ Jeff ]</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Jeff Lagarias is a mathematician <b>or</b> a professor at the University of Michigan.</p>
<p>
Today I wish to discuss Diophantine equations.</p>
<p>
Note, the “or” is a poor joke: For mathematicians <img alt="{A \text{ or } B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA+%5Ctext%7B+or+%7D+B%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A \text{ or } B}"/> is true also when both <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> and <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> are true.</p>
<p>
Jeff has a paper titled <i>Complexity of Diophantine Equations</i> and related <a href="http://www.math.lsa.umich.edu/~lagarias/TALK-SLIDES/dioph-cplx-icerm2011aug.pdf">talk</a> version. It is a nice review of some of the issues around Diophantine equations. </p>
<p>
He has worked on number theory, on complexity theory, and on many other <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2013/09/05/eulers-constants/">problems</a>. Some are applied and some theoretical. He with Peter Shor solved an open problem years ago that was first stated by Ott-Heinrich Keller in 1930. Our friends at Wikipedia <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keller%27s_conjecture">state</a>: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> In geometry, Keller’s conjecture is the conjecture that in any tiling of Euclidean space by identical hypercubes there are two cubes that meet face to face. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>For dimensions ten or more it is now proved to be false thanks to Jeff and Peter. I am amazed by such geometric results, since I have no geometric intuition. Ten dimensions is way beyond me—although curiously I am okay in <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> dimensions. Strange? Jeff has a relevant <a href="https://www.azquotes.com/quote/765002">quote</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Every dimension is special.</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Complexity of Diophantine Equations </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Recall the main problem is to find solutions to equations usually restricted to be integers or rationals. This restriction makes the problems hard as in <em>open</em>, and hard as in <em>computationally difficult</em>. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h3>  Factoring-Hard </h3><p/>
<p>Jeff mentions the following hardness result in his talk: Solving in nonnegative integers for <img alt="{x,y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%2Cy%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x,y}"/> 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  (x+2)(y+2) = N, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%28x%2B2%29%28y%2B2%29+%3D+N%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  (x+2)(y+2) = N, "/></p>
<p>is as hard as integer factoring. This follows since <img alt="{x+2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%2B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x+2}"/> and <img alt="{y+2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%2B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y+2}"/> must be non-trivial factors of <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/>. Note this relies on the fact that <img alt="{x+2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%2B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x+2}"/> and <img alt="{y+2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%2B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y+2}"/> are both greater than or equal to <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/>.</p>
<p>
We can delete “nonnegative” in the above by the following simple idea. Suppose that <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> has two factors that are both congruent to <img alt="{3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{3}"/> modulo <img alt="{8}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B8%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{8}"/>. If not, then we can still factor, but I believe the idea is clearer without adding extra complications. Then solve in integers 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  (8x + 3)(8y+3) = N. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%288x+%2B+3%29%288y%2B3%29+%3D+N.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  (8x + 3)(8y+3) = N. "/></p>
<p>By assumption on <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> there is a solution of this equation. Moreover suppose that <img alt="{x,y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%2Cy%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x,y}"/> are some solution. The key is that <img alt="{8x + 3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B8x+%2B+3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{8x + 3}"/> cannot be <img alt="{\pm 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpm+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\pm 1}"/> and <img alt="{8y+3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B8y%2B3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{8y+3}"/> also cannot be <img alt="{\pm 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpm+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\pm 1}"/>. Then it follows that each is also not equal to <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> in absolute value. Thus 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  1 &lt; |8x+3| &lt; N, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++1+%3C+%7C8x%2B3%7C+%3C+N%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  1 &lt; |8x+3| &lt; N, "/></p>
<p>and we have factored <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/>.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h3>  NP-hard </h3><p/>
<p/><p>
Jeff points out that it is unlikely that Diophantine problems are going to be classified by the NP-hard machinery. He says </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\dots}"/> shows the (possible) mismatch of “natural” Diophantine problems with the P versus NP question. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Factoring is one of those in between problems that could be in P, but most believe that it could not be NP-hard.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Rational Case </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The problem of deciding whether a polynomial has a <i>rational</i> root is still open. That is given a polynomial with integer coefficients, does the equation 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  F(x,y,z,\dots)= 0, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++F%28x%2Cy%2Cz%2C%5Cdots%29%3D+0%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  F(x,y,z,\dots)= 0, "/></p>
<p>have a rational solution <img alt="{x,y,z,\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%2Cy%2Cz%2C%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x,y,z,\dots}"/>? Of course the famous Hilbert’s Tenth problem asks for integer solutions of polynomials and is undecidable. The rational case is open. We have discussed it before <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2010/08/07/hilberts-tenth-over-the-rationals/">here</a>. See <a href="https://sites.math.washington.edu/~morrow/336_16/2016papers/peter%20gc.pdf">this</a> for a survey. </p>
<p>
I had tried to see if we could at least prove the following: The decision problem over the rationals is at NP-hard. I thought for a while that I could show that solving equations over the rationals is at least NP-hard. My idea was to try to replace <img alt="(x+2)(y+2)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28x%2B2%29%28y%2B2%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="(x+2)(y+2)"/> by a equation that works over the rationals. The attempt failed. I was also unable to find a reference for such a result either. So perhaps it is open.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Is it undecidable to determine whether a polynomial has a root over the rationals? Can we at least get that it is factoring hard?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-19T22:32:53Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-19T22:32:53Z</published>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Diophantine"/>
    <category term="equations"/>
    <category term="Hilbert Tenth"/>
    <category term="NP"/>
    <category term="NP-hard"/>
    <category term="open problem"/>
    <category term="polynomial"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:20:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=359</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2019/06/19/the-spring-season-is-behind-us/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Spring season of TCS+ is behind us!</title>
    <summary>With John Wright‘s talk last week, the Spring ’19 season of TCS+ concluded. Thanks to all our followers who tuned in, everyone who suggested a talk or spread the word, and, of course, thanks to all our speakers! For those who missed a talk, or would like to watch them again in the comfort of […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>With <a href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2019/06/06/tcs-talk-wednesday-june-12th-john-wright-mit/">John Wright</a>‘s talk last week, the Spring ’19 season of TCS+ concluded. Thanks to all our followers who tuned in, everyone who <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">suggested a talk</a> or spread the word, and, of course, thanks to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks">all our speakers</a>!</p>
<p>For those who missed a talk, or would like to watch them again in the comfort of your home, institution, or on the seaside: all past talks are now uploaded and available, along with the speakers’ slides.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<ul>
<li>Ran Canetti (Boston University and Tel Aviv University) on <em><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks/20190206rancanettibostonuniversityandtelavivuniversity">Fully Bideniable Interactive Encryption</a></em></li>
<li>Sepehr Assadi (Princeton) on <em><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks/20190220sepehrassadiprincetonuniversity">A Simple Sublinear-Time Algorithm for Counting Arbitrary Subgraphs via Edge Sampling</a></em></li>
<li>Shayan Oveis Gharan (University of Washington) on <em><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks/20190306shayanoveisgharanuniversityofwashington">Strongly log concave polynomials, high dimensional simplicial complexes, and an FPRAS for counting Bases of Matroids </a></em></li>
<li>Aleksandar Nikolov (University of Toronto) on <em><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks/03202019aleksandarnikolovuniversityoftoronto">Sticky Brownian Rounding and its Applications to Constraint Satisfaction Problems</a><br/>
</em></li>
<li>Richard Peng (Georgia Tech) on <em><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks/04032019richardpenggeorgiatech">Fully Dynamic Spectral Vertex Sparsifiers and Applications</a><br/>
</em></li>
<li>Thatchaphol Saranurak (TTIC) on <em><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks/04172019thatchapholsaranurakttic">Breaking Quadratic Time for Small Vertex Connectivity</a><br/>
</em></li>
<li>Chris Peikert (University of Michigan) on <em><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks/20190501chrispeikertuniversityofmichigan">Noninteractive Zero Knowledge for NP from Learning With Errors</a><br/>
</em></li>
<li>Ewin Tang (University of Washington) on <em><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks/20190515ewintanguniversityofwashington">Quantum-inspired classical linear algebra algorithms: why and how?</a><br/>
</em></li>
<li>Lior Kamma (Aarhus University) on <em><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks/20190529liorkammaaarhusuniversity">Lower Bounds for Multiplication via Network Coding</a><br/>
</em></li>
<li>John Wright (MIT) on <em><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/past-talks/20190612johnwrightmit">NEEXP in MIP*</a><br/>
</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Have a great summer, and see you in the Fall!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-19T18:07:07Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-19T18:07:07Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:21:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-819529627944448924</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/819529627944448924/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=819529627944448924" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/819529627944448924" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/819529627944448924" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2019/06/postdoctoral-positions-at-gssi-on.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral positions at the GSSI on modelling and verification for cyber-physical and smart systems</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The <a href="http://cs.gssi.it/">Computer Science group at the Gran Sasso Science Institute</a> (GSSI, an international PhD school and centre for advanced studies located in L’Aquila, Italy) has two available postdoctoral positions on topics related to modelling and verification for cyber-physical and smart systems. The positions are in the context of two PRIN projects funded by the Italian Ministry for University and Research, namely  "Designing Spatially Distributed Cyber-Physical Systems under Uncertainty (SEDUCE)" (Catia Trubiani, PI at the GSSI) and "IT MATTERS: Methods and Tools for Trustworthy Smart Systems" (Luca Aceto, PI at the GSSI).  Each position is for two years and the salary is 36,000€ per year before taxes. The positions are renewable for a third year if this is mutually agreeable.<br/><br/>The positions are briefly described below. We foresee a close collaboration between the members of the teams working on the two projects.   The application must be submitted through the online form available at <a href="https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/">https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/</a> by <b>Thursday, 11 July 2019 at 6 p.m. (Central European Time)</b>. For more information, please consult the Call for Applications at <a href="https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/">https://applications.gssi.it/postdoc/ </a>or write an email to the PIs of the respective projects.<br/><br/>Note that the Computer Science group at the GSSI also has a further position financed by the institute, which can be filled in any of the research themes within the group. See <a href="http://cs.gssi.it/">http://cs.gssi.it</a> for more information.<br/><br/>Requirements: Candidates are expected to have a PhD degree in Computer Science or related disciplines. Preference will be given to applicants who have previous research experience on topics related to the themes of the project.<br/><br/>P<b>ostdoctoral position within the project "Designing Spatially Distributed Cyber-Physical Systems under Uncertainty"</b>, supervised by Catia Trubiani: <a href="https://cs.gssi.it/catia.trubiani">https://cs.gssi.it/catia.trubiani</a>.<br/><br/>Brief description of the project: Emerging scenarios such as autonomous vehicles and the Internet-of-Things require large-scale cyber-physical systems (CPS), i.e., computing devices that interact with the physical world. To cope with their complexity, model-based design has long been advocated as a prominent approach for their rigorous development. However, the state of the art does not adequately account for two major issues: space, to capture the distribution of CPS devices as well as their mobility; and uncertainty, e.g., to reflect lack of knowledge about the environment, the accuracy of the model, or errors occurring in the real world. Our goal is to develop modelling and analysis techniques for CPS where space and uncertainty are first-class citizens. We envisage a component-based framework where digital and physical components have locality and mobility features, and where uncertainty is captured by means of probabilistically distributed activities to describe their dynamics. We devise a system to specify spatio-temporal CPS requirements, turning them into probabilistic spatio-temporal logical specifications that will be at the basis of efficient algorithms for the analysis, verification, and synthesis. We will apply our techniques to real case studies on smart buildings and crowd-navigating robots.<br/><br/>Main activities: The successful candidate will develop a component-based modelling language for the specification of cyber physical systems, where digital components (i.e., the computational devices), need to co-exist with physical components (i.e., the dynamical models of the physical world). Each component will feature an appropriate location and mobility model. Uncertainty will be specified with either probabilistically distributed activities, or nondeterministically, leading to reasoning that will take into account worst- and best-case scenarios under any possible value of such uncertain actions. The modelling framework will allow the specification of spatio-temporal requirements, which establish the behavioural guarantees to be satisfied by the CPS under analysis.   The postdoctoral researcher will work with Catia Trubiani at the GSSI, and she/he will also collaborate with the project partners at IMT Lucca (Mirco Tribastone, coordinator of the project), University of Trieste (Luca Bortolussi and Stefano Seriani), and University of Camerino (Francesco Tiezzi).<br/><br/><br/><b>Postdoctoral position within the project "IT MATTERS: Methods and Tools for Trustworthy Smart Systems"</b> supervised by Luca Aceto: <a href="http://www.gssi.it/people/professors/lectures-computer-science/item/225-aceto-luca">http://www.gssi.it/people/professors/lectures-computer-science/item/225-aceto-luca</a>.<br/><br/>Brief description of the project: The goal of the project is the development and the application of a novel methodology for the specification, implementation and validation of trustworthy smart systems based on formal methods. We envisage system development in three steps by first providing and analysing system models to find design errors, then moving from models to executable code by translation into domain-specific programming languages and, finally, monitoring runtime execution to detect anomalous behaviours and to support systems in taking context-dependent decisions autonomously. Scientifically, the research will yield new, fundamental insights on the general properties of large scale, physically located, smart systems, leading to an end-to-end, principled approach to their design, implementation and deployment. The developed software tools and the work on the case studies will show the effectiveness of our proposed approach in three practical scenarios at different application scales.<br/><br/>Main activities: The successful candidate will develop runtime-monitoring and software-model-checking techniques for “smart systems”, that is, systems that take context-dependent decisions autonomously. The research activities will involve developing frameworks that can deal with the distributed nature of smart systems and will  build on existing work on specification-based monitoring and software model checking of cyber-physical systems. The postdoctoral researcher will also devise techniques to use information derived from the runtime analysis to guide the software-model-checking effort and to refine the models of the runtime environment used in model checking.    The postdoctoral researcher will work with Luca Aceto, Omar Inverso, Ludovico Iovino and Emilio Tuosto at the GSSI. He/she will also collaborate with the project partners at IMT Lucca, CNR Pisa, University of Camerino, University of Pisa and University of Udine. Moreover, he/she will also interact with the concurrency group at ICE-TCS (<a href="http://icetcs.ru.is/">http://icetcs.ru.is/</a>), Reykjavik University, led by Luca Aceto and Anna Ingólfsdóttir.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-19T11:58:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-19T11:58:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T10:36:22Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-2592965474602859939</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/2592965474602859939/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/06/why-does-nevalina-prize-now-abacus-got.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2592965474602859939" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2592965474602859939" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/06/why-does-nevalina-prize-now-abacus-got.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Why does the Nevalina Prize (now Abacus) got to Algorithms/Complexity people</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In my post about the Nevanlinna prize  name change (see <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/06/imus-non-controversial-changing-name-of.html">here</a>) one of my readers raised a different question about the prize:<br/>
<br/>
BEGIN QUOTE<br/>
<br/>
<div style="text-align: start;">
<br/></div>
<span>So there's one of my main questions about the prize answered (or at least resolved). The second remains. The IMU's website(which still refers to the Nevanlinna Prize) says that it is awarded "for outstanding contributions in Mathematical Aspects of Information Sciences including:"</span><br/>
<br/>
<span>1)All mathematical aspects of computer science, including complexity theory, logic of programming languages, analysis of algorithms, cryptography, computer vision, pattern recognition, information processing and modelling of intelligence.</span><br/>
<br/>
<span>2)Scientific computing and numerical analysis. Computational aspects of optimization and control theory. Computer algebra.</span><br/>
<br/>
<span>Correct me if I'm wrong, but it seems that the recognized work of the ten winners of the award all fits into two or three of the possible research areas for which the prize may be rewarded. Why do people think that this is the case?</span><br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;">END QUOTE</span></span></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;"><br/></span></span></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;">First off, lets see if this is true. Here is a list of all the winners:</span></span></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;"><br/></span></span></div>
<div style="text-align: justify;">
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;">Tarjan, Valiant, Razborov, Wigderson, Shor, Sudan, Kleinberg, Spielman, Khot, Daskalakis </span></span><br/>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;"><br/></span></span>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;">Yup, they all seem to be in Algorithms or Complexity.</span></span><br/>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;"><br/></span></span>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;">Speculation as to why:</span></span><br/>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;"><br/></span></span>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;">1) Algorithms and Complexity have problems with short descriptions that can easily be understood: Tarjan proved Planarity was in O(n) time. Valiant defined Sharp-P and showed the Permanent was Sharp-P complete. Hence it is easy to see what they have done. In many of the fields listed, while people have done great work, it may be harder to tell since the questions are not as clean.  If my way to do Vision is better than your way to do Vision, that may be hard to prove. And the proof  may need to be non-rigorous.</span></span><br/>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;"><br/></span></span>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;">2) If someone does great work in (for example) Logic of Programming Languages, it may not be recognized until she is past 40 years old. </span></span><br/>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;"><br/></span></span>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;">3) This one I am less sure of (frankly I'm not that sure of any of these and invite polite commentary): areas that are more practical may take longer to build and get to work.</span></span><br/>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;"><br/></span></span>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;">But there is still a problem with this. Numerical Analysis and Cryptography would seem to not have these problems. </span></span><br/>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;"><br/></span></span>
<span><span style="background-color: #ccff99; font-size: 14px;">I invite the reader to speculate</span></span></div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-18T00:59:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-18T00:59:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T20:40:23Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/18/robustness-in-learning-and-statistics-past-and-future/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/18/robustness-in-learning-and-statistics-past-and-future/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Robustness in Learning and Statistics: Past and Future</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">August 12-15, 2019 UC San Diego http://cseweb.ucsd.edu/~slovett/workshops/robust-statistics-2019/ Registration deadline: July 31, 2019 Robust statistics and related topics offer ways to stress test estimators to the assumptions they are making. It offers insights into what makes some estimators behave well in the face of model misspecification, while others do not. In this summer school, we will … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/18/robustness-in-learning-and-statistics-past-and-future/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Robustness in Learning and Statistics: Past and Future</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-18T00:13:18Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-18T00:13:18Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:22:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?p=23</id>
    <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/17/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hello World!</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Welcome to my blog! My name is Gautam Kamath, and I just started as an assistant professor in computer science at the University of Waterloo (for more info, see About). This blog will, broadly speaking, be about topics relevant to those interested in the the theory of computer science, statistics, and machine learning. Posts will … <a class="more-link" href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/17/hello-world/">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Hello World!"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Welcome to my blog! My name is Gautam Kamath, and I just started as an assistant professor in computer science at the University of Waterloo (for more info, see <a href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/about/">About</a>).</p>



<p>This blog will, broadly speaking, be about topics relevant to those interested in the the theory of computer science, statistics, and machine learning. Posts will range from technical, to informational, to meta (read: basically whatever I want to write about, but I’ll do my best to keep it topical). Stay tuned!</p>



<p>The unofficial theme song of this blog is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8Ir-zFC9nFE">“Mathematics” by Mos Def</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-17T23:42:13Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-17T23:42:13Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://kamathematics.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Kamathematics</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:23:07Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/17/3rd-school-on-foundations-of-programming-and-software-systems/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/17/3rd-school-on-foundations-of-programming-and-software-systems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>3rd School on Foundations of Programming and Software Systems</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">September 10-15, 2019 Warsaw, Poland https://www.mimuw.edu.pl/~fopss19/ The Summer School on Foundations of Programming and Software Systems (FoPSS) was jointly created by EATCS, ETAPS, ACM SIGLOG and ACM SIGPLAN. It was first organised in 2017. The goal is to introduce the participants to various aspects of computation theory and programming languages. The school, spread over a … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/17/3rd-school-on-foundations-of-programming-and-software-systems/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">3rd School on Foundations of Programming and Software Systems</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-17T12:23:27Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-17T12:23:27Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:22:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16001</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/06/17/contraction-and-explosion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Contraction and Explosion</title>
    <summary>Different ways of recursing on graphs Bletchley Park 2017 source William Tutte was a British combinatorialist and codebreaker. He worked in a different group at Bletchley Park from that of Alan Turing. He supplied several key insights and algorithms for breaking the Lorenz cipher machine. His algorithms were implemented alongside Turing’s on Colossus code-breaking computers. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Different ways of recursing on graphs</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<img alt="TutteBletchley" class="alignright wp-image-16003" height="200" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/tuttebletchley.jpg?w=120&amp;h=200" width="120"/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Bletchley Park 2017 <a href="https://bletchleypark.org.uk/news/codebreaker-bill-tutte-to-be-celebrated-in-centenary-exhibition">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
William Tutte was a British combinatorialist and codebreaker. He worked in a different group at Bletchley Park from that of Alan Turing. He supplied several key insights and algorithms for breaking the Lorenz cipher <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorenz_cipher">machine</a>. His algorithms were implemented alongside Turing’s on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colossus_computer">Colossus</a> code-breaking computers.</p>
<p>
Today we discuss graph recursions discovered by Tutte and Hassler Whitney.</p>
<p>
Tutte wrote a doctoral thesis after the war on graph theory and its generalization into <em>matroid theory</em>. We will follow the same arc in this and a followup post. He joined the faculty of the universities of Toronto and then Waterloo, where he was active long beyond his retirement. </p>
<p>
For more on Tutte and his work, see this <a href="https://theconversation.com/remembering-bill-tutte-another-brilliant-codebreaker-from-world-war-ii-77556">article</a> and <a href="http://thelaborastory.com/stories/william-thomas-tutte/">lecture</a> by Graham Farr, who is a professor at Monash University and a longtime friend of Ken’s from their Oxford days. We covered some of Tutte’s other work <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2010/06/02/the-tensor-trick-and-tuttles-flow-conjectures/">here</a>.</p>
<p/><h2> Deletion and Contraction </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The two most basic recursion operations are <em>deleting</em> and <em>contracting</em> a chosen edge <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/> in a given graph <img alt="{G = (V,E)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%3D+%28V%2CE%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G = (V,E)}"/>:</p>
<p><img alt="deletion_contraction" class="aligncenter wp-image-16004" height="118" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/deletion_contraction.png?w=400&amp;h=118" width="400"/></p>
<p>
These operations produce graphs denoted by <img alt="{G \setminus e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%5Csetminus+e%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G \setminus e}"/> and <img alt="{G/e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%2Fe%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G/e}"/>, respectively. A motive for them harks back to Gustav Kirchhoff’s counting of spanning trees:</p>
<ul>
<li>
A spanning tree of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> avoids using edge <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/> if and only if it is a spanning tree of the graph <img alt="{G \setminus e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%5Csetminus+e%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G \setminus e}"/> with <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/> deleted.<p/>
</li><li>
A spanning tree of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> uses edge <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/> if and only if the rest of it is a spanning tree of the graph <img alt="{G/e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%2Fe%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G/e}"/> after contracting <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/>.
</li></ul>
<p>
Well, this is not how Kirchhoff counted trees. Counting via the recursion would take exponential time. Our whole object will be telling which cases of the recursions can be computed more directly.</p>
<p>Note that contracting one edge of the triangle graph <img alt="{C_3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{C_3}"/> produces a <em>multi-</em>graph <img alt="{C_2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{C_2}"/> with one double-edge. Then contracting one edge of <img alt="{C_2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{C_2}"/> yields the loop graph <img alt="{C_1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{C_1}"/>.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<img alt="triangle" class="aligncenter wp-image-16005" height="73" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/triangle.png?w=250&amp;h=73" width="250"/></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Thus contraction yields non-simple undirected graphs, but the logic of counting their spanning trees remains valid.</p>
<p>
The order of edges does not matter as long as one avoids disconnecting the graph, and the base case is a tree (ignoring any loops) which contributes <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/>.</p>
<p/><h2> Tutte’s Polynomial </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
A similar recursion counts colorings <img alt="{c: V \rightarrow \{1,...,k\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%3A+V+%5Crightarrow+%5C%7B1%2C...%2Ck%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c: V \rightarrow \{1,...,k\}}"/> that are <em>proper</em>, meaning that for each edge <img alt="{e = (u,v)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be+%3D+%28u%2Cv%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e = (u,v)}"/>, <img alt="{c(u) \neq c(v)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%28u%29+%5Cneq+c%28v%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c(u) \neq c(v)}"/>.</p>
<ul>
<li>
A proper coloring <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/> of <img alt="{G \setminus e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%5Csetminus+e%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G \setminus e}"/> makes <img alt="{c(u) \neq c(v)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%28u%29+%5Cneq+c%28v%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c(u) \neq c(v)}"/> iff it is a proper coloring of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/>.<p/>
</li><li>
A proper coloring <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/> of <img alt="{G \setminus e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%5Csetminus+e%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G \setminus e}"/> makes <img alt="{c(u) = c(v)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%28u%29+%3D+c%28v%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c(u) = c(v)}"/> iff it induces a proper coloring of <img alt="{G/e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%2Fe%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G/e}"/>.
</li></ul>
<p>
This leads to the recursive definition of the <em>chromatic polynomial</em>:</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle    P_G(x) = P_{G\setminus e}(x) - P_{G/e}(x).   " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++++P_G%28x%29+%3D+P_%7BG%5Csetminus+e%7D%28x%29+-+P_%7BG%2Fe%7D%28x%29.+++&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle    P_G(x) = P_{G\setminus e}(x) - P_{G/e}(x).   "/></p>
<p>
The base cases are that an isolated vertex contributes <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/>, whereas an isolated loop contributes <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0}"/> since its single edge is never properly colored. The final rule is that <img alt="{P_G(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP_G%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P_G(x)}"/> is always the product of <img alt="{P_H(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP_H%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P_H(x)}"/> over all connected components <img alt="{H}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BH%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{H}"/> of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/>. Then <img alt="{P_G(k)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP_G%28k%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P_G(k)}"/> counts the number of proper <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k}"/>-colorings.</p>
<p>
This is like the recursion for coutning spanning terees except for the minus sign. Tutte’s brilliant insight, which was anticipated by Whitney in less symbolic form, was that the features can be combined by using two variables <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> and <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/>. Call an edge a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bridge_(graph_theory)">bridge</a> if it is not part of any cycle. If <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/> is not a bridge, the recursion is</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle    T_G(x,y) = T_{G \setminus e}(x,y) + T_{G/e}(x,y).   " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++++T_G%28x%2Cy%29+%3D+T_%7BG+%5Csetminus+e%7D%28x%2Cy%29+%2B+T_%7BG%2Fe%7D%28x%2Cy%29.+++&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle    T_G(x,y) = T_{G \setminus e}(x,y) + T_{G/e}(x,y).   "/></p>
<p>
The base case is now a graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> with some number <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k}"/> of bridges and some number <img alt="{\ell}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cell%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\ell}"/> of loops, which gives <img alt="{T_G(x,y) = x^k y^\ell}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT_G%28x%2Cy%29+%3D+x%5Ek+y%5E%5Cell%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T_G(x,y) = x^k y^\ell}"/>. An important feature is that all <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-vertex trees have the same Tutte polynomial <img alt="{x^{n-1}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%5E%7Bn-1%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x^{n-1}}"/>, since there are <img alt="{n-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n-1}"/> edges and they are all bridges. The following are just some of the beautiful <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tutte_polynomial#Specialisations">rules</a> that <img alt="{T_G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT_G%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T_G}"/> follows. Let <img alt="{c = c_G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc+%3D+c_G%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c = c_G}"/> stand for the number of connected components of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/>.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<img alt="{T_G(1,1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT_G%281%2C1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T_G(1,1)}"/> counts the number of spanning trees forests. This counts the number of spanning trees if <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> is connected.<p/>
</li><li>
<img alt="{T_G(1-x,0)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT_G%281-x%2C0%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T_G(1-x,0)}"/>, when multiplied by <img alt="{(-1)^{n-c} x^c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28-1%29%5E%7Bn-c%7D+x%5Ec%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(-1)^{n-c} x^c}"/>, yields the chromatic polynomial.<p/>
</li><li>
<img alt="{T_G(1,2)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT_G%281%2C2%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T_G(1,2)}"/> counts the number of spanning subgraphs.<p/>
</li><li>
<img alt="{T_G(2,2)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT_G%282%2C2%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T_G(2,2)}"/> is just <img alt="{2^{|E|}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7B%7CE%7C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{|E|}}"/>.<p/>
</li><li>
<img alt="{T_G(x,\frac{1}{x})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT_G%28x%2C%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Bx%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T_G(x,\frac{1}{x})}"/> gives the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jones_polynomial">Jones polynomial</a> of a knot related to <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/>.
</li></ul>
<p>
There are many further relations. The Jones polynomial has many applications including in quantum physics.</p>
<p/><h2> Contraction With a Twist </h2><p/>
<p>
Recall our definition of the “amplitude” <img alt="{a(G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%28G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a(G)}"/> of an undirected <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-vertex graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> from the “Net-Zero Graphs” <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/06/10/net-zero-graphs/">post</a>:</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle    a(G) = \frac{c_0 - c_1}{2^n},   " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++++a%28G%29+%3D+%5Cfrac%7Bc_0+-+c_1%7D%7B2%5En%7D%2C+++&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle    a(G) = \frac{c_0 - c_1}{2^n},   "/></p>
<p>
where <img alt="{c_0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc_0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c_0}"/> is the number of black-and-white 2-colorings that make an even number of edges have both nodes colored black, and <img alt="{c_1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc_1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c_1}"/> for an odd number. </p>
<p>
There does not seem to be a simple recursion for <img alt="{a(G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%28G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a(G)}"/> from <img alt="{G \setminus e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%5Csetminus+e%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G \setminus e}"/> and <img alt="{G/e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%2Fe%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G/e}"/>. We can, however, obtain one by using another kind of contraction that adds a loop at the combined vertex:</p>
<p><img alt="inchworm_contraction" class="aligncenter wp-image-16006" height="128" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/inchworm_contraction.png?w=250&amp;h=128" width="250"/></p>
<p>
We denote this by <img alt="{G/\!/e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%2F%5C%21%2Fe%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G/\!/e}"/>. We have not found a simple reference for this. We obtain the following recursive formula:</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle    a(G) = a(G\backslash e) + \frac{1}{2}a(G/\!/e) - \frac{1}{2}a(G/e).   " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++++a%28G%29+%3D+a%28G%5Cbackslash+e%29+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7Da%28G%2F%5C%21%2Fe%29+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7Da%28G%2Fe%29.+++&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle    a(G) = a(G\backslash e) + \frac{1}{2}a(G/\!/e) - \frac{1}{2}a(G/e).   "/></p>
<p>
This recursion allows <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/> to be a bridge, so the base cases are <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/> for an isolated vertex and <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0}"/> for a loop. More generally, the basis is <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/> for a node with an even number of loops, <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0}"/> for odd. Here is an example for the ‘star graph’ <img alt="{S_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S_4}"/> on 4 vertices:</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<img alt="starGraph" class="aligncenter wp-image-16007" height="294" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/stargraph.png?w=520&amp;h=294" width="520"/></p>
<p/><p><br/>
The diagram would need another layer to get down to (products of) base cases, which we have shortcut by putting values of <img alt="{a(H)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%28H%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a(H)}"/> for each graph <img alt="{H}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BH%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{H}"/> at a leaf. Adding the products over all branches gives <img alt="{a(G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%28G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a(G)}"/>. For the star graph,</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle    a(S_4) = \frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{4} - \frac{1}{4} + \frac{1}{4} + \frac{1}{8} - \frac{1}{8} - \frac{1}{4} - \frac{1}{8} + \frac{1}{8} = \frac{1}{2}.   " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++++a%28S_4%29+%3D+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B4%7D+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B4%7D+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B4%7D+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B8%7D+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B8%7D+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B4%7D+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B8%7D+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B8%7D+%3D+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D.+++&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle    a(S_4) = \frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{4} - \frac{1}{4} + \frac{1}{4} + \frac{1}{8} - \frac{1}{8} - \frac{1}{4} - \frac{1}{8} + \frac{1}{8} = \frac{1}{2}.   "/></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Clearly this brute-force recursion grows as <img alt="{3^n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B3%5En%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{3^n}"/>. This is slower than the order-<img alt="{2^n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5En%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^n}"/> time of using the coloring definition directly, but what all this underscores is how singular it is to be able to compute <img alt="{a(G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%28G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a(G)}"/> in polynomial time, indeed <img alt="{O(n^\omega)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E%5Comega%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n^\omega)}"/> time. The search for a more-efficient recursion, one that might apply to <img alt="{\mathsf{NP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BNP%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{NP}}"/>-hard quantities, leads us to consider a more-drastic operation on edges.</p>
<p/><h2> Exploding Edges </h2><p/>
<p>
The new recursion operation is well illustrated by this figure:</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<img alt="explosionSolo" class="aligncenter wp-image-16008" height="203" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/explosionsolo.png?w=300&amp;h=203" width="300"/></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Two vertices disappear, not just one. Not only does the edge <img alt="{e = (u,v)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be+%3D+%28u%2Cv%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e = (u,v)}"/> disappear, but any other edge incident to <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> or <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> from a vertex <img alt="{w \neq u,v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw+%5Cneq+u%2Cv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w \neq u,v}"/> gets “recoiled” into a loop at <img alt="{w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bw%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{w}"/>. We denote this operation by <img alt="{G \backslash\!\backslash e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%5Cbackslash%5C%21%5Cbackslash+e%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G \backslash\!\backslash e}"/> to connote that <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/> is not just deleted but “exploded.” </p>
<p>
Properly speaking, we need to specify what happens if there are other edges between <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> and <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> or loops at <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> or <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/>. In an upcoming post we will see that those become <em>circles</em> in a <em>graphical polymatroid</em> which generalizes the notion of a graph. For now, however, it suffices to let <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> be the total number of vaporized edges, including <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/>. Then we obtain a two-term recursive formula:</p>
<p><a name="expl"/></p><a name="expl">
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle    a(G) = a(G \backslash e) + \frac{(-1)^r}{2} a(G\backslash \!\backslash e).   \ \ \ \ \ (1)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++++a%28G%29+%3D+a%28G+%5Cbackslash+e%29+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B%28-1%29%5Er%7D%7B2%7D+a%28G%5Cbackslash+%5C%21%5Cbackslash+e%29.+++%5C+%5C+%5C+%5C+%5C+%281%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle    a(G) = a(G \backslash e) + \frac{(-1)^r}{2} a(G\backslash \!\backslash e).   \ \ \ \ \ (1)"/></p>
</a><p><a name="expl"/></p>
<p>
The base cases for isolated vertices are the same as before, but explosion also needs a base case for pure emptiness. This contributes <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/>. In the following example diagram, for the path graph <img alt="{P_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P_4}"/> on four nodes, we denote such base cases by `w’ for “wisp”:</p>
<p><img alt="P3explosion" class="aligncenter wp-image-16009" height="291" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/06/p3explosion.png?w=450&amp;h=291" width="450"/></p>
<p>
Note again the rule that when the recursion disconnects the graph, the component values multiply together. Thus the value is</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle    a(P_4) = (1 - \frac{1}{2})(1 - \frac{1}{2}) - 0 = \frac{1}{4}.   " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++++a%28P_4%29+%3D+%281+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%29%281+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%29+-+0+%3D+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B4%7D.+++&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle    a(P_4) = (1 - \frac{1}{2})(1 - \frac{1}{2}) - 0 = \frac{1}{4}.   "/></p>
<p>
This is different from the amplitude <img alt="{\frac{1}{2}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\frac{1}{2}}"/> of the star graph. What this means is that <img alt="{a(G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%28G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a(G)}"/> does not obey the rules of the Tutte polynomial, which is the same for both of these 4-vertex trees. </p>
<p>
To prove the recursion equation (<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/#expl">1</a>), for <img alt="{e = (u,v)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be+%3D+%28u%2Cv%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e = (u,v)}"/>, note that every coloring has the same odd/even parity of black-black edges for <img alt="{G\setminus e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%5Csetminus+e%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G\setminus e}"/> as for <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> except those that color both <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> and <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> black. Let <img alt="{c_0^{uv}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc_0%5E%7Buv%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c_0^{uv}}"/> denote the colorings among the latter that make an even number of black-black edges (including <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/>) overall, <img alt="{c_1^{uv}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc_1%5E%7Buv%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c_1^{uv}}"/> for an odd number. Then</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle    a(G) = a(G \setminus e) + \frac{2}{2^n}(c_1^{uv} - c_0^{uv}).   " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++++a%28G%29+%3D+a%28G+%5Csetminus+e%29+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B2%7D%7B2%5En%7D%28c_1%5E%7Buv%7D+-+c_0%5E%7Buv%7D%29.+++&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle    a(G) = a(G \setminus e) + \frac{2}{2^n}(c_1^{uv} - c_0^{uv}).   "/></p>
<p>
Now if there are no other edges between or loops at <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> and <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/>, then <img alt="{c_1^{uv}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc_1%5E%7Buv%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c_1^{uv}}"/> is the same as the number of colorings of <img alt="{G \backslash\!\backslash e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%5Cbackslash%5C%21%5Cbackslash+e%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G \backslash\!\backslash e}"/> that make an even number of black-black edges, and <img alt="{c_0^{uv}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc_0%5E%7Buv%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c_0^{uv}}"/> becomes the odd case in <img alt="{G \backslash\!\backslash e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%5Cbackslash%5C%21%5Cbackslash+e%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G \backslash\!\backslash e}"/> again because we subtracted <img alt="{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e}"/>. Considering the sign change from other <img alt="{(u,v)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28u%2Cv%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(u,v)}"/> edges or loops and <img alt="{\frac{2}{2^n} = \frac{1/2}{2^{n-2}}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7B2%7D%7B2%5En%7D+%3D+%5Cfrac%7B1%2F2%7D%7B2%5E%7Bn-2%7D%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\frac{2}{2^n} = \frac{1/2}{2^{n-2}}}"/> yields equation (<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/#expl">1</a>).  It is also possible to “explode” a loop, and our readers may enjoy figuring out how to define it.</p>
<p/><h2> The Amplitude Polynomial </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We can expand on this by defining a polynomial <img alt="{Q_G(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BQ_G%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{Q_G(x)}"/> such that <img alt="{a(G) = Q_G(1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%28G%29+%3D+Q_G%281%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a(G) = Q_G(1)}"/>. The base cases are <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> for an isolated vertex but still <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/> for a “wisp” and <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0}"/> for a loop. The basis extends to give <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> for an isolated node with an even number of loops and <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0}"/> for odd. Another way to put it is that two edges with the same endpoints, or two loops at the same node, can be removed. The above diagram shows that for the path graph <img alt="{P_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P_4}"/>,</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle    Q_{P_4}(x) = (x^2 - \frac{1}{2})^2 = x^4 - x^2 + \frac{1}{4}.   " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++++Q_%7BP_4%7D%28x%29+%3D+%28x%5E2+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%29%5E2+%3D+x%5E4+-+x%5E2+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B4%7D.+++&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle    Q_{P_4}(x) = (x^2 - \frac{1}{2})^2 = x^4 - x^2 + \frac{1}{4}.   "/></p>
<p>
Whereas, the recursion for the star graph—noting that the “star” <img alt="{S_2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS_2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S_2}"/> on two nodes is just a single edge—gives:</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}    Q_{S_4}(x) &amp;=&amp; xQ_{S_3}(x) - \frac{1}{2}0\\   &amp;=&amp; x^2 Q_{S_2}(x) - \frac{1}{2}0 - \frac{1}{2}0\\   &amp;=&amp; x^4 - x^2 \frac{1}{2}(1\!\cdot\! 1) - \frac{1}{2}0 - \frac{1}{2}0 = x^4 - \frac{1}{2}x^2.   \end{array} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Brcl%7D++++Q_%7BS_4%7D%28x%29+%26%3D%26+xQ_%7BS_3%7D%28x%29+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D0%5C%5C+++%26%3D%26+x%5E2+Q_%7BS_2%7D%28x%29+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D0+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D0%5C%5C+++%26%3D%26+x%5E4+-+x%5E2+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%281%5C%21%5Ccdot%5C%21+1%29+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D0+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D0+%3D+x%5E4+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7Dx%5E2.+++%5Cend%7Barray%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}    Q_{S_4}(x) &amp;=&amp; xQ_{S_3}(x) - \frac{1}{2}0\\   &amp;=&amp; x^2 Q_{S_2}(x) - \frac{1}{2}0 - \frac{1}{2}0\\   &amp;=&amp; x^4 - x^2 \frac{1}{2}(1\!\cdot\! 1) - \frac{1}{2}0 - \frac{1}{2}0 = x^4 - \frac{1}{2}x^2.   \end{array} "/></p>
<p>
This is not the same polynomial as <img alt="{Q_{P_4}(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BQ_%7BP_4%7D%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{Q_{P_4}(x)}"/>, again implying that <img alt="{Q_G(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BQ_G%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{Q_G(x)}"/> is not a specialization of the Tutte polynomial. We will show in the last post in this series that <img alt="{Q_G(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BQ_G%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{Q_G(x)}"/> does specialize the polynomial <img alt="{S_G(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS_G%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S_G(x,y)}"/> introduced in this 1993 <a href="http://homepages.mcs.vuw.ac.nz/~whittle/pubs/Tutte_invariants_of_2-polymatroids.pdf">paper</a> titled, “A Characterization of Tutte Invariants of 2-Polymatroids” and covered further in this 2006 <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/49399603_Evaluating_the_Rank_Generating_Function_of_a_Graphic_2-Polymatroid">paper</a>.</p>
<p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>
What other rules does our “amplitude polynomial” follow?  We will explore this in the mentioned upcoming post.  What other quantities can it be made to count?</p>
<p>
What we called “explosion” is in fact attested as the natural form of <em>contraction</em> for the <b>polymatroids</b> considered in these papers. What further uses might “explosion” have in graph theory apart from polymatroids?</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-17T08:27:09Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-17T08:27:09Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="algebra"/>
    <category term="graph theory"/>
    <category term="graphs"/>
    <category term="polynomials"/>
    <category term="quantum"/>
    <category term="Tutte polynomial"/>
    <category term="William Tutte"/>
    <author>
      <name>Chaowen Guan and K.W. Regan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:20:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>http://offconvex.github.io/2019/06/16/modeconnectivity/</id>
    <link href="http://offconvex.github.io/2019/06/16/modeconnectivity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Landscape Connectivity of Low Cost Solutions for Multilayer Nets</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A big mystery about deep learning is how, in a highly nonconvex loss landscape, gradient descent often finds near-optimal solutions —those with training cost almost zero— even starting from a random initialization. This conjures an image of a landscape filled with deep pits.  Gradient descent started at a random point falls easily to the bottom of the nearest pit. In this mental image the pits are disconnected from each other, so there is no way to go from the bottom of one pit to bottom of another without going through regions of high cost.</p>

<p>The current post is about our <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.06247">new paper with Rohith Kuditipudi, Xiang Wang, Holden Lee, Yi Zhang, Wei Hu, Zhiyuan Li and Sanjeev Arora</a> which provides a mathematical explanation of  the following surprising phenomenon reported last year.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Mode connectivity</strong> (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1611.01540">Freeman and Bruna, 2016</a>, <a href="https://papers.nips.cc/paper/8095-loss-surfaces-mode-connectivity-and-fast-ensembling-of-dnns.pdf">Garipov et al. 2018</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.00885">Draxler et al. 2018</a>) All pairs of low-cost solutions found via gradient descent  can actually be connected by simple paths in the parameter space, such that every point on the path is another solution of almost the same cost. In fact the low-cost path connecting two near-optima  can be <em>piecewise linear</em> with two line-segments, or a Bezier curve.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>See Figure 1 below from <a href="https://papers.nips.cc/paper/8095-loss-surfaces-mode-connectivity-and-fast-ensembling-of-dnns.pdf">Garipov et al. 2018</a> for an illustration. Solutions A and B have low cost but the line connecting them goes through solutions with high cost. But we can find C of low cost such that paths AC and CB only pass through low-cost region.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<img src="http://www.offconvex.org/assets/modes.PNG" style="width: 300px;"/>
<br/>
<b>Figure 1</b> Mode Connectivity. Warm colors represent low loss. 
</div>

<p>Using a very simple example let us see that this phenomenon is highly counterintuitive. Suppose we’re talking about 2-layer nets with linear activations and a real-valued output. Let the two nets $\theta_A$ and 
$\theta_B$  with zero loss be
<br/>
respectively where $x, U_1, U_2 \in \Re^n$
and matrices $W_1, W_2$ are $n\times n$. Then the straight line connecting them in parameter space corresponds to nets of the type $(\alpha U_1 + (1-\alpha)U_2)^\top(\alpha W_1 + (1-\alpha)W_2)$ which can be rewritten as</p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<img src="http://www.offconvex.org/assets/hybridnet.jpg" style="width: 650px;"/> 
</div>

<p>Note that the middle terms correspond to putting the top layer of one net on top of the bottom of the other, which in general is a nonsensical net (reminiscent of a <em>centaur</em>, a mythical half-man half-beast) that in general would be expected to have high loss.</p>

<p>Originally we figured mode connectivity would not be mathematically understood for a long time, because of the seeming difficulty of proving any mathematical theorems  about, say, $50$-layer nets trained on ImageNet data, and in particular dealing with such “centaur-like” nets in the interpolation.</p>

<p>Several authors (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1611.01540">Freeman and Bruna, 2016</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1802.06384">Venturi et al. 2018</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.00909">Liang et al. 2018</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1809.10749">Nguyen et al. 2018</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07417">Nguyen et al. 2019</a>) did try to explain the phenomenon of mode connectivity in simple settings (the first of these demonstrated mode connectivity empirically for multi-layer nets). But these explanations only work for very unrealistic 2-layer nets (or multi-layer nets with special structure) which are highly redundant e.g., the number of neurons may have to be larger than the number of training samples.</p>

<p>Our paper starts by clarifying an important point: redundancy with respect to a ground truth neural network is  insufficient for mode connectivity, which we show via a simple counterexample sketched below.</p>

<p>Thus to explain mode connectivity for multilayer nets we  will need to leverage some stronger property of <em>typical</em> solutions discovered via gradient-based training, as we will see below.</p>

<h2 id="mode-connectivity-need-not-hold-for-2-layer-overparametrized-nets">Mode Connectivity need not hold for 2-layer overparametrized nets</h2>

<p>We show that the strongest version of mode connectivity (every two minimizers are connected) does not hold even for a simple two-layer setting, where $f(x) = W_2\sigma(W_1x)$, even where the net is vastly overparametrized than it needs to be for the dataset in question.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem</strong> For any $h&gt;1$ there exists a data set which is perfectly fitted by  a ground truth neural network with $2$ layers and only $2$ hidden neurons, but if we desire to train neural network with $h$ hidden units on this dataset then the set of global minimizers are not connected.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="stability-properties-of-typical-nets">Stability properties of typical nets</h2>

<p>Since mode connectivity has been found to hold for a range of architectures and datasets, any explanation probably should only rely upon properties that <em>generically</em> seem to hold for deep net standard training. Our explanation relies upon properties that were discovered in recent years in the effort to understand the generalization properties of deep nets.  These properties say that the output of the final net is stable to various kinds of added noise.
The properties imply that the loss function does not change much when the net parameters are perturbed; this is informally described as the net being a <em>flat minimum</em> (<a href="https://www.cs.toronto.edu/~hinton/absps/colt93.html">Hinton and Van Camp 1993</a>).</p>

<p>Our explanation of mode connectivity will involve the following two properties.</p>

<h3 id="noise-stability-and-dropout-stability">Noise stability and Dropout Stability</h3>

<p><em>Dropout</em> was introduced by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0580">Hinton et al. 2012</a>: during gradient-based training, one  zeroes out the output of $50\%$ of the nodes, and doubles the output of the remaining nodes. The gradient used in the next update is computed for this net. While dropout may not be as popular these days, it can be added to any existing net training without loss of generality. We’ll say a net is “$\epsilon$-dropout stable” if applying dropout to $50\%$ of the nodes increases its loss by at most $\epsilon$. Note that unlike dropout training where nodes are <em>randomly</em> dropped out, in our definition a network is dropout stable as long as there <em>exists</em> a way of dropping out $50\%$ of the nodes that does not increase its loss by too much.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem 1:</strong> If two trained multilayer ReLU nets with the same architecture  are $\epsilon$-dropout stable, then they can be connected in the loss landscape via a piece-wise linear path in which the number of linear segments is linear in the number of layers, and the loss of every point on the path is at most $\epsilon$ higher than the loss of the two end points.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>Noise stability</em> was discovered by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1802.05296">Arora et al. ICML18</a>; this   was described in a <a href="http://www.offconvex.org/2018/02/17/generalization2/">previous blog post</a>. They found that trained nets are very stable to noise injection: if one adds a fairly large Gaussian noise vector to the output of a layer, then this has only a small effect on the output of higher layers. In other words, the network <em>rejects</em> the injected noise. That paper showed that noise stability can be used to prove that the net is compressible. Thus noise stability is indeed a form of redundancy in the net.</p>

<p>In the new paper we show that a minor variant of the noise stability property (which we empirically find to still hold in trained nets) implies dropout stability. More importantly, solutions satisfying this property can be connected using a piecewise linear path with at most $10$ segments.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem 2:</strong> If two trained multilayer ReLU nets with the same architecture are $\epsilon$-noise stable, then they can be connected in the loss landscape via a piece-wise linear path with at most 10 segments, and the loss of every point on the path is at most $\epsilon$ higher than the loss of the two end points.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="proving-mode-connectivity-for-dropout-stable-nets">Proving mode connectivity for dropout-stable nets</h2>
<p>We exhibit the main ideas by proving mode connectivity for  fully connected nets that are dropout-stable, meaning training loss is stable to dropping out $50\%$ of the nodes.</p>

<p>Let $W_1,W_2,…,W_p$ be the weight matrices of the neural network, so the function that is computed by the network is $f(x) = W_p\sigma(\cdots \sigma(W_2(\sigma(W_1x)))\cdots)$. Here $\sigma$ is the ReLU activation (our result in this section works for any activations). We use $\theta = (W_1,W_2,…,W_p)\in \Theta$ to denote the parameters for the neural network. Given a set of data points $(x_i,y_i)~i=1,2,…,n$, the empirical loss $L$ is just an average of the losses for the individual samples $L(\theta) = \frac{1}{n}\sum_{i=1}^n l(y_i, f_\theta(x_i))$. The function $l(y, \hat{y})$ is a loss function that is convex in the second parameter (popular loss functions such as cross-entropy or mean-squared-error are all in this category).</p>

<p>Using this notation, Theorem 1 can be restated as:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem 1 (restated)</strong> Let $\theta_A$ and $\theta_B$ be two solutions that are both $\epsilon$-dropout stable, then there exists a path $\pi:[0,1]\to \Theta$ such that $\pi(0) = \theta_A$, $\pi(1) = \theta_B$ and for any $t\in(0,1)$ the loss $L(\pi(t)) \le \max{L(\theta_A), L(\theta_B)} + \epsilon$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To prove this theorem, the major step is to connect a network with its dropout version where half of the neurons are not used (see next part). Then intuitively it is not too difficult to connect two dropout versions as they both have a large number of inactive neurons.</p>

<p>As we discussed before, directly interpolating between two networks may not work as it give rise to <em>centaur-like</em> networks.  A key idea in this simpler theorem is that each linear segment in the path involves varying the parameters of only one layer, which allows careful control of this issue. (Proof of Theorem 2 is more complicated because the number of layers in the net are allowed to exceed the number of path segments.)</p>

<p>As a simple example, we show how to connect a 3-layer neural network with its dropout version. (The same idea can be easily extended to more layers by a simple induction on number of layers.) Assume without loss of generality that we are going to dropout the second half of neurons for both hidden layers. For the weight matrices $W_3, W_2, W_1$, we will write them in block form: $W_3$ is a $1\times 2$ block matrix $W_3 = [L_3, R_3]$, $W_2$ is a $2\times 2$ block matrix $W_2 = \left[L_2, C_2; D_2, R_2 \right]$, and $W_1$ is a $2\times 1$ block matrix $W_1 = \left[L_1; B_1\right]$ (here ; represents the end of a row). The dropout stable property implies that the networks with weights $(W_3, W_2, W_1)$, $(2[L_3, 0], W_2, W_1)$, $([2L_3, 0], [2L_2, 0; 0, 0], W_1)$ all have low loss (these weights correspond to the cases of no dropout, dropout only applied to the top hidden layer and dropout applied to both hidden layers). Note that the final set of weights $([2L_3, 0], [2L_2, 0; 0, 0], W_1)$ is equivalent to $([2L_3, 0], [2L_2, 0; 0, 0], [L_1; 0])$ as the output from the $B_1$ part of $W_1$ has no connections. The path we construct is illustrated in Figure 2 below:
As a simple example, we show how to connect a 3-layer neural network with its dropout version. (The same idea can be easily extended to more layers by a simple induction on number of layers.) Assume without loss of generality that we are going to dropout the second half of neurons for both hidden layers. For the weight matrices $W_3, W_2, W_1$, we will write them in block form: $W_3$ is a $1\times 2$ block matrix $W_3 = [L_3, R_3]$, $W_2$ is a $2\times 2$ block matrix $W_2 = \left[L_2, C_2; D_2, R_2 \right]$, and $W_1$ is a $2\times 1$ block matrix $W_1 = \left[L_1; B_1\right]$ (here ; represents the end of a row). The dropout stable property implies that the networks with weights $(W_3, W_2, W_1)$, $(2[L_3, 0], W_2, W_1)$, $([2L_3, 0], [2L_2, 0; 0, 0], W_1)$ all have low loss (these weights correspond to the cases of no dropout, dropout only applied to the top hidden layer and dropout applied to both hidden layers). Note that the final set of weights $([2L_3, 0], [2L_2, 0; 0, 0], W_1)$ is equivalent to $([2L_3, 0], [2L_2, 0; 0, 0], [L_1; 0])$ as the output from the $B_1$ part of $W_1$ has no connections. The path we construct is illustrated in Figure 2 below:</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<img src="http://www.offconvex.org/assets/path.png" style="width: 400px;"/> <br/>
<b>Figure 2</b> Path from a 3-layer neural network to its dropout version.
</div>

<p>We use two types of steps to construct the path: (a) Since the loss function is convex in the weight of the top layer, we can interpolate between two different networks that only differ in top layer weights; (b) if a set of neurons already has 0 output weights, then we can set its input weights arbitrarily.</p>

<p>Figure 2 shows how to alternate between these two types of steps to connect a 3-layer network to its dropout version. The red color highlights weights that have changed. In the case of type (a) steps, the red color only appears in the top layer weights; in the case of type (b) steps, the 0 matrices highlighted by the green color are the 0 output weights, where because of these 0 matrices setting the red blocks to any matrix will not change the output of the neural network.</p>

<p>The crux of this construction appears in steps (3) and (4). When we are going from (2) to (3), we changed the bottom rows of $W_2$ from $[D_2, R_2]$ to $[2L_2, 0]$. This is a type (b) step, and because currently the top-level weight is $[2L_3, 0]$, changing the bottom row of $W_2$ has no effect on the output of the neural network. However, making this change allows us to do the interpolation between (3) and (4), as now the two networks only differ in the top layer weights. The loss is bounded because the weights in (3) are equivalent to $(2[L_3, 0], W_2, W_1)$ (weights with dropout applied to top hidden layer), and the weights in (4) are equivalent to $([2L_3, 0], [2L_2, 0; 0, 0], W_1)$ (weights with dropout applied to both hidden layers). The same procedure can be repeated if the network has more layers.</p>

<p>The number of line segments in the path is linear in the number of layers. As mentioned, the paper also gives stronger results assuming noise stability, where we can actually consruct a path with constant number of line segments.</p>

<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>

<p>Our results are a first-cut explanation for how mode connectivity can arise in realistic deep nets. Our methods do not answer all mysteries about mode connectivity. In particular, in many cases (especially when the number of parameters is not as large) the solutions found in practice are not as robust as we require in our theorems (either in terms of dropout stability or noise stability), yet empirically it is still possible to find simple paths connecting the solutions. Are there other properties satisfied by these solutions that allow them to be connected? Also, our results can be extended to convolutional neural networks via <em>channel-wise dropout</em>, where one randomly turn off half of the channels (this was considered before in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1411.4280">Thompson et al. 2015</a>,<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1812.03965">Keshari et al.2018</a>). While it is possible to train networks that are robust to channel-wise dropout, standard networks or even the ones trained with standard dropout do not satisfy this property.</p>

<p>It would also be interesting to utilize the insights into the landscape given by our explanation to design better training algorithms.</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-16T22:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-16T22:00:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>http://offconvex.github.io/</id>
      <author>
        <name>Off the Convex Path</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://offconvex.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://offconvex.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Algorithms off the convex path.</subtitle>
      <title>Off the convex path</title>
      <updated>2019-06-20T23:31:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/088</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/088" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-088 |  On the Complexity of Estimating the Effective Support Size | 

	Oded Goldreich</title>
    <summary>Loosely speaking, the effective support size of a distribution is the size of the support of a distribution that is close to it (in totally variation distance). 
We study the complexity of estimating the effective support size of an unknown distribution when given samples of the distributions as well as an evaluation oracle (which returns the probability that the queried element appears in the distribution).
In this context, we present several algorithms that exhibit a trade-off between the quality of the approximation and the complexity of obtaining it, and leave open the question of their optimality.</summary>
    <updated>2019-06-16T15:33:01Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-16T15:33:01Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:20:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:typepad.com,2003:post-6a00d83452383469e20240a466212d200c</id>
    <link href="https://3dpancakes.typepad.com/ernie/2019/06/buy-my-free-book.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://3dpancakes.typepad.com/ernie/2019/06/buy-my-free-book.html" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Buy My Free Book!</title>
    <summary>I'm happy to finally announce the publication of an actual dead-tree paperback edition of my Algorithms textbook. The book can be purchased from Amazon (US, UK, DE, ES, FR, IT, JP), for the ludicrous price of $27.50 (or the equivalent...</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a class="asset-img-link" href="https://3dpancakes.typepad.com/.a/6a00d83452383469e20240a48f6b37200d-popup"><img alt="Al-khwarizmi" class="asset  asset-image at-xid-6a00d83452383469e20240a48f6b37200d img-responsive" src="https://3dpancakes.typepad.com/.a/6a00d83452383469e20240a48f6b37200d-500wi" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" title="Al-khwarizmi"/></a></p>
<p>I'm happy to finally announce the publication of an actual dead-tree paperback edition of my <em>Algorithms</em> textbook.  The book can be purchased from Amazon (<a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/1792644833">US</a>, <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/1792644833">UK</a>, <a href="https://www.amazon.de/dp/1792644833">DE</a>, <a href="https://www.amazon.es/dp/1792644833">ES</a>, <a href="https://www.amazon.fr/dp/1792644833">FR</a>, <a href="https://www.amazon.it/dp/1792644833">IT</a>, <a href="https://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/1792644833">JP</a>), for the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ygE01sOhzz0">ludicrous</a> price of $27.50 (or the equivalent in pounds, euros, and yen).</p>
<p>I've also updated the freely available, full-color electronic version at <a href="http://algorithms.wtf/">http://algorithms.wtf</a>; this electronic version will remain free indefinitely.  The same site includes several additional lecture notes and other course materials.</p>
<p>Thanks to everyone who reported dozens of errors in the 0th and ½th edition on the <a href="https://github.com/jeffgerickson/algorithms">Github issue-tracker</a>.  Please keep the bug reports and feature requests coming!</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-15T20:29:59Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-15T20:29:59Z</published>
    <category term="Algorithms"/>
    <category term="Books"/>
    <category term="Writing"/>
    <category term="algorithms"/>
    <category term="textbook"/>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Erickson</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:typepad.com,2003:weblog-6686</id>
      <link href="https://3dpancakes.typepad.com/ernie/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://3dpancakes.typepad.com/ernie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Let Σ be a combinatorial surface with n vertices, genus g, and b boundaries.  Amen.</subtitle>
      <title>Ernie's 3D Pancakes</title>
      <updated>2019-06-15T20:29:59Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/06/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/06/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage for the end of an academic year</title>
    <summary>The Spring term just ended at UCI (we’re on a quarter system, so we run later into June and then start up again later in September than most other US universities). I haven’t yet turned in my grades, but I can already feel summer setting in.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Spring term just ended at UCI (we’re on a quarter system, so we run later into June and then start up again later in September than most other US universities). I haven’t yet turned in my grades, but I can already feel summer setting in.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://hackaday.com/2019/06/01/paper-strandbeest-is-strong-enough-to-walk/">Remote-controlled papercraft steerable Strandbeest</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102197633382208469"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20068166">via</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BaSVpX_nMpU/">Voronoi origami</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102206289543572358"/>, <a href="http://orderinspace.blogspot.com/2015/07/voronoi.html">see also</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://archive.org/details/@mirtitles">Mir Books</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102212071495683563"/>, <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@jarban/102209797748141088">via</a>). A big collection of interesting-looking Soviet-era mathematics and science books and booklets, translated into English and free to read.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathenchant.wordpress.com/2017/09/17/how-do-you-write-one-hundred-in-base-32/">Chip-firing games and sesquinary notation</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102217258990536291"/>). Jim Propp writes a monthly long-form math blog and somehow I hadn’t encountered it before; this is one of its many interesting entries. One of the oddities about base  is that you calculate it bottom-up (by starting from a ones digit that’s too big and then carrying things higher) instead of top-down (by greedily subtracting powers).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@JordiGH/102226037720885699">A discussion on whether proofs in Wikipedia articles need references</a>, and what those references are for.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://theinnerframe.wordpress.com/2018/07/16/death-of-proof-the-pleasures-of-failure-i/">The tale of Horgan’s surface</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102228263549241096"/>, <a href="https://mathenchant.wordpress.com/2019/06/06/carnival-of-mathematics-170/">via</a>, <a href="http://www.indiana.edu/~minimal/essays/horgan/index.html">see also</a>, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4133">see also</a>), a nonexistent minimal surface whose existence was incorrectly predicted by numerical experiments, named sarcastically after a journalist who incautiously suggested that proof was a dead concept.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.02231">Compact packings of the plane with three sizes of discs</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102240130646118434"/>), Thomas Fernique, Amir Hashemi, and Olga Sizova. Here, “compact packing” means interior-disjoint disks forming only 3-sided gaps. The circle packing theorem constructs these for any finite maximal planar graph, with little control over disk size. Instead this paper seeks packings of the whole plane by infinitely many disks, with few sizes. 9 pairs of sizes and 164 triples work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Luca Trevisan posts a series of tutorials on online convex optimization, where you want to approximately minimize a sequence of convex functions before discovering what the functions are (parts <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/04/17/online-optimization-for-complexity-theorists/"/>, <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/04/22/online-optimization-post-0-definitions/"/>, <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/04/24/online-optimization-post-1-multiplicative-weights/"/>, <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/04/25/online-optimization-post-2-constructing-pseudorandom-sets/"/>, <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/05/06/online-optimization-post-3-follow-the-regularized-leader/"/>, <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/05/16/online-optimization-post-4-regularity-lemmas/"/>, <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/05/20/online-optimization-post-5-bregman-projections-and-mirror-descent/"/>; <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102244702633232612"/>). It’s a hot topic in TCS with connections to regularity lemmas, fast SDP approximation, and spectral sparsifiers.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross_sea">Squared patterns of ocean waves</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102251731269228854"/>), and wave patterns in social media: search for “cross sea” and note its appearance on gizmodo in 2014, amusingplanet in 2015, azula in 2017, providr in 2018, sciencealert in 2019…all repeating the same somewhat garbled explanation of mathematical wave models and danger to shipping.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2019/06/11/wikipedia-edit-a-thon-at-stoc19/">The SIGACT Committee for the Advancement of Theoretical Computer Science is planning a Wikipedia edit-a-thon, in Phoenix on June 24 as part of STOC</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102262460312659446"/>). You can help, and you don’t even have to brave the desert heat to do so! There’s <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2017/05/02/tcs-wikipedia-project/">a shared spreadsheet</a> where CATCS is crowdsourcing TCS topics on Wikipedia that need help. Add your favorite missing algorithm, theorem, complexity class, etc, and it’s likely it’ll get some attention.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>While I’m publicizing activities associated with STOC and FCRC next week in Phoenix, here’s another: <a href="https://sigact.org/tcswomen/tcs-women-2019/">the TCS Women Spotlight Workshop</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102266092255364896"/>). It features an inspirational talk from Ronitt Rubinfeld (in my experience a great speaker), four “rising star” talks by Naama Ben-David, Debarati Das, Andrea Lincoln, and Oxana Poburinnaya, a panel/lunch for women at STOC, and a poster session of recent theoretical computer science research by women.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Two colleagues from my department, Alex Nicolau and Alex Veidenbaum, are participating in <a href="http://artdaily.com/news/114313/University-of-California--Irvine-computer-scientists-breathe-life-into-Venice-Biennale-installations">a Venice Biennale project</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102272037129033816"/>) in which viewers converse with computerized simulations of poet <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Celan">Paul Celan</a> and politician <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolae_Ceau%C8%99escu">Nicolae Ceaușescu</a>.
The Alexes usually work on the more technical side of CS (parallelizing compilers, computer architecture, and embedded systems) so it’s interesting to me to see this softer direction from them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-01796-1"><em>Nature</em> on how word processors and text editors have been shifting from roll-your-own equation editing to LaTeX</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102277832022967684"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20191348">via</a>).</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-15T17:58:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-15T17:58:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T00:20:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/14/3rd-symposium-on-simplicity-in-algorithms/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/14/3rd-symposium-on-simplicity-in-algorithms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>3rd Symposium on Simplicity in Algorithms</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">January 6-7, 2020 Salt Lake City, UT https://www.siam.org/Conferences/CM/Conference/sosa20 Submission deadline: August 9, 2019 Symposium on Simplicity in Algorithms is a new conference in theoretical computer science dedicated to advancing algorithms research by promoting simplicity and elegance in the design and analysis of algorithms. The benefits of simplicity are manifold: simpler algorithms manifest a better understanding … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/14/3rd-symposium-on-simplicity-in-algorithms/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">3rd Symposium on Simplicity in Algorithms</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-14T04:09:04Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-14T04:09:04Z</published>
    <category term="other"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:22:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/13/5th-algorithmic-and-enumerative-combinatorics-summer-school-2019-2/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/13/5th-algorithmic-and-enumerative-combinatorics-summer-school-2019-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>5th Algorithmic and Enumerative Combinatorics Summer School 2019</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">July 29 – August 2, 2019 Linz, Austria https://www3.risc.jku.at/conferences/aec2019/local.html Registration deadline: June 16, 2019 The goal of this summer school is to put forward the interplay between the fields of Enumerative Combinatorics, Analytic Combinatorics, and Algorithmics. This is a very active research area, which, aside from the three fields fueling each other mutually, receives as … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/13/5th-algorithmic-and-enumerative-combinatorics-summer-school-2019-2/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">5th Algorithmic and Enumerative Combinatorics Summer School 2019</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-13T22:21:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-13T22:21:19Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:22:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/13/adfocs-2019-games-brains-and-distributed-computing/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/13/adfocs-2019-games-brains-and-distributed-computing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>ADFOCS 2019 – Games, Brains, and Distributed Computing</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">August 19-23, 2019 Saarbrücken, Germany http://resources.mpi-inf.mpg.de/conferences/adfocs/ Registration deadline: July 19, 2019 ADFOCS is an international summer school held annually at the Max Planck Institute for Informatics (MPII). It is organized as part of the activities of the MPII, in particular the International Max-Planck Research School (IMPRS), MPII’s graduate program. The purpose of this summer school … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/06/13/adfocs-2019-games-brains-and-distributed-computing/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">ADFOCS 2019 – Games, Brains, and Distributed Computing</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-06-13T22:20:55Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-13T22:20:55Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-06-21T05:22:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
