<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-11-19T17:21:49Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6939903186223741314</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6939903186223741314/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/vaughan-jones-and-kaikoura.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6939903186223741314" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6939903186223741314" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/vaughan-jones-and-kaikoura.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Vaughan Jones and Kaikoura</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaughan_Jones">Vaughan Jones</a>, one of the greatest mathematicians from New Zealand, passed away on September 6 at 67. Jones is an expert in knot theory among other areas and received the Fields Medal in 1990.</p><p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jones_polynomial">Jones polynomial</a> captures information about knots. Vaughan Jones himself co-authored a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0511096">paper</a> on a polynomial-time quantum algorithm for approximating the Jones polynomial, one of the few natural problems outside of factoring that has an exponential improvement with a quantum algorithm. </p><p>From his Vanderbilt <a href="https://news.vanderbilt.edu/2020/09/09/vaughan-jones-preeminent-vanderbilt-mathematician-has-died/">obituary</a></p><blockquote><p>One way he worked to improve the field of mathematics in his native country was to organize a “summer school” in January each year and attract leading mathematicians from around the world to give lectures and interact with local students and professional mathematicians at a variety of beautiful locations around New Zealand. Out of this activity grew the New Zealand Mathematics Research Institute, which he co-founded and then led from the mid-1990s to this year.</p></blockquote><p>I had the pleasure of teaching in one of those summer schools in January 2000 in Kaikoura on the South Island. In between the whale watching, mountain hiking, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2008/09/jogging-on-trips.html">jogging</a>, gorging on mussels, and Maori ceremonies, the NZMRI summer school <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Aspects_of_Complexity/XlB_JTR0sV8C">Aspects of Complexity</a> had short courses to a mix of students and researchers in complexity and logic. I gave some <a href="https://lance.fortnow.com/papers/files/kaikoura.pdf">lectures</a> on Kolmogorov complexity that preceded a study of algorithmic randomness in the logic community. Other speakers included Eric Allender on basic complexity, Felipe Cucker on real computation, Mike Fellows on parameterized complexity, and Dominic Welsh on counting complexity. </p><p>It took me 36 hours door-to-door to get to Kaikoura but definitely worth it. Thanks to Vaughan Jones, for his research, his polynomial and creating a summer school that gave me that one perfect week in New Zealand.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-19T16:56:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-19T16:56:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:01:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7906</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/11/19/updated-research-masters-programs-database-by-aviad-rubinstein-and-matt-weinberg/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Updated Research Masters programs database by Aviad Rubinstein and Matt Weinberg</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Guest post by Aviad Rubinstein and Matt Weinberg As explained in Boaz’s previous posts [1] [2], the PhD admission process can be challenging for students who discover their passion for Theory of Computer Science late in their undergraduate studies. Discovering TCS earlier is especially challenging for students who aren’t exposed to CS in high school, … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/11/19/updated-research-masters-programs-database-by-aviad-rubinstein-and-matt-weinberg/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Updated Research Masters programs database by Aviad Rubinstein and Matt Weinberg</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Guest post by <a href="https://cs.stanford.edu/~aviad/">Aviad Rubinstein</a> and <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~smattw/">Matt Weinberg</a></p>



<p>As explained in Boaz’s previous posts <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/02/20/research-masters/">[1]</a> <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/07/02/crowdsourcing-masters-program/">[2]</a>, the PhD admission process can be challenging for students who discover their passion for Theory of Computer Science late in their undergraduate studies. Discovering TCS earlier is especially challenging for students who aren’t exposed to CS in high school, and this bias aggravates the diversity issues we have in our community. Masters programs are one way to mitigate this issue.<br/>On a personal note, one of us (Aviad), worked half-time during undergraduate and would not have been in academia today -let alone TCS of all subjects- if it weren’t for the awesome TCS masters program at Tel-Aviv University.</p>



<p><br/>But where would you go (or send your students) to do a masters in TCS?A little over a year ago, we were discussing how useful it would be to have a unified resource that can help students choose. We decided that we should create one! Months passed, and right before we ran out of excuses to procrastinate, Boaz made this <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/07/02/crowdsourcing-masters-program/">post</a> crowdsourcing information on TCS masters programs.<br/>After some more procrastination, we eventually did send a lot of emails and tried to clean and organize the information to the best of our ability. Thanks to everyone who contributed! You can find the latest version <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~smattw/masters/masters.html">here</a>. (Short url: <a href="http://tiny.cc/tcsmasters">http://tiny.cc/tcsmasters</a>)</p>



<p>Now you should share it with your brightest students!</p>



<p><br/>This is also meant to be a live project. Please email aviad [at] <a href="http://cs.stanford.edu/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">cs.stanford.edu</a> if you have more new information or find any inaccuracies.</p>



<p>Thanks!</p>



<p>-Aviad and Matt</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-19T14:40:09Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-19T14:40:09Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:21:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/19/assistant-professor-at-london-school-of-economics-and-political-science-apply-by-january-11-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/19/assistant-professor-at-london-school-of-economics-and-political-science-apply-by-january-11-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor at London School of Economics and Political Science (apply by January 11, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Mathematics at LSE seeks to appoint an Assistant Professor with expertise in a subject area related to the Mathematics of Game Theory. Website: https://tinyurl.com/MathJobLSE2020 Email: j.van-den-heuvel@lse.ac.uk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Mathematics at LSE seeks to appoint an Assistant Professor with expertise in a subject area related to the Mathematics of Game Theory.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://tinyurl.com/MathJobLSE2020">https://tinyurl.com/MathJobLSE2020</a><br/>
Email: j.van-den-heuvel@lse.ac.uk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-19T10:12:32Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-19T10:12:32Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17791</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/19/traveling-salesman-problem-meets-complexity-theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Traveling Salesman Problem Meets Complexity Theory</title>
    <summary>Crazy ideas meet crazed audience Merrill Flood was a mathematician who publicized the Traveling salesman problem TSP back in the 1940s. He says that he found the problem while: I was struggling with the problem in connecting with a school-bus routing study in New Jersey. Today I thought we might look at the TSP from […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Crazy ideas meet crazed audience</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/19/traveling-salesman-problem-meets-complexity-theory/flood/" rel="attachment wp-att-17793"><img alt="" class="alignright  wp-image-17751" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/flood.jpg?w=144" width="144"/></a></p>
<p>
Merrill Flood was a mathematician who publicized the Traveling salesman problem <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merrill_M._Flood">TSP</a> back in the 1940s.  </p>
<p>He says that he found the problem while: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\dots}"/> I was struggling with the problem in connecting with a school-bus routing study in New Jersey. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Today I thought we might look at the TSP from a viewpoint of complexity theory.</p>
<p>
First, we note that the origins of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travelling_salesman_problem">TSP</a> are unclear. In 1832 it was mentioned in a handbook for traveling salesmen in Germany and Switzerland. William Hamilton talked about the related problem later named for him: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> On finding a circuit through all points of graph. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Karl Menger, in the 1930s, defined the TSP, and considered the obvious brute-force algorithm, and observed the non-optimality of the nearest neighbor heuristic. We have annotated Wikipedia’s optimal-tour example to show (in blue) one case where a node is not connected to either of its two nearest neighbors in the tour and another where a mutual nearest-neighbor edge is not used in the optimal tour (the latter is a slight fib as-is but can be nudged, we believe): </p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/19/traveling-salesman-problem-meets-complexity-theory/tspwikimod/" rel="attachment wp-att-17815"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-17815" height="287" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/tspwikimod-1.png?w=300&amp;h=287" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Modern Times–Practice </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The TSP is now well known to be NP-complete thanks to Dick Karp’s brilliant work in the 1970s. Flood would be happy to hear—we believe—that there is now a computer program <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concorde_TSP_Solver">Concorde</a> that can solve TSP with many cites and get a nearly optimal solution. The authors of this program are: David Applegate, Robert Bixby, Vasek Chvatal, and William Cook. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Concorde has been applied to problems of gene mapping, protein function prediction, vehicle routing, conversion of bitmap images to continuous line drawings, scheduling ship movements for seismic surveys, and in studying the scaling properties of combinatorial optimization problems. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Modern Times–Theory </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Concorde’s solutions are guaranteed to be within 2-3% of optimal and have worked for problems with tens of thousand cities or more. A lot more than Flood considered. </p>
<p>
So why are we interested in the TSP still? A good question. </p>
<p>
The answer is not simple. In spite of the problem’s NP-completeness and widespread belief that P<img alt="{&lt;}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{&lt;}"/>NP we still do not know for sure. Could there be an algorithm that always solves TSP in polynomial time? We do not know. </p>
<p>
We also as complexity theorists want provable algorithms, want exact algorithms, or at least approximate algorithms with provable bounds. These are lacking. This is why we were excited by the <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/10/26/a-vast-and-tiny-breakthrough/">recent</a> result of a tiny improvement to the <img alt="{1.5}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1.5%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{1.5}"/> bound on TSP by Anna Karlin, Nathan Klein, and Shayan Oveis Gharan. </p>
<p>
Maybe we are crazy to be excited over a microscopic shaving off from <img alt="{1.5}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1.5%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{1.5}"/>.  But their result comes with new ideas, and since we don’t believe that <img alt="{1.5 - \epsilon}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1.5+-+%5Cepsilon%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{1.5 - \epsilon}"/> is Nature’s final answer, those ideas should yield further advances.  What we are really crazy over is new ideas, and that prompts us to attempt to find another in the rest of this post.  What complexity theorists do have more of than when Ken and I started is receptacles for new ideas, and we try for one in resource-bounded communication complexity.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Alice and Bob </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
In this spirit of craziness let’s take a complexity viewpoint of TSP. Let’s visit Alice and Bob. By the way I always have thought the invention of them by Ron Rivest, Adi Shamir, and Leonard Adleman in their 1978 RSA <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_and_Bob">paper</a> was important. This idea has probably helped improve exposition more than any other single idea. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> They Meet the TSP </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
So suppose that Alice and Bob are presented with a <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> city TSP. Further suppose that Alice can solve the TSP, but Bob like the rest of us cannot. An issue is: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Can Alice send a succinct message to Bob that allows him to find an optimal tour in polynomial time? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Without the word “succinct” there would be the simple answer of sending Bob her optimal tour. We will discuss a modest improvement: she can send half as many bits to Bob as it takes to describe the optimal tour. We suspect the following is known, but it suggests a possible interesting direction.</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 1 (Main)</b> <em> Alice can send Bob a message of <img alt="{\frac{n}{2} \lceil \log_{2}n \rceil}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bn%7D%7B2%7D+%5Clceil+%5Clog_%7B2%7Dn+%5Crceil%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\frac{n}{2} \lceil \log_{2}n \rceil}"/> bits, so that he can get an optimal TSP tour in polynomial time. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This theorem holds for general TSP: it can be asymmetric and need not satisfy the triangle inequality. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Proof </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
<em>Proof:</em>  Let’s assume that <img alt="{n=2m}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%3D2m%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n=2m}"/>; the argument is the essentially same if <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> is odd. </p>
<p>
Alice will first solve the TSP exactly. Assume she finds an optimal tour that visits the cities in order 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{2}, \dots, x_{n}, x_{1}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x_%7B1%7D%2C+x_%7B2%7D%2C+%5Cdots%2C+x_%7Bn%7D%2C+x_%7B1%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{2}, \dots, x_{n}, x_{1}. "/></p>
<p>To simply the notation let <img alt="{d(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{d(i,j)}"/> be the distance from <img alt="{x_{i}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_%7Bi%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{x_{i}}"/> to <img alt="{x_{j}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_%7Bj%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{x_{j}}"/>. Then let Alice send Bob the odd cities in order 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{3}, \dots, x_{2m-1}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x_%7B1%7D%2C+x_%7B3%7D%2C+%5Cdots%2C+x_%7B2m-1%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{3}, \dots, x_{2m-1}. "/></p>
<p>This message has the right length in bits of <img alt="{\frac{n}{2} \lceil \log_{2}n \rceil}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bn%7D%7B2%7D+%5Clceil+%5Clog_%7B2%7Dn+%5Crceil%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\frac{n}{2} \lceil \log_{2}n \rceil}"/>.</p>
<p>
Bob receives this message and creates the following bipartite graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/>: The left vertices are the cities 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x_{2}, x_{4}, \dots, x_{2m}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x_%7B2%7D%2C+x_%7B4%7D%2C+%5Cdots%2C+x_%7B2m%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x_{2}, x_{4}, \dots, x_{2m}. "/></p>
<p>The right vertices are 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{3}, \dots, x_{2m-1}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x_%7B1%7D%2C+x_%7B3%7D%2C+%5Cdots%2C+x_%7B2m-1%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{3}, \dots, x_{2m-1}. "/></p>
<p>
<img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> has edges connecting every left vertex to every right vertex; i.e., <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> is the complete bipartite graph.</p>
<p>
The first idea is that any perfect matching in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> extends uniquely to a tour, because Bob knows the order of the odd vertices in Alice’s tour.  That is, if <img alt="{(2k+1,2l)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%282k%2B1%2C2l%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{(2k+1,2l)}"/> is an edge in the tour, then Bob knows that the next edge goes to node <img alt="{2k+3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2k%2B3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{2k+3}"/> (modulo <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/>).</p>
<p>
The second idea—which is a caveat—is that an optimal matching under the graph’s original distance function might not produce Alice’s tour.  For this to be true, it would need to be the case that for every optimal tour, either one of the two perfect matchings it induces would need to be an optimal matching for the tour’s odd and even vertices.  An example where this fails is shown at lower left in our diagram above: The green edge is part of the optimal odd-even matching but is not in Alice’s optimal tour.</p>
<p>
The trick is to change the distance function to include the edge that Bob must add to the tour.  That is, we give the edge <img alt="{(2k+1,2l)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%282k%2B1%2C2l%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{(2k+1,2l)}"/> the cost 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  d(2k+1,2l) + d(2l,2k+3). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++d%282k%2B1%2C2l%29+%2B+d%282l%2C2k%2B3%29.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  d(2k+1,2l) + d(2l,2k+3). "/></p>
<p>Note<img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> has edges connecting every left vertex to every right vertex; i.e., <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> is the complete bipartite graph.</p>
<p>
Bob then finds a minimum cost matching for the graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/>. This can be done in polynomial time. We claim the following: </p>
<ol>
<li>
The matching 		<p/>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x_{2k+2} \rightarrow x_{2k+1}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x_%7B2k%2B2%7D+%5Crightarrow+x_%7B2k%2B1%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x_{2k+2} \rightarrow x_{2k+1}, "/></p>
<p>has the cost of the original TSP tour. </p>
</li><li>
Every minimum complete matching of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> yields a tour for the original TSP with the same cost as the matching.
</li></ol>
<p>These claims imply that Bob can solve the TSP in polynomial time.</p>
<p>
We note that (1) follows from the definition of the graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> and its costs. In order to see (2) let <img alt="{2\pi(k)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5Cpi%28k%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{2\pi(k)}"/> match to <img alt="{2k+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2k%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{2k+1}"/>. This means that there are edges 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  2k+1 \rightarrow 2\pi(k) \rightarrow 2k+3, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++2k%2B1+%5Crightarrow+2%5Cpi%28k%29+%5Crightarrow+2k%2B3%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  2k+1 \rightarrow 2\pi(k) \rightarrow 2k+3, "/></p>
<p>for all <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{k}"/>. This is clearly a tour, since <img alt="{\pi(k)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%28k%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\pi(k)}"/> is a permutation by the definition of matching. 	 <img alt="\Box" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5CBox&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\Box"/></p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The fact that Alice can send only half of the tour to Bob suggests: can we avoid having Alice solve the TSP in order to compute her message? This is the direction we are interested in. If she could do that it would improve some known complexity bounds on TSP. A possible idea is: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Replace having Alice solve the <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> city TSP exactly. Instead have her solve some randomly selected subproblem exactly, and then use the above method to add in the remaining cities. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Can this work?</p>
<p>
We have not found something like this when searching on TSP and communication complexity, but would not be surprised if the matching idea, caveat, and trick have been noticed and remarked on before.</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-19T05:08:54Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-19T05:08:54Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="Alice and Bob"/>
    <category term="communication complexity"/>
    <category term="complexity"/>
    <category term="complexity theory"/>
    <category term="Merrill Flood"/>
    <category term="TSP"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5101</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5101" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5101#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5101" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Annual post: Come join UT Austin’s Quantum Information Center!</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Hook ’em Hadamards! If you’re a prospective PhD student: Apply here for the CS department (the deadline this year is December 15th), here for the physics department (the deadline is December 1st), or here for the ECE department (the deadline is 15th). GREs are not required this year because of covid. If you apply to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~qic/">Hook ’em Hadamards!</a></p>



<p><strong>If you’re a prospective PhD student:</strong> Apply <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/graduate/prospective-students/apply">here</a> for the CS department (the deadline this year is December 15th), <a href="https://ph.utexas.edu/prospective-graduate-students/admissions">here</a> for the physics department (the deadline is December 1st), or <a href="https://www.ece.utexas.edu/academics/graduate/admissions">here</a> for the ECE department (the deadline is 15th).  GREs are not required this year because of covid.  If you apply to CS and specify that you want to work with me, I’ll be sure to see your application.  If you apply to physics or ECE, I <em>won’t</em> see your application, but once you arrive, I can sometimes supervise or co-supervise PhD students in other departments (or, of course, serve on their committees).  In any case, everyone in the UT community is extremely welcome at our quantum information group meetings (which are now on Zoom, naturally, but depending on vaccine distribution, hopefully won’t be by the time you arrive!).  Emailing me won’t make a difference.  Admissions are very competitive, so apply broadly to maximize your chances.</p>



<p><strong>If you’re a prospective postdoctoral fellow:</strong> By January 1, 2021, please email me a cover letter, your CV, and two or three of your best papers (links or attachments).  Please also ask two recommenders to email me their letters by January 1.  While my own work tends toward computational complexity, I’m open to all parts of theoretical quantum computing and information.</p>



<p><strong>If you’re a prospective faculty member:</strong> Yes, faculty searches are still happening despite covid!  Go <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/faculty/recruiting">here</a> to apply for an opening in the CS department (which, in quantum computing, currently includes me and <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4512">MIP*=RE</a> superstar <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~wright/">John Wright</a>), or <a href="https://faculty.utexas.edu/career/66111">here</a> to apply to the physics department (which, in quantum computing, currently includes <a href="https://cns.utexas.edu/directory/item/18-physics/2826-potter-andrew?Itemid=349">Drew Potter</a>, along with a world-class condensed matter group).</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-19T01:50:07Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-19T01:50:07Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T01:50:07Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/postdoc-at-princeton-university-apply-by-december-10-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/postdoc-at-princeton-university-apply-by-december-10-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at Princeton University (apply by December 10, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Positions are for one year anticipated to start in September 2021 with the possibility of renewal contingent upon satisfactory performance and continued funding. Candidates must have a PhD in Computer Science or a related field. For full consideration, we recommend that candidates apply by December 10, 2020 11:59pm, EST, though we will continue to review […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Positions are for one year anticipated to start in September 2021 with the possibility of renewal contingent upon satisfactory performance and continued funding. Candidates must have a PhD in Computer Science or a related field.</p>
<p>For full consideration, we recommend that candidates apply by December 10, 2020 11:59pm, EST, though we will continue to review applications past that date.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://puwebp.princeton.edu/AcadHire/apply/application.xhtml?listingId=18501">https://puwebp.princeton.edu/AcadHire/apply/application.xhtml?listingId=18501</a><br/>
Email: smweinberg@princeton.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-18T23:20:35Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-18T23:20:35Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/174</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/174" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-174 |  Isoperimetric Inequalities for Real-Valued Functions with Applications to Monotonicity Testing | 

	Hadley Black, 

	Iden Kalemaj, 

	Sofya Raskhodnikova</title>
    <summary>We generalize the celebrated isoperimetric inequality of Khot, Minzer, and Safra (SICOMP 2018) for Boolean functions to the case of real-valued functions $f \colon \{0,1\}^d\to\mathbb{R}$. Our main tool in the proof of the generalized inequality is a new Boolean decomposition that represents every real-valued function $f$ over an arbitrary partially ordered domain as a collection of Boolean functions over the same domain, roughly capturing the distance of $f$ to monotonicity and the structure of violations of $f$ to monotonicity.

We apply our generalized isoperimetric inequality to improve algorithms for testing monotonicity and approximating the distance to monotonicity for real-valued functions. Our tester for monotonicity has query complexity $\widetilde{O}(\min(r \sqrt{d},d))$, where $r$ is the size of the image of the input function. (The best previously known tester, by Chakrabarty and Seshadhri (STOC 2013), makes $O(d)$ queries.) Our tester is nonadaptive and has 1-sided error. We show a matching lower bound for nonadaptive, 1-sided error testers for monotonicity. We also show that the distance to monotonicity of real-valued functions that are $\alpha$-far from monotone can be approximated nonadaptively within a factor of $O(\sqrt{d\log d})$ with query complexity polynomial in  $1/\alpha$ and the dimension $d$. This query complexity is known to be nearly optimal for nonadaptive algorithms even for the special case of Boolean functions. (The best previously known distance approximation algorithm for real-valued functions, by Fattal and Ron (TALG 2010) achieves $O(d\log r)$-approximation.)</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T19:33:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-18T19:33:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/faculty-at-idaho-state-university-apply-by-december-15-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/faculty-at-idaho-state-university-apply-by-december-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty at Idaho State University  (apply by December 15, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Be part of a great team! Idaho State University’s College of Science and Engineering is seeking an Assistant Professor of Computer Science for our Idaho Falls campus. For complete job description, requirements, and application instructions visit jobs.isu.edu. For priority consideration, apply by November 22, 2020. Website: https://isu.csod.com/ats/careersite/JobDetails.aspx?id=1124&amp;site=1 Email: burkstep@isu.edul</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Be part of a great team! Idaho State University’s College of Science and Engineering is seeking an Assistant Professor of Computer Science for our Idaho Falls campus. For complete job description, requirements, and application instructions visit jobs.isu.edu. For priority consideration, apply by November 22, 2020.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://isu.csod.com/ats/careersite/JobDetails.aspx?id=1124&amp;site=1">https://isu.csod.com/ats/careersite/JobDetails.aspx?id=1124&amp;site=1</a><br/>
Email: burkstep@isu.edul</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-18T17:24:32Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-18T17:24:32Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/173</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/173" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-173 |  Block Rigidity: Strong Multiplayer Parallel Repetition implies Super-Linear Lower Bounds for Turing Machines | 

	Kunal Mittal, 

	Ran Raz</title>
    <summary>We prove that a sufficiently strong parallel repetition theorem for a special case of multiplayer (multiprover) games implies super-linear lower bounds for multi-tape Turing machines with advice. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first connection between parallel repetition and lower bounds for time complexity and the first major potential implication of a parallel repetition theorem with more than two players.

Along the way to proving this result, we define and initiate a study of block rigidity, extending Valiant's notion of rigidity [Val77]. While rigidity was originally defined for matrices, or, equivalently, for (multi-output) linear functions, we extend and study both rigidity and block rigidity for general (multi-output) functions. Using techniques of Paul, Pippenger, Szemer{\'{e}}di and Trotter [PPST83], we show that a block-rigid function cannot be computed by multi-tape Turing machines that run in linear (or slightly super-linear) time, even in the non-uniform setting, where the machine gets an arbitrary advice tape.

We then describe a class of multiplayer games, such that, a sufficiently strong parallel repetition theorem for that class of games implies an explicit block-rigid function. The games in that class have the following property that may be of independent interest: for every random string for the verifier (which, in particular, determines the vector of queries to the players), there is a unique correct answer for each of the players, and the verifier accepts if and only if all answers are correct. We refer to such games as independent games. The theorem that we need is that parallel repetition reduces the value of games in this class from $v$ to $v^{\Omega(n)}$, where $n$ is the number of repetitions.

As another application of block rigidity, we show conditional size-depth tradeoffs for boolean circuits, where the gates compute arbitrary functions over large sets.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T05:19:58Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-18T05:19:58Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/faculty-positions-in-quantum-computing-and-theoretical-computer-science-at-stony-brook-university-apply-by-january-5-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/faculty-positions-in-quantum-computing-and-theoretical-computer-science-at-stony-brook-university-apply-by-january-5-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty Positions in Quantum Computing and Theoretical Computer Science at Stony Brook University (apply by January 5, 2021)</title>
    <summary>Stony Brook University’s Department of Computer Science invites applicants for *two* tenure-track/tenured faculty positions in theoretical computer science starting Fall 2021. Areas of interest are 1) quantum computing/information science; (2) algorithms and complexity theory; and 3) theory of machine learning. Website: https://apptrkr.com/2039466 Email: skiena@cs.stonybrook.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Stony Brook University’s Department of Computer Science invites applicants for *two* tenure-track/tenured faculty positions in theoretical computer science starting Fall 2021. Areas of interest are 1) quantum computing/information science; (2) algorithms and complexity theory; and 3) theory of machine learning.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://apptrkr.com/2039466">https://apptrkr.com/2039466</a><br/>
Email: skiena@cs.stonybrook.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-18T01:23:26Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-18T01:23:26Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08806</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08806" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Ultrasparse Ultrasparsifiers and Faster Laplacian System Solvers</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1605657600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jambulapati:Arun.html">Arun Jambulapati</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sidford:Aaron.html">Aaron Sidford</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.08806">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper we provide an $O(m (\log \log n)^{O(1)}
\log(1/\epsilon))$-expected time algorithm for solving Laplacian systems on
$n$-node $m$-edge graphs, improving improving upon the previous best expected
runtime of $O(m \sqrt{\log n} (\log \log n)^{O(1)} \log(1/\epsilon))$ achieved
by (Cohen, Kyng, Miller, Pachocki, Peng, Rao, Xu 2014). To obtain this result
we provide efficient constructions of $\ell_p$-stretch graph approximations
with improved stretch and sparsity bounds. Additionally, as motivation for this
work, we show that for every set of vectors in $\mathbb{R}^d$ (not just those
induced by graphs) and all $k &gt; 0$ there exist an ultra-sparsifiers with $d-1 +
O(d/k)$ re-weighted vectors of relative condition number at most $k^2$. For
small $k$, this improves upon the previous best known multiplicative factor of
$k \cdot \tilde{O}(\log d)$, which is only known for the graph case.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T22:41:21Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08676</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08676" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Topology-Based Feature Design and Tracking for Multi-Center Cyclones</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1605657600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Engelke:Wito.html">Wito Engelke</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Masood:Talha_Bin.html">Talha Bin Masood</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Beran:Jakob.html">Jakob Beran</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Caballero:Rodrigo.html">Rodrigo Caballero</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hotz:Ingrid.html">Ingrid Hotz</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.08676">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we propose a concept to design, track, and compare
application-specific feature definitions expressed as sets of critical points.
Our work has been inspired by the observation that in many applications a large
variety of different feature definitions for the same concept are used. Often,
these definitions compete with each other and it is unclear which definition
should be used in which context. A prominent example is the definition of
cyclones in climate research. Despite the differences, frequently these feature
definitions can be related to topological concepts.
</p>
<p>In our approach, we provide a cyclone tracking framework that supports
interactive feature definition and comparison based on a precomputed tracking
graph that stores all extremal points as well as their temporal correspondents.
The framework combines a set of independent building blocks: critical point
extraction, critical point tracking, feature definition, and track exploration.
One of the major advantages of such an approach is the flexibility it provides,
that is, each block is exchangeable. Moreover, it also enables us to perform
the most expensive analysis, the construction of a full tracking graph, as a
prepossessing step, while keeping the feature definition interactive. Different
feature definitions can be explored and compared interactively based on this
tracking graph. Features are specified by rules for grouping critical points,
while feature tracking corresponds to filtering and querying the full tracking
graph by specific requests. We demonstrate this method for cyclone
identification and tracking in the context of climate research.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T22:42:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08557</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08557" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Simple Iterative Methods for Linear Optimization over Convex Sets</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1605657600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dadush:Daniel.html">Daniel Dadush</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hojny:Christopher.html">Christopher Hojny</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Huiberts:Sophie.html">Sophie Huiberts</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Weltge:Stefan.html">Stefan Weltge</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.08557">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We give simple iterative methods for computing approximately optimal primal
and dual solutions for the problem of maximizing a linear functional over a
convex set $K$ given by a separation oracle. In contrast to prior work, our
algorithms directly output primal and dual solutions and avoid a common
requirement of binary search on the objective value.
</p>
<p>Under the assumption that $K$ contains a ball of radius $r$ and is contained
inside the origin centered ball of radius $R$, using $O(\frac{R^4}{r^2
\varepsilon^2})$ iterations and calls to the oracle, our main method outputs a
point $x \in K$ together with a non-negative combination of the inequalities
outputted by the oracle and one inequality of the $R$-ball certifying that $x$
is an additive $\varepsilon$-approximate solution. In the setting where the
inner $r$-ball is centered at the origin, we give a simplified variant which
outputs a multiplicative $(1 + \varepsilon)$-approximate primal and dual
solutions using $O(\frac{R^2}{r^2 \varepsilon^2})$ iterations and calls to the
oracle. Similar results hold for packing type problems. Our methods are based
on variants of the classical Von Neumann and Frank-Wolfe algorithms.
</p>
<p>Our algorithms are also easy to implement, and we provide an experimental
evaluation of their performance on a testbed of maximum matching and stable set
instances. We further compare variations of our method to the standard cut loop
implemented using Gurobi.This comparison reveals that in terms of iteration
count, our methods converge on average faster than the standard cut loop on our
test set.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T22:37:31Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08448</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08448" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal diameter computation within bounded clique-width graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1605657600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Ducoffe:Guillaume.html">Guillaume Ducoffe</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.08448">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Coudert et al. (SODA'18) proved that under the Strong Exponential-Time
Hypothesis, for any $\epsilon &gt;0$, there is no ${\cal
O}(2^{o(k)}n^{2-\epsilon})$-time algorithm for computing the diameter within
the $n$-vertex cubic graphs of clique-width at most $k$. We present an
algorithm which given an $n$-vertex $m$-edge graph $G$ and a $k$-expression,
computes all the eccentricities in ${\cal O}(2^{{\cal O}(k)}(n+m)^{1+o(1)})$
time, thus matching their conditional lower bound. It can be modified in order
to compute the Wiener index and the median set of $G$ within the same amount of
time. On our way, we get a distance-labeling scheme for $n$-vertex $m$-edge
graphs of clique-width at most $k$, using ${\cal O}(k\log^2{n})$ bits per
vertex and constructible in ${\cal O}(k(n+m)\log{n})$ time from a given
$k$-expression. Doing so, we match the label size obtained by Courcelle and
Vanicat (DAM 2016), while we considerably improve the dependency on $k$ in
their scheme. As a corollary, we get an ${\cal O}(kn^2\log{n})$-time algorithm
for computing All-Pairs Shortest-Paths on $n$-vertex graphs of clique-width at
most $k$. This partially answers an open question of Kratsch and Nelles
(STACS'20).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T22:42:06Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08447</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08447" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Exact recovery of Planted Cliques in Semi-random graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1605657600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Khanna:Yash.html">Yash Khanna</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.08447">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this short paper, we study the Planted Clique problem in a semi-random
model. Our model is inspired from the Feige-Kilian model [FK01] which has been
studied in many other works [Ste17, MMT20]. Our algorithm and analysis is on
similar lines to the one studied for the Densest $k$-subgraph problem in the
recent work of Khanna and Louis [KL20]. However since our algorithm fully
recovers the planted clique w.h.p., we require some new ideas.
</p>
<p>As a by-product of our main result, we give an alternate SDP based rounding
algorithm (with matching guarantees) for solving the Planted Clique problem in
a random graph. Also, we are able to solve a special case of the D$k$SReg$(n,
k, d, \delta, \gamma)$ model introduced in [KL20], when the planted subgraph
$G[S]$ is a clique.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T22:41:15Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08404</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08404" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Natural Stratifications of Reeb Spaces and Higher Morse Functions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1605657600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grady:Ryan_E=.html">Ryan E. Grady</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schenfisch:Anna.html">Anna Schenfisch</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.08404">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Both Reeb spaces and higher Morse functions induce natural stratifications.
In the former, we show that the data of the Jacobi set of a function $f:X \to
\mathbb{R}^k$ induces stratifications on $X,\mathbb{R}^k$, and the associated
Reeb space, and give conditions under which maps between these three spaces are
stratified maps. We then extend this type of construction to the codomain of
higher Morse functions, using the singular locus to induce a stratification of
which sub-posets are equivalent to multi-parameter filtrations.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T22:43:12Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08384</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08384" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal Sub-Gaussian Mean Estimation in $\mathbb{R}$</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1605657600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lee:Jasper_C=_H=.html">Jasper C. H. Lee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Valiant:Paul.html">Paul Valiant</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.08384">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We revisit the problem of estimating the mean of a real-valued distribution,
presenting a novel estimator with sub-Gaussian convergence: intuitively, "our
estimator, on any distribution, is as accurate as the sample mean is for the
Gaussian distribution of matching variance." Crucially, in contrast to prior
works, our estimator does not require prior knowledge of the variance, and
works across the entire gamut of distributions with bounded variance, including
those without any higher moments. Parameterized by the sample size $n$, the
failure probability $\delta$, and the variance $\sigma^2$, our estimator is
accurate to within $\sigma\cdot(1+o(1))\sqrt{\frac{2\log\frac{1}{\delta}}{n}}$,
tight up to the $1+o(1)$ factor. Our estimator construction and analysis gives
a framework generalizable to other problems, tightly analyzing a sum of
dependent random variables by viewing the sum implicitly as a 2-parameter
$\psi$-estimator, and constructing bounds using mathematical programming and
duality techniques.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T22:40:59Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08232</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08232" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Conversion Between Bezier and Catmull-Rom Splines</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1605657600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Arasteh:Soroosh_Tayebi.html">Soroosh Tayebi Arasteh</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kalisz:Adam.html">Adam Kalisz</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.08232">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Splines are one of the main methods of mathematically representing
complicated shapes, which have become the primary technique in computer
graphics for modeling complex surfaces. Among all, Bezier and Catmull-Rom
splines are of the most used in the subfields of engineering. In this document,
we focus on conversion of splines rather than going through the properties of
them, i.e, converting the control points of a spline to the control points of
another spline, which results in approximately the same curve, as the spline
before conversion represents.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T22:43:23Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.07107</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.07107" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A universal predictor-corrector type incremental algorithm for the construction of weighted straight skeletons based on the notion of deforming polygon</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1605657600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Irhan:Baris.html">Baris Irhan</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.07107">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A new predictor-corrector type incremental algorithm is proposed for the
exact construction of weighted straight skeletons of 2D general planar polygons
of arbitrary complexity based on the notion of deforming polygon. In the
proposed algorithm, the raw input provided by the polygon itself is enough to
resolve edge collapse and edge split events. Neither the construction of a
kinetic triangulation nor the computation of a motorcycle graph is required.
Due to its incremental nature, there is always a room in the algorithm for the
interactive construction of the straight skeleton. The proposed algorithm is of
predictor-corrector type. In the algorithm, the edge collapse and edge split
events are tackled by a completely different novel original approach which is
first of its kind. In the predictor step, the position of the vertices is
advanced in time by direct integration assuming no event. Then predicted
positions are corrected by using linear interpolation if there are edge
collapse or edge split events within the same increment. In the algorithm edge
collapse and edge split events are detected by, respectively, edge swap and
edge penetration. The proposed algorithm has been used to construct roof
topology starting from a floor plan of various complexity ranging from simple
convex to highly nonconvex with holes. In order to construct, improve and test
the building blocks of the underlying algorithm, a graphical user interface,
Straight Skeleton Development Kit, has also been developed in parallel by the
author using C++ programming language.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T22:42:19Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7895</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/11/17/election-insecurity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Election insecurity</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Election security has been studied for many years by computer scientists, but it is not as often that it attracts so much mainstream attention. I would never have expected to see my former Princeton colleague Andrew Appel on a Sean Hannity segment tweeted by President Trump. It may seem that even if it has partisan … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/11/17/election-insecurity/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Election insecurity</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Election security has been studied for many years by <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/rsa-cryptographer-ronald-rivest-seeks-secure-elections-20200312/">computer scientists</a>, but it is not as often that it attracts so much mainstream attention. I would never have expected to see my former Princeton colleague <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~appel/">Andrew Appel</a> on a Sean Hannity segment tweeted by President Trump.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/image.png"><img alt="" class="wp-image-7899" src="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/image.png?w=1024"/></a></figure>



<p/>



<p>It may seem that even if it has partisan motivations, the recent GOP interest in election security is overall a positive thing. Who wouldn’t want elections to be more secure? Who wouldn’t want less fraud? However, in a very precise sense, the definition of “election security” used by the GOP these days corresponds to <strong>election insecurity</strong>.</p>



<p>To understand this claim, consider what it means for an election to be secure. (Let’s focus just on the correctness aspect of the count, since it is at the heart of the current issues, and not on the very interesting privacy aspect.) Computer scientists use <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1605.08554">the technical terms</a> “<strong>cast as intended</strong>“, “<strong>recorded as cast</strong>“, and “<strong>tallied as recorded</strong>“. In other words: if a voter X intends to cast vote for candidate Y,  then this vote should be recorded and tallied, and only such votes should be tallied.</p>



<p>With mail-in voting, there are several potential points of failure on the path between voter intent and the final tally:</p>



<ol><li>Mail can be lost or delayed too much, leading to the vote not counting.</li><li>A third party could intercept the ballot and impersonate the voter.</li><li>A ballot may not be formatted properly in some way, leading to it being disqualified.</li><li>There can be errors or hacks in the tallying process.</li></ol>



<p>Election security is about combatting points 1-4 (of which the last 3 are also applicable to in-person voting) , ideally in a way that is <em>verifiable</em> to the individual voters. Achieving verifiability while maintaining secrecy and not requiring the voter to trust complex technology is a challenging task, but there have been some proposed solutions (see above links).<br/><br/>The Hannity segment and much of the “Dominion” non story focused on point 4. This is an important point, but as <a href="https://freedom-to-tinker.com/2020/11/13/did-sean-hannity-misquote-me/">Appel himself notes</a>, paper ballots, which are mostly used in the US, serve as a way to audit counting. Re-counting is important, and is commonly done, but such recounts often change the total counts by relatively little (and the changes mostly cancel out). For example, here is the list of ballots changed and reasons from the Wisconsin 2016 count (taken from <a href="https://t.co/AUagggIp6j?amp=1">this paper</a>)</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img alt="Image" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/Emk1EJaU4AAtAJm?format=jpg&amp;name=4096x4096"/></figure>



<p>In contrast, many of the legal cases by the Trump campaign focused on signature verification and other ballot irregularities. There are two main reasons why a signature would not match between a ballot and driver’s license or other records:</p>



<ol><li>The signature may have been forged by someone trying to impersonate the voter.<br/></li><li>The voter’s signature might not very consistent, or maybe they have more than one signature (for example, I sometimes sign in Hebrew and sometimes in English) .</li></ol>



<p>Empirically, reason 2 is much more common than reason 1. If a ballot is tossed out because of the second reason it corresponds to a <strong>break between the voter intent and the final tally</strong>, and hence it is a case of <em>election insecurity</em>. For this reason, making more stringent signature checks could make elections less secure!</p>



<p>While President Trump might claim on Twitter that the election was stolen by a massive conspiracy involving forging of tens of thousands of ballots, this is not the actual content of the court cases (especially after some <a href="https://lawandcrime.com/2020-election/lawyers-pan-significant-shrinkage-of-trump-campaigns-pennsylvania-lawsuit-only-addresses-a-handful-of-ballots/">recent</a> <a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/484456818/Redline-Trump-Complaint">amendments</a>). For example, at the heart of the PA case is the process of “<a href="https://www.factcheck.org/2020/11/ballot-curing-in-pennsylvania/">curing a ballot</a>“. This is when a ballot is disqualified due to some technical issue, and a voter has a chance to fix it. Curing a ballot ensures that the voters intent is captured, and hence makes elections more secure. </p>



<p>In PA, the decision of whether to notify voters in such cases was left to the counties, and apparently Democrat-controlled counties were more likely to do so Republican-controlled counties. This is a shame, and had the Trump campaign asked to extend the deadline for curing  ballots, then I would think it makes perfect sense. However, this is not what their lawsuit is about. To quote their complaint: <em>“plaintiffs seek a permanent injunction requiring the County Election Boards to invalidate ballots cast by voters who were notified and given an opportunity to cure their invalidly cast mail-in ballot.”</em> This are ballots where there is no question of the eligibility of the voter, nor of the accuracy of their intent, yet the Trump campaign seeks to prevent them from counting. I call this election insecurity.</p>



<p/>



<p>p.s. See <a href="https://twitter.com/KlasfeldReports">Adam Klasfeld’s feed</a> for more about the various Trump campaign cases</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-twitter wp-block-embed-twitter"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-twitter"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p dir="ltr" lang="en">The DNC's lawyer Uzoma Nkwonta, from Perkins Coie, is up. <br/><br/>He reiterates a point made earlier by the counties that Trump's co-plaintiffs sued the wrong counties.<br/><br/>They're from Trump-backing Fayette and Lancaster Counties. <br/><br/>They sued seven blue counties, alleging vote denial.</p>— Adam Klasfeld (@KlasfeldReports) <a href="https://twitter.com/KlasfeldReports/status/1328823948319076355?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 17, 2020</a></blockquote></div>
</div></figure></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T22:31:11Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T22:31:11Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:21:03Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/tenure-track-assistant-professor-position-at-university-of-british-columbia-apply-by-december-20-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/tenure-track-assistant-professor-position-at-university-of-british-columbia-apply-by-december-20-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure-track assistant professor position at University of British Columbia (apply by December 20, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at the University of British Columbia (Vancouver campus) is inviting applications for one position at the rank of Assistant Professor. We invite applications from candidates of outstanding scientific talent in all areas of computer science. Website: https://www.cs.ubc.ca/our-department/employment/tenure-track-assistant-professor-department-computer-science-ubc-research Email: research-recruiting-chair@cs.ubc.ca</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at the University of British Columbia (Vancouver campus) is inviting applications for one position at the rank of Assistant Professor. We invite applications from candidates of outstanding scientific talent in all areas of computer science.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.cs.ubc.ca/our-department/employment/tenure-track-assistant-professor-department-computer-science-ubc-research">https://www.cs.ubc.ca/our-department/employment/tenure-track-assistant-professor-department-computer-science-ubc-research</a><br/>
Email: research-recruiting-chair@cs.ubc.ca</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T19:33:56Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T19:33:56Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/3-tenure-track-professors-w2-at-saarland-university-saarbrucken-germany-apply-by-december-11-2020-2/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/3-tenure-track-professors-w2-at-saarland-university-saarbrucken-germany-apply-by-december-11-2020-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>3 Tenure Track Professors (W2) at Saarland University, Saarbrücken, Germany (apply by December 11, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Saarland University is seeking to hire up to 3 Tenure Track Professors (W2) in computer science and related areas with six-year tenure track to a permanent professorship (W3). Areas of interest include: * Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning * Data Science, Big Data * Computational Logic and Verification * Theory and Algorithms * Quantum Computing Website: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Saarland University is seeking to hire up to 3 Tenure Track Professors (W2)<br/>
in computer science and related areas with six-year tenure track to a permanent professorship (W3). Areas of interest include:</p>
<p>* Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning<br/>
* Data Science, Big Data<br/>
* Computational Logic and Verification<br/>
* Theory and Algorithms<br/>
* Quantum Computing</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.uni-saarland.de/fileadmin/user_upload/verwaltung/stellen/wissenschaftler/W1786_W2TT-Informatik_Ausschreibung_final.pdf">https://www.uni-saarland.de/fileadmin/user_upload/verwaltung/stellen/wissenschaftler/W1786_W2TT-Informatik_Ausschreibung_final.pdf</a><br/>
Email: apply@saarland-informatics-campus.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T16:19:45Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T16:19:45Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/3-tenure-track-professors-w2-at-saarland-university-saarbrucken-germany-apply-by-december-11-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/3-tenure-track-professors-w2-at-saarland-university-saarbrucken-germany-apply-by-december-11-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>3 Tenure Track Professors (W2) at Saarland University, Saarbrücken, Germany (apply by December 11, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Saarland University is seeking to hire up to 3 Tenure Track Professors (W2) in computer science and related areas with six-year tenure track to a permanent professorship (W3). Areas of interest include: * Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning * Data Science, Big Data * Computational Logic and Verification * Theory and Algorithms * Quantum Computing Website: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Saarland University is seeking to hire up to 3 Tenure Track Professors (W2)<br/>
in computer science and related areas with six-year tenure track to a permanent professorship (W3). Areas of interest include:</p>
<p>* Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning<br/>
* Data Science, Big Data<br/>
* Computational Logic and Verification<br/>
* Theory and Algorithms<br/>
* Quantum Computing</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.uni-saarland.de/fileadmin/user_upload/verwaltung/stellen/wissenschaftler/W1786_W2TT-Informatik_Ausschreibung_final.pdf">https://www.uni-saarland.de/fileadmin/user_upload/verwaltung/stellen/wissenschaftler/W1786_W2TT-Informatik_Ausschreibung_final.pdf</a><br/>
Email: apply@saarland-informatics-campus.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T16:19:39Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T16:19:39Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-2955644832205049973</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/2955644832205049973/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=2955644832205049973" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/2955644832205049973" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/2955644832205049973" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2020/11/faculty-positions-at-department-of.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty positions at the Department of Computer Science, Reykjavik University</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The <a href="https://en.ru.is/st/dcs/">Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University</a> is hiring and invites applications for faculty positions at any rank. </p><p>We are looking for energetic, highly qualified academics with a proven international research record.  We particularly welcome applications from researchers who have a strong network of research collaborators, can strengthen internal collaborations within the department, and generally have potential to flourish in our setting. </p><p>We have just posted three separate calls for applications. <br/></p><ul style="text-align: left;"><li>If you are interested in applying for one of the faculty positions in the fields of Data Science, Machine Learning, Software Engineering, and Computer Security, please follow <a href="https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/is/5933" target="_blank">this link</a> for more information on the positions and on how to apply. </li><li>If you are interested in applying for the faculty position in Game Design and Development, see <a href="https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/is/5938" target="_blank">here</a> for more information on the position and on how to apply. <br/></li><li>We also have a call for faculty positions in any area of Computer Science. You can find further information on those positions <a href="https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/is/5937" target="_blank">here</a>. </li></ul><p><b>Addendum dated 19 November 2020: </b>Scientists coming to Iceland from abroad for work can apply for a tax relief for the first <i>three</i> years of their employment. If the application is successful, 25% of their salary is tax free. </p><p><b>Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University </b><br/></p><p>The Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University has about 650 full-time-equivalent students and 22 faculty members. It provides an excellent working environment that encourages and supports independence in academic endeavors, and in which a motivated academic can have impact at all levels. The department offers undergraduate and graduate programs in computer science and software engineering, as well as a combined undergraduate program in discrete mathematics and computer science.  The department is home to several research centers producing high-quality collaborative research in areas such as artificial intelligence, financial technology, language technology, software systems, and theoretical computer science, among others; for more information on those research centers, see <a href="https://en.ru.is/research/units/">https://en.ru.is/research/units/</a>.</p><p> <b>Reykjavík University </b></p><p>On the Times Higher Education rankings for 2021, Reykjavík University is ranked in first place along with eight other universities for the average number of citations per faculty. Overall, RU is ranked among the 350 best universities world-wide, 59th of all universities established fewer than 50 years ago, and first among Icelandic universities.  Reykjavík University has around 3.700 students and 250 faculty and employees in addition to numerous adjunct faculty in two schools: Technology and Social Sciences. We offer a welcoming and stimulating environment in which to work and live. The University is centrally located in Reykjavík, the capital city of Iceland.  The role of Reykjavik University is to create and disseminate knowledge to enhance the competitiveness and quality of life for individuals and society, guided by good ethics, sustainability and responsibility. Education and research at RU are based on strong ties with industry and society. We emphasize interdisciplinary collaboration, international relations and entrepreneurship. </p><p><b>Iceland</b> </p><p>Iceland is well known for breathtaking natural beauty, with volcanoes, hot springs, lava fields and glaciers offering a dramatic landscape. It consistently ranks as one of the best places in the world to live. It offers a high quality of life, is one of the safest places in the world, has high gender equality, and strong health-care and social-support systems. It is in fourth position in the 2020 UN World Happiness Report, which correlates with various life factors.  </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T15:15:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T15:15:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T10:22:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/postdoc-at-hdsi-simons-institute-at-halicioglu-data-science-institute-ucsd-apply-by-february-15-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/postdoc-at-hdsi-simons-institute-at-halicioglu-data-science-institute-ucsd-apply-by-february-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at HDSI/Simons Institute at Halıcıoğlu Data Science Institute, UCSD (apply by February 15, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Halıcıoğlu Data Science Institute (HDSI) and the UC Berkeley Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing have created a joint two-year postdoctoral fellowship opening aimed at preparing outstanding researchers for academic and leadership careers in the theoretical aspects of Data Science. Website: https://datascience.ucsd.edu/jobs/hdsi-post-doctoral/ Email: esnee@ucsd.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Halıcıoğlu Data Science Institute (HDSI) and the UC Berkeley Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing have created a joint two-year postdoctoral fellowship opening aimed at preparing outstanding researchers for academic and leadership careers in the theoretical aspects of Data Science.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://datascience.ucsd.edu/jobs/hdsi-post-doctoral/">https://datascience.ucsd.edu/jobs/hdsi-post-doctoral/</a><br/>
Email: esnee@ucsd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T04:55:39Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T04:55:39Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/postdoc-at-university-of-waterloo-apply-by-december-31-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/postdoc-at-university-of-waterloo-apply-by-december-31-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at University of Waterloo (apply by December 31, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Algorithms &amp; Complexity group at the University of Waterloo is offering postdoctoral positions starting in the Fall of 2021. We seek candidates from all areas of theoretical computer science. Interested applicants should have their CV, research statement, and three recommendation letters emailed to theory.waterloo@gmail.com. Applications are due December 31st. Website: https://algcomp.uwaterloo.ca/positions/ Email: theory.waterloo@gmail.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Algorithms &amp; Complexity group at the University of Waterloo is offering postdoctoral positions starting in the Fall of 2021. We seek candidates from all areas of theoretical computer science.<br/>
Interested applicants should have their CV, research statement, and three recommendation letters emailed to theory.waterloo@gmail.com. Applications are due December 31st.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://algcomp.uwaterloo.ca/positions/">https://algcomp.uwaterloo.ca/positions/</a><br/>
Email: theory.waterloo@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T02:38:26Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T02:38:26Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/simons-berkeley-research-fellowships-for-fall-2021-and-spring-2022-at-simons-institute-for-the-theory-of-computing-apply-by-december-15-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/simons-berkeley-research-fellowships-for-fall-2021-and-spring-2022-at-simons-institute-for-the-theory-of-computing-apply-by-december-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Simons-Berkeley Research Fellowships for Fall 2021 and Spring 2022 at Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing (apply by December 15, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing invites applications for Simons-Berkeley Postdoctoral Fellowships and Simons-Berkeley Research Fellowships to participate in the semester-long programs at the institute in Fall 2021 and Spring 2022: “Computational Complexity of Statistical Inference”, “Geometric Methods in Optimization and Sampling”, “Causality”, and “Learning and Games.” Website: https://simons.berkeley.edu/ Email: simonsvisitorservices@berkeley.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing invites applications for Simons-Berkeley Postdoctoral Fellowships and Simons-Berkeley Research Fellowships to participate in the semester-long programs at the institute in Fall 2021 and Spring 2022: “Computational Complexity of Statistical Inference”, “Geometric Methods in Optimization and Sampling”, “Causality”, and “Learning and Games.”</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/">https://simons.berkeley.edu/</a><br/>
Email: simonsvisitorservices@berkeley.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T01:17:29Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T01:17:29Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=20411</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/17/to-cheer-you-up-14-hong-liu-and-richard-montgomery-solved-the-erdos-and-hajnals-odd-cycle-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>To cheer you up 14: Hong Liu and Richard Montgomery solved the Erdős and Hajnal’s odd cycle problem</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The news: In 1981, Paul Erdős and András Hajnal asked whether the sum of the reciprocals of the odd cycle lengths in a graph with infinite chromatic number is necessarily infinite. Hong Liu and Richard Montgomery have just proved that … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/17/to-cheer-you-up-14-hong-liu-and-richard-montgomery-solved-the-erdos-and-hajnals-odd-cycle-problem/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/solvers.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-20426" height="359" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/solvers.png?w=640&amp;h=359" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>The news: In 1981, Paul Erdős and András Hajnal asked whether the sum of the reciprocals of the odd cycle lengths in a graph with infinite chromatic number is necessarily infinite. Hong Liu and Richard Montgomery <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.15802">have just proved</a> that the answer is positive!  They also proved a variety of other old standing conjectures. This is remarkable. Congratulations!</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;">Before going on let me pose an even stronger conjecture</span></p>
<p><strong>Conjecture:</strong> The sum of the reciprocals of the odd<strong> induced</strong> cycle lengths in a <em>triangle-free</em> graph with no triangles and infinite chromatic number is necessarily infinite.</p>
<p>The same conclusion should apply to graphs with bounded clique numbers; it is related to the general area of <img alt="\chi" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cchi&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\chi"/>-boundedness, see <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2014/12/19/when-a-few-colors-suffice/">this post</a> and this <a href="https://web.math.princeton.edu/~pds/papers/chibounded/paper.pdf">recent survey</a> by Alex Scott and Paul Seymour.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Returning to Liu and Montgomery’s breakthrough</span>, let me mention two other conjectures that Hong and Richard proved in the same paper:</p>
<p>A) (Conjecture by Erdős from 1984) There is a constant <em>d</em> such that any graph with average degree <em>d</em> has a cycle whose length is a power of 2.</p>
<p>B) (Conjecture by Carsten Thomassen from 1984) for every <em><span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-11-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-84"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-85"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-86">k</span></span></span></span></em>, there is some <em><span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-12-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-87"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-88"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-89">d</span></span></span></span></em> so that every graph with average degree at least <em><span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-13-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-90"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-91"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-92">d</span></span></span></span></em> has a subdivision of the complete graph <img alt="K_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=K_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="K_k"/> in which each edge is subdivided the same number of times.</p>
<p>I am thankful to Benny Sudakov for telling me about the new result.</p>
<p>A key ingredient of the proof is the study of expanders that you can always find in graphs. Komlós and Szemerédi showed in 1996 that every graph <em>G</em> contains an expander with comparable average degree to <em>G </em>and since their work, with greater and greater sophistication, finding expanders in general graphs has become an important tool for a large number of extremal problems.</p>
<h2 class="title mathjax">Hong Liu, Richard Montgomery: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.15802">A solution to Erdős and Hajnal’s odd cycle problem</a> (click for the arXive.)</h2>
<p><strong>Abstract:</strong></p>
<p>In 1981, Erdős and Hajnal asked whether the sum of the reciprocals of the odd cycle lengths in a graph with infinite chromatic number is necessarily infinite. Let <img alt="\mathcal{C}(G)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathcal%7BC%7D%28G%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathcal{C}(G)"/> be the set of cycle lengths in a graph <img alt="G" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G"/> and let <img alt="\mathcal{C}_\text{odd}(G)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathcal%7BC%7D_%5Ctext%7Bodd%7D%28G%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathcal{C}_\text{odd}(G)"/> be the set of odd numbers in <img alt="\mathcal{C}(G)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathcal%7BC%7D%28G%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathcal{C}(G)"/>. We prove that, if <img alt="G" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G"/> has chromatic number <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/>, then <img alt="\sum_{\ell\in  \mathcal{C}_\text{odd}(G)}1/\ell\geq (1/2-o_k(1))\log k." class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Csum_%7B%5Cell%5Cin++%5Cmathcal%7BC%7D_%5Ctext%7Bodd%7D%28G%29%7D1%2F%5Cell%5Cgeq+%281%2F2-o_k%281%29%29%5Clog+k.&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\sum_{\ell\in  \mathcal{C}_\text{odd}(G)}1/\ell\geq (1/2-o_k(1))\log k."/> This solves Erdős and Hajnal’s odd cycle problem, and, furthermore, this bound is asymptotically optimal.<br/>
In 1984, Erdős asked whether there is some d such that each graph with chromatic number at least d (or perhaps even only average degree at least <img alt="d" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="d"/>) has a cycle whose length is a power of 2. We show that an average degree condition is sufficient for this problem, solving it with methods that apply to a wide range of sequences in addition to the powers of 2.<br/>
Finally, we use our methods to show that, for every <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/>, there is some <img alt="d" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="d"/> so that every graph with average degree at least d has a subdivision of the complete graph <img alt="K_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=K_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="K_k"/> in which each edge is subdivided the same number of times. This confirms a conjecture of Thomassen from 1984.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-16T22:56:06Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-16T22:56:06Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Andr&#xE1;s Hajnal"/>
    <category term="Carsten Thomassen"/>
    <category term="Hong Liu"/>
    <category term="Paul Erdos"/>
    <category term="Richard Montgomry"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/16/postdoc-at-sandia-national-labs-apply-by-december-15-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/16/postdoc-at-sandia-national-labs-apply-by-december-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at Sandia National Labs (apply by December 15, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Sandia Labs is seeking a postdoc to work on quantum or quantum-inspired classical (approximation) algorithms for discrete optimization and machine learning problems, as part of a DOE-funded collaboration among several national labs and universities. We encourage theoretical computer scientists interested in quantum information but without prior expertise to apply (job #673907 at below URL). Website: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Sandia Labs is seeking a postdoc to work on quantum or quantum-inspired classical (approximation) algorithms for discrete optimization and machine learning problems, as part of a DOE-funded collaboration among several national labs and universities. We encourage theoretical computer scientists interested in quantum information but without prior expertise to apply (job #673907 at below URL).</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://www.sandia.gov/careers/">http://www.sandia.gov/careers/</a><br/>
Email: odparek@sandia.gov</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-16T20:14:51Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-16T20:14:51Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="673907"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T09:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://theorydish.blog/?p=1802</id>
    <link href="https://theorydish.blog/2020/11/16/hiring-postdocs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hiring Postdocs</title>
    <summary>I am looking to hire postdocs in the coming years on topics of algorithmic fairness with relation to a Simons Collaboration and on the meaning of individual probabilities with relation to a Sloan Foundation project. Please contact me (reingold@stanford.edu) for details and please forward to any relevant individual. Some comments: The Simons Collaboration will offer additional postdoc opportunities across the participating institutions. To be advertised soon. The perspective taken in both these projects is of TOC but the research will gain from collaborations with other fields within and outside of CS (Statistics, Economics, Philosophy, Law, Social Sciences at large). I will therefore be open to postdocs with various backgrounds (and would consider co-hosting with colleagues in other fields). Candidates from under-represented populations are encouraged to apply and I promise to give those applications my close attention.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I am looking to hire postdocs in the coming years on topics of algorithmic fairness with relation to a <a href="https://www.simonsfoundation.org/2020/06/18/foundation-announces-simons-collaboration-on-the-theory-of-algorithmic-fairness/">Simons Collaboration</a> and on the meaning of individual probabilities with relation to a <a href="https://sloan.org/">Sloan Foundation</a> project. Please contact me (reingold@stanford.edu) for details and please forward to any relevant individual. Some comments:</p>



<ol type="1"><li>The Simons Collaboration will offer additional postdoc opportunities across the participating institutions. To be advertised soon.</li></ol>



<ul><li>The perspective taken in both these projects is of TOC but the research will gain from collaborations with other fields within and outside of CS (Statistics, Economics, Philosophy, Law, Social Sciences at large). I will therefore be open to postdocs with various backgrounds (and would consider co-hosting with colleagues in other fields).</li></ul>



<ul><li>Candidates from under-represented populations are encouraged to apply and I promise to give those applications my close attention.</li></ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-16T17:39:07Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-16T17:39:07Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Omer Reingold</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://theorydish.blog</id>
      <logo>https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/cropped-nightdish1.jpg?w=32</logo>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Stanford's CS Theory Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Theory Dish</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:21:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>The early history of continued fractions (\(\mathbb{M}\)). Includes the equivalences of infinitude with irrationality and periodicity with quadraticness, and the work of Euler and Gauss on continued fractions for values with nice series expansions.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/2020/09/five_levels_of_continued_fract.html">The early history of continued fractions</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105139147272940535">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Includes the equivalences of infinitude with irrationality and periodicity with quadraticness, and the work of Euler and Gauss on continued fractions for values with nice series expansions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>According to <a href="http://cams.ehess.fr/">EHESS</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Rosenstiehl">Pierre Rosenstiehl</a> has died (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105147747900598849">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). I don’t think I met or interacted with Rosenstiehl, but I definitely interacted with his works: he was one of the founders of the International Symposium on Graph Drawing and co-editor in chief of the European Journal of Combinatorics, with important publications in topological and algorithmic graph theory on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bipolar_orientation">bipolar orientations</a> and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Left-right_planarity_test">left-right planarity test</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.aerialphotoawards.com/aerial-photos-of-the-year-2020-man-made-category">Aerial photos of the year, 2020</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105155256595043126">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://www.metafilter.com/189287/A-Different-Perspective">via</a>). The link shows only the “man-made” category; be sure to click on all the others as well.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.slac.stanford.edu/~kaehler/homepage/visualizations/dark-matter.html">Simulation and visualization of the large-scale structure of the universe</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105161855079392754">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap201025.html">via</a>), including webs of dark matter and the transition from an opaque early universe to its present mostly-transparent state.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.06838">The cocked hat</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105167862476053808">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). This interestingly-titled recent preprint by Bárány, Steiger, and Toledo concerns locating yourself by measuring angles to three landmarks. Usually, random error causes rays from the landmarks to form a triangle rather than meeting at a point. Supposedly this triangle contains your position with probability 1/4, but the preprint shows that this can be proven only for distributions that force the rays to form a triangle. See also Toledo’s new book, <em><a href="http://www.cs.tau.ac.il/~stoledo/LocationEstimationFromTheGroundUp/">Location Estimation from the Ground Up</a></em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:DMacks&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=987454393">MDPI is asking its authors to spam Wikipedia with their work</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105176559718608713">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), and <a href="https://www.elsevier.com/__data/assets/pdf_file/0013/201325/Get-Noticed_Brochure_2018.pdf">so is Elsevier</a>. I’m not surprised by MDPI doing this but, despite my low opinion of them, I thought Elsevier were better than that.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://drawingmachines.org/">Drawing machines</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105181738042763529">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25033793">via</a>). An archive of optical/mechanical/automated drawing machines/devices/aids.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LdnvxN4UUfs">Origami Fibonacci torus and knotted torus</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105184956163150834">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). I have the impression that the Fibonacci part just gives it a nice organic look, <a href="http://www.starcage.org/englishindex.html">visible in much of Akio Hizume’s other architecture</a>, but what interests me is the way it rotates smoothly. That’s not something unfolded paper can do, because the inner parts of a torus have negative curvature, the outer parts are positive, and unfolded paper can’t change curvature.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The floorplan below is of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K%C3%B6lntriangle">KölnTriangle</a>, a building in Cologne which has been claimed to be a Reuleaux triangle in cross-section (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105195769927037078">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Obviously it’s not. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torre_de_Collserola">Torre de Collserola in Barcelona</a> looks <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Barcelona_Torre_de_Collserola_Planol_Evacuacio.jpg">much more promising</a> but a published description of its specific architecture would help make that more clear.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="K&#xF6;lntriangle floor plan from CC-BY-SA image https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Fluchtwegeplan_K%C3%B6ln_Trangle.JPG by Bin im Garten, with overlaid Reuleaux triangle" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/KoelnTriangle-not-Reuleaux.jpg"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5094">The <em>Complexity Zoo</em> needs a new home</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105199077818825073">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Scott Aaronson’s collection of complexity classes and their relations had been at the U. Waterloo Institute for Quantum Computing, but their bureaucrats have decided that they cannot accept the liability of it possibly being out of compliance with accessibility rules, without allowing him to fix any issues or even tell him what issues it might have. As Scott writes, “Do you find it ironic that a central effect of these accessibility policies seems to be to make free academic content less accessible than before?”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Two more recent deaths in discrete mathematics and theoretical computer science (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105205573414576460">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>): <a href="http://emps.exeter.ac.uk/mathematics/news-events/news/articles/robinchapmanobituary.html">Robin J. Chapman, problem-solver extraordinaire</a> (and scarily almost exactly the same age as me), and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chung_Laung_Liu">Dave (C. L.) Liu</a>, early researcher in scheduling algorithms and VLSI layout and later president of National Tsing Hua University (<a href="https://news.ltn.com.tw/amp/news/life/breakingnews/3346060">Chinese-language obituary</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.the-sandpit.com/contortions/contort.htm">Contortion engineering</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105217523608810155">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Engineering-style drawings of Escher-like impossible objects. An old link from my old Geometry Junkyard site — its old earthlink url went dead some time after 2016, when archive.org last captured it, but now it has a new home.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-15T21:05:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-15T21:05:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T22:25:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=797</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2020/11/15/marijuana-brings-good-to-your-community/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Marijuana brings good to your community</title>
    <summary>Subsequence of official communication from Newton: […] recently reviewed applications from […] marijuana retailers who have submitted proposals […]. […] has a diverse management team with experience in the cannabis industry, equity, community relations and public health. […] certified by the Cannabis Control Commission as an Economic Empowerment Applicant, signifying that the applicant demonstrates experience […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Subsequence of official communication from Newton:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td><br/>[…] recently reviewed applications from […] marijuana retailers who have submitted proposals […].<br/><br/>[…] has a diverse management team with experience in the cannabis industry, equity, community relations and public health. […] certified by the Cannabis Control Commission as an Economic Empowerment Applicant, signifying that the applicant demonstrates experience in or business practices that promote economic empowerment in disproportionately impacted communities. Their plan involves […] additional parking on-site.<br/><br/>[…] also signing […] is a family owned and operated business. The company is certified by the Massachusetts Supplier Diversity Office as both a Minority Business and a Women Business Enterprise. […] will renovate the building and create surface parking. It has indicated it is willing to make transportation infrastructure improvements to the intersection […].<br/><br/>I am also signing […]. […] brings experience in the cannabis industry along with commitments to equity, public health, and community relations. […] will be constructing a new building and parking on what is currently a vacant parcel. <br/><br/>[…] with a revised plan to […] include more parking.<br/><br/></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td>Et cetera.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-15T12:40:43Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-15T12:40:43Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="marijuana"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:21:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-3746629932537659579</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/3746629932537659579/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/alex-trebekwhat-is-todays-post-about.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3746629932537659579" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3746629932537659579" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/alex-trebekwhat-is-todays-post-about.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Alex Trebek/What is today's post about?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> Alex Trebek, long time host of the TV show Jeopardy! (the exclamation point is part of the name, though I will omit it for the rest of the post), passed away in November of 2020 at the age of 80. He announced he had pancreatic cancer in March 2019.</p><p>0) <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/search?q=Jeopardy">Here</a> is a pointer to a page that has all of our posts with the word <i>Jeopardy </i>in them. Some are about the show and others mention the show in passing. All of the posts relate to the TV show. That is because Lance and I lead fairly safe lives.</p><p>1) On April Fools day of 1997 Pat Sajak hosted <i>Jeopardy</i> and Alex Trebek hosted <i>Wheel of Fortune</i>. Both are on You tube: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dtIT-jr1hmQ">Trebek hosts wheel</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LwVNmYjClXE">Pat hosts Jeopardy</a> Alex's hosting was more fun because- well, you can see for yourself. </p><p>2) Aside from that one day, Alex Trebek hosted <i>Jeopardy</i> every night since he began in 1984. </p><p>3) My favorite pangram (sentence that has all 26 letters) is</p><p>Watch <i>Jeopardy!</i>, Alex Trebek's fun TV quiz game show. </p><p>(See my post on natural pangrams <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2017/11/can-you-measure-which-panagrams-are.html">here</a> for... more natural pangrams and a discussion of what natural means.) </p><p>It's my favorite since I can really imagine someone saying it. The show should have used it for its tagline. And now they can't :-(</p><p>4) From Alex's comments he seems to like high scoring games that are not run-a-ways. He also likes when people bet big on the daily doubles and on<i> final Jeopardy</i>.  I think he liked having long win streaks like Ken Jenning's  and James Holzhauer, but see point 7 below.  I think he didn't like it when people go for the high scoring questions first (perhaps looking for the Daily Double) since sometimes the category name is not quite clear (e.g., <i>Country Groups</i> could be things like<i> NATO </i>or things like <i>The Charlie Daniels Band</i>) so you want to do a cheap question to get your feet wet, and also easier for the audience to see what the category means.  IMHO they should really make the Daily Double Uniformly distributed on all the squares instead of having it tend to be the bigger-money questions. </p><p>5) When the final <i>Jeopardy</i> category is  revealed he sometimes says <i>that's a  good category!</i> or <i>that sounds hard. </i> Makes me wonder that if he makes no comment he is thinking<i> that's a stupid categor</i>y  or <i>Gee that's easy.</i></p><p>6) Because of the pandemic they could not, for a while, make new shows. Hence  they aired old shows including the  first ever Alex-Trebek-<i>Jeopardy</i> (the show had been hosted by Art Fleming and the Trebek-version was really a reboot). From that show I found out WHY it's called<i> Jeopardy</i> (a question I had never thought about). It's because if you get an answer WRONG you can LOSE money- that's the Jeopardy. Not really a good name, but by now everyone knows the show by that name.</p><p>7) Art Fleming also died of pancreatic cancer, back in 1995 (he was 70). Coincidence? Well, yes, though two game show hosts of the same show dying of the same disease 25 years apart could be the premise of a really bad murder mystery. </p><p>8) Alex makes some small talk with the contestants  (though some is edited for time). Things like <i>I hear you have a book on muffins that is not a cookbook-- what's that all about?</i>' I wonder if during Ken Jenning's 74-long winning streak, towards the end,  Alex ran out of things to ask him. I can imagine <i>I hear you're pretty good at Jeopardy.</i></p><p>9) I wonder how good Alex would be playing <i>Jeopardy</i>. When he hosted <i>Wheel of Fortune</i> he said in passing that he would NEVER go on <i>Jeopardy</i> as a contestant, so he doesn't think he would do well. He could be wrong about that since over time they ask questions that are not quite repeats but draw on the same knowledge- and he's heard all of them. However, it could be that he is too busy concentrating on other things to really absorb all of this knowledge. </p><p>10) The <i>we give the answers you give the questions </i>is a bit odd. However, in my classes I  sometimes say  <i>We'll Trebek this - we know what the answer is, we have to find the question</i>.</p><p>11) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A7UgxCayfV0">This</a> youtube video is of a contestant singing WORDS to the <i>Jeopardy</i> theme song that he wrote.The contestant  refers to Jon Stewart as having also written words to the <i>Jeopardy</i> theme, but I can't find that anywhere- if you can, let me know. </p><p>12) Weird Al did a novelty song about <i>Jeopardy</i> using Art Fleming in the video (see  <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BvUZijEuNDQ">here</a>)  I always hoped he would update it and use Alex Trebek. He never did and now he can't :-( OR-with todays technology maybe he can. Here's hoping!</p><p>13) Alex Trebek was in a category by himself!</p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-14T20:26:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-14T20:26:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:01:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/14/pathbreaking-for-intervals</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/14/pathbreaking-for-intervals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Pathbreaking for intervals</title>
    <summary>The use of Nash’s Hex lemma in my previous post, according to which any 2-coloring of a triangular grid has a long monochromatic path, naturally raises the question: for which graphs other than the triangular grid is this true? In that post I mentioned that it is also true for certain outerplanar graphs, but false for bipartite graphs and for subcubic graphs. Here’s another class of graphs for which it is false: the graphs of bounded pathwidth. These graphs can always be 2-colored in a way that breaks up all long paths, leaving the remaining monochromatic paths of bounded size.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The use of Nash’s Hex lemma in <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/10/hex-books-queues.html">my previous post</a>, according to which any 2-coloring of a triangular grid has a long monochromatic path, naturally raises the question: for which graphs other than the triangular grid is this true? In that post I mentioned that it is also true for certain outerplanar graphs, but false for bipartite graphs and for subcubic graphs. Here’s another class of graphs for which it is false: the graphs of bounded <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pathwidth">pathwidth</a>. These graphs can always be 2-colored in a way that breaks up all long paths, leaving the remaining monochromatic paths of bounded size.</p>

<p>Rather than dealing with pathwidth directly, I want to formulate it geometrically in terms of interval graphs. Every graph can be completed (by adding extra edges) to form an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interval_graph">interval graph</a> of the same pathwidth; an interval graph has one-dimensional closed intervals as its vertices, connected by an edge whenever they intersect. The pathwidth of an interval graph is always one less than the maximum number of intervals that overlap at the same point (their ply). So rather than looking at graphs of bounded pathwidth I’ll be considering sets of intervals of bounded ply. For example in the illustration below which I drew a few years ago for Wikipedia, the intervals shown have ply 3, and their interval graph has pathwidth 2.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="A set of intervals and their associated interval graph" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/interval-graph.svg"/></p>

<p>Intervals with low ply that are all either nested or disjoint can have no long paths in their intersection graph regardless of coloring. In any set of intervals forming a path, the path can pass through the outermost level of nesting at most once, subdividing it into two smaller paths with lower ply. It follows by induction the number of intervals in the path can be at most \(2^{\operatorname{ply}}-1\). (This is the standard argument behind an equivalence in graphs between longest path length and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tree-depth">tree-depth</a>.) So if we could partition an arbitrary set of intervals into two subsets within which all intervals are nested or disjoint, we’d be done. For instance, in the example above, the partition into \(\{A,B,F\}\) and \(\{C,D,E,G\}\) works. Not every set of intervals can be partitioned in this way, but I’ll show below that it’s always possible to lengthen some intervals, keeping the ply small, so that the lengthened intervals can be partitioned (colored) into two nested subsets.</p>

<p>As a subroutine in the construction, let’s find a set of points with the following properties:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Each interval lies strictly between the leftmost and rightmost selected points.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>No interval covers more than one selected point.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The union of the intervals that cover selected points equals the union of all the intervals.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>This can be done by a greedy algorithm that repeatedly selects an uncovered interval endpoint until the intervals that cover selected points also cover all other interval endpoints. Finish by selecting any two points to the left and right of all the intervals, and then number the selected points as \(x_0,x_1,\dots\) in left-to-right order. For example, one possible choice for our example would have \(x_0\) to the left of the intervals, \(x_1\) at the left endpoint of \(D\), \(x_2\) at the left endpoint of \(F\), and \(x_3\) to the right of the intervals. For this choice, \(B\) and \(E\) do not cover any selected points, but that’s not a problem. It’s not necessary to optimize how many points are selected.</p>

<p>Call an interval “odd” if it covers an odd-numbered point \(x_i\) and “even” if it covers an even-numbered point. In our example, \(A\), \(C\), and \(D\) are odd, and \(F\), and \(G\) are even, but \(B\) and \(E\) are neither odd nor even. We will color the odd intervals blue and the even intervals red. Because they are different colors, we don’t have to worry about nesting between odd and even intervals. However, the intervals that contain any single point \(x_i\) will have the same color and need to be lengthened to nesting intervals. To do so, we extend all these intervals to a single longer interval, from just after \(x_{i-1}\) to just before \(x_{i+1}\). Because of the way the points \(x_i\) were chosen, this does not create new intersections between intervals of the same color, and it makes all colored intervals nest with all uncolored ones (not just with each other). However, it can also increase the ply. If the ply was \(p\) previously, it can increase by as much as \(2p-1\), when a point that was previously covered by only one odd or even interval becomes covered by \(2p-1\) more of them.</p>

<p>Finally, we apply the same coloring and lengthening process recursively, to the remaining subsets of uncolored intervals between each pair of selected points.
To make sure the intervals stay nested after lengthening, we take care in each recursive subproblem to select its first and last points to be inside all intervals of the outer problem that contain the subproblem. Because every point in an interval of a recursive subproblem is also in at least one of the outer colored intervals, the recursive subproblem has smaller ply than the initial ply of the outer problem. The recursion stops at ply 2; for this ply the intersection graph is a tree (more precisely a caterpillar) and it is possible to 2-color the intervals without any lengthening so that no two intervals of the same color intersect, by 2-coloring the tree.</p>

<p>So if we start with intervals of ply 2, we produce a lengthened, 2-colored, and monochromatically nested set of intervals of ply 2 again (no change to the ply). If we start with intervals of ply 3, we produce a lengthened, 2-colored, and monochromatically nested set of intervals of ply at most 8, because the ply-3 interval-lengthening process added at most 5 to the existing ply. More generally for any starting ply \(p\) the new ply will be at most \(p^2+p-4\). And since the interval graph for the lengthened intervals has no monochromatic path with more than \(2^{p^2+p-4}-1\) intervals in it, neither does the interval graph for the original intervals, with the same 2-coloring.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105211974100055236">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-14T17:59:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-14T17:59:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T22:25:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=20366</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/14/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-13-triangulating-real-projective-spaces-with-subexponentially-many-vertices/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>To cheer you up in difficult times 13: Triangulating real projective spaces with subexponentially many vertices</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wolfgang Kühnel Today I want to talk about a new result in a newly arXived paper: A subexponential size by Karim Adiprasito, Sergey Avvakumov, and Roman Karasev. Sergey Avvakumov gave about it a great zoom seminar talk about the result … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/14/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-13-triangulating-real-projective-spaces-with-subexponentially-many-vertices/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/wk.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-20381" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/wk.jpg?w=640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Wolfgang Kühnel</span></p>
<p>Today I want to talk about a new result in a newly arXived paper: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.02703">A subexponential size <img alt="\mathbb RP^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+RP%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb RP^n"/> by Karim Adiprasito, Sergey Avvakumov, and Roman Karasev</a>. Sergey Avvakumov gave about it a <strong>great</strong> zoom seminar talk about the result in our combinatorics seminar. <a href="https://huji.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=602454e6-d104-42fe-849c-ac6000b7517b">Here is the link</a>.</p>
<p>The question is very simple: <strong>W<span style="color: #0000ff;">hat is the smallest number of vertices required to triangulate the <em>n</em>-dimensional real projective space?</span></strong></p>
<p>The short paper exhibits a triangulation with <img alt="\exp (\frac {1}{2} \sqrt n \log n)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cexp+%28%5Cfrac+%7B1%7D%7B2%7D+%5Csqrt+n+%5Clog+n%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\exp (\frac {1}{2} \sqrt n \log n)"/> vertices.  This is the first construction that requires subexponential number of vertices in the dimension. The best lower bound by Pierre Arnoux and Alexis Marin (from 1999) are quadratic, so there is quite a way to go with the problem. I am thankful to Ryan Alweiss who was the first to tell me about the new result.</p>
<h2>Reasons to care</h2>
<p>Representing a topological space using simplicial complexes arose in the early days of algebraic topology, but there are certainly more “efficient” representations. What is the reason to to care specifically about representations via simplicial complexes? Here are my answers</p>
<ol>
<li>Constructions of triangulated manifolds with few vertices are occasionally amazing mathematical objects.</li>
<li>Simplicial complexes arise in many combinatorial and algebraic contexts,</li>
<li>The study of face numbers of simplicial complexes with various topological properties is often related to deep questions in algebra, geometry, and topology,</li>
<li>We care also about other types of representation.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Kühnel and Lassmann’s complex projective plane with nine vertices and other miracles</h2>
<p>You may all be familiar with the 6-vertex triangulation of the projective space. It is obtained by identifying opposite faces of the icosahedron. It is 2-neighborly, namely every pair of vertices span an edge of the triangulation. (It also played a role in my high dimensional extension of Cayley’s counting trees formula.) The existence of 2-neighborly triangulations of other closed surfaces is essentially the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heawood_conjecture">Heawood 1890 conjecture</a> solved by Ringel and Young in the 1960s.</p>
<p>In 1980 Wolfgang Kühnel set out to construct a 3-neighborly triangulation of the complex projective plane with 9 vertices. The construction, achieved in <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0097316583900055?via%3Dihub">a paper by Kühnel and Lassmann</a> (who also proved uniqueness), and discussed in <a href="http://www.math.brown.edu/~banchoff/howison/newbanchoff/publications/pdfs/9Vertex.pdf">a paper of the same year by Kühnel and Banchof</a>, is, in my view, among the most beautiful constructions in mathematics with additional hidden structures and many connections. Some motivation to the work came from the study of tight embeddings of smooth manifolds and Morse theory.</p>
<p>Ulrich Brehm and Kühnel <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0040938387900425?via%3Dihub">proved</a> that if a <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-1-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-1"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-2"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-3">d</span></span></span></span>-manifold has fewer than <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-2-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-4"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-5"><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-6">3</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-7">⌈</span><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-8">d</span><span class="texatom" id="MathJax-Span-9"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-10"><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-11">/</span></span></span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-12">2</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-13">⌉</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-14">+</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-15">3</span></span></span></span> vertices then it is homeomorphic to a sphere, and if it has exactly <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-3-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-16"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-17"><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-18">3</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-19">(</span><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-20">d</span><span class="texatom" id="MathJax-Span-21"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-22"><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-23">/</span></span></span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-24">2</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-25">)</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-26">+</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-27">3</span></span></span></span> vertices and is not a sphere, then <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-4-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-28"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-29"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-30">d</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-31">=</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-32">2</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-33">,</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-34">4</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-35">,</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-36">8</span></span></span></span> or <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-5-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-37"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-38"><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-39">16</span></span></span></span> and the manifold has a nondegenerate height function with exactly three critical points. The 6-vertex <img alt="\mathbb RP^2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+RP%5E2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb RP^2"/> and the 9-vertex $\mathbbCP^2$ are examples for dimensions 2 and 4. We can expect further such examples for projective planes over the quaternions and octonions. <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2FBF01934320">Brehm and Kühnel</a> constructed three 8-dimensional 5-neighborly “manifolds” which are not combinatorially isomorphic. It is conjectured but not known that they all triangulate the quaternionic projective plane.</p>
<h2>The result of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.02703">Adiprasito, Avvakumov, and Karasev</a> as <a href="https://huji.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=602454e6-d104-42fe-849c-ac6000b7517b">told by Sergey Avvakumov</a>.</h2>
<p>Here is a brief description of Sergey Avvakumov’s lecture. (As far as I could see the proof of their result is fully presented along with  3 other proofs for basic related results.)</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>06:00</strong></span>  The lecture starts. A simple inductive constructions of  a triangulation of <img alt="\mathbb R P^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+R+P%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb R P^n"/>.</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>08:00</strong></span>  Equivalent statement: we seek a centrally symmetric triangulation of the n-sphere with diameter 3.</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">09:00</span></strong> 6-vertex triangulation of  <img alt="\mathbb R P^2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+R+P%5E2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb R P^2"/></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">11:00</span></strong> The construction: triangulate the positive facets of the cross polytope and symmetrically the negative facet. Follow a recipe to triangulate the side facets. Crucial question: what is needed from the triangulation T of the positive facet. Answer: <span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>No edge between two disjoint faces</strong></span>.</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>23:00</strong> </span>Spherical interpretation and Delaunay triangulations of a certain configuration V</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">31:00</span></strong>   A sufficient combinatorial condition</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">39:00</span></strong> Proof of sufficiency</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">54:00</span></strong> The construction!</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">1:09:00</span></strong> Counting the number of vertices completes the proof of the theorem.</p>
<p>Additional matters</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">1:11:00</span></strong> A proof of a quadratic lower bound by Kuhnel.</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">1:21:00</span></strong> Proof of the facet lower bound (Barany and Lovasz) via Borsuk-Ulam</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/semtri7.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-20397" height="306" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/semtri7.png?w=640&amp;h=306" width="640"/></a></p>
<h2>Open problems and Low dimensions</h2>
<p>Of course a main question is what is the minimum number of vertices required for a triangulation of n dimensional real projective space. What about the n-dimensional complex projective space? What is the situation for low dimensions? See also the paper by Sonia Balagopalan, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1409.6149">On a vertex-minimal triangulation of RP^4</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-14T17:52:54Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-14T17:52:54Z</published>
    <category term="Algebra"/>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <category term="Karim Adiprasito"/>
    <category term="Roman Karasev"/>
    <category term="Sergey Avvakumov"/>
    <category term="Wolfgang Kuhnel"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/14/postdoc-positions-at-foundations-of-data-science-institute-fodsi-apply-by-december-1-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/14/postdoc-positions-at-foundations-of-data-science-institute-fodsi-apply-by-december-1-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc positions at Foundations of Data Science Institute (FODSI) (apply by December 1, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Foundations of Data Science Institute (FODSI), funded by the National Science Foundation TRIPODS program, is announcing a competitive postdoctoral fellowship. Multiple positions are available. FODSI is a collaboration between UC Berkeley and MIT, partnering with Boston University, Northeastern University, Harvard University, Howard University and Bryn Mawr College. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17305 Email: see the URL</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Foundations of Data Science Institute (FODSI), funded by the National Science Foundation TRIPODS program, is announcing a competitive postdoctoral fellowship. Multiple positions are available. FODSI is a collaboration between UC Berkeley and MIT, partnering with Boston University, Northeastern University, Harvard University, Howard University and Bryn Mawr College.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17305">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17305</a><br/>
Email: see the URL</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-14T17:52:02Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-14T17:52:02Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T22:44:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/172</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/172" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-172 |  Optimal rate list decoding over bounded alphabets using algebraic-geometric codes | 

	Venkatesan Guruswami, 

	Chaoping Xing</title>
    <summary>We construct two classes of algebraic code families which are efficiently list decodable with small output list size from a fraction $1-R-\epsilon$ of adversarial errors where $R$ is the rate of the code, for any desired positive constant $\epsilon$. The alphabet size depends only on $\epsilon$ and is nearly-optimal.

The first class of codes are obtained by folding algebraic-geometric codes using automorphisms of the underlying function field. The second class of codes are obtained by restricting evaluation points of an algebraic-geometric code to rational points from a subfield. In both cases, we develop a linear-algebraic approach to perform list decoding, which pins down the candidate messages to a subspace with a nice "periodic" structure.

To prune this subspace and obtain a good bound on the list-size, we pick subcodes of these codes by pre-coding into certain subspace-evasive sets which are guaranteed to have small intersection with the sort of periodic subspaces that arise in our list decoding. We develop two approaches for constructing such subspace-evasive sets. The first is a Monte Carlo construction of hierearchical subspace-evasive (h.s.e) sets which leads to excellent list-size but is not explicit. The second approach exploits a further ultra-periodicity of our subspaces and uses a novel construct called subspace designs, which were subsequently constructed explicitly and also found further applications in pseudorandomness.

To get a family of codes over a fixed alphabet size, we instantiate our approach with algebraic-geometric codes based on the Garcia-Stichtenoth tower of function fields. Combining this with pruning via h.s.e sets yields codes list-decodable up to a $1-R-\epsilon$ error fraction with list size bounded by $O(1/\epsilon)$, matching the existential bound for random codes up to constant factors. Further, the alphabet size can be made $\exp(\tilde{O}(1/\epsilon^2))$ which is not much worse than the lower bound of $\exp(\Omega(1/\epsilon))$. The parameters we achieve are thus quite close to the  existential bounds in all three aspects---error-correction radius, alphabet size, and list-size---simultaneously. This construction is, however, Monte Carlo and the claimed list decoding property only holds with high probability. Once the code is (efficiently) sampled, the encoding/decoding algorithms are deterministic with a running time $O_\epsilon(N^c)$ for an absolute constant $c$, where $N$ is the code's block length.

Using subspace designs instead for the pruning, our approach yields a deterministic construction of an algebraic code family of rate $R$ with efficient list decoding from $1-R-\epsilon$ fraction of errors over an alphabet of constant size $\exp(\tilde{O}(1/\epsilon^2))$.  The list size bound is upper bounded by a very slowly growing function of the block length $N$; in particular, it is at most $O(\log^{(r)} N)$ (the $r$'th iterated logarithm) for any fixed integer $r$. The explicit construction avoids the shortcoming of the Monte Carlo sampling at the expense of a worse list size.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-13T15:16:25Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-13T15:16:25Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17747</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/12/the-art-of-math/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Art of Math</title>
    <summary>Art, history, and controversy Jemma Lorenat is an assistant professor at Pitzer College in Los Angeles. She teaches and does research on the history of mathematics. Today I thought we’d look at some of her work. History of math is one topic that we have focused on many times before. More on that in a […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Art, history, and controversy</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p>
Jemma Lorenat is an assistant professor at <a href="https://www.pitzer.edu">Pitzer College</a> in Los Angeles. She teaches and does research on the history of mathematics.<br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/12/the-art-of-math/jemma/" rel="attachment wp-att-17751"><img alt="" class="alignright size-full wp-image-17751" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/10/jemma.png?w=600"/></a></p>
<p>
Today I thought we’d look at some of her work. </p>
<p>
History of math is one topic that we have focused on many times before. More on that in a moment. </p>
<p>
<span id="more-17747"/></p>
<p/><h2> Her Art </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
But before we do that I wish to present Lorenat’s art work. My late father, Jack Lipton, was an artist and so perhaps I have a genetic interest in art. Lorenat is an artist besides being a mathematician. You can see some of her drawings of famous mathematicians <a href="https://www.maa.org/press/periodicals/convergence/portrait-gallery">here</a>. Her elegant style I find appealing. See if you like it as much as I do. My dad taught me: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> A clean drawing is more difficult to execute than a busy one. It is hard to hide flaws when your art is clean. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Her drawings are clean indeed. </p>
<p>
Here are three of Lorenat’s drawings of the following three famous mathematicians in some order: Which is which? Prizes will not be given to those with correct answers.</p>
<ol>
<li>
Eric Temple Bell <p/>
</li><li>
Jacques Hadamard <p/>
</li><li>
Henri Lebesgue
</li></ol>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/12/the-art-of-math/group-2/" rel="attachment wp-att-17753"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-17753" height="274" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/10/group.png?w=600&amp;h=274" width="600"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>

</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Her Research </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Lorenat’s research is on the history of mathematics. My first choice is to create math, but I am intrigued by the history of who did what, when, and why. We must understand history—at least in broad strokes—if we are to continue to make progress. History helps us understand how progress was made and how it was not. History teaches us much about our field, about mathematics. </p>
<p>
<a href="http://archives.math.utk.edu/topics/history.html">Several</a> online <a href="https://www.math.tamu.edu/~dallen/masters/hist_frame.htm">sources</a> show the field’s breadth and scope. Among issues and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_mathematics_history_topics">topics</a>, we note:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Who is a result named for? <p/>
</li><li>
Who gets the credit for a result? <p/>
</li><li>
What is the strongest result known? <p/>
</li><li>
Is this result correct?
</li></ul>
<p>
It is fun to see the process in action. One example I have been involved in for a long time is the study of vector addition systems and reachability problems. There continues to be exciting news, for instance, a <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1809.07115.pdf">paper</a> last year showing that a central reachability problem is vastly harder than had been conjectured. I will discuss, however, an issue from two centuries ago that Lorenat has illuminated.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Duality Controversy </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Lorenat has a <a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/78167-culturalcontextconference2015.pdf">talk</a> on the geometric theory of duality. It was a prime example of a controversy in the discover of a basic math idea. Here duality means: Given a statement from projective geometry we can flip points and lines and still leave its correctness invariant. This is the duality: 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  points \iff lines. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++points+%5Ciff+lines.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  points \iff lines. "/></p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/12/the-art-of-math/dual/" rel="attachment wp-att-17754"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-17754" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/10/dual.png?w=600"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>

</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
In complexity theory we have our own duality. Instead of flipping points and lines we can exchange boolean operations 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  AND \iff OR, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++AND+%5Ciff+OR%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  AND \iff OR, "/></p>
<p>and also exchange 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  0 \iff 1. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++0+%5Ciff+1.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  0 \iff 1. "/></p>
<p>	 Thus 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  (x \wedge y) \vee (x \wedge z) \iff (x \vee y) \wedge (x \vee z). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%28x+%5Cwedge+y%29+%5Cvee+%28x+%5Cwedge+z%29+%5Ciff+%28x+%5Cvee+y%29+%5Cwedge+%28x+%5Cvee+z%29.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  (x \wedge y) \vee (x \wedge z) \iff (x \vee y) \wedge (x \vee z). "/></p>
<p>		 Lorenat’s talk highlights a controversy between: Joseph Diaz Gergonne, Jean-Victor Poncelet, and Julius Plucker. Her work is <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/science-in-context/article/polemics-in-public-poncelet-gergonne-plucker-and-the-duality-controversy/C305E6B9326F2AC4C8AC31D4194FEDC6">here</a>. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> A plagiarism charge in 1827 sparked a public controversy centered between Jean-Victor Poncelet (1788-1867) and Joseph-Diez Gergonne (1771-1859) over the origin and applications of the principle of duality in geometry. Over the next three years and through the pages of various journals, monographs, letters, reviews, reports, and footnotes, vitriol between the antagonists increased as their potential publicity grew. While the historical literature offers valuable resources toward understanding the development, content, and applications of geometric duality, the hostile nature of the exchange seems to have deterred an in-depth textual study of the explicitly polemical writings. We argue that the necessary collective endeavor of beginning and ending this controversy constitutes a case study in the circulation of geometry. In particular, we consider how the duality controversy functioned as a medium of communicating new fundamental principles to a wider audience of practitioners. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
A further comment is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duality_(projective_geometry)">here</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Of this feud, Pierre Samuel has quipped that since both men were in the French army and Poncelet was a general while Gergonne a mere captain, Poncelet’s view prevailed, at least among their French contemporaries. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Did you see which drawing was which? </p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/12/the-art-of-math/answer-3/" rel="attachment wp-att-17763"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-17763" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/10/answer-1.png?w=600"/></a></p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-12T19:14:31Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-12T19:14:31Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="controversy"/>
    <category term="duality"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5094</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5094" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5094#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5094" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">The Complexity Zoo needs a new home</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Update (Nov. 14): I now have a deluge of serious hosting offers—thank you so much, everyone! No need for more. Since I’m now feeling better that the first authoritarian coup attempt in US history will probably sort itself out OK, here’s a real problem: Nearly a score years ago, I created the Complexity Zoo, a […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update (Nov. 14):</span></strong> I now have a deluge of serious hosting offers—thank you so much, everyone!  No need for more.</p>



<p/><hr/><p/>



<p>Since I’m now feeling better that the first authoritarian coup attempt in US history will probably sort itself out OK, here’s a <em>real</em> problem:</p>



<p>Nearly a score years ago, I created the <a href="https://complexityzoo.uwaterloo.ca/Complexity_Zoo">Complexity Zoo</a>, a procrastination project turned encyclopedia of complexity classes.  Nearly half a score years ago, the Zoo moved to my former employer, the <a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/institute-for-quantum-computing/">Institute for Quantum Computing</a> in Waterloo, Canada, which graciously hosted it ever since.  Alas, IQC has decided that it can no longer do so.  The reason is new regulations in Ontario about the accessibility of websites, which the Zoo might be out of compliance with.  My students and I were willing to look into what was needed—like, does the <a href="https://complexityzoo.uwaterloo.ca/Complexity_Zoo:P#ph">polynomial hierarchy</a> need ramps between its levels or something?  The best would be if we heard from actual blind or other disabled complexity enthusiasts about how we could improve their experience, rather than trying to parse bureaucratese from the Ontario government.  But IQC informed us that in any case, they can’t deal with the potential liability and their decision is final.  I thank them for hosting the Zoo for eight years.</p>



<p>Now I’m looking for a volunteer for a new host.  The Zoo runs on the <a href="https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/MediaWiki">MediaWiki</a> platform, which doesn’t work with my own hosting provider (Bluehost) but is apparently easy to set up if you, unlike me, are the kind of person who can do such things.  The IQC folks kindly offered to help with the transfer; I and my students can help as well.  It’s a small site with modest traffic.  The main things I need are just assurances that you can host the site for a long time (“forever” or thereabouts), and that you or someone else in your organization will be reachable if the site goes down or if there are other problems.  I own the complexityzoo.com domain and can redirect from there.</p>



<p>In return, you’ll get the immense prestige of hosting such a storied resource for theoretical computer science … plus free publicity for your cause or organization on <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em>, and the eternal gratitude of thousands of my readers.</p>



<p>Of course, if you’re <em>into</em> complexity theory, and you want to update or improve the Zoo while you’re at it, then so much the awesomer!  It could use some updates, badly.  But you don’t even <em>need</em> to know P from NP.</p>



<p>If you’re interested, leave a comment or shoot me an email.  Thanks!!</p>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Unrelated Announcement:</span></strong> I’ll once again be doing an Ask-Me-Anything session at the <a href="https://q2b.qcware.com/">Q2B (“Quantum to Business”)</a> conference, December 8-10.  Other speakers include Umesh Vazirani, John Preskill, Jennifer Ouellette, Eric Schmidt, and many others.  Since the conference will of course be virtual this year, registration is a lot cheaper than in previous years.  Check it out!  (Full disclosure: Q2B is organized by <a href="https://qcware.com/">QC Ware, Inc.</a>, for which I’m a scientific advisor.)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-12T19:10:44Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-12T19:10:44Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Self-Referential"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T01:50:07Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7166344296310393734</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7166344296310393734/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/recovery.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7166344296310393734" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7166344296310393734" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/recovery.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Recovery</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Lance</b>: Perhaps we should do a post-election vidcast--what does it mean for complexity!</p><p><b>Bill</b>: Not sure if you are serious- but I doubt a Biden presidency will either speed up or slow down the proof that P NE NP or anything else in complexity. Did Trump give LESS money to the NSF and other funding agencies, and will Biden give more? I doubt it. </p><p><b>Lance: </b>Trump's budget did call for a massive cut for the NSF but luckily he doesn't control the purse strings. It's the immigration policy that worried me--both that it keeps good students from coming to the US and that it cuts off a revenue source that will cause many good schools to close down.</p><p><b>Bill: </b>Excellent point- but sounds more like a post you could write since you... know stuff, as opposed to a vidcast with me who... doesn't know stuff. </p><hr/><p>Bill sells himself short and me long but here is my post.</p><p>After Trump was elected in 2016 I thought maybe Trump with all his bluster will just be a typical conservative politician that we can live through until the next election. That didn't last long with his travel ban for Iranians just a few weeks after his inauguration <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2017/02/we-are-all-iranians.html">when I said</a> "This is not the America I believe in."</p><p>Judges have stopped the worst of Trump's travel bans but he has continued to whittle down the number of available visas, made it harder to get visas and get visas after they graduate. New students can't come to America if they take only on-line courses at a time many universities are online. Now students will have to get their visas renewed after two or four years. Few get a PhD in four years and would students come here and take the risk that their visas won't get renewed before they can finish? The <a href="https://cra.org/govaffairs/blog/2020/10/three-new-immigration-rule-changes/">CRA has some details</a> on the newest rules. Not to mention Trump's handling of COVID--would you send your kid to America now?</p><p>Trump hasn't hidden his disdain for higher education and had he won a second term his policies would greatly diminish the country's academic strength. Biden can and certainly will undo much of these changes and I hope it is not too late. </p><p>More from <a href="https://www.chronicle.com/article/bidens-victory-has-elated-international-students-but-the-road-to-lasting-reform-is-long">The Chronicle</a>.</p><p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-12T15:07:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-12T15:07:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T17:01:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
