<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-04-09T00:21:42Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/04/08/computer-science-summer-in-russia/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/04/08/computer-science-summer-in-russia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Computer Science Summer in Russia</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">June 24 – July 5, 2019 Akademgorodok, Novosibirsk, Russia http://cssr.nsu.ru/school/ Registration deadline: May 12, 2019 The school will take place from 24 -29 June, 2019 at Novosibirsk State University and targets student audience from Russia and neighbor countries. The school consists of two parallel tracks: The Theory of Programming + Methods of Software Verification &amp; … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/04/08/computer-science-summer-in-russia/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Computer Science Summer in Russia</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:07:16Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-08T23:07:16Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:21:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://bit-player.org/?p=2150</id>
    <link href="http://bit-player.org/2019/737-the-max-mess" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://bit-player.org/2019/737-the-max-mess#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://bit-player.org/2019/737-the-max-mess/feed/atom" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">737: The MAX Mess</title>
    <summary type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Controlled Flight into Terrain is the aviation industry’s term for what happens when a properly functioning airplane plows into the ground because the pilots are distracted or disoriented. What a nightmare. Even worse, in my estimation, is Automated Flight into … <a href="http://bit-player.org/2019/737-the-max-mess">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>Controlled Flight into Terrain</em> is the aviation industry’s term for what happens when a properly functioning airplane plows into the ground because the pilots are distracted or disoriented. What a nightmare. Even worse, in my estimation, is <em>Automated Flight into Terrain</em>, when an aircraft’s control system forces it into a fatal nose dive despite the frantic efforts of the crew to save it. That is the conjectured cause of two recent crashes of new Boeing 737 MAX 8 airplanes. I’ve been trying to reason my way through to an understanding of how those accidents could have happened.</p>
<p>Disclaimer: The investigations of the MAX 8 disasters are in an early stage, so much of what follows is based on secondary sources—in other words, on leaks and rumors and the speculations of people who may or may not know what they’re talking about. As for my own speculations: I’m not an aeronautical engineer, or an airframe mechanic, or a control theorist. I’m not even a pilot. Please keep that in mind if you choose to read on.</p>
<h3>The accidents</h3>
<p>Early on the morning of October 29, 2018, Lion Air Flight 610 departed Jakarta, Indonesia, with 189 people on board. The airplane was a four-month-old 737 MAX 8—the latest model in a line of Boeing aircraft that goes back to the 1960s. Takeoff and climb were normal to about 1,600 feet, where the pilots retracted the flaps (wing extensions that increase lift at low speed). At that point the aircraft unexpectedly descended to 900 feet. In radio conversations with air traffic controllers, the pilots reported a “flight control problem” and asked about their altitude and speed as displayed on the controllers’ radar screens. Cockpit instruments were giving inconsistent readings. The pilots then redeployed the flaps and climbed to 5,000 feet, but when the flaps were stowed again, the nose dipped and the plane began to lose altitude. Over the next six or seven minutes the pilots engaged in a tug of war with their own aircraft, as they struggled to keep the nose level but the flight control system repeatedly pushed it down. In the end the machine won. The airplane plunged into the sea at high speed, killing everyone aboard.</p>
<p>The second crash happened March 8, when Ethiopian Airlines Flight 302 went down six minutes after taking off from Addis Ababa, killing 157. The aircraft was another MAX 8, just two months old. The pilots reported control problems, and data from a satellite tracking service showed sharp fluctuations in altitude. The similarities to the Lion Air crash set off alarm bells: If the same malfunction or design flaw caused both accidents, it might also cause more. Within days, the worldwide fleet of 737 MAX aircraft was grounded. Data recovered since then from the Flight 302 wreckage has reinforced the suspicion that the two accidents are closely related.</p>
<p>The grim fate of Lion Air 610 can be traced in brightly colored squiggles extracted from the flight data recorder. (The chart was published in November in a <a href="http://jacdec.de/database/2018-10-29_PK-LQP-NTSC_Preliminary%20Report.pdf">preliminary report</a> from the Indonesian National Committee on Transportation Safety.)</p>
<p><img alt="Lion Air 610 flight data chart 1280" border="0" class="centered withLoupe" height="834" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Lion-Air-610-flight-data-chart-1280.jpg" width="900"/></p>
<p>The outline of the story is given in the altitude traces at the bottom of the chart. The initial climb is interrupted by a sharp dip; then a further climb is followed by a long, erratic roller coaster ride. At the end comes the dive, as the aircraft plunges 5,000 feet in a little more than 10 seconds. (Why are there two altitude curves, separated by a few hundred feet? I’ll come back to that question at the end of this long screed.)</p>
<p>All those ups and downs were caused by movements of the horizontal stabilizer, the small winglike control surface at the rear of the fuselage. <img alt="Stabilizer elevator diagram" border="0" class="alignright" height="" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/stabilizer_elevator_diagram.svg" style="margin-bottom: 12px;" width="250"/>The stabilizer controls the airplane’s pitch attitude—nose-up vs. nose-down. On the 737 it does so in two ways. A mechanism for pitch <em>trim</em> tilts the entire stabilizer, whereas push­ing or pulling on the pilot’s control yoke moves the elevator, a hinged tab at the rear of the stabilizer. In either case, moving the trailing edge of the surface upward tends to force the nose of the airplane up, and vice versa. Here we’re mainly concerned with trim changes rather than elevator movements.</p>
<p>Commands to the pitch-trim system and their effect on the airplane are shown in three traces from the flight data, which I reproduce here for convenience:</p>
<p><img alt="Lion Air 610 flight data chart trim commands" border="0" class="aligncenter" height="117" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Lion-Air-610-flight-data-chart-trim-commands.jpg" width="640"/></p>
<p>The line labeled “trim manual” <em>(light blue)</em> reflects the pilots’ inputs, “trim automatic” <em>(orange)</em> shows commands from the airplane’s electronic systems, and “pitch trim position” <em>(dark blue)</em> represents the tilt of the stabilizer, with higher position on the scale denoting a nose-up command. This is where the tug of war between man and machine is clearly evident. In the latter half of the flight, the automatic trim system repeatedly commands nose down, at intervals of roughly 10 seconds. In the breaks between those automated commands, the pilots dial in nose-up trim, using buttons on the control yoke. In response to these conflicting commands, the position of the horizontal stabilizer oscillates with a period of 15 or 20 seconds. The see-sawing motion continues for at least 20 cycles, but toward the end the unrelenting automatic nose-down adjustments prevail over the briefer nose-up commands from the pilots. The stabilizer finally reaches its limiting nose-down deflection and stays there as the airplane plummets into the sea.</p>
<h3>Angle of attack</h3>
<p>What’s to blame for the perverse behavior of the automatic pitch trim system? The accusatory finger is pointing at something called MCAS, a new feature of the 737 MAX series. MCAS stands for Maneuvering Characteristics Augmentation System—an im­pressively polysyllabic name that tells you nothing about what the thing is or what it does. As I understand it, MCAS is not a piece of hardware; there’s no box labeled MCAS in the airplane’s electronic equipment bays. MCAS consists entirely of software. It’s a program running on a computer.</p>
<p>MCAS has just one function. It is designed to help prevent an aerodynamic stall, a situation in which an airplane has its nose pointed up so high with respect to the surrounding airflow that the wings can’t keep it aloft. A stall is a little like what happens to a bicyclist climbing a hill that keeps getting steeper and steeper: Eventually the rider runs out of oomph, wobbles a bit, and then rolls back to the bottom. Pilots are taught to recover from stalls, but it’s not a skill they routinely practice with a planeful of passengers. In commercial aviation the emphasis is on <em>avoiding</em> stalls—forestalling them, so to speak. Airliners have mechanisms to detect an imminent stall and warn the pilot with lights and horns and a “stick shaker” that vibrates the control yoke. On Flight 610, the captain’s stick was shaking almost from start to finish.</p>
<p>Some aircraft go beyond mere warnings when a stall threatens. If the aircraft’s nose continues to pitch upward, an automated system intervenes to push it back down—if necessary overriding the manual control inputs of the pilot. MCAS is designed to do exactly this. It is armed and ready whenever two criteria are met: The flaps are up (generally true except during takeoff and landing) and the airplane is under manual control (not autopilot). Under these conditions the system is triggered whenever an aerodynamic quantity called angle of attack, or AoA, rises into a dangerous range.</p>
<p>Angle of attack is a concept subtle enough to merit a diagram:Adapted from Lisa R. Le Vie, <a href="https://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/20140011419.pdf">Review of Research on Angle-of-Attack Indi­cator Effectiveness</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="Le Vie angle of attack diagram detail" border="0" class="centered" height="229" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/Le-Vie-angle-of-attack-diagram-detail.png" width="607"/></p>
<p class="undent">The various angles at issue are rotations of the aircraft body around the pitch axis, a line parallel to the wings, perpendicular to the fuselage, and passing through the airplane’s center of gravity. If you’re sitting in an exit row, the pitch axis might run right under your seat. Rotation about the pitch axis tilts the nose up or down. <em>Pitch attitude</em> is defined as the angle of the fuselage with respect to a horizontal plane. The <em>flight-path angle</em> is measured between the horizontal plane and the aircraft’s velocity vector, thus showing how steeply it is climbing or descending. <em>Angle of attack</em> is the difference between pitch attitude and flight-path angle. It is the angle at which the aircraft is moving through the surrounding air (assuming the air itself is motionless, <em>i.e.</em>, no wind).</p>
<p>AoA affects both lift (the upward force opposing the downward tug of gravity) and drag (the dissipative force opposing forward motion and the thrust of the engines). As AoA increases from zero, lift is enhanced because of air impinging on the underside of the wings and fuselage. For the same reason, however, drag also increases. As the angle of attack grows even steeper, the flow of air over the wings becomes turbulent; beyond that point lift diminishes but drag continues increasing. That’s where the stall sets in. The critical angle for a stall depends on speed, weight, and other factors, but usually it’s no more than 15 degrees.</p>
<p>Neither the Lion Air nor the Ethiopian flight was ever in danger of stalling, so if MCAS was activated, it must have been by mistake. The working hypothesis mentioned in many press accounts is that the system received and acted upon erroneous input from a failed AoA sensor. </p>
<p>A sensor to measure angle of attack is conceptually simple. It’s essentially a weather­vane poking out into the airstream. In the photo below, the angle-of-attack sensor is the small black vane just forward of the “737 MAX” legend. Hinged at the front, the vane rotates to align itself with the local airflow and generates an electrical signal that rep­resents the vane’s angle with respect to the axis of the fuselage. The 737 MAX has two angle-of-attack vanes, one on each side of the nose. (The protruding devices above the AoA vane are pitot tubes, used to measure air speed. Another device below the word MAX is probably a temperature sensor.)</p>
<p><img alt="SpiritofRenton nose1280" border="0" class="centered" height="452" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/SpiritofRenton-nose1280.jpg" width="640"/></p>
<p class="indent">Angle of attack was not among the variables displayed to the pilots of the Lion Air 737, but the flight data recorder did capture signals derived from the two AoA sensors:</p>
<p><img alt="Lion Air 610 flight data chart AoA details" border="0" class="centered" height="60" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Lion-Air-610-flight-data-chart-AoA-details.jpg" width="640"/></p>
<p class="undent">There’s something dreadfully wrong here. The left sensor is indicating an angle of attack about 20 degrees steeper than the right sensor. That’s a huge discrepancy. There’s no plausible way those disparate readings could reflect the true state of the airplane’s motion through the air, with the left side of the nose pointing sky-high and the right side near level. One of the measurements must be wrong, and the higher reading is the suspect one. If the true angle of attack ever reached 20 degrees, the airplane would already be in a deep stall. Unfortunately, on Flight 610 MCAS was taking data only from the left-side AoA sensor. It interpreted the nonsensical measurement as a valid indicator of aircraft attitude, and worked relentlessly to correct it, up to the very moment the airplane hit the sea.</p>
<h3>Cockpit automation</h3>
<p>The tragedies in Jakarta and Addis Ababa are being framed as a cautionary tale of automation run amok, with computers usurping the authority of pilots. The <em>Washington Post</em> <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/the-boeing-crashes-are-a-cautionary-tale-about-automation/2019/03/27/62c09154-4fd0-11e9-8d28-f5149e5a2fda_story.html?utm_term=.514085b92e47">editorialized</a>: </p>
<blockquote><p>A second fatal airplane accident involving a Boeing 737 MAX 8 may have been a case of man vs. machine…. The debacle shows that regulators should apply extra review to systems that take control away from humans when safety is at stake.</p></blockquote>
<p class="undent">Tom Dieusaert, a Belgian journalist who writes often on aviation and computation, offered this <a href="https://medium.com/crash-investigators/computer-crash-on-a-boeing-what-we-do-know-about-lion-air-jt610-9b5dbd654c75">opinion</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>What can’t be denied is that the Boeing of Flight JT610 had serious computer problems. And in the hi-tech, fly-by-wire world of aircraft manufacturers, where pilots are reduced to button pushers and passive observers, these accidents are prone to happen more in the future.</p></blockquote>
<p>The button-pushing pilots are particularly irate. <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1249KS8xtIDKb5SxgpeFI6AD-PSC6nFA5/view">Gregory Travis</a>, who is both a pilot and software developer, summed up his feelings in this acerbic comment:</p>
<blockquote><p>“Raise the nose, HAL.” </p>
<p class="undent">“I’m sorry, Dave, I can’t do that.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even Donald Trump <a href="https://twitter.com/realDonaldTrump/status/1105468569800839169">tweeted</a> on the issue:</p>
<blockquote><p>Airplanes are becoming far too complex to fly. Pilots are no longer needed, but rather computer scientists from MIT. I see it all the time in many products. Always seeking to go one unnecessary step further, when often old and simpler is far better. Split second decisions are…. </p>
<p>….needed, and the complexity creates danger. All of this for great cost yet very little gain. I don’t know about you, but I don’t want Albert Einstein to be my pilot. I want great flying professionals that are allowed to easily and quickly take control of a plane!</p></blockquote>
<p>There’s considerable irony in the complaint that the 737 is too automated; in many respects the aircraft is in fact quaintly old-fashioned. The basic design goes back more than 50 years, and even in the latest MAX models quite a lot of 1960s technology survives. The primary flight controls are hydraulic, with a spider web of high-pressure tubing running directly from the control yokes in the cockpit to the ailerons, elevator, and rudder. If the hydraulic systems should fail, there’s a purely mechanical backup, with cables and pulleys to operate the various control surfaces. For stabilizer trim the primary actuator is an electric motor, but again there’s a mechanical fallback, with crank wheels near the pilots’ knees pulling on cables that run all the way back to the tail.</p>
<p>Other aircraft are much more dependent on computers and electronics. The 737′s principal competitor, the Airbus A320, is a thoroughgoing fly-by-wire vehicle. The pilot flies the computer, and the computer flies the airplane. Specifically, the pilot decides where to go—up, down, left, right—but the computer decides how to get there, choosing which control surfaces to deflect and by how much. Boeing’s own more recent designs, the 777 and 787, also rely on digital controls. Indeed, the latest models from both companies go a step beyond fly-by-wire to fly-by-network. Most of the communication from sensors to computers and onward to control surfaces consists of digital packets flowing through a <a href="https://ntrs.nasa.gov/archive/nasa/casi.ntrs.nasa.gov/20150011061.pdf">variant of Ethernet</a>. The airplane is a computer peripheral.</p>
<p>Thus if you want to gripe about the dangers and indignities of automation on the flight deck, the 737 is not the most obvious place to start. And a Luddite campaign to smash all the avionics and put pilots back in the seat of their pants would be a dangerously off-target response to the current predicament. There’s no question the 737 MAX has a critical problem. It’s a matter of life and death for those who would fly in it and possibly also for the Boeing Company. But the problem didn’t start with MCAS. It started with earlier decisions that made MCAS necessary. Furthermore, the problem may not end with the remedy that Boeing has proposed—a software update that will hobble MCAS and leave more to the discretion of pilots.</p>
<h3>Maxing out the 737</h3>
<p>The 737 flew its first passengers in 1968. It was (and still is) the smallest member of the Boeing family of jet airliners, and it is also the most popular by far. More than 10,000 have been sold, and Boeing has orders for another 4,600. Of course there have been changes over the years, especially to engines and instruments. A 1980s update came to be known as 737 Classic, and a 1997 model was called 737 NG, for “next generation.” (Now, with the MAX, the NG has become the <em>previous</em> generation.) Through all these revisions, however, the basic structure of the airframe has hardly changed.</p>
<p>Ten years ago, it looked like the 737 had finally come to the end of its life. Boeing announced it would develop an all-new design as a replacement, with a hull built of lightweight composite materials rather than aluminum. Competitive pressures forced a change of course. Airbus had a head start on the A320neo, an update that would bring more efficient engines to their entry in the same market segment. The revised Airbus would be ready around 2015, whereas Boeing’s clean-slate project would take a decade. Customers were threatening to defect. In particular, American Airlines—long a Boeing loyalist—was negotiating a large order of A320neos. </p>
<p>In 2011 Boeing scrapped the plan for an all-new design and elected to do the same thing Airbus was doing: bolt new engines onto an old airframe. This would eliminate most of the up-front design work, as well as the need to build tooling and manufacturing facilities. Testing and certification by the FAA would also go quicker, so that the first deliveries might be made in five or six years, not too far behind Airbus.</p>
<p>A 737-800 (a pre-MAX model) burns about 800 gallons of jet fuel per hour aloft. That comes to $2,000 at $2.50 per gallon. If the airplane flies 10 hours a day, the annual fuel bill is $7.3 million. Fourteen percent of that is just over $1 million.The new engines mated to the 737 promised a 14 percent gain in fuel efficiency, which might save an airline a million dollars a year in operating costs. The better fuel economy would also increase the airplane’s range. And to sweeten the deal Boeing proposed to keep enough of the airframe unchanged that the new model would operate under the same “type certificate” as the old one. A pilot qualified to fly the 737 NG could step into the MAX without extensive retraining.</p>
<p><img alt="737 200 and 737 MAX compared" border="0" class="centered" height="272" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/737-200-and-737-MAX-compared.jpg" width="640"/>Sources: <em>(left)</em> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/people/12094576@N08">Bryan</a> via Wikimedia, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/deed.en">CC BY 2.0</a>; <em>(right)</em> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/people/71965027@N02">Steve Lynes</a> via Wikimedia, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/deed.en">CC BY 2.0</a>.</p>
<p class="indent">The original 1960s 737 had two cigar-shaped engines, long and skinny, tucked up under the wings <em>(left photo above)</em>. Since then, jet engines have grown fat and stubby. They derive much of their thrust not from the jet exhaust coming out of the tailpipe but from “bypass” air moved by a large-diameter fan. Such engines would scrape on the ground if they were mounted under the wings of the 737; instead they are perched on pylons that extend forward from the leading edge of the wing. The engines on the MAX models <em>(right photo)</em> are the fattest yet, with a fan 69 inches in diameter. Compared with the NG series, the MAX engines are pushed a few inches farther forward and hang a few inches lower.</p>
<p>A <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/23/business/boeing-737-max-crash.html?action=click&amp;module=RelatedCoverage&amp;pgtype=Article&amp;region=Footer">New York Times article</a> by David Gelles, Natalie Kitroeff, Jack Nicas, and Rebecca R. Ruiz describes the plane’s development as hurried and hectic.</p>
<blockquote><p>Months behind Airbus, Boeing had to play catch-up. The pace of the work on the 737 Max was frenetic, according to current and former employees who spoke with <em>The New York Times</em>…. Engineers were pushed to submit technical drawings and designs at roughly double the normal pace, former employees said.</p></blockquote>
<p>The <em>Times</em> article also notes:  “Although the project had been hectic, current and former employees said they had finished it feeling confident in the safety of the plane.” </p>
<h3>Pitch instability</h3>
<p>Sometime during the development of the MAX series, Boeing got an unpleasant surprise. The new engines were causing unwanted pitch-up movements under certain flight con­ditions. When I first read about this problem, soon after the Lion Air crash, I found the following explanation is an article by Sean Broderick and Guy Norris in <em>Aviation Week and Space Technology</em> (Nov. 26–Dec. 9, 2018, pp. 56–57):</p>
<blockquote><p>Like all turbofan-powered airliners in which the thrust lines of the engines pass below the center of gravity (CG), any change in thrust on the 737 will result in a change of flight path angle caused by the vertical component of thrust.</p></blockquote>
<p>In other words, the low-slung engines not only push the airplane forward but also tend to twirl it around the pitch axis. It’s like a motorcycle doing wheelies. Because the MAX engines are mounted farther below and in front of the center of gravity, they act through a longer lever arm and cause more severe pitch-up motions. </p>
<p>I found more detail on this effect in an <a href="https://aviationweek.com/commercial-aviation/pilot-report-flying-737-8-boeing-s-new-narrowbody-breadwinner">earlier <em>Aviation Week</em> article</a>, a 2017 pilot report by Fred George, describing his first flight at the controls of the new MAX 8. </p>
<blockquote><p>The aircraft has sufficient natural speed stability through much of its flight envelope. But with as much as 58,000 lb. of thrust available from engines mounted well below the center of gravity, there is pronounced thrust-versus-pitch coupling at low speeds, especially with aft center of gravity (CG) and at light gross weights. Boeing equips the aircraft with a speed-stability augmen­tation function that helps to compensate for the coupling by automatically trimming the horizontal stabilizer according to indicated speed, thrust lever position and CG. Pilots still must be aware of the effect of thrust changes on pitching moment and make purposeful control-wheel and pitch-trim inputs to counter it.</p></blockquote>
<p>The reference to an “augmentation function” that works by “automatically trimming the horizontal stabilizer” sounded awfully familiar, but it turns out this is <em>not</em> MCAS. The system that compensates for thrust-pitch coupling is known as <em>speed-trim</em>. Like MCAS, it works “behind the pilot’s back,” making adjustments to control surfaces that were not directly commanded. There’s yet another system of this kind called <em>mach-trim</em> that silently corrects a different pitch anomally when the aircraft reaches transonic speeds, at about mach 0.6. Neither of these systems is new to the MAX series of aircraft; they have been part of the control algorithm at least since the NG came out in 1997. MCAS runs on the same computer as speed-trim and mach-trim and is part of the same software system, but it is a distinct function. And according to what I’ve been reading in the past few weeks, it addresses a different problem—one that seems more sinister.</p>
<p>Most aircraft have the pleasant property of static stability. When an airplane is properly trimmed for level flight, you can let go of the controls—at least briefly—and it will continue on a stable path. Moreover, if you pull back on the control yoke to point the nose up, then let go again, the pitch angle should return to neutral. The layout of the airplane’s various airfoil surfaces accounts for this behavior. When the nose goes up, the tail goes down, pushing the underside of the horizontal stabilizer into the airstream. The pressure of the air against this tail surface provides a restoring force that brings the tail back up and the nose back down. (That’s why it’s called a <em>stabilizer</em>!) This negative feedback loop is built in to the structure of the airplane, so that any departure from equilibrium creates a force that opposes the disturbance.</p>
<p><img alt="Pitch stability" border="0" class="centered" height="" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/pitch-stability.svg" width="600"/></p>
<p class="indent">However, the tail surface, with its helpful stablizing influence, is not the only structure that affects the balance of aerodynamic forces. Jet engines are not designed to contribute lift to the airplane, but at high angles of attack they can do so, as the airstream impinges on the lower surface of each engine’s outer covering, or nacelle. When the engines are well forward of the center of gravity, the lift creates a pitch-up turning moment. If this moment exceeds the counterbalancing force from the tail, the aircraft is unstable. A nose-up attitude generates forces that raise the nose still higher, and positive feedback takes over.</p>
<p>Is the 737 MAX vulnerable to such runaway pitch excursions? The possibility had not occurred to me until I read a <a href="http://www.b737.org.uk/mcas.htm">commentary on MCAS</a> on the <a href="http://www.b737.org.uk/index.htm">Boeing 737 Technical Site</a>, a web publication produced by Chris Brady, a former 737 pilot and flight instructor. He writes:</p>
<blockquote><p>MCAS is a longitudinal stability enhancement. It is not for stall prevention or to make the MAX handle like the NG; it was introduced to counteract the non-linear lift of the LEAP-1B engine nacelles and give a steady increase in stick force as AoA increases. The LEAP engines are both larger and relocated slightly up and forward from the previous NG CFM56-7 engines to accommodate their larger fan diameter. This new location and size of the nacelle cause the vortex flow off the nacelle body to produce lift at high AoA; as the nacelle is ahead of the CofG this lift causes a slight pitch-up effect (ie a reducing stick force) which could lead the pilot to further increase the back pressure on the yoke and send the aircraft closer towards the stall. This non-linear/reducing stick force is not allowable underFAR = Federal Air Regulations. <a href="https://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=1a3ab2a8cbd0ea0ab242c75558315fc2&amp;mc=true&amp;node=pt14.1.25&amp;rgn=div5">Part 25</a> deals with airworthiness standards for transport category airplanes. FAR §25.173 “Static longitudinal stability”. MCAS was therefore introduced to give an automatic nose down stabilizer input during steep turns with elevated load factors (high AoA) and during flaps up flight at airspeeds approaching stall.</p></blockquote>
<p class="indent">Brady cites no sources for this statement, and as far as I know Boeing has neither confirmed nor denied. But <em>Aviation Week</em>, which earlier mentioned the thrust-pitch linkage, has more recently (<a href="https://aviationweek.com/commercial-aviation/boeing-737-max-mcas-explained">issue of March 20</a>) gotten behind the nacelle-lift instability hypothesis:</p>
<blockquote><p>The MAX’s larger CFM Leap 1 engines create more lift at high AOA and give the aircraft a greater pitch-up moment than the CFM56-7-equipped NG. The MCAS was added as a certification requirement to minimize the handling difference between the MAX and NG.</p></blockquote>
<p class="indent">Assuming the Brady account is correct, an interesting question is when Boeing noticed the instability. Were the designers aware of this hazard from the outset? Did it emerge during early computer simulations, or in wind tunnel testing of scale models? A story by Dominic Gates in the <em>Seattle Times</em> hints that Boeing may not have recognized the severity of the problem until flight tests of the first completed aircraft began in 2015.</p>
<p>According to Gates, the safety analysis that Boeing submitted to the FAA specified that MCAS would be allowed to move the horizontal stabilizer by no more than 0.6 degree. In the airplane ultimately released to the market, MCAS can go as far as 2.5 degrees, and it can act repeatedly until reaching the mechanical limit of motion at about 5 degrees. <a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/business/boeing-aerospace/failed-certification-faa-missed-safety-issues-in-the-737-max-system-implicated-in-the-lion-air-crash/">Gates writes</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>That limit was later increased after flight tests showed that a more powerful movement of the tail was required to avert a high-speed stall, when the plane is in danger of losing lift and spiraling down.</p>
<p>The behavior of a plane in a high angle-of-attack stall is difficult to model in advance purely by analysis and so, as test pilots work through stall-recovery routines during flight tests on a new airplane, it’s not uncommon to tweak the control software to refine the jet’s performance.</p></blockquote>
<p>The high-AoA instability of the MAX appears to be a property of the aerodynamic form of the entire aircraft, and so a direct way to suppress it would be to alter that form. For example, enlarging the tail surface might restore static stability. But such airframe modifications would have delayed the delivery of the airplane, especially if the need for them was discovered only after the first prototypes were already flying. Structural changes might also jeopardize inclusion of the new model under the old type certificate. Modifying software instead of aluminum must have looked like an attractive alternative. Someday, perhaps, we’ll learn how the decision was made.</p>
<p>By the way, according to Gates, the safety document filed with the FAA specifying a 0.6 degree limit has yet to be amended to reflect the true range of MCAS commands.</p>
<h3>Flying while unstable</h3>
<p>Instability is not necessarily the kiss of death in an airplane. There have been at least a few successful unstable designs, starting with the 1903 Wright Flyer. The Wright brothers deliberately put the horizontal stabilizer in front of the wing rather than behind it because their earlier experiments with kites and gliders had shown that what we call stability can also be described as sluggishness. The Flyer’s forward control surfaces (known as canards) tended to amplify any slight nose-up or nose-down motions. Maintaining a steady pitch attitude demanded high alertness from the pilot, but it also allowed the airplane to respond more quickly when the pilot <em>wanted</em> to pitch up or down. (The pros and cons of the design are reviewed in a 1984 <a href="https://authors.library.caltech.edu/21217/">paper</a> by Fred E. C. Culick and Henry R. Jex.)</p>
<p><img alt="Wright First Flight 1903Dec17" border="0" class="centered" height="213" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Wright_First_Flight_1903Dec17.jpg" width="640"/>Orville at the controls, Wilbur running alongside, at Kitty Hawk on December 17, 1903. In this view we are seeing the airplane from the stern. The canards—dual adjustable horizontal surfaces at the front—seem to be calling for nose-up pitch. (Photo from <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wright_First_Flight_1903Dec17_(full_restore_115).jpg">WikiMedia</a>.</p>
<p class="indent">Another dramatically unstable aircraft was the Grumman X-29, a research platform designed in the 1980s. The X-29 had its wings on backwards; to make matters worse,<img alt="X 29 at High Angle of Attack with Smoke Generators" border="0" class="alignleft" height="234" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/X-29_at_High_Angle_of_Attack_with_Smoke_Generators.jpg" style="margin-bottom: 12px;" width="300"/> the primary surfaces for pitch control were canards mounted in front of the wings, as in the Wright Flyer. The aim of this quirky project was to explore designs with exceptional agility, sacrificing static stability for tighter maneuvering. No unaided human pilot could have mastered such a twitchy vehicle. It required a digital fly-by-wire system that sampled the state of the airplane and adjusted the control surfaces up to 80 times per second. The controller was successful—perhaps too much so. It allowed the airplane to be flown safely, but in taming the instability it also left the plane with rather tame handling characteristics.</p>
<p>I have a glancing personal connection with the X-29 project. In the 1980s I briefly worked as an editor with members of the group at Honeywell who designed and built the X-29 control system. I helped prepare publications on the control laws and on their implementation in hardware and software. That experience taught me just enough to recognize something odd about MCAS: It is way too slow to be suppressing aerodynamic instability in a jet aircraft. Whereas the X-29 controller had a response time of 25 milliseconds, MCAS takes 10 seconds to move the 737 stabilizer through a 2.5-degree adjustment. At that pace, it cannot possibly keep up with forces that tend to flip the nose upward in a positive feedback loop.</p>
<p>There’s a simple explanation. MCAS is not meant to control an unstable aircraft. It is meant to restrain the aircraft from entering the regime where it becomes unstable. This is the same strategy used by other mechanisms of stall prevention—intervening before the angle of attack reaches the critical point. However, if Brady is correct about the instability of the 737 MAX, the task is more urgent for MCAS. Instability implies a steep and slippery slope. MCAS is a guard rail that bounces you back onto the road when you’re about to drive over the cliff. </p>
<p>Which brings up the question of Boeing’s announced plan to fix the MCAS problem. <a href="https://aviationweek.com/commercial-aviation/boeing-max-changes-add-redundancy-pilot-control">Reportedly</a>, the revised system will not keep reactivating itself so persistently, and it will automatically disengage if it detects a large difference between the two AoA sensors. These changes should prevent a recurrence of the recent crashes. But do they provide adequate protection against the kind of mishap that MCAS was designed to prevent in the first place? With MCAS shut down, either manually or automatically, there’s nothing to stop an unwary or misguided pilot from wandering into the corner of the flight envelope where the MAX becomes unstable.</p>
<p>Without further information from Boeing, there’s no telling how severe the instability might be—if indeed it exists at all. The Brady article at the Boeing 737 Technical Site implies the problem is partly pilot-induced. Normally, to make the nose go higher and higher you have to pull harder and harder on the control yoke. In the unstable region, however, the resistance to pulling suddenly fades, and so the pilot may unwittingly pull the yoke to a more extreme position.</p>
<p>Is this human interaction a <em>necessary</em> part of the instability, or is it just an exacer­bating factor? In other words, without the pilot in the loop, would there still be positive feedback causing runaway nose-up pitch? I have yet to find answers.</p>
<p>Another question: If the root of the problem is a deceptive change in the force resisting a nose-up movements of the control yoke, why not address that issue directly? The elevator feel computer and the elevator feel and centering unit pro­vide “fake” forces to the pilot’s control yoke. Figure borrowed from <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/theoryce/b737-ng-flight-controls">B737 NG Flight controls</a>, a presentation by <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/theoryce">theoryce</a>. The presentation is for the 737 NG, not the MAX series; it’s possible the architecture has changed.<img alt="Pitch controls diagram" border="0" class="alignright" height="407" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/pitch-controls-diagram.png" width="300"/>In the 737 (and most other large aircraft) the forces that the pilot “feels” through the control yoke are not simple reflections of the aerodynamic forces acting on the elevator and other control surfaces. The feedback forces are largely synthetic, generated by an “elevator feel computer” and an “elevator feel and centering unit,” devices that monitor the state of the airplane and gen­erate appro­priate hydraulic pressures push­ing the yoke one way or another. Those systems could have been given the addi­tional task of maintaining or increasing back force on the yoke when the angle of attack approaches the instability. Artificially en­hanced resis­tance is already part of the stall warning system. Why not extend it to MCAS? (There may be a good answer; I just don’t know it.)</p>
<h3>Where’s the off switch?</h3>
<p>Even after the spurious activation of MCAS on Lion Air 610, the crash and the casualties would have been avoided if the pilots had simply turned the damn thing off. Why didn’t they? Apparently because they had never heard of MCAS, and didn’t know it was installed on the airplane they were flying, and had not received any instruction on how to disable it. There’s no switch or knob in the cockpit labeled “MCAS ON/OFF.” The Flight Crew Operation Manual does not mention it (<a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/business/boeing-737-manual-mcas-system-plane-crash-1.5065842">except in a list of abbreviations</a>), and neither did the transitional training program the pilots had completed before switching from the 737 NG to the MAX. The training consisted of either one or two hours (reports differ) with an iPad app.</p>
<p>Boeing’s explanation of these omissions was captured in a <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/boeing-withheld-information-on-737-model-according-to-safety-experts-and-others-1542082575"><em>Wall Street Journal</em> story</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>One high-ranking Boeing official said the company had decided against disclos­ing more details to cockpit crews due to concerns about inundating average pilots with too much information—and significantly more technical data—than they needed or could digest.</p></blockquote>
<p>To call this statement disingenuous would be disingenuous. What it is is preposterous. In the first place, Boeing did not withhold “more details”; they failed to mention the very existence of MCAS. And the too-much-information argument is silly. I don’t have access to the Flight Crew Operation Manual for the MAX, but <a href="http://www.737ng.co.uk/737NG%20POH.pdf">the NG edition</a> runs to more than 1,300 pages, plus another 800 for the Quick Reference Handbook. A few paragraphs on MCAS would not have sunk any pilot who wasn’t already drowning in TMI. Moreover, the manual carefully documents the speed-trim and mach-trim features, which seem to fall in the same category as MCAS: They act autonomously, and offer the pilot no direct interface for monitoring or adjusting them.</p>
<p>In the aftermath of the Lion Air accident, Boeing stated that the procedure for disabling MCAS was spelled out in the manual, even though MCAS itself wasn’t mentioned. That procedure is given in a checklist for “runaway stabilizer trim.” It is not complicated: Hang onto the control yoke, switch off the autopilot and autothrottles if they’re on; then, if the problem persists, flip two switches labeled “STAB TRIM” to the “CUTOUT” position. Only the last step will actually matter in the case of an MCAS malfunction.</p>
<p>This checklist is considered a “memory item”; pilots must be able to execute the steps without looking it up in the handbook. The Lion Air crew should certainly have been familiar with it. But could they recognize that it was the right checklist to apply in an airplane whose behavior was unlike anything they had seen in their training or previous 737 flying experience? According to the handbook, the condition that triggers use of the runaway checklist is “Uncommanded stabilizer trim movement occurs continuously.” The MCAS commands were not continuous but repetitive, so some leap of inference would have been needed to make this diagnosis.</p>
<p><img alt="Center console trim wheels" border="0" class="aligncenter" height="576" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/center-console-trim-wheels.png" width="500"/></p>
<p class="indent">By the time of the Ethiopian crash, 737 pilots everywhere knew all about MCAS and the procedure for disabling it. A <a href="http://www.ecaa.gov.et/documents/20435/0/Preliminary+Report+B737-800MAX+,(ET-AVJ).pdf">preliminary report</a> issued last week by Ethiopian Airlines indicates that after a few minutes of wrestling with the control yoke, the pilots on Flight 302 did invoke the checklist procedure, and moved the STAB TRIM switches to CUTOUT. The stabilizer then stopped responding to MCAS nose-down commands, but the pilots were unable to regain control of the airplane. </p>
<p>It’s not entirely clear why they failed or what was going on in the cockpit in those last minutes. One factor may be that the cutout switch disables not only automatic pitch trim movements but also manual ones requested through the buttons on the control yoke. The switch cuts all power to the electric motor that moves the stabilizer. In this situation the only way to adjust the trim is to turn the hand crank wheels near the pilots’ knees. During the crisis on Flight 302 that mechanism may have been too slow to correct the trim in time, or the pilots may have been so fixated on pulling the control yoke back with maximum force that they did not try the manual wheels. It’s also possible that they flipped the switches back to the NORMAL setting, restoring power to the stabilizer motor. The report’s narrative doesn’t mention this possibility, but the graph from the flight data recorder suggests it <em>(see below)</em>.</p>
<h3>The single point of failure</h3>
<p>There’s room for debate on whether the MCAS system is a good idea when it is operating correctly, but when it activates <em>mistakenly</em> and sends an airplane diving into the sea, no one would defend it. By all appearances, the rogue behavior in both the Lion Air and the Ethiopian accidents was triggered by a malfunction in a single sensor. That’s not supposed to happen in aviation. It’s unfathomable that any aircraft manufacturer would knowingly build a vehicle in which the failure of a single part would lead to a fatal accident.</p>
<p>Protection against single failures comes from redundancy, and the 737 is so committed to this principle that it almost amounts to two airplanes wrapped up in a single skin. Aircraft that rely more heavily on automation generally have <em>three</em> of everything—sensors, computers, and actuators.The cockpit has stations for two pilots, who look at separate sets of instruments and operate separate sets of controls. The left and right instrument panels receive signals from separate sets of sensors, and those signals are processed by separate computers. Each side of the cockpit has its own inertial guidance system, its own navigation computer, its own autopilot. There are two electric power supplies and two hydraulic systems—plus mechanical backups in case of a dual hydraulic failure. The two control yokes normally move in unison—they are linked under the floor—but if one yoke should get stuck, the connection can be broken, allowing the other pilot to continue flying the airplane.</p>
<p>There’s one asterisk in this roster of redundancy: A device called the flight control computer, or FCC, apparently gets special treatment. There are two FCCs, but <a href="http://www.b737.org.uk/mcas.htm">according to the Boeing 737 Technical Site</a> only one of them operates during any given flight. All the other duplicated components run in parallel, receiving independent inputs, doing independent computations, emitting independent control actions. But for each flight just one FCC does all the work, and the other is put on standby. The scheme for choosing the active computer seems strangely arbitrary. Each day when the airplane is powered up, the left side FCC gets control for the first flight, then the right side unit takes over for the second flight of the day, and the two sides alternate until the power is shut off. After a restart, the alternation begins again with the left FCC.</p>
<p>Aspects of this scheme puzzle me. I don’t understand why redundant FCC units are treated differently from other components. If one FCC dies, does the other automatically take over? Can the pilots switch between them in flight? If so, would that be an effective way to combat MCAS misbehavior? I’ve tried to find answers in the manuals, but I don’t trust my interpretation of what I read.</p>
<p>I’ve also had a hard time learning anything about the FCC itself. I don’t know who makes it, or what it looks like, or how it is programmed. <img alt="Honeywell 737 Flight Control Computer" border="0" class="alignleft" height="253" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Honeywell-737-Flight-Control-Computer.jpg" style="margin-bottom: 12px;" width="300"/> On a website called <a href="https://www.closetwonderfuls.top/737-boeing-honeywell-flight-controller-computer-asremoved-pn4051600914-p-18738.html">Closet Wonderfuls</a> an item identified as a 737 flight control computer is on offer for $43.82, with free shipping.A website called <a href="http://www.airframer.com/aircraft_detail.html?model=B737">Airframer</a> lists many suppliers of parts and materials for the 737, but there’s no entry for a flight control computer. It has a Honeywell label. I’m tempted, but I’m pretty sure this is not the unit installed in the latest MAX models. I’ve learned that the FCC was once the FCE, for flight control elec­tronics, suggesting it was an analog device, doing its integrations and differ­entiations with capacitors and resis­tors. By now I’m sure the FCC has caught up with the digital age, but it might still be special-purpose, custom-built hardware. Or it might be an off-the-shelf Intel CPU in a fancy box, maybe even running Linux or Windows. I just don’t know.</p>
<p>In the context of the MAX crashes, the flight control computer is important for two reasons. First, it’s where MCAS lives; this is the computer on which the MCAS software runs. Second, the curious procedure for choosing a different FCC on alternating flights also winds up choosing which AoA sensor is providing input to MCAS. The left and right sensors are connected to the corresponding FCCs.</p>
<p>If the two FCCs are used in alternation, that raises an interesting question about the history of the aircraft that crashed in Indonesia. The preliminary crash report describes trouble with various instruments and controls on five flights over four days (including the fatal flight). All of the problems were on the left side of the aircraft or involved a dis­agreement between the left and right sides.<br/>
The flight in the gray row is not mentioned in the preliminary report, but the airplane had to get from Manado to Denpasar for the following day’s flight.</p>

<table class="tg" style="margin-top: 16px;">
<tbody><tr>
<th class="tg-7btt">date</th>
<th class="tg-amwm">route</th>
<th class="tg-amwm">trouble reports</th>
<th class="tg-amwm">maintenance</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tg-c3ow">Oct 26</td>
<td class="tg-baqh">Tianjin → Manado</td>
<td class="tg-baqh">left side: no airspeed<br/>or altitude indications</td>
<td class="tg-baqh">test left Stall Management and<br/>Yaw Damper computer; passed<br/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tg-yj5y">?</td>
<td class="tg-uqo3">Manado → Denpasar</td>
<td class="tg-uqo3">?</td>
<td class="tg-uqo3">?</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tg-c3ow">Oct 27</td>
<td class="tg-baqh">Denpasar → Manado</td>
<td class="tg-baqh">left side: no airspeed<br/>or altitude indications<br/><br/>speed trim and mach trim<br/>warning lights</td>
<td class="tg-baqh">test left Stall Management and<br/>Yaw Damper computer; failed<br/><br/>reset left Air Data and Inertial<br/>Reference Unit<br/><br/>retest left Stall Management and<br/>Yaw Damper computer; passed<br/><br/>clean electrical connections</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tg-c3ow">Oct 27</td>
<td class="tg-baqh">Manado → Denpasar</td>
<td class="tg-baqh">left side: no airspeed<br/>or altitude indications<br/><br/>speed trim and mach trim<br/>warning lights<br/><br/>autothrottle disconnect</td>
<td class="tg-baqh">test left Stall Management and<br/>Yaw Damper computer; failed<br/><br/>reset left Air Data and Inertial<br/>Reference Unit<br/><br/>replace left AoA sensor</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tg-bolj">Oct 28</td>
<td class="tg-cmwg">Denpasar → Jakarta</td>
<td class="tg-cmwg">left/right disagree warning<br/>on airspeed and altitude<br/><br/>stick shaker<br/><br/>[MCAS activation]</td>
<td class="tg-cmwg">flush left pitot tube<br/>and static port<br/><br/>clean electrical connectors<br/>on elevator “feel” computer</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="tg-bolj">Oct 29</td>
<td class="tg-cmwg">Jakarta → Pangkal Pinang</td>
<td class="tg-cmwg">stick shaker<br/><br/>[MCAS activation]</td>
<td class="tg-cmwg"/>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p class="indent">Which of the five flights had the left-side FCC as active computer? The final two flights <em>(red)</em>, where MCAS activated, were both first-of-the-day flights and so presumably under control of the left FCC. For the rest it’s hard to tell, especially since maintenance operations may have entailed full shutdowns of the aircraft, which would have reset the alternation sequence.</p>
<p>The revised MCAS software will reportedly consult signals from both AoA sensors. What will it do with the additional information? Only one clue has been published so far: If the readings differ by more than 5.5 degrees, MCAS will shut down. What if the readings differ by 4 or 5 degrees? A <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/306356837_Enhanced_detection_and_isolation_of_angle_of_attack_sensor_faults">recent paper</a> by Daniel Ossmann of the German Aerospace Center dis­cusses algorithmic detection of fail­ures in AoA sensors.Which sensor will MCAS choose to believe? Conservative (or pessimistic) engineering practice would seem to favor the higher reading, in order to provide better protection against instability and a stall. But that choice also raises the risk of dangerous “corrections” mandated by a faulty sensor.</p>
<p>The present MCAS system, with its alternating choice of left and right, has a 50 percent chance of disaster when a single random failure causes an AoA sensor to spew out falsely high data. With the same one-sided random failure, the updated MCAS will have a 100 percent chance of ignoring a pilot’s excursion into stall territory. Is that an improvement?</p>
<h3>The broken sensor</h3>
<p>Although a faulty sensor should not bring down an airplane, I would still like to know what went wrong with the AoA vane.</p>
<p>It’s no surprise that AoA sensors can fail. They are mechanical devices operating in a harsh environment: winds exceeding 500 miles per hour and temperatures below –40. <img alt="Lion Air 610 flight data chart AoA detail" border="0" class="alignright" height="110" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Lion-Air-610-flight-data-chart-AoA-detail.jpg" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" width="300"/>A common failure mode is a stuck vane, often caused by ice (despite a built-in de-icing heater). But a seized vane would produce a constant output, regardless of the real angle of attack, which is not the symptom seen in Flight 610. The flight data recorder shows small fluctuations in the signals from both the left and the right instruments. Furthermore, the jiggles in the two curves are closely aligned, suggesting they are both tracking the same movements of the aircraft. In other words, the left-hand sensor appears to be functioning; it’s just giving measurements offset by a constant deviation of roughly 20 degrees.</p>
<p>Is there some other failure mode that might produce the observed offset? Sure: Just bend the vane by 20 degrees. Maybe a catering truck or an airport jetway blundered into it. Another creative thought is that the sensor might have been installed wrong, with the entire unit rotated by 20 degrees. Several writers on a website called the <a href="https://www.pprune.org/tech-log/616624-maintenance-lapse-identified-initial-problem-leading-lion-air-crash.html">Professional Pilots Rumour Network</a> explored this possibility, but they ultimately concluded it was impossible. The manufacturer, doubtless aware of the risk, placed the mounting screws and locator pins asymmetrically, so the unit will only go into the hull opening one way.</p>
<p>You might get the same effect through an assembly error during the manufacture of the sensor. The vane could be incorrectly attached to the shaft, or else the internal transducer that converts angular position into an electrical signal might be mounted wrong. Did the designers also ensure that such mistakes are impossible? I don’t know; I haven’t been able to find any drawings or photographs of the sensor’s innards.</p>
<p>Looking for other ideas about what might have gone wrong, I made a quick, scattershot survey of <a href="https://www.faa.gov/regulations_policies/airworthiness_directives/">FAA airworthiness directives</a> that call for servicing or replacing AoA sensors. I found dozens of them, including several that discuss the same sensor installed on the 737 MAX (the <a href="https://utcaerospacesystems.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/Angle-of-Attack-AOA-Systems.pdf">Rosemount 0861</a>). But none of the reports I read describes a malfunction that could cause a consistent 20-degree error.</p>
<p>For a while I thought that the fault might lie not in the sensor itself but farther along the data path. It could be something as simple as a bad cable or connector. Signals from the AoA sensor go to the Air Data and Inertial Reference Unit (ADIRU), where the sine and cosine components are combined and digitized to yield a number representing the measured angle of attack. The ADIRU also receives inputs from other sensors, including the pitot tubes for measuring airspeed and the static ports for air pressure. And it houses the gyroscopes and accelerometers of an inertial guidance system, which can keep track of aircraft motion without reference to external cues. (There’s a separate ADIRU for each side of the airplane.) Maybe there was a problem with the digitizer—a stuck bit rather than a stuck vane.</p>
<p>Further information has undermined this idea. For one thing, the AoA sensor removed by the Lion Air maintenance crew on October 27 is now in the hands of investigators. According to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/04/04/world/asia/ethiopia-crash-boeing.html">news reports</a>, it was “deemed to be defective,” though I’ve heard no hint of what the defect might be. Also, it turns out that one element of the control system, the Stall Management and Yaw Damper (SMYD) computer, receives the raw sine and cosine voltages directly from the sensor, not a digitized angle calculated by the ADIRU. It is the SMYD that controls the stick-shaker function. On both the Lion Air and the Ethiopian flights the stick shaker was active almost continuously, so those undigitized sine and cosine voltages must have been indicating a high angle of attack. In other words the error already existed before the signals reached the ADIRU.</p>
<p>I’m still stumped by the fixed angular offset in the Lion Air data, but the question now seems a little less important. The release of the preliminary report on Ethiopian Flight 302 shows that the left-side AoA sensor on that aircraft also failed badly, but in a way that looks totally different. Here are the relevant traces from the flight data recorder:</p>
<p><img alt="Ethiopian 302 FDR AoA" border="0" class="centered withLoupe" height="175" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Ethiopian-302-FDR-AoA.png" width="900"/></p>
<p>The readings from the AoA sensors are the uppermost lines, red for the left sensor and blue for the right. At the left edge of the graph they differ somewhat when the airplane has just begun to move, but they fall into close coincidence once the roll down the runway has built up some speed. At takeoff, however, they suddenly diverge dramtically, as the left vane begins reading an utterly implausible 75 degrees nose up. Later it comes down a few degrees but otherwise shows no sign of the ripples that would suggest a response to airflow. At the very end of the flight there are some more unexplained excursions.</p>
<p>By the way, in this graph the light blue trace of automatic trim commands offers another clue to what might have happened in the last moments of Flight 302. Around the middle of the graph, the STAB TRIM switches were pulled, with the result that an automatic nose-down command had no effect on the stabilizer position. But at the far right, another automatic nose-down command does register in the trim-position trace, suggesting that the cutout switches may have been turned on again.</p>
<h3>Still more stumpers</h3>
<p>There’s so much I still don’t understand.</p>
<p>Puzzle 1. If the Lion Air and Ethiopian accidents were both caused by faulty AoA sensors, then there were three parts with similar defects in brand new aircraft (including the replacement sensor installed by Lion Air on October 27). A recent news item says the replacement was not a new part but one that had been refurbished by a Florida shop called <a href="http://www.xtaero.com/">XTRA Aerospace</a>. This fact offers us somewhere else to point the accusatory finger, but presumably the two sensors installed by Boeing were not retreads, so XTRA can’t be blamed for all of them.</p>
<p>There are roughly 400 MAX aircraft in service, with 800 AoA sensors. Is a failure rate of 3 out of 800 unusual or unacceptable? Does that judgment depend on whether or not it’s the same defect in all three cases?</p>
<p>Puzzle 2. Let’s look again at the traces for pitch trim and angle of attack in the Lion Air 610 data. The conflicting manual and automatic commands in the second half of the flight have gotten lots of attention, but I’m also baffled by what was going on in the first few minutes.</p>
<p><img alt="Lion Air 610 flight data chart  trim and AoA detail" border="0" class="centered" height="185" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Lion-Air-610-flight-data-chart-trim-and-AoA-detail.jpg" width="640"/></p>
<p>During the roll down the runway, the pitch trim system was set near its maximum pitch-up position <em>(dark blue line)</em>. Immediately after takeoff, the automatic trim system began calling for further pitch-up movement, and the stabilizer probably reached its mechanical limit. At that point the pilots manually trimmed it in the pitch-down direction, and the automatic system replied with a rapid sequence of up adjustments. In other words, there was already a tug-of-war underway, but the pilots and the automated controls were pulling in directions opposite to those they would choose later on. All this happened while the flaps were still deployed, which means that MCAS could not have been active. Some other element of the control system must have been issuing those automatic pitch-up orders. Deepening the mystery, the left side AoA sensor was already feeding its spurious high readings to the left-side flight control computer. If the FCC was acting on that data, it should not have been commanding nose-up trim.</p>
<p>Puzzle 3. The AoA readings are not the only peculiar data in the chart from the Lion Air preliminary report. Here are the altitude and speed traces:</p>
<p><img alt="Lion Air 610 flight data chart alt and ias details" border="0" class="centered" height="198" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Lion-Air-610-flight-data-chart-alt-and-ias-details.jpg" width="640"/></p>
<p>The left-side altitude readings <em>(red)</em> are low by at least a few hundred feet. The error looks like it might be multiplicative rather than additive, perhaps 10 percent. The left and right computed airspeeds also disagree, although the chart is too squished to allow a quantitative comparison. It was these discrepancies that initially upset the pilots of Flight 610; they could see them on their instruments. (They had no angle of attack indicators in the cockpit, so that conflict was invisible to them.)</p>
<p>Altitude, airspeed, and angle of attack are all measured by different sensors. Could they all have gone haywire at the same time? Or is there some common point of failure that might explain all the weird behavior? In particular, is it possible a single wonky AoA sensor caused all of this havoc? My guess is yes. The sensors for altitude and airspeed and even temperature are influenced by angle of attack. The measured speed and pressure are therefore adjusted to compensate for this confounding variable, using the output of the AoA sensor. That output was wrong, and so the adjustments allowed one bad data stream to infect all of the air data measurements.</p>
<h3>Man or machine</h3>
<p>Six months ago, I was <a href="http://bit-player.org/2018/another-technological-tragedy">writing</a> about another disaster caused by an out-of-control control system. In that case the trouble spot was a natural gas distribution network in Massa­chusetts, where a misconfigured pressure-regulating station caused fires and explosions in more than 100 buildings, with one fatality and 20 serious injuries. I lamented: “The special pathos of technological tragedies is that the engines of our destruction are machines that we ourselves design and build.”</p>
<p>In a world where defective automatic controls are blowing up houses and dropping aircraft out of the sky, it’s hard to argue for <em>more</em> automation, for adding further layers of complexity to control systems, for endowing machines with greater autonomy. Public sentiment leans the other way. Like President Trump, most of us trust pilots more than we trust computer scientists. We don’t want MCAS on the flight deck. We want Chesley Sullenberger III, the hero of USAir Flight 1549, who guided his crippled A320 to a dead-stick landing in the Hudson River and saved all 155 souls on board. No amount of cockpit automation could have pulled off that feat.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, a cold, analytical view of the statistics suggests a different reaction. The human touch doesn’t always save the day. On the contrary, pilot error is responsible for more fatal crashes than any other cause. One <a href="https://ageconsearch.umn.edu/record/207282/files/2010_164_Why_Airplanes_Crash.pdf">survey</a> lists pilot error as the initiating event in 40 percent of fatal accidents, with equipment failure accounting for 23 percent. No one is (yet) advocating a <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2016/03/has-the-self-flying-plane-arrived/472005/">pilotless cockpit</a>, but at this point in the history of aviation technology that’s a nearer prospect than a computer-free cockpit.</p>
<p>The MCAS system of the 737 MAX represents a particularly awkward compromise between fully manual and fully automatic control. The software is given a large measure of responsibility for flight safety and is even allowed the override the decisions of the pilot. And yet when the system malfunctions, it’s entirely up to the pilot to figure out what went wrong and how to fix it—and the fix had better be quick, before MCAS can drive the plane into the ground.</p>
<p>Two lost aircraft and 346 deaths are strong evidence that this design was not a good idea. But what to do about it? <a href="https://www.boeing.com/commercial/737max/737-max-software-updates.page">Boeing’s plan</a> is a retreat from automatic control, returning more responsibility and authority to the pilots: </p>
<blockquote><ul>
<li>Flight control system will now compare inputs from both AOA sensors. If the sensors disagree by 5.5 degrees or more with the flaps retracted, MCAS will not activate. An indicator on the flight deck display will alert the pilots.</li>
<li>If MCAS is activated in non-normal conditions, it will only provide one input for each elevated AOA event. There are no known or envisioned failure conditions where MCAS will provide multiple inputs.</li>
<li>MCAS can never command more stabilizer input than can be counter­acted by the flight crew pulling back on the column. The pilots will continue to always have the ability to override MCAS and manually control the airplane.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>A <a href="https://www.boeing.com/commercial/737max/737-max-update.page">statement</a> from Dennis Muilenburg, Boeing’s CEO, says the software update “will ensure accidents like that of Lion Air Flight 610 and Ethiopian Airlines Flight 302 never happen again.” I hope that’s true, but what about the accidents that MCAS was designed to prevent? I also hope we will not be reading about a 737 MAX that stalled and crashed because the pilots, believing MCAS was misbehaving, kept hauling back on the control yokes.</p>
<p>If Boeing were to take the opposite approach—not curtailing MCAS but enhancing it with still more algorithms that fiddle with the flight controls—the plan would be greeted with hoots of outrage and derision. Indeed, it seems like a terrible idea. MCAS was installed to prevent pilots from wandering into hazardous territory. A new supervisory system would keep an eye on MCAS, stepping in if it began acting suspiciously. Wouldn’t we then need another custodian to guard the custodians, ad infinitum? Moreoever, with each extra layer of complexity we get new side effects and unintended consequences and opportunities for something to break. The system becomes harder to test, and impossible to prove correct.</p>
<p>Those are serious objections, but the problem being addressed is also serious.</p>
<p>Suppose the 737 MAX didn’t have MCAS but did have a cockpit indicator of angle of attack. On the Lion Air flight, the captain would have felt the stick-shaker warning him of an incipient stall and would have seen an alarmingly high angle of attack on his instrument panel. His training would have impelled him to do the same thing MCAS did: Push the nose down to get the wings working again. Would he have continued pushing it down until the plane crashed? Surely not. He would have looked out the window, he would have cross-checked the instruments on the other side of the cockpit, and after some scary moments he would have realized it was a false alarm. (In darkness or low visibility, where the pilot can lose track of the horizon, the outcome might be worse.)</p>
<p>I see two lessons in this hypothetical exercise. First, erroneous sensor data is dangerous, whether the airplane is being flown by a computer or by Chesley Sullenberger. A prudently designed instrument and control system would take steps to detect (and ideally correct) such errors. At the moment, redundancy is the only defense against these failures—and in the unpatched version of MCAS even that protection is compromised. It’s not enough. One key to the superiority of human pilots is that they exercise judgment and sometimes skepticism about what the instruments tell them. That kind of reasoning is not beyond the reach of automated systems. There’s plenty of information to be exploited. For example, inconsistencies between AoA sensors, pitot tubes, static pressure ports, and air temperature probes not only signal that something’s wrong but can offer clues about <em>which</em> sensor has failed. The inertial reference unit provides an independent check on aircraft attitude; even GPS signals might be brought to bear. Admittedly, making sense of all this data and drawing a valid conclusion from it—a problem known as sensor fusion—is a major challenge.</p>
<p>Second, a closed-loop controller has yet another source of information: an implicit model of the system being controlled. If you change the angle of the horizontal stabilizer, the state of the airplane is expected to change in known ways—in angle of attack, pitch angle, airspeed, altitude, and in the rate of change in all these parameters. If the result of the control action is not consistent with the model, something’s not right. To persist in issuing the same commands when they don’t produce the expected results is not reasonable behavior. Autopilots include rules to deal with such situations; the lower-level control laws that run in manual-mode flight could incorporate such sanity checks as well.</p>
<p>I don’t claim the answer to the MCAS problem. And I don’t want to fly in an airplane I designed. (Neither do you.) But there’s a general principle here that I believe should be taken to heart: If an autonomous system makes life-or-death decisions based on sensor data, it ought to verify the validity of the data.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-08T21:34:51Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-08T21:34:51Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://bit-player.org" term="computing"/>
    <category scheme="http://bit-player.org" term="technology"/>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Hayes</name>
      <uri>http://bit-player.org</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://bit-player.org/feed/atom</id>
      <link href="http://bit-player.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://bit-player.org/feed/atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">An amateur's outlook on computation and mathematics</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">bit-player</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T23:05:23Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-5672867789279325982</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/5672867789279325982/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/problems-with-point-not-plug-just-some.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/5672867789279325982" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/5672867789279325982" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/problems-with-point-not-plug-just-some.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Problems with a point- NOT a plug, just some thoughts on books and book writing</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Problems with a Point: Exploring Math and Computer Science by Gasarch and Kruskal, available on amazon <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Problems-Point-Exploring-Computer-Science/dp/9813279974/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=gasarcj&amp;qid=1553111113&amp;s=gateway&amp;sr=8-1-spell">here</a>, came out a while back  and I plugged it in my  blog post <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/02/problems-with-point-exploring-math-and.html">here</a>. Regan-Lipton reviewed it <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/10/problems-with-a-point/">here</a>.<br/>
<br/>
This post is NOT a plug, its random points about the book and book writing<br/>
<br/>
1) On Feb 28 I checked my Amazon ranking twice. At noon it was at 400,000 and at 4:00PM it was at  roughly 80,000.  Either (a) someone bought a copy, or (b) the number of sales of such books is so small that amazon does rankings arbitrarily. A counter argument to that: Bounded Queries in Recursion Theory, which I wrote in 1998 and, despite an awesome review on amazon that I wrote,  sold literally 0 copies last year, is ranked 5,000,000. So even within the low numbers there is SOME logic to the rankings. (Update- Today, April 7, PWAP is at 800,000 and BQIRT is at 12,000,000. I suspect that nothing has changed with BQIRT and the 5,000,000 or 12,000,000 is arbitrary. As for PWAP--- since its still a new book the ranking might mean something. Oh well- fame is fleeting!)<br/>
<br/>
1.5) At one time my book was 29th in the category <i>Teen and Young Adult Computer Programming. </i>Really? While teens and young adults might read it, I don't think of it as geared towards them (only one use of  <i>OMG</i> and two uses of <i>awesome</i>  in the entire book). And as for Computer Programming... uh... no.<br/>
<br/>
2) I emailed many people about it and many people are buying it. Some tell me that the cover looks great so YES, they are judging a book by its cover. My mom asked how it was selling. I told her that (a) about 20 people told me they bought it, and (b) I doubt that's how JK Rowling responds when she's asked how her Harry Potter books are selling.<br/>
<br/>
3) Many people could actually read this book and would care about its content. When I wrote Bounded Queries in Recursion Theory (with Georgia Martin) I didn't email a lot of people about it since it was rather specialized.<br/>
<br/>
4) Some people said `Gee bill, we didn't know you were working on a book'. That's true- I didn't talk about it much. Clyde knew (my co-author, so he had  to know), Lance knew. Darling knew. Mom Knew. That might be about it. Why so few? see next point.<br/>
<br/>
5) I had heard there are two kinds of people:<br/>
<br/>
<i>Those that talk about writing a book but don't do it</i><br/>
<br/>
<i>Those that write a book instead of talking about it</i>.<br/>
<br/>
I chose to be the second type.<br/>
<br/>
6) When I got an advanced copy I couldn't stop reading it. Ego? Disbelieve? Some of each?<br/>
<br/>
7) ADVICE for book writers: just get it done. You can polish it later but first get it done so you have something to polish.<br/>
<br/>
8) More advice: You can never have too many proofreaders. Even though its been gone over a lot I still read it and find minor things to fix OR think `gee why didn't I include BLAH in the book'<br/>
<br/>
9) Title: `Problems with a Point' I came up with very early and I liked it a lot. World Scientific (our publisher) pointed out, correctly, that we need a subtitle since  PWAP didn't really tell the reader whats in it. I wanted to make it alliterative but it was hard. Here were some possibilities<br/>
<br/>
PWAP: Mathematical Musing Made Magnificent (can replace Musings with Morsels)<br/>
<br/>
PWAP: Mathematical Meditations  and Computer Science Cogitations<br/>
<br/>
PWAP: Mathematical Musings and the Math that Makes those Musings Matter<br/>
<br/>
All in all I am happy with the non-alliterative, but informative<br/>
<br/>
PWAP: Exploring Math and Computer Science.<br/>
<br/>
10) Odd thing I learned- if I quote someone who made a comment on my blog or emailed me I needed permission. Actually I doubt I NEEDED it but the laws here are murky so I got it just to make sure. That explains this blog from a while back: <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2018/10/john-sidles-mike-roman-matt-howell.html">here</a><br/>
<br/>
11) ADVICE for book writers: Write the preface last since then you have a better idea of why you wrote the book.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-08T03:02:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-08T03:02:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T17:26:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03139</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03139" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Parameter estimation for integer-valued Gibbs distributions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Harris:David_G=.html">David G. Harris</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kolmogorov:Vladimir.html">Vladimir Kolmogorov</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.03139">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the family of \emph{Gibbs distributions}, which are probability
distributions over a discrete space $\Omega$ given by
$\mu^\Omega_\beta(x)=\frac{e^{\beta H(x)}}{Z(\beta)}$. Here
$H:\Omega\rightarrow \{0,1,\ldots,n\}$ is a fixed function (called a {\em
Hamiltonian}), $\beta$ is the parameter of the distribution, and
$Z(\beta)=\sum_{x\in\Omega}e^{\beta H(x)} = \sum_{k=0}^n c_k e^{\beta k}$ is
the normalization factor called the {\em partition function}. We study how
function $Z(\cdot)$ can be estimated using an oracle that produces samples
$x\sim \mu_\beta(\cdot)$ for a value $\beta$ in a given interval
$[\beta_{\min}, \beta_{\max}]$.
</p>
<p>Recently, it has been shown how to estimate quantity
$q=\log\frac{Z(\beta_{\max})}{Z(\beta_{\min})}$ with additive
error~$\varepsilon$ using $\tilde O(\frac{q}{\varepsilon^2})$ samples in
expectation. We improve this result to $\tilde O(\frac
{\min\{q,n^2\}}{\varepsilon^2})$, matching a lower bound of Kolmogorov (2018)
up to logarithmic factors.
</p>
<p>We also consider the problem of estimating the normalized coefficients $c_k$
for indices $k\in\{0,1,\ldots,n\}$ that satisfy $\max_{\beta}
\mu_\beta^\Omega(\{x\:|\:H(x)=k\}) \ge\mu_\ast$, where $\mu_\ast\in(0,1)$ is a
given parameter. We solve this problem using $\tilde O(\frac{\min\{ q + \frac{
\sqrt{q}}{\mu_{\ast}}, n^2 + \frac{ n}{\mu_{\ast}} \}}{\varepsilon^2})$
expected samples, and we show that this complexity is optimal up to logarithmic
factors. This is improved to roughly $\tilde O( \frac{1/\mu_{\ast}+\min\{q +
n,n^2\}}{\varepsilon^2})$ for applications in which the coefficients are known
to be log-concave (e.g.\ for connected subgraphs of a given graph).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:21:33Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03117</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03117" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Knot Diagrams of Treewidth Two</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bodlaender:Hans_L=.html">Hans L. Bodlaender</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Burton:Benjamin.html">Benjamin Burton</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fomin:Fedor_V=.html">Fedor V. Fomin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grigoriev:Alexander.html">Alexander Grigoriev</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.03117">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we study knot diagrams for which the underlying graph has
treewidth two. We give a linear time algorithm for the following problem: given
a knot diagram of treewidth two, does it represent the unknot? We also show
that for a link diagram of treewidth two we can test in linear time if it
represents the unlink. From the algorithm, it follows that a diagram of the
unknot of treewidth 2 can always be reduced to the trivial diagram with at most
$n$ (un)twist and (un)poke Reidemeister moves.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:22:46Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03050</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03050" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Experimental Study of Algorithms for Geodesic Shortest Paths in the Constant-Workspace Model</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cleve:Jonas.html">Jonas Cleve</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mulzer:Wolfgang.html">Wolfgang Mulzer</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.03050">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We perform an experimental evaluation of algorithms for finding geodesic
shortest paths between two points inside a simple polygon in the
constant-workspace model. In this model, the input resides in a read-only array
that can be accessed at random. In addition, the algorithm may use a constant
number of words for reading and for writing. The constant-workspace model has
been studied extensively in recent years, and algorithms for geodesic shortest
paths have received particular attention.
</p>
<p>We have implemented three such algorithms in Python, and we compare them to
the classic algorithm by Lee and Preparata that uses linear time and linear
space. We also clarify a few implementation details that were missing in the
original description of the algorithms. Our experiments show that all
algorithms perform as advertised in the original works and according to the
theoretical guarantees. However, the constant factors in the running times turn
out to be rather large for the algorithms to be fully useful in practice.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:43:13Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03039</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03039" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Drawing k-linear Metro Maps</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Soeren Nickel, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/N=ouml=llenburg:Martin.html">Martin Nöllenburg</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.03039">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Schematic metro maps in practice as well as metro map layout algorithms
usually adhere to an octilinear layout style with all paths composed of
horizontal, vertical, and 45$^\circ$-diagonal edges. Despite growing interest
in non-octilinear metro maps, generic algorithms to draw metro maps based on a
system of $k \ge 2$ equidistant slopes have not been investigated thoroughly.
In this paper we present and implement an adaptation of the octilinear
mixed-integer linear programming approach of N\"ollenburg and Wolff (2011) that
can draw k-linear metro maps.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:42:09Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03015</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03015" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Faster Algorithm for the Limited-Capacity Many-to-Many Point Matching in One Dimension</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rajabi=Alni:Fatemeh.html">Fatemeh Rajabi-Alni</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bagheri:Alireza.html">Alireza Bagheri</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.03015">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given two point sets S and T on a line, we present a linear time algorithm
for the limited capacity many-to-many matching between S and T which improves
the previous quadratic algorithm.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:42:56Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02991</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02991" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Automating Resolution is NP-Hard</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Atserias:Albert.html">Albert Atserias</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/M=uuml=ller:Moritz.html">Moritz Müller</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.02991">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We show that the problem of finding a Resolution refutation that is at most
polynomially longer than a shortest one is NP-hard. In the parlance of proof
complexity, Resolution is not automatizable unless P = NP. Indeed, we show it
is NP-hard to distinguish between formulas that have Resolution refutations of
polynomial length and those that do not have subexponential length refutations.
This also implies that Resolution is not automatizable in subexponential time
or quasi-polynomial time unless NP is included in SUBEXP or QP, respectively.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:20:49Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02944</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02944" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Reducing Topological Minor Containment to the Unique Linkage Theorem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fomin:Fedor_V=.html">Fedor V. Fomin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lokshtanov:Daniel.html">Daniel Lokshtanov</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Panolan:Fahad.html">Fahad Panolan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saurabh:Saket.html">Saket Saurabh</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zehavi:Meirav.html">Meirav Zehavi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.02944">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the Topological Minor Containment problem (TMC) problem two undirected
graphs, $G$ and $H$ are given and the objective is to check whether $G$
contains $H$ as a topological minor. Grohe, Kawarabayashi, Marx, and
Wollan~[STOC 2011] resolved the parameterized complexity of this problem by
designing an algorithm with running time $f(k)n^{3}$. Here, $k=|V(H)|$ and
$n=|V(G)|$. Among several other tools, this algorithm was based on a variant of
the linkage theorem of Robertson-Seymour, tailor-made for TMC, by adapting
elements of the new proof of the unique linkage theorem of Kawarabayashi and
Wollan~[STOC 2010]. In this paper we turn the wheel back, and design an
alternate algorithm for TMC by giving a direct reduction to a version of unique
linkage theorem appearing in Graph Minors XXII of Robertson and Seymour. That
is, the new proof requires a black-box invocation of a known result arising in
the proof of graph minor theorem. Our result has the following advantages:
</p>
<p>(1) Graph classes where the bounds in the unique linkage theorem are known,
this immediately results in explicit time-bounds for TMC on those graph
classes. For example, we get first algorithm with explicit time bounds for TMC
on planar graphs and more generally for graphs of genus $g$. In particular, the
algorithm runs in time $2^{2^{2^{{\cal O}(k)}}}$ on planar graphs.
</p>
<p>(2) Any new development on the unique linkage theorem will immediately led to
a faster algorithm for TMC. That is, one does not need to design a similar
theorem specifically for TMC.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:31:03Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02861</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02861" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Achieving Optimal Backlog in Multi-Processor Cup Games</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bender:Michael_A=.html">Michael A. Bender</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Farach=Colton:Martin.html">Martin Farach-Colton</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kuszmaul:William.html">William Kuszmaul</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.02861">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The single- and multi- processor cup games can be used to model natural
problems in areas such as processor scheduling, deamortization, and buffer
management. At the beginning of the single-processor cup game, $n$ cups are
initially empty. In each step of the game, a filler distributes $1$ unit of
water among the cups, and then an emptier selects a cup and removes $1 +
\epsilon$ units from that cup. The goal of the emptier is to minimize the
amount of water in the fullest cup, also known as the backlog. It is known that
the greedy algorithm (i.e., empty the fullest cup) achieves backlog $O(\log
n)$, and that no deterministic algorithm can do better. We show that the
performance of the greedy algorithm can be greatly improved with a small amount
of randomization: After any step $i$, and for any $k \ge \Omega(\log
\epsilon^{-1})$, the emptier achieves backlog at most $O(k)$ with probability
at least $1 -O(2^{-2^k})$. Whereas bounds for the single-processor cup game
have been known for more than fifteen years, proving nontrivial bounds on
backlog for the multi-processor extension has remained open. We present a
simple analysis of the greedy algorithm for the multi-processor cup game,
establishing a backlog of $O(\epsilon^{-1} \log n)$, as long as $\delta$, the
game's other speed-augmentation constant, is at least $1/poly(n)$. Turning to
randomized algorithms, we encounter an unexpected phenomenon: When the number
of processors $p$ is large, the backlog after each step drops to
\emph{constant} with large probability. Specifically, we show that if $\delta$
and $\epsilon$ satisfy reasonable constraints, then there exists an algorithm
that bounds the backlog after a given step by three or less with probability at
least $1 - O(\exp(-\Omega(\epsilon^2 p))$. We further extend the guarantees of
our randomized algorithm to consider larger backlogs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:39:44Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02824</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02824" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Taming the Knight's Tour: Minimizing Turns and Crossings</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Juan Jose Besa, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Johnson:Timothy.html">Timothy Johnson</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mamano:Nil.html">Nil Mamano</a>, Martha C. Osegueda <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.02824">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We introduce two new metrics of simplicity for knight's tours: the number of
turns and the number of crossings. We give a novel algorithm that produces
tours with $9.5n+O(1)$ turns and $13n+O(1)$ crossings on a $n\times n$ board.
We show lower bounds of $(6-\varepsilon)n$, for any $\varepsilon&gt;0$, and
$4n-O(1)$ on the respective problems of minimizing these metrics. Hence, we
achieve approximation ratios of $19/12+o(1)$ and $13/4+o(1)$. We generalize our
techniques to rectangular boards, high-dimensional boards, symmetric tours, odd
boards with a missing corner, and tours for $(1,4)$-leapers. In doing so, we
show that these extensions also admit a constant approximation ratio on the
minimum number of turns, and on the number of crossings in most cases.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:22:12Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02809</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02809" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Proving tree algorithms for succinct data structures</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Affeldt:Reynald.html">Reynald Affeldt</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Garrigue:Jacques.html">Jacques Garrigue</a>, XuanruiQi, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tanaka:Kazunari.html">Kazunari Tanaka</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.02809">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Succinct data structures give space-efficient representations of large
amounts of data without sacrificing performance. They rely one cleverly
designed data representations and algorithms. We present here the formalization
in Coq/SSReflect of two different tree-based succinct representations and their
accompanying algorithms. One is the Level-Order Unary Degree Sequence, which
encodes the structure of a tree in breadth-first order as a sequence of bits,
where access operations can be defined in terms of Rank and Select, which work
in constant time for static bit sequences. The other represents dynamic bit
sequences as binary balanced trees, where Rank and Select present a low
logarithmic overhead compared to their static versions, and with efficient
insertion and deletion. The two can be stacked to provide a dynamic
representation of dictionaries for instance. While both representations are
well-known, we believe this to be their first formalization and a needed step
towards provably-safe implementations of big data.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:22:28Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02763</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1904.02763" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Compact Error-Resilient Self-Assembly of Recursively Defined Patterns</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554681600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Shutters:Brad.html">Brad Shutters</a>, Timothy P. Hartke Jr., Robert J. Sammelson <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1904.02763">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A limitation to molecular implementations of tile-based self-assembly systems
is the high rate of mismatch errors which has been observed to be between 1%
and 10%. Controlling the physical conditions of the system to reduce this
intrinsic error rate $\epsilon$ prohibitively slows the growth rate of the
system. This has motivated the development of techniques to redundantly encode
information in the tiles of a system in such a way that the rate of mismatch
errors in the final assembly is reduced even without a reduction in $\epsilon$.
Winfree and Bekbolatov, and Chen and Goel, introduced such error-resilient
systems that reduce the mismatch error rate to $\epsilon^2$ by replacing each
tile in an error-prone system with a $k \times k$ block of tiles in the
error-resilient system, but this increases the number of tile types used by a
factor of $k^2$, and the scale of the pattern produced by a factor of $k$.
Reif, Sahu and Yin, and Sahu and Reif, introduced compact error-resilient
systems for the self-assembly of Boolean arrays that reduce the mismatch error
rate to $\epsilon^2$ without increasing the scale of the pattern produced. In
this paper, we give a technique to design compact error-resilient systems for
the self-assembly of the recursively defined patterns introduced by Kautz and
Lathrop. We show that our compact error-resilient systems reduce the mismatch
error rate to $\epsilon^2$ by using the independent error model introduced by
Sahu and Reif. Surprisingly, our error-resilient systems use the same number of
tile types as the error-prone system from which they are constructed.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-08T23:41:58Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/04/07/photos-from-barbados</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/04/07/photos-from-barbados.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Photos from Barbados</title>
    <summary>I spent this year’s spring break at Erik Demaine’s annual computational geometry workshop in Barbados again. A few photos of workshop participants:</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I spent this year’s spring break at Erik Demaine’s annual computational geometry workshop in Barbados again. A few photos of workshop participants:</p>

<div><table style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
<tbody><tr style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">
<td style="padding: 10px;"><img alt="Hannah Alpert and Tom Hull" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/bellairs19/9-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="360"/></td>
<td style="padding: 10px;"><img alt="Jonathan Shoemaker, Ryuhei Uehara, and Bob Hearn" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/bellairs19/13-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="266"/></td>
</tr><tr style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">
<td style="padding: 10px;"><img alt="Bel&#xE9;n Palop and Vera Sacrist&#xE1;n" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/bellairs19/26-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="240"/></td>
<td style="padding: 10px;"><img alt="Yushi Uno, Walker Anderson, Ryan Williams, Dylan Hendrickson, and Jayson Lynch" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/bellairs19/10-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="360"/></td>
</tr></tbody></table></div>

<p>This time around, as well as the usual suspects, Erik included two high school students, incoming to MIT. You can see them at the left of the second and fourth photos.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/bellairs19/index.html">Here are the rest of my photos</a>.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101888686019377462">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-07T18:52:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-07T18:52:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T04:33:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7500</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/04/06/pcp-fest-videos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PCP Fest videos</title>
    <summary>In December I participated in the wonderful “PCP Fest” workshop in Tel Aviv. The videos from these workshops are now online on their youtube channel. The channel contains not just videos of talks but also two wide ranging interviews of Alon Rosen with Avi Wigderson and Christos Papadimitriou, as well as a discussion between them. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In December I participated in the wonderful <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/pcpfest/home">“PCP Fest”</a> workshop in Tel Aviv. The videos from these workshops are now online on their <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLGRBwz8taWHiBHlgnX98zrbnWQCeDtFQ_">youtube channel</a>.</p>



<p>The channel contains not just videos of talks but also two wide ranging interviews of Alon Rosen with <a href="https://youtu.be/-GQnK6ys6C0">Avi Wigderson</a> and <a href="https://youtu.be/vKCE7QnsFcw">Christos Papadimitriou</a>, as well as a discussion between them.  I think many people, especially students, might find these interviews inspiring. They cover Avi’s and Christos’ personal and intellectual journeys, that are similar in some ways and quite different in others. </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-07T02:48:23Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-07T02:48:23Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>windowsontheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3394</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/04/06/learning-in-the-presence-of-strategic-behavior-ec-2019-workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Learning in the Presence of Strategic Behavior (EC 2019 Workshop)</title>
    <summary>Workshop on Learning in Presence of Strategic Behavior at EC 2019 (co-located with FCRC 2019) June 28, 2019 at Phoenix, AZ, USA Submission deadline: May 1. Website: https://sites.google.com/view/eclearning2019/ The ACM EC Workshop on Learning in Presence of Strategic Behavior will be held in conjunction with ACM Federated Computing Research Conference (FCRC) 2019, Phoenix, Arizona on […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p dir="ltr"><strong>Workshop on Learning in Presence of Strategic Behavior at EC 2019</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">(co-located with FCRC 2019)</p>
<p dir="ltr">June 28, 2019 at Phoenix, AZ, USA</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Submission deadline: May 1.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Website:<a href="https://sites.google.com/view/eclearning2019/" rel="noopener" target="_blank"> https://sites.google.com/view/eclearning2019/</a></p>
<p dir="ltr">The ACM EC Workshop on Learning in Presence of Strategic Behavior will be held in conjunction with ACM Federated Computing Research Conference (FCRC) 2019, Phoenix, Arizona on June 28, 2019.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The main goal of this workshop is to address current challenges and opportunities that arise from interactions of learning systems with social and strategic agents. This workshop aims at bringing together members of different communities; including  economics, machine learning, theoretical computer science, and social computing; to share recent results, discuss important directions for future research, and foster collaborations. In particular, we expect our workshop to be of interest to the larger research community present at ACM FCRC 2019, including participants of EC, COLT, and STOC.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The workshop will include 4-5 invited talks by experts from machine learning, theoretical computer science, economics, and operations research, as well as contributed talks and posters.</p>
<p dir="ltr">******* Call for Papers *******</p>
<p dir="ltr">Papers from a rich set of theoretical and applied perspectives are invited. Some areas of interest at the interface of learning and strategic behavior include, but are not limited to:</p>
<p dir="ltr">1. Learning from data that is produced by agents who have vested interest in the outcome or the learning process. Examples of this include learning a measure of quality of universities by surveying members of the academia who stand to gain or lose from the outcome, or when a GPS routing app has to learn patterns of traffic delay by routing individuals who have no interest in taking slower routes.</p>
<p dir="ltr">2. Learning a model for the strategic behavior of one or more agents by observing their interactions. Examples of this include applications of learning in economic paradigms.</p>
<p dir="ltr">3. Learning as a model of interactions between agents. Examples of this include applications to  swarm robotics, where individual agents have to learn to interact in a multi-agent setting in order to achieve individual or collective goals.</p>
<p dir="ltr">4. Interactions between multiple learners. Examples of this include scenarios where two or more learners learn about the same or multiple related concepts. How do these learners interact? What are the scenarios under which they would share knowledge, information, or data. What are the desirable interactions between learners?</p>
<p dir="ltr">******* Submissions Guidelines *******</p>
<p dir="ltr">We solicit submission of published and unpublished works. For the former, we request that the authors clearly state the venue of previous publication. Authors are also encouraged to provide a link to an online version of the paper (such as on arXiv).  If accepted, such papers will be linked via an index to give an informal record of the workshop. This workshop will have no published proceedings. Accepted submissions will be presented as posters or talks.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Submissions can be made in any format and length, but have to be accompanied by a one page summary of the paper, its contributions, and relevance to the workshop (this applies to previously published papers as well).  The review process is not blind. All submissions will be made through<a href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=eclearning2019" rel="noopener" target="_blank"> EasyChair</a> on or before May 1, 2019, 11:59pm AoE. Notification of acceptance will be on May 20, 2019.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Submissions will be evaluated based on their relevance to the theme of the workshop and the novelty of the work.</p>
<p dir="ltr">******* Important Information *******</p>
<p dir="ltr">Website:<a href="https://sites.google.com/view/eclearning2019/" rel="noopener" target="_blank"> https://sites.google.com/view/eclearning2019/</a></p>
<p dir="ltr">Submission Deadline: May 1, 2019, 11:59pm AoE</p>
<p dir="ltr">Submission page:<a href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=eclearning2019" rel="noopener" target="_blank"> https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=eclearning2019</a></p>
<p dir="ltr">Notification: May 15, 2019</p>
<p dir="ltr">Workshop Date: June 28, 2019</p>
<p dir="ltr">******* Workshop Registration *******</p>
<p dir="ltr">Please refer to the<a href="http://www.sigecom.org/ec19/" rel="noopener" target="_blank"> EC 2019</a> website for registration details.</p>
<p dir="ltr">******* Organizing Committee *******</p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/omerbp/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Omer Ben-Porat</a>, Technion</p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/nihaghta/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Nika Haghtalab</a>, Microsoft Research and Cornell University</p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://www.cs.tau.ac.il/~mansour/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Yishay Mansour</a>, Tel Aviv University</p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="http://timroughgarden.org/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Tim Roughgarden</a>, Columbia University</p>
<p dir="ltr">******* More Information *******</p>
<p dir="ltr">All questions about submissions should be emailed to: <a href="mailto:eclearning2019@easychair.org" rel="noopener" target="_blank">eclearning2019@easychair.org</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-06T21:20:12Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-06T21:20:12Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>timroughgarden</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1111</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1111" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for March 2019</title>
    <summary>Last month was very calm. Eerily calm in fact: no property testing or related sublinear-time algorithm in view!* Gird your loins for the April batch, I reckon? \({}^\ast\) That we saw, at least. if we missed some, please mention it in the comments below!) Update: As mentioned in the comments, we did indeed missed two […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Last month was very calm. Eerily calm in fact: no property testing or related sublinear-time algorithm in view!* Gird your loins for the April batch, I reckon?</p>



<p>\({}^\ast\) <em>That we saw, at least. if we missed some, please mention it in the comments below!)</em></p>



<p><strong>Update:</strong> As mentioned in the comments, we did indeed missed two (related)  works on distribution estimation from a competitive viewpoint. Namely, for a large class of properties (entropy, distance to uniformity, support size…),  Hao, Orlitsky, Suresh, and Wu provide in the first paper (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.00070">arXiv 1904.00070</a>) an “instance-optimal(ish)” estimator which does “as well” with \(m/\sqrt{\log m}\) samples than the natural and naive empirical estimator would do with \(m\) (thus, in some sense, <em>amplifying</em> the data size). In the following paper (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.01432">arXiv 1903.01432</a>), Hao and Orlitsky improve this and remove the “ish” to get the optimal amplification \(m/\log m\).</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-05T20:56:37Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-05T20:56:37Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Clement Canonne</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T23:46:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7497</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/04/05/stoc-2019-travel-grants/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>STOC 2019 travel grants</title>
    <summary>(As you’re working on your FOCS papers, an announcement about STOC 2019 from Eric Allender –Boaz) STOC registration is now open acm-stoc.org/stoc2019/. The deadline to apply for travel grants is April 22 . Apply on ﻿acm-stoc.org/stoc2019/travel-support.html There is also travel support available via TCS Women (deadline April 25), see sigact.org/tcswomen/</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>(As you’re working on your FOCS papers,  an announcement about <a href="http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2019/">STOC 2019 </a>from Eric Allender –Boaz)</em></p>



<p>STOC registration is now open <a href="http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2019/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">acm-stoc.org/stoc2019/.</a> The deadline to apply for travel grants is <strong>April 22 </strong>. Apply on  <br/><a href="http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2019/travel-support.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">﻿acm-stoc.org/stoc2019/travel-support.html</a> <br/></p>



<p>There is also travel support available via <strong>TCS Women</strong> (deadline <strong>April 25</strong>), see  <a href="http://sigact.org/tcswomen/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">sigact.org/tcswomen/</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-05T20:47:10Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-05T20:47:10Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>windowsontheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:21:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3383</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/04/05/3rd-workshop-on-mechanism-design-for-social-good-at-ec-19/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>3rd Workshop on Mechanism Design for Social Good at EC ’19</title>
    <summary>MD4SG ’19 Call for Participation  The 3rd Workshop on Mechanism Design for Social Good (MD4SG ’19) will take place at this year’s ACM Conference on Economics and Computation (EC ’19) in Phoenix, AZ, USA on 28 June 2019.     The goal of the workshop is to highlight work where techniques from algorithms, optimization, and mechanism design, along with insights […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div dir="ltr">
<div><strong><span style="font-size: large;">MD4SG ’19</span></strong></div>
<div><strong>Call for Participation </strong></div>
</div>


<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>The <a href="http://md4sg.com/workshop/EC19/index.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">3rd Workshop on Mechanism Design for Social Good</a> (MD4SG ’19) will take place at this year’s <a href="http://www.sigecom.org/ec19/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">ACM Conference on Economics and Computation</a> (EC ’19) in Phoenix, AZ, USA on <strong>28 June 2019</strong>.     </p>



<p>The goal of the workshop is to highlight work where techniques from algorithms, optimization, and mechanism design, along with insights from other disciplines, have the potential to improve access to opportunity for historically underserved and marginalized communities. The workshop will feature keynote presentations, contributed talks, problem pitches and demonstrations, a poster session, and a panel discussion, with a focus on <em>bridging research and practice</em>.     </p>



<p>We solicit submissions of research papers, as well as special problem- and practice-driven submissions, to be presented at the workshop. The deadline for submissions is <strong>27 April 2019 at 5 PM GMT</strong>.     </p>



<p>We also solicit applications for travel grants. The deadline for travel grant applications is <strong>15 April 2019 at 5 PM GMT</strong>.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>We encourage submissions from across various disciplines and covering domains including bias and discrimination, civic participation, computational sustainability, developing nations, economic inequality, education, healthcare, housing, on- and off-line labor markets, and privacy and security. Submissions can be research papers introducing new theory or applications, as well as position papers synthesizing existing work and perspectives or highlighting future directions. For the first time, the workshop will also accept problem pitches and demonstration submissions. Submissions will fall into one of four tracks:   </p>



<p class="has-background has-very-light-gray-background-color">1. <strong>AI and Machine Learning</strong> including bias, fairness, and ethics, fair division and resource allocation, human computer interaction in socio-technical systems; multi-agent systems, privacy and security, social choice theory, and statistical reasoning. </p>



<p class="has-background has-very-light-gray-background-color">2. <strong>Empirical Studies</strong> including applied machine learning, causal inference, computational social science, empirical analysis of real-world systems, empirical methods, and experimental results. </p>



<p class="has-background has-very-light-gray-background-color">3. <strong>Theory</strong> including algorithm design, fair division and resource allocation, game theory, market and mechanism design, optimization, operations management, computational social choice, social network analysis, and theory of machine learning.   </p>



<p>In addition, we will also accept special submissions as problem pitches or demonstrations. We especially encourage individuals from government and non-government organizations and industry to submit to this track.   </p>



<p class="has-background has-very-light-gray-background-color">4. <strong>Problems and Demonstrations: </strong><br/><br/>a. <strong>Problem Pitches</strong> including white papers on problems arising in practice that deserve wider academic attention, and papers pitching methods for addressing real-world problems through research. Submissions should provide <br/><strong>(1)</strong> background information on the problems, <br/><strong>(2)</strong> examples of how techniques for resource allocation, definition of appropriate metrics and objectives, design of systems, alignment of incentives, and related issues could significantly alleviate these problems, and <br/><strong>(3)</strong> a summary of any existing methods or approaches for addressing these problems. Submissions are also encouraged to provide a discussion of challenges in providing holistic solutions and/or introduce new methods for addressing the problems.   <br/><br/>Submissions will be evaluated based on their contributions to one or more of the following:<br/><strong>(i)</strong> Novelty of problem/domain to the EC community<br/><strong>(ii)</strong> Comprehensive exposition of background on problem and attempted solutions<br/><strong>(iii)</strong> Potential for future collaborations and/or follow up from the EC community<br/><strong>(iv) </strong>Discussion of practical, structural and/or societal challenges in attempted or proposed solution<br/><br/>b. <strong>Demonstrations</strong> including prototyped and/or deployed software systems and mobile platforms. Demo submissions should be accompanied by a short description describing the system or platform, the problems it seeks to address, and the potential to use the tool in conjunction with algorithm and mechanism design and related tools to improve access to opportunity. Submissions should also include instructions for using the system or platform.   </p>



<p>For all submissions, topics of interest include <em>but are not limited to</em>: </p>



<ul><li>market and mechanism design challenges in resource-constrained settings</li><li>measuring and evaluating progress to achieve sustainable development goals</li><li>reducing inefficiencies in smallholder farms and under-resourced supply chains</li><li>allocating health insurance funds and managing access to healthcare</li><li>equitable provision of healthcare across communities</li><li>algorithmic proposals to encourage civic participation</li><li>evaluating fairness in electoral representation</li><li>redistributive mechanisms to improve access to opportunity</li><li>economic inequality and intergenerational mobility</li><li>mitigating unequal economic outcomes in on- and off-line labor markets</li><li>detecting existence or causes of exploitative market behavior in on- and off-line labor markets</li><li>the design of algorithms that mitigate bias and improve diversity</li><li>allocating low-income housing assistance</li><li>evaluating students, teachers, or schools and improving allocation of educational resources</li><li>design of transportation systems</li><li>market regulations for data and privacy</li><li>ethics of using solutions informed by algorithm and mechanism design in public sector settings</li></ul>



<p>

 
Submissions will be evaluated based on the following criteria:

</p>



<ul><li><em>Quality of submission</em> as measured by accuracy and clarity of exposition.</li><li><em>Relevance</em> to MD4SG and the workshop theme of bridging research and practice.</li><li><em>Novelty of domain</em>, especially work on applications that have historically been less explored by those in the EC community.</li><li>In line with the focus on bridging research and practice, submissions will also be evaluated based on either:
<ul><li><em>Potential for interdisciplinary follow-up work.</em> We welcome submissions with the potential to spark interdisciplinary collaborations with the EC community,</li><li><em>Presentation of domain-specific knowledge.</em> We especially welcome practitioners with interest or experience in translating between practical problems and academic research approaches.</li></ul>
</li></ul>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><strong>Submission Instructions:</strong> </p>



<p>Authors should upload a PDF of their paper to <a href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=md4sg19" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">EasyChair</a>. There are no specific formatting instructions or length requirements. In addition to the PDF, authors are asked to upload a 200-250 word description onto EasyChair summarizing their submission and its relevance to the workshop. Authors do not need to be first author of the submitted work. Authors should list all co-authors on the presented work both in the PDF of the submission as well as on EasyChair.</p>



<p>Authors may submit papers that are working papers, papers that have already been published, or are under review. If the work is already published, please include a citation on EasyChair.</p>



<p>There will be no published proceedings. All submissions will be peer-reviewed by at least 2 reviewers. The committee reserves the right not to review all the technical details of submissions. Submissions are single-blind (i.e., authors should include their name and affiliation in the paper).</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><strong>Travel Grants:</strong></p>



<p>The workshop will provide a number of need-based travel grants to participants to subsidize the costs of registration, travel, and accommodation at the workshop. Awardees of the travel grants will have the opportunity to participate in an interdisciplinary networking session with members of the broader MD4SG and EC community. Preference will be given to individuals who have submitted papers to the workshop or the EC conference before the travel grant submission deadline. We especially encourage those from underrepresented communities and institutions to <a href="https://goo.gl/forms/HplMVBKtTOcaJIO42" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">submit a travel grant application</a>.</p>



<p><strong>All travel grant applications must be submitted by 15 April 2019 at 5 PM GMT</strong>; applications received after this date will not be considered.
 </p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><strong>Important Information:</strong></p>



<ul><li>Travel Grant Application Deadline: 15 April 2019 at 5 PM GMT</li><li>Paper Submission Deadline: 27 April 2019 at 5 PM GMT</li><li>Notification: 15 May 2019</li><li>Workshop Date: 28 June 2019</li><li>Travel Grant: <a href="https://goo.gl/forms/HplMVBKtTOcaJIO42" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Application Form</a></li><li>Paper Submission: <a href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=md4sg19" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">EasyChair</a></li></ul>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><strong>Organizing Committee:</strong><strong>Program Chairs:</strong></p>



<ul><li><a href="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/~red/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Rediet Abebe</a>, Cornell University</li><li><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/irene-lo" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Irene Lo</a>, Stanford University</li></ul>



<p><strong>Area Chairs:</strong></p>



<ul><li><strong>Theory:</strong> <a href="https://hamsabastani.github.io/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Hamsa Bastani</a>, Wharton, University of Pennsylvania; <a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~kgoldner/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Kira Goldner</a>, University of Washington</li><li><strong>Empirical Studies:</strong> <a href="http://www.danielwaldinger.com/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Daniel Waldinger</a>, New York University</li><li><strong>AI and ML:</strong> <a href="https://www.cse.wustl.edu/~sanmay/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Sanmay Das</a>, Washington University in St. Louis</li><li><strong>Problems and Demos:</strong> <a href="http://www.linardi.gspia.pitt.edu/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Sera Linardi</a>, University of Pittsburgh; <a href="https://www.adityavashistha.com/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Aditya Vashistha</a>, University of Washington</li></ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-05T16:51:17Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-05T16:51:17Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>robertkleinberg</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4156</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4156" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4156#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4156" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Congratulations!</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Congrats to Geoffrey Hinton, Yann LeCun, and Yoshua Bengio, who won the 2018 Turing Award for their work on deep learning (i.e., what used to be called neural nets). This might be the first Turing Award ever given for something where no one really understands why it works … and it’s years overdue. Congrats to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Congrats to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoffrey_Hinton">Geoffrey Hinton</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yann_LeCun">Yann LeCun</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoshua_Bengio">Yoshua Bengio</a>, who <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/27/technology/turing-award-ai.html">won</a> the 2018 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turing_Award">Turing Award</a> for their work on deep learning (i.e., what used to be called neural nets).  This might be the first Turing Award ever given for something where no one really understands why it works … and it’s years overdue.</p>



<p>Congrats to <a href="https://www.math.ias.edu/avi/home">Avi Wigderson</a> for <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/04/05/avi-wins-the-knuth-prize/">winning</a> the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knuth_Prize">Knuth Prize</a>.  When I was asked to write a supporting nomination letter, my first suggestion was to submit a blank sheet of paper—since for anyone in theoretical computer science, there’s nothing that needs to be said about why Avi should win any awards we have.  I hope Avi remains a guiding light of our community for many years to come.</p>



<p>And congrats to <a href="http://www.cs.princeton.edu/~mbraverm/pmwiki/index.php?n=Site.Main?setview=display">Mark Braverman</a> for <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/news/news_summ.jsp?cntn_id=298217&amp;WT.mc_id=USNSF_51&amp;WT.mc_ev=click">winning</a> the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_T._Waterman_Award">Alan T. Waterman Award</a>, one that I have some personal fondness for, along with materials scientist Jennifer Dionne.  As Sasha Razborov once put it, after he (Sasha), I, and others recoiled from the task of proving the <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2009/01/fooling-constant-depth-circuits.html">Linial-Nisan Conjecture</a>, that polylog-wise independent distributions are indistinguishable from uniform by AC<sup>0</sup> circuits, a “braver man” <a href="http://www.cs.toronto.edu/~mbraverm/FoolAC0v7.pdf">stepped in</a> to do the job.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-05T15:45:16Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-05T15:45:16Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-04-05T19:51:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=15725</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/04/05/avi-wins-the-knuth-prize/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Avi Wins The Knuth Prize</title>
    <summary>Wigderson wins the well deserved Knuth Prize From Avi’s 60Fest at IAS Avi Wigderson is this year’s selection for the ACM/IEEE Donald E. Knuth Prize. Today Ken and I wish to congratulate Avi and say a bit more. We thank first the Knuth Prize committee, chaired by Avrim Blum, for their excellent selection. It must […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Wigderson wins the well deserved Knuth Prize</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/avi60cropped.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-15727" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/avi60cropped.png?w=215&amp;h=300"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption aligncenter"><font size="-2">From Avi’s <a href="https://www.ias.edu/ideas/2016/avi-wigderson-60">60Fest</a> at IAS</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Avi Wigderson is this year’s <a href="http://www.sigact.org/prizes/knuth/citation2019.pdf">selection</a> for the ACM/IEEE Donald E. Knuth Prize. </p>
<p>
Today Ken and I wish to congratulate Avi and say a bit more.</p>
<p>
We thank first the Knuth Prize committee, chaired by Avrim Blum, for their excellent selection. It must be very difficult each year to select one person for this honor. There are so many strong candidates. Of course the Knuth Prize is awarded to individuals for their overall impact in the field. Who could deny that Avi has had vast impact on the whole field?</p>
<p>
Here is a nice comment from the “in theory” <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/04/02/knuth-prize-to-avi-wigderson/">blog</a> by Luca Tresvian. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Avi has worked on all aspects of computational complexity theory, and he has had a transformative influence on the way theoretical computer science relates to pure mathematics. I will not repeat what I wrote about his work on the occasion of his 60th birthday here and here. Long-term readers of in theory will remember that I consider him as one of the saints of computational complexity. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Hmmm. Saints of computing—we find that a pretty interesting comment. </p>
<p/><h2> The Three-Chain Race </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Since the prize was created in 1996, it has been awarded to:</p>
<p>
1996 Andrew Yao <br/>
1997 Leslie Valiant <br/>
1999 László Lovasz <br/>
2000 Jeffrey Ullman <br/>
2002 Christos Papadimitriou <br/>
2003 Miklos Ajtai <br/>
2005 Mihalis Yannakakis <br/>
2007 Nancy Lynch <br/>
2008 Volker Strassen <br/>
2010 David S. Johnson <br/>
2011 Ravi Kannan <br/>
2012 Leonid Levin <br/>
2013 Gary Miller <br/>
2014 Richard J. Lipton <br/>
2015 László Babai <br/>
2016 Noam Nisan <br/>
2017 Oded Goldreich <br/>
2018 Johan Håstad <br/>
2019 Avi Wigderson</p>
<p>
I am now cheering for a number of potential future Knuth Prize winners. The reason is that just now Jeff Ullman and I have become tied for the longest chain of advisor-to-advisee all with the Prize. We both have a chain of length two: Ullman to Yannakakis is his. The next prize winner could tip the scale toward one of us or the other. Or could create another chain of length two. We will see.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Lower Bounds and Randomness </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We thought we would present some cool story about Avi. We have already given some good ones—the Chinese Remainder Theorem <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2009/08/01/the-chinese-remainder-theorem-with-limits/">story</a> is a favorite. Or the brilliant first <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2009/07/07/linear-equations-over-composite-moduli/">theorem</a> he proved while a graduate student: The approximation method for coloring three-colorable <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-vertex graphs in <img alt="{\mathsf{poly}(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7Bpoly%7D%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{poly}(n)}"/> time with <img alt="{O(\sqrt{n})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Csqrt%7Bn%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\sqrt{n})}"/> colors, when poly time with <img alt="{O(n/\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%2F%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n/\log n)}"/> colors had been best-known. That was really beautiful. We could <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2009/05/21/zig-zag-zig-zag-zig-zag/">zig-zag</a> through some of his great papers <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\dots}"/> <a href="http://www.math.ias.edu/~avi/PUBLICATIONS/MYPAPERS/W06/w06.pdf">and</a> <a href="http://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~nati/PAPERS/expander_survey.pdf">surveys</a>. We could go on and on. </p>
<p>
What Ken and I find most emblematic is that Avi has been at the forefront of lower bounds in complexity throughout the four decades since I knew him as a student. He and Noam Nisan <a href="http://www.math.ias.edu/~avi/PUBLICATIONS/MYPAPERS/NOAM/HARDNESS/final.pdf">delineated</a> the “Hardness Versus Randomness” tradeoff at the end of the 1980s, pulling together work that began with Adi Shamir and Andy Yao at the beginning of that decade and was furthered by others including Russell Impagliazzo, with whom Avi later had <a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.441.2818&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf">two</a> famous <a href="http://www.math.ias.edu/~avi/PUBLICATIONS/MYPAPERS/IW98/proc.pdf">papers</a>. The main theorem of the former paper connects upper and lower bounds in iconic fashion:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 1</b> <em> If there are problems in exponential time having no <img alt="{2^{o(n)}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7Bo%28n%29%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{o(n)}}"/>-sized circuits, then <img alt="{\mathsf{BPP = P}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BBPP+%3D+P%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{BPP = P}}"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Just like the flip side of a coin, this work has also put Avi at the forefront of our understanding of <i>randomness</i>. That was the subject of an <a href="https://www.polityka.pl/tygodnikpolityka/nauka/1564697,3,jak-matematycznie-okielznac-przypadkowosc.read">interview</a> in 2013 with the Polish magazine <em>Polityka</em> titled, “How to Rule Randomness Mathematically.” Quoting him in it (Ken’s translation):</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> The concept of secrecy on the Internet almost makes no sense without random bits. If you use a procedure, one that I know, I can impersonate you in a perfect way. I can become your master. Secrets must be generated in a random way. Of course, we do not have to do it ourselves—our laptop or phone does the work for us. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The interview goes on to marvel yet also warn how all of this is still founded on properties of prime numbers and the putative hardness of factoring. It looks to implementations of more advanced crypto whether “we will be forced to do it” or not. In all of this, Avi truly represents dedication to <em>foundations</em>. He backs that up with tireless advocacy and organizational work for people in our field—extending to the 2018 IAS workshop we <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/06/06/princeton-is-invariant/">covered</a> last June.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> A Symbolic Gift </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
As a symbol of our affection we dedicate to Avi a simple riff on lower bounds. We start with arguably the oldest lower bound, except that the vocabulary to realize it was lacking 2,000 years ago—and Ken and I weren’t conscious of it until recently. This is that <img alt="{\pi(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\pi(x)}"/>—the number of primes <img alt="{\leq x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cleq+x%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\leq x}"/>—satisfies 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \log\log(x) \le \pi(x) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Clog%5Clog%28x%29+%5Cle+%5Cpi%28x%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \log\log(x) \le \pi(x) "/></p>
<p>for <img alt="{x \geq 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx+%5Cgeq+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x \geq 2}"/>, with logs to base 2. To show this, argue as in Euclid’s famous proof: <i>Suppose that 	</i></p><i>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  0 &lt; p_{1} &lt; p_{2} &lt; \cdots &lt; p_{n}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++0+%3C+p_%7B1%7D+%3C+p_%7B2%7D+%3C+%5Ccdots+%3C+p_%7Bn%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  0 &lt; p_{1} &lt; p_{2} &lt; \cdots &lt; p_{n}, "/></p>
<p>are the first <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> primes. The Euclid argument proves that the next prime, say <img alt="{p_{n+1}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp_%7Bn%2B1%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p_{n+1}}"/>, must be so that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  p_{n+1} \le 1 + p_{1}p_{2}\cdots p_{n}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++p_%7Bn%2B1%7D+%5Cle+1+%2B+p_%7B1%7Dp_%7B2%7D%5Ccdots+p_%7Bn%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  p_{n+1} \le 1 + p_{1}p_{2}\cdots p_{n}. "/></p>
<p>The property <img alt="{p_n \leq 2^{2^{n-1}}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp_n+%5Cleq+2%5E%7B2%5E%7Bn-1%7D%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p_n \leq 2^{2^{n-1}}}"/> is maintained by induction, because we have <img alt="{p_1 \leq 2^{2^0} = 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp_1+%5Cleq+2%5E%7B2%5E0%7D+%3D+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p_1 \leq 2^{2^0} = 2}"/> and thus </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  p_{n+1} &amp;\le&amp; 1 + 2^{1}\cdot 2^{2}\cdot 2^{4} \cdots 2^{2^{n-1}}\\ &amp;=&amp; 1 + 2^{1 + 2 + 4 + \cdots + 2^{n-1}}\\ &amp;\le&amp; 1 + 2^{2^n - 1} \le 2^{2^n}. \end{array} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Brcl%7D++p_%7Bn%2B1%7D+%26%5Cle%26+1+%2B+2%5E%7B1%7D%5Ccdot+2%5E%7B2%7D%5Ccdot+2%5E%7B4%7D+%5Ccdots+2%5E%7B2%5E%7Bn-1%7D%7D%5C%5C+%26%3D%26+1+%2B+2%5E%7B1+%2B+2+%2B+4+%2B+%5Ccdots+%2B+2%5E%7Bn-1%7D%7D%5C%5C+%26%5Cle%26+1+%2B+2%5E%7B2%5En+-+1%7D+%5Cle+2%5E%7B2%5En%7D.+%5Cend%7Barray%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  p_{n+1} &amp;\le&amp; 1 + 2^{1}\cdot 2^{2}\cdot 2^{4} \cdots 2^{2^{n-1}}\\ &amp;=&amp; 1 + 2^{1 + 2 + 4 + \cdots + 2^{n-1}}\\ &amp;\le&amp; 1 + 2^{2^n - 1} \le 2^{2^n}. \end{array} "/></p>
</i><p><i>So if <img alt="{x = p_{n+1} - 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx+%3D+p_%7Bn%2B1%7D+-+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x = p_{n+1} - 1}"/>, giving <img alt="{\pi(x) = n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%28x%29+%3D+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\pi(x) = n}"/> in a worst-case manner, then <img alt="{2^{2^n} \geq x+1 &gt; x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7B2%5En%7D+%5Cgeq+x%2B1+%3E+x%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{2^n} \geq x+1 &gt; x}"/>, so <img alt="{n &gt; \log_2\log_2 x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn+%3E+%5Clog_2%5Clog_2+x%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n &gt; \log_2\log_2 x}"/>. Thus <img alt="{\pi(x) &gt; \log_2\log_2 x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%28x%29+%3E+%5Clog_2%5Clog_2+x%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\pi(x) &gt; \log_2\log_2 x}"/>.</i></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Now we note from <a href="https://blameitontheanalyst.wordpress.com/2011/10/07/primes-less-than-a-given-number-2/">here</a> an exponentially better lower bound that is almost as easy to prove: Take <img alt="{x = p_{n+1} - 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx+%3D+p_%7Bn%2B1%7D+-+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x = p_{n+1} - 1}"/> again. Now if <img alt="{1 \leq y \leq x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1+%5Cleq+y+%5Cleq+x%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1 \leq y \leq x}"/>, then it must be possible to write </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  y = s^2 p_1^{a_1} p_2^{a_2} \cdots p_n^{a_n} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++y+%3D+s%5E2+p_1%5E%7Ba_1%7D+p_2%5E%7Ba_2%7D+%5Ccdots+p_n%5E%7Ba_n%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  y = s^2 p_1^{a_1} p_2^{a_2} \cdots p_n^{a_n} "/></p>
<p>with <img alt="{s \leq \sqrt{x}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs+%5Cleq+%5Csqrt%7Bx%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s \leq \sqrt{x}}"/> and each <img alt="{a_i \in \{0,1\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba_i+%5Cin+%5C%7B0%2C1%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a_i \in \{0,1\}}"/>. This is because <img alt="{s}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s}"/>, the largest square dividing <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/>, can be at most <img alt="{\sqrt{x}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7Bx%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{x}}"/>, and then <img alt="{y/s^2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%2Fs%5E2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y/s^2}"/> has no squared prime dividing it. How many different such numbers can we make? There are at most <img alt="{2^n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5En%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^n}"/> for the possible <img alt="{a_1,\dots,a_n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba_1%2C%5Cdots%2Ca_n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a_1,\dots,a_n}"/> exponents, multiplied by the initial <img alt="{\sqrt{x}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7Bx%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{x}}"/>. This means </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x \leq 2^n \sqrt{x}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x+%5Cleq+2%5En+%5Csqrt%7Bx%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  x \leq 2^n \sqrt{x}, "/></p>
<p>so </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \sqrt{x} \leq 2^n = 2^{\pi(x)}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Csqrt%7Bx%7D+%5Cleq+2%5En+%3D+2%5E%7B%5Cpi%28x%29%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \sqrt{x} \leq 2^n = 2^{\pi(x)}. "/></p>
<p>Taking the base-2 log of both sides gives </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \pi(x) \geq \frac{1}{2}\log_2(x). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cpi%28x%29+%5Cgeq+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%5Clog_2%28x%29.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \pi(x) \geq \frac{1}{2}\log_2(x). "/></p>
<p>Again this works for all <img alt="{x \geq 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx+%5Cgeq+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x \geq 2}"/>. This lower bound is much better, but it is still far from the truth that <img alt="{\pi(x) = \Theta(x/\log x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%28x%29+%3D+%5CTheta%28x%2F%5Clog+x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\pi(x) = \Theta(x/\log x)}"/>. The involvement of <img alt="{\sqrt{x}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7Bx%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{x}}"/> in the derivation, however, harks us back to Avi’s graph-coloring example. So in that spirit let us ask:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> What is the easiest way to prove <img alt="{\pi(x) \geq C\sqrt{x}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%28x%29+%5Cgeq+C%5Csqrt%7Bx%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\pi(x) \geq C\sqrt{x}}"/> for some constant <img alt="{C}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{C}"/>? Is there a really easy way? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We congratulate Avi once more. The same Polish interview notes at the end that the Gödel and Nevanlinna Prizes “did not do any evident damage to his personal charm,” nor does his 1956 birthday diminish the energy “to bound down stairs … several breakneck steps at a time.” We are sure the new prize will have no effect on either. </p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-05T05:30:44Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-05T05:30:44Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="primes"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="trick"/>
    <category term="Avi Wigderson"/>
    <category term="complexity"/>
    <category term="crypto"/>
    <category term="foundations"/>
    <category term="Knuth Prize"/>
    <category term="lower bounds"/>
    <category term="randomness"/>
    <category term="tricks"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6372871065307387905</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6372871065307387905/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/cuckoo-cycles.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6372871065307387905" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6372871065307387905" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/cuckoo-cycles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Cuckoo Cycles</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><span style="font-weight: normal;"><i>Guest Blog by John Tromp (Thanks for the opportunity, Lance)</i></span><br/>
<br/>
In the past few months, cycle finding has become one of the most widely run
graph theory problems. An estimated quarter-to-half million GPUs are constantly
looking for 42-cycles in random bipartite graphs on a billion or more nodes.
Customized chips have been designed to perform this specific application an
order of magnitude more efficiently, thanks to integrating as much as 1GB of
SRAM on a single chip, where Intel/AMD CPUs top out at 64 MB.

<br/>
<br/>
The purpose of all this? To compete for block rewards in various
cryptocurrencies using the <a href="https://github.com/tromp/cuckoo">Cuckoo Cycle Proof of Work</a>.


<br/>
<br/>
It is named after the Cuckoo Hashtable, in which each data item can be stored
at two possible locations, one in each of two arrays.  A hash function maps the
pair of item and choice of array to its location in that array. When a newly
stored item finds both its locations already occupied, one is kicked out and
replaced by the new item. This forces the kicked-out item to move to its
alternate location, possibly kicking out yet another item. Problems arise
if the corresponding Cuckoo graph, a bipartite graph with array locations as
nodes and item location pairs as edges, has cycles.
While n items, whose edges form a cycle, could barely be stored in the table,
any n+1st item mapping within the same set of locations (a chord in the cycle)
would not fit, as the pigeonhole principle tells us.

<br/>
In the Proof-of-Work problem, we typically set n ≥ 29, and use edge indices
(items) 0 .. N-1, where N = 2<sup>n</sup>.  The endpoints of edge i are (siphash(i|0) % N, siphash(i|1) % N), with
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SipHash">siphash</a> being a popular keyed hash function.
A solution is a cycle of length L in this Cuckoo graph, where typically L = 42.<br/>
<br/>
While looking for cycles takes a lot of time and memory, solutions can be instantly verified.
This sets Cuckoo Cycle apart from many other memory hard proofs of work that require computing a memory hard hash function, such as scrypt,
both for proving and verifying.

Some luck is also required to find a 42-cycle;
Slides 18 and 19 of this <a href="https://github.com/mimblewimble/grin-pm/blob/master/presentations/grinconUS0/12-Tromp-Proof_of_Work.pdf">Grincon.US presentation</a> sketch a proof of the
<br/>
<br/>
<b>Cuckoo Cycle Theorem</b>:
The expected number of L-cycles tends to 1/L

<br/>
<br/>
While there is a known linear time-memory trade-off, it suffers from a large constant factor penalty.
A large bounty is offered on the project webpage for better trade-offs.

<br/>
<br/>
Cuckoo Cycle solvers spend nearly all cycles on edge trimming; identifying and
removing edges that end in a leaf node (of degree 1), as such edges cannot be
part of a cycle. Trimming rounds alternate between the two node
partitions. This can be done using N bits for the edge bitmap, and N log<sub>2</sub>(3) bits
for the (truncated) node degrees. The random accesses to the latter,
while not a problem for custom chips using enough SRAM, cause large memory latencies
on commodity hardware. These can be mostly avoided by storing remaining edges explicitly
and (bucket) sorting them to determine node degrees.
Despite using an order of magnitude more memory than the edge bitmap, this is still over 4x faster.<br/>
<br/>
The fraction f<sub>i</sub> of remaining edges after i trimming rounds (in the limit as N
goes to infinity) appears to obey the
<br/>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<b>Cuckoo Cycle Conjecture:</b>
f<sub>i</sub> = a<sub>i-1</sub> * a<sub>i</sub>, where a<sub>-1</sub> = a<sub>0</sub> = 1, and a<sub>i+1</sub> = 1 - e<sup>-a<sub>i</sub></sup></div>
f<sub>i</sub> could equivalently be defined as the fraction of edges whose first endpoint is the middle of a (not necessarily simple) path of length 2i.<br/>
<br/>
So far I have only been able to prove the conjecture for i ≤ 3.
For instance, for i = 1, the probability that an edge endpoint is not the endpoint
of any other edge is (1-1/N)<sup>N-1</sup> ~ 1/e.

Here's hoping someone finds an elegant proof...</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-04T11:50:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-04T11:50:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T17:26:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4154</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4154" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4154#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4154" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Beware of fake FOCS site!</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">As most of you in theoretical computer science will know, the submission deadline for the 2019 FOCS conference is this Friday, April 5. The FOCS’2019 program committee chair, my UT Austin colleague David Zuckerman, has asked me to warn everyone that a fake submission site was set up at aconf.org—apparently as a phishing scam—and is […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>As most of you in theoretical computer science will know, the submission deadline for the <a href="http://focs2019.cs.jhu.edu/">2019 FOCS conference</a> is <strong>this Friday, April 5</strong>.  The FOCS’2019 program committee chair, my UT Austin colleague David Zuckerman, has asked me to warn everyone that a fake submission site was set up at aconf.org—apparently as a phishing scam—and is one of the first results to come up when you google “FOCS 2019.”  <strong>Do not submit there!</strong>  The true URL is <a href="http://focs2019.cs.jhu.edu/">focs2019.cs.jhu.edu</a>; accept no substitutes!</p>



<p>Anyway, I’ve been thrashing for several weeks—just barely escaping spaghettification at the <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=388">Email Event Horizon</a>—but I hope to be back shortly with your regularly scheduled programming.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-03T22:27:25Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-03T22:27:25Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-04-05T19:51:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7494</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/04/03/focs-2019-real-website-and-submission-server/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>FOCS 2019 Real website and submission server</title>
    <summary>The website for the FOCS 2019 conference is http://focs2019.cs.jhu.edu/ , and the submission server is https://focs19.cs.utexas.edu/ The deadline is 3:00pm PDT, April 5, 2019. The reason I am posting this is that there is a fake FOCS website that ranks first or second on searches for “FOCS 2019”. The website is under the domain “aconf […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The website for the FOCS 2019 conference is  <br/><a href="http://focs2019.cs.jhu.edu/">http://focs2019.cs.jhu.edu/</a>  , and the submission server is  <br/><a href="https://focs19.cs.utexas.edu/">https://focs19.cs.utexas.edu/</a> </p>



<p>The deadline is 3:00pm PDT, April 5, 2019.</p>



<p>The reason I am posting this is that there is a fake FOCS website that ranks first or second on searches for “FOCS 2019”. The website is under the domain “aconf dot org” (I don’t want to increase ranking and traffic to it even further by linking to it). This website contains fake pages for many other conferences, and in fact sometimes is ranked highly enough in searchers that conference organizers mistakenly link to it in their  own web page. Apparently it is owned by a company called Chaytey who also has a  similar webpage for journals under the address xjournal dot net. (Thanks to <a href="http://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~sara/">Sara Cohen</a> ,colleague of FOCS general chair Yuval Rabani for finding this out.) </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-03T12:49:32Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-03T12:49:32Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>windowsontheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:21:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/050</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/050" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-050 |  NP-Completeness, Proof Systems, and Disjoint NP-Pairs | 

	Titus Dose, 

	Christian Glaßer</title>
    <summary>The article investigates the relation between three well-known hypotheses.   
1) Hunion:   the union of disjoint complete sets for NP is complete for NP
2) Hopps:    there exist optimal propositional proof systems
3) Hcpair:   there exist complete disjoint NP-pairs

The following results are obtained:
a) The hypotheses are pairwise independent under relativizable proofs, except for the known implication Hopps \Rightarrow Hcpair.
b)Answers to questions by Pudlák in terms of an oracle relative to which  \neg Hcpair,  \neg Hopps, UP has many-one-complete sets, but NP \cap coNP has no many-one-complete sets.
c) The converse of Koebler, Messner, and Toran's implication NEE \cap TALLY \subseteq coNEE \Rightarrow Hopps fails relative to an oracle, where NEE := NTIME(2^{O(2^n)}).
d) New characterizations of Hunion and two variants in terms of coNP-completeness and P-producibility of the set of hard formulas of propositional proof systems.</summary>
    <updated>2019-04-02T20:32:20Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-02T20:32:20Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4221</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/04/02/knuth-prize-to-avi-wigderson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Knuth Prize to Avi Wigderson</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Congratulations to the Knuth prize committee chaired by Avrim Blum for the excellent choice of awarding the 2019 Knuth prize to Avi Wigderson. Avi has worked on all aspects of computational complexity theory, and he has had a transformative influence … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/04/02/knuth-prize-to-avi-wigderson/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img alt="avi" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4222" src="https://lucatrevisan.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/avi.jpg?w=584"/> </p>
<p>Congratulations to the Knuth prize committee chaired by Avrim Blum for the excellent choice of <a href="http://www.sigact.org/prizes/knuth.html">awarding the 2019 Knuth prize to Avi Wigderson</a>.</p>
<p>Avi has worked on all aspects of computational complexity theory, and he has had a transformative influence on the way theoretical computer science relates to pure mathematics. I will not repeat what I wrote about his work on the occasion of his 60th birthday <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2016/10/04/avi60/">here</a> and <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2016/10/07/avi60-zero-knowledge-for-all-np/">here</a>. Long-term readers of <i>in theory</i> will remember that I consider him as one of the <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2013/05/20/on-paul-erdos-and-kim-kardashian/">saints of computational complexity</a>.</p>
<p>The organizers of the coming FOCS would like me to remind you that the deadline is this Friday, and that someone, for some reason, has set up a fake submission site (on the domain aconf dot org) but the true submission site (that, to be honest, looks less legit than the fake one) is at <a href="https://focs19.cs.utexas.edu/">focs19.cs.utexas.edu</a>.</p>
<p>Also, the deadline to submit nominations for the inaugural FOCS test of time award is in three weeks. There will be three awards, one for papers appeared in FOCS 1985-89, one for FOCS 1995-99 and one for FOCS 2005-09.</p>
<p>On an unrelated note, GMW appeared in FOCS 1986 and the Nisan-Wigderson “Hardness versus randomness” paper appeared in FOCS 1988.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-02T20:02:53Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-02T20:02:53Z</published>
    <category term="theory"/>
    <category term="Avi Wigderson"/>
    <category term="FOCS 2019"/>
    <category term="things that are excellent"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:14Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/049</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/049" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-049 |  A Tight Parallel-Repetition Theorem for Random-Terminating Interactive Arguments | 

	Itay Berman, 

	Iftach Haitner, 

	Eliad Tsfadia</title>
    <summary>Parallel repetition is known to reduce the soundness error of some special cases of interactive arguments:  three-message protocols and public-coin protocols. However, it does not do so in the general case.

Haitner [FOCS '09, SiCOMP '13] presented a simple method for transforming any interactive argument $\pi$ into a slightly modified protocol $\widetilde{\pi}$, which he named the random terminating variant of $\pi$, such that the parallel repetition of $\widetilde{\pi}$ does reduce the soundness error at a weak exponential rate. More precisely, if $\pi$ has $m$ rounds and soundness error $(1-\epsilon)$, then Haitner proved that $\widetilde{\pi}^k$, the $k$-parallel repetition of $\widetilde{\pi}$, has soundness error $(1-\epsilon)^{\epsilon k / m^4}$.

We emphasize that parallel repetition of the random-terminating variant of a protocol is the only unconditional round-preserving hardness amplification technique we have for arbitrary interactive arguments. Since the security of many cryptographic protocols (e.g., binding) depends on the soundness of a related interactive argument, improving the analysis of Haitner is a key challenge in the study of cryptographic protocols.

In this work we introduce a different analysis for Haitner's method, proving that parallel repetition of random terminating protocols reduces the soundness error at a much stronger exponential rate: the soundness error of $\widetilde{\pi}^k$ is $(1-\epsilon)^{k / m}$, only an $m$ factor from the optimal rate of $(1-\epsilon)^k$, achievable in public-coin and three-message protocols.  We prove the tightness of our analysis by presenting a matching protocol.</summary>
    <updated>2019-04-02T12:39:48Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-02T12:39:48Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/048</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/048" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-048 |  Simplified inpproximability of hypergraph coloring via t-agreeing families | 

	Amey Bhangale, 

	Per Austrin, 

	Aditya Potukuchi</title>
    <summary>We reprove the results on the hardness of approximating hypergraph coloring using a different technique based on bounds on the size of extremal $t$-agreeing families of $[q]^n$.  Specifically, using theorems of Frankl-Tokushige [FT99], Ahlswede-Khachatrian [AK98] and Frankl [F76] on the size of such families, we give simple and unified proofs of quasi NP-hardness of the following problems:

$\bullet$ coloring a $3$ colorable $4$-uniform hypergraph with $(\log n)^\delta$ many colors
$\bullet$ coloring a $3$ colorable $3$-uniform hypergraph with $\tilde{O}(\sqrt{\log \log n})$ many colors
$\bullet$ coloring a $2$ colorable $6$-uniform hypergraph with $(\log n)^\delta$ many colors
$\bullet$ coloring a $2$ colorable $4$-uniform hypergraph with $\tilde{O}(\sqrt{\log \log n})$ many colors

where $n$ is the number of vertices of the hypergraph and $\delta&gt;0$ is a universal constant.</summary>
    <updated>2019-04-02T09:46:20Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-02T09:46:20Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/047</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/047" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-047 |  Lower Bounds for Matrix Factorization | 

	Mrinal Kumar, 

	Ben Lee Volk</title>
    <summary>We study the problem of constructing explicit families of matrices which cannot be expressed  as a product of a few sparse matrices. In addition to being a natural mathematical question on its own, this problem appears in various incarnations in computer science; the most significant being in the context of lower bounds for algebraic circuits which compute linear transformations,  matrix rigidity and  data structure lower bounds.

We first show, for every constant $d$, a deterministic construction in subexponential time of a family $\{M_n\}$ of $n \times n$ matrices which cannot be expressed as a product $M_n = A_1 \cdots A_d$ where the total sparsity of $A_1,\ldots,A_d$ is less than $n^{1+1/(2d)}$. In other words, any depth-$d$ linear circuit computing the linear transformation $M_n\cdot \mathbf{x}$ has size at least $n^{1+\Omega(1/d)}$. This improves upon the prior best lower bounds for this problem, which are barely super-linear, and were obtained by a long line of research based on the study of  super-concentrators (albeit at the cost of a blow up in the time required to construct these matrices). 

We then outline an approach for proving improved lower bounds through a certain derandomization problem, and use this approach to prove asymptotically optimal quadratic lower bounds for natural special cases, which generalize many of the common matrix decompositions.</summary>
    <updated>2019-04-02T04:45:45Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-02T04:45:45Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/04/01/ph-d-postdoc-positions-at-technical-university-of-munich-germany-apply-by-april-23-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/04/01/ph-d-postdoc-positions-at-technical-university-of-munich-germany-apply-by-april-23-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Ph.D. &amp; Postdoc Positions at Technical University of Munich (Germany) (apply by April 23, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The group of Alexander-von-Humboldt Professor Andreas S. Schulz at Technische Universität München (TUM) is seeking exceptional, highly motivated talents with expertise or interest in algorithms, algorithmic game theory, combinatorial optimization, graph theory, integer programming, machine learning, network flows, operations research, stochastic optimization, or a related subject. Website: https://www.or.tum.de/fileadmin/w00bwl/www/PDFs/TUM_Job_Offer.pdf Email: or@tum.de</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The group of Alexander-von-Humboldt Professor Andreas S. Schulz at Technische Universität München (TUM) is seeking exceptional, highly motivated talents with expertise or interest in algorithms, algorithmic game theory, combinatorial optimization, graph theory, integer programming, machine learning, network flows, operations research, stochastic optimization, or a related subject.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.or.tum.de/fileadmin/w00bwl/www/PDFs/TUM_Job_Offer.pdf">https://www.or.tum.de/fileadmin/w00bwl/www/PDFs/TUM_Job_Offer.pdf</a><br/>
Email: or@tum.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-01T19:11:28Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-01T19:11:28Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:48Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-5766992926243003607</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/5766992926243003607/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/an-interdisciplinary-approach-to-p-vs-np.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/5766992926243003607" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/5766992926243003607" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/an-interdisciplinary-approach-to-p-vs-np.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Interdisciplinary approach to P vs NP</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have a grant with some brain scientists on the following exciting approach to P vs NP.<br/>
<br/>
We want to prove:<br/>
<br/>
                               There is no algorithm for SAT in P<br/>
<br/>
This seems hard.  So lets scale down our goals to:<br/>
<br/>
                              Lance cannot find an algorithm for SAT in P<br/>
<br/>
You can replace Lance with someone else, but Lance has volunteered to have brain scans done. The idea is to scan the P vs NP part of his brain and see what we can discern.<br/>
<br/>
I know what you are thinking. Lance truly believes that SAT is NOT in P so perhaps even if SAT is in P, he would have a mental block. Hence I am hoping to also get some serious theorists that think SAT is in P to participate.  This might also shed light on the following conjecture:  is it easier to prove a theorem if you believe it is true.<br/>
<br/>
Lance has proposed another line of research. Barriers. Try to establish<br/>
<br/>
                             Lance cannot prove that SAT is NOT in P<br/>
<br/>
using brain scans and he volunteered.<br/>
<br/>
<table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody>
<tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-w0aJgcjWXp0/XI-8jhzGnlI/AAAAAAABmv4/xmXbmb5HDy4zahASbPwc-RjOqeRjLD0DgCLcBGAs/s1600/mribrain.jpg" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="320" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-w0aJgcjWXp0/XI-8jhzGnlI/AAAAAAABmv4/xmXbmb5HDy4zahASbPwc-RjOqeRjLD0DgCLcBGAs/s320/mribrain.jpg" width="259"/></a></td></tr>
<tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">Brain Scan of Lance's Proving Ability</td></tr>
</tbody></table>
<br/>
For this one the mental block problem is gone; however,   as you can clearly see from his brain scan, Lance will never prove that SAT is not in P. Seven years as department chair has caused irreversible damage to his ability to reason logically.<br/>
<br/>
We hope to recruit other theorists to the project. The sticking point might be privacy: if we prove that professor X cannot solve P vs NP will the affect their being hired? For this reason we will restrict the study to professors with Tenure. But this is a weakness of the study since we had wanted to study if younger people have a better chance to resolve P vs NP.  So we need to find very young tenured professors.<br/>
<br/>
After we get the technology working on Theorists and P vs NP we will try to expand it for home use. For example, if a spouse claims <i>I could never learn to cook </i>or <i>I could never learn to drive (that's me) </i>their partner  will be able to verify the statement. It is not clear if this will make the divorce rate go up or down. Or if a child says <i>I just can't do algebra</i> the parents can test the child and say <i>Oh yes you can</i>!</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-01T16:43:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-01T16:43:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T17:26:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/046</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/046" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-046 |  andom walks and forbidden minors II: A $\poly(d\eps^{-1})$-query tester for minor-closed properties of bounded degree graphs | 

	Akash Kumar, 

	C. Seshadhri, 

	Andrew Stolman</title>
    <summary>Let $G$ be a graph with $n$ vertices and maximum degree $d$. Fix some minor-closed property $\mathcal{P}$ (such as planarity).
We say that $G$ is $\varepsilon$-far from $\mathcal{P}$ if one has to remove $\varepsilon dn$ edges to make it have $\mathcal{P}$.
The problem of property testing $\mathcal{P}$ was introduced in the seminal work of Benjamini-Schramm-Shapira (STOC 2008)
that gave a tester with query complexity triply exponential in $\varepsilon^{-1}$.
Levi-Ron (TALG 2015) have given the best tester to date, with a quasipolynomial (in $\varepsilon^{-1}$) query complexity.
It is an open problem to get property testers whose query complexity is $\poly(d\varepsilon^{-1})$,
even for planarity.

In this paper, we resolve this open question. For any minor-closed property,
we give a tester with query complexity $d\cdot \poly(\varepsilon^{-1})$.
The previous line of work on (independent of $n$, two-sided) testers is primarily combinatorial.
Our work, on the other hand, employs techniques from spectral graph theory. This paper
is a continuation of recent work of the authors (FOCS 2018) analyzing random walk algorithms
that find forbidden minors.</summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T08:45:13Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-01T08:45:13Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/04/01/the-sat-smt-ar-summer-school/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/04/01/the-sat-smt-ar-summer-school/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The SAT/SMT/AR Summer School</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">July 3-6, 2019 Lisbon, Portugal https://reason.di.fc.ul.pt/ssa-school-2019/ Registration deadline: May 31, 2019 Satisfiability (SAT), Satisfiability Modulo Theories (SMT), and Automated Reasoning (AR) continue to make rapid advances and find novel uses in a wide variety of applications, both in computer science and beyond. The SAT/SMT/AR Summer School aims to bring a select group of students up … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/04/01/the-sat-smt-ar-summer-school/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">The SAT/SMT/AR Summer School</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T08:39:38Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-01T08:39:38Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:21:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=15715</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/04/01/the-breakthrough-result-of-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Breakthrough Result Of 2019</title>
    <summary>Our nomination for best result of the year Cropped from source Faadosly Polir has had an incredible year of research success. A year ago we covered his research on universal information entropy in baseball. This led to uncredited co-authorship on a paper, which Quanta covered last week, about reversal of entropy in a previously-built 51-qubit […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Our nomination for best result of the year</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/carnivalfool.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-15716" height="135" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/carnivalfool.png?w=123&amp;h=135" width="123"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Cropped from <a href="https://pxhere.com/en/photo/1036632">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Faadosly Polir has had an incredible year of research success. A year ago we <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/04/01/the-entropy-of-baseball/">covered</a> his research on universal information entropy in baseball. This led to uncredited co-authorship on a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1812.05561">paper</a>, which <em>Quanta</em> <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/quantum-scarring-appears-to-defy-universes-push-for-disorder-20190320/">covered</a> last week, about reversal of entropy in a previously-built 51-qubit quantum <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nature24622">computer</a>. The paper focuses on quantum many-body scarring in a Bunimovich <a href="https://blogs.ams.org/visualinsight/2016/11/15/bunimovich-stadium/">stadium</a>, but Polir’s work on athletic body scarring in baseball stadiums was integral. </p>
<p>
Today we report on his exciting and topical new findings.<br/>
<span id="more-15715"/></p>
<p>
Polir’s next project implemented a <a href="https://www.quora.com/How-do-random-events-of-quantum-physics-influence-the-information-content-of-the-universe">suggestion</a> by the complexity theorist Vaughan Pratt on how to research the influence of random events on the information content of the universe:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Picture inserting a giant eggbeater into the deep state cloud servers and relocating all its bits at random. How would you recover important information like the net worth of Meghan Markle or President Trump’s tax returns? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Polir began the Cloud Beater Project using spare Amazon Web Services credits from Ken. The results so far are classified, but in addition to the above objectives there is a current push to infer from web traffic the full text of the impending <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_Counsel_investigation_(2017-2019)">report</a> by Robert Mueller. The string length has been <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/28/us/politics/mueller-report-length.html">inferred</a>. Polir’s model algebraically represents the entire cloud as a finite automaton analogous to Alan Turing’s model of the Enigma machine during World War II. The inferencing process is similar and <a href="https://www.nhregister.com/technology/businessinsider/article/With-just-60-and-internet-access-researchers-13628061.php">cheap</a>. </p>
<p>
The newest work, however, will have the greatest social impact for the research community.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Problem </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The problem is one we all are familiar with: the impact of the Internet and computing technology resources on critical thinking and academic research <a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2018/03/is-technology-hurting-productivity">productivity</a>. After extensive analysis-of-variance runs on Google Scholar data, Polir’s team isolated one key adverse factor:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <i>LaTeX forces one to compile and recompile multiple times</i>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
In retrospect the effect of this should have been suspected—after all, LaTeX is the one factor common to a major part of research across all scientific disciplines. Here are examples of relevant user <a href="https://tex.stackexchange.com/questions/107967/need-to-typeset-twice-for-correct-compile">comments</a>, some paraphrased:</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet}"/> You cannot avoid it. LaTeX has to build the .aux file to store the table of contents (ToC) and such, because when typesetting the ToC it cannot know beforehand what sections will occur. </p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet}"/> Often not only two but three or more runs are necessary. Imagine a document with lots of figures and a list of figures somewhere at the first pages of the document. All pages are numbered using ascending Arabic numbers. First compilation run will typeset the document without any entry at the list of figures but collects the information at the .lof file (via .aux file). Second compilation run will typeset the list of figures with several pages and as a consequence of this the page numbers of all figures will change. So you need a third run to get the correct numbers at the list of figures.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet}"/> To correctly line up the various parts of a longtable, “In the typical case the algorithm will converge after three or four passes” (manual, section 4).</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Magnitude </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The result is the observation that there now are so many uses of LaTeX that any inefficiency in using it has great consequences. The bottom line of the first findings chapter in the report led by Polir is:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> We found that over 100 million hours of productive time per year are lost to the multiple-pass issue in LaTeX. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
There are now billions of LaTeX pages being worked on each year. See <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/blog/219-youve-created-three-million-projects-and-counting-dot-dot-dot">this</a> for some data. Thus at a conservative estimate of $100 dollars per hour this means that we are losing <i>over ten billion dollars per year</i>. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Ken’s Solution </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Ken has a way of coping. He spends the time waiting for LaTeX documents to open and compile on his office PC in a productive way. He used to check fantasy baseball or football player news during these waits. But last year he acquired a Facebook friend (FBF) from the chess world who became the first—out of his several hundred FBFs—to post cat videos. Several times daily cat videos, all new. </p>
<p>
Ken had never seen a Facebook cat video before. So now he goes to the FBF’s page and clicks the next one while waiting for LaTeX to finish. This does, however, have less relevance to his statistical chess research than <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2012/07/29/benfords-law-and-baseball/">fantasy</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2015/10/12/is-the-hot-hand-fallacy-a-fallacy/">sports</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/03/28/is-there-momentum-in-chess/">had</a>.</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/videocat.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-15717" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/videocat.png?w=600"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">The mother <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recurring_Saturday_Night_Live_characters_and_sketches_introduced_1988%E2%80%931989#Toonces_The_Driving_Cat">lode</a>?</font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p/><h2> Polir’s Solution </h2><p/>
<p>
Polir found a different solution that does not use cat videos—too bad for the cats. Polir first approached the most recently responsible party, who won the 2013 ACM Turing Award for solving the <em>broken deli number dispenser</em> problem. The prize-winning solution, as described in the <a href="https://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/lamport_1205376.cfm">citation</a>, is to have each customer choose a number higher than all the other customers’ numbers. But how to leverage this brilliant solution to solve the multi-pass problem?</p>
<p>
Polir’s insight came while consulting the original responsible party and author of the following computer <a href="https://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/programs/sat13.w">code</a> for a SAT solver. While hearing the author explain how this code emerged from his Pascal-based <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WEB">WEB</a> and C-based <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CWEB">CWEB</a> programming environments, Polir realized this in a flash:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> A LaTeX document is a <b>network</b>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This led to the realization that the quick-compilation problems could be formulated as instances of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_network_coding">network coding</a> problems upon dividing the document into <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/>-sized chunks. A helpful reader of this blog supplied the final needed piece last week in a <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/#comment-100107">comment</a>: via this new <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.10935">paper</a>, there is an efficient reduction from network coding to integer multiplication. The reduction is not a string mapping but rather “corporate” via direct analysis of solving circuits.</p>
<p>
Thus the solution came down to ideas in the brilliant new <a href="https://web.maths.unsw.edu.au/~davidharvey/papers/nlogn/">paper</a> on integer multiplication which we just <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/">posted</a> about. It means that we can solve the multi-pass problem essentially by multiplying pieces of the document together—or more exactly, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convolution#Discrete_convolution">convolving</a> them. We needn’t be concerned about our remarks on the algorithm in that paper being galactic—there is a clear proof of concept in that the paper’s second author is also the chief developer of the <a href="http://texmacs.org/tmweb/home/welcome.en.html">TeXmacs</a> composition environment. We thus nominate the paper plus Polir’s breakthrough consequence for result of the year.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Incidentally, that comment has tag number 100,107—which means we just passed the 100,000 milepost in whatever those tags signify. We actually have 18,694 comments over the history of the blog and have been intending to mark its passing 20K. This again gives us a “no-fooling” opportunity to thank our readers.</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-01T06:01:57Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-01T06:01:57Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="April Fool"/>
    <category term="breakthrough"/>
    <category term="cat videos"/>
    <category term="entropy"/>
    <category term="Faadosly Polir"/>
    <category term="information theory"/>
    <category term="integer multiplication"/>
    <category term="internet"/>
    <category term="LaTeX"/>
    <category term="multi-pass compiling"/>
    <category term="network coding"/>
    <category term="Robert Mueller"/>
    <category term="TeX"/>
    <category term="TeXmacs"/>
    <category term="Vaughan Pratt"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/03/31/summer-school-on-randomness-and-learning-in-non-linear-algebra/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/03/31/summer-school-on-randomness-and-learning-in-non-linear-algebra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Summer School on Randomness and Learning in Non-Linear Algebra</title>
    <summary>July 1-4, 2019 Leipzig, Germany https://www.mis.mpg.de/calendar/conferences/2019/ranlearn2019.html This summer school aims at bringing together researchers working on probabilistic and statistical methods and questions in nonlinear algebra. Keynote speakers will be: Peter Bürgisser (Technische Universität Berlin) Daniel Erman (University of Wisconsin-Madison) Antonio Lerario (Scuola Internazionale Superiore di Studi Avanzati)</summary>
    <updated>2019-03-31T20:03:04Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-31T20:03:04Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:21:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=17274</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/03/31/is-it-legitimate-ethical-for-google-to-close-google/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Is it Legitimate/Ethical for Google to close Google+?</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Update April 2, 2019: the links below are not working anymore.  Google Plus is a nice social platform with tens of millions participants. I found it especially nice for scientific posts, e.g. by John Baez, Moshe Vardi, or about symplectic … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/03/31/is-it-legitimate-ethical-for-google-to-close-google/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/03/google.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17276" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/03/google.png?w=640"/></a></p>
<h3><span style="color: #ff6600;"><strong>Update April 2, 2019: the links below are not working anymore. </strong></span></h3>
<p>Google Plus is a nice social platform with tens of millions participants. I found it especially nice for scientific posts, e.g. by <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/117663015413546257905">John Baez</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/104488217075635760621">Moshe Vardi</a>, or about <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/s/symplectic%20geometry/top">symplectic geometry, </a> about <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/s/majorana%20fermions/top">Majorana Fermions</a>, and with a discussion about <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/106808239073321070854/posts/cwzYpKXSACM">What is combinatorics</a>. A few months ago Google announced  that Google+ will be closed. This is going to happen today (March 31, 2019) in a few hours. For example, I am not even sure if the above valuable links will continue to operate. (Every individual user can get his own stuff.)</p>
<p>For possible answers on why Google shut down Google Plus see this <a href="https://www.quora.com/Why-is-Google+-closed">Quora question</a>.</p>
<p>My question is different. <span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>Is it legitimate for Google to close Google+? Is it legitimate and is it ethical for Google to eliminate existing content from the public domain?</strong> </span></p>
<h3>Let me state clearly my opinion:</h3>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #000080;"><strong>Google has strong ethical/moral obligation to maintain at least for several years public access to all Google+ existing material. </strong></span></h3>
<p>The fact that huge content that millions of people spent time and effort creating and that people spent time and effort to search and find, is deleted — by a huge and successful company — is very problematic</p>
<p> </p>
<p>(Related post: <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/06/06/what-do-firms-want/">What do firms want</a> .)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-31T17:51:53Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-31T17:51:53Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Economics"/>
    <category term="Open discussion"/>
    <category term="Rationality"/>
    <category term="Google plus"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/03/31/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/03/31/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>A 3-regular matchstick graph of girth 5 consisting of 54 vertices, Mike Winkler, Peter Dinkelacker, and Stefan Vogel (). The previous smallest-known graph with these properties had 180 vertices, but this one might still not be optimal, as the known lower bound is only 30. I found it difficult to understand the connectivity of the graph from its matchstick representation so I made another drawing of the same graph in a different style:</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.04304">A 3-regular matchstick graph of girth 5 consisting of 54 vertices</a>, Mike Winkler, Peter Dinkelacker, and Stefan Vogel (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101761530841835018"/>). The previous smallest-known graph with these properties had 180 vertices, but this one might still not be optimal, as the known lower bound is only 30. I found it difficult to understand the connectivity of the graph from <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Winkler_3-reg_girth5_54.svg">its matchstick representation</a> so I made another drawing of the same graph in a different style:</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="The 54-vertex 3-regular girth-5 matchstick graph of Winkler, Dinkelacker, and Vogel in Lombardi drawing style" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/girth-5-matchstick.svg"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/plexodus/comments/az285j/saving_of_public_google_content_at_the_internet/">Saving public Google+ content at the Internet Archive</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101767934776473984"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19407865">via</a>). Archive.org and the <a href="https://www.archiveteam.org/">Archive Team</a> (a separate “loose collective of rogue archivists, programmers, writers and loudmouths dedicated to saving our digital heritage”) are undertaking an organized effort to capture it all before Google takes it down at the end of the month.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@shonk/101807604452877379">Symmetric minimality</a>, Clayton Shonkwiler. An animation of a symmetric minimal-length grid realization of a trefoil knot, posted after I complained that <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@shonk/101768569662399661">his earlier animation</a> was too asymmetric, and suggested using the realization below (drawn using  <a href="http://vzome.com/home/">vZome</a>). Clayton also posted a <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@shonk/101819922406308000">bcc figure-8</a> and <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@shonk/101825678378019686">bcc </a>. Not every symmetric knot has a symmetric lattice realization (e.g. the  lattice knot doesn’t) but it may be an interesting question whether every lattice-realizable symmetry of a knot can be realized by a minimal lattice knot.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Symmetric lattice trefoil knot drawn using vZome" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/zomeknot.png"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karen_Uhlenbeck">Karen Uhlenbeck</a> becomes <a href="http://www.abelprize.no/c73996/seksjon/vis.html?tid=74011&amp;strukt_tid=73996">the first woman to win the Abel Prize</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@JordiGH/101778053801507834"/>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1073">The curse of the Euclidean metric</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101785024820380513"/>). Krzysztof Fleszar posts about a big difficulty with algorithms for problems like Euclidean shortest paths where the answer is a sum of distances: we don’t know how to compare two solutions efficiently. Fortunately in the case of <a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/10.1137/1.9781611975482.67">Krzysztof’s SODA 2019 paper on approximate TSP of hyperplanes</a> (find a short tour that touches each given hyperplane) it’s possible to use approximate numerical comparisons.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-02070778/document">Integer multiplication in time </a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@erou/101787744661719386"/>, <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/">see also</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment/arts/la-ca-cm-inksap-linda-lack-20190314-story.html">An odd couple of Los Angeles street art</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101794533654899105"/>): 20-something Inksap, a son of Vietnamese refugees, and 70-something dance teacher Linda Lack.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://archive.org/stream/BrainfillingCurves-AFractalBestiary/BrainFilling">Brain-filling curves: A fractal bestiary</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101801960587162487"/>). A 200-page compendium by Jeffrey Ventrella of space-filling curves, generated by subdivision rules that expand line segments to lattice paths whose sum of squared edge lengths equals the square of the segment.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.graphics.rwth-aachen.de/software/zometool">Automatically translate any 3d model into a zometool approximation of it</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101807397098535057"/>, <a href="http://www.zometool.com/news/amazing-app-zometool-shape-approximation/">via</a>). With obligatory Stanford bunny. See also their <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=piDPsHTLV1A">1-minute video introduction</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arstechnica.com/science/2019/03/physicists-are-decoding-math-y-secrets-of-knitting-to-make-bespoke-materials/">Physicists are decoding math-y secrets of knitting to make bespoke materials</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101813393444829450"/>). Jennifer Ouelette writes on <em>Ars Technica</em> that by varying the stitching one can control both the stretchiness and shape of the resulting knit.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathml.igalia.com/news/2019/02/12/launch-of-the-project/">The MathML people are trying again</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101820557668090856"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19344843">via</a>). Much as I think MathML has failed and that promotion by its proponents after its failure was already obvious directly caused the continued bad mathematics rendering on Wikipedia, I wish them well. A working web mathematics markup language (if it can be achieved) would be a step up from Javascripted LaTeX. Of course I’m not about to give up LaTeX in my source but that’s what markup processors are for.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@ccppurcell/101822142519831628">Chris Purcell asks “who is the mathematician/scientist who has the most Wikipedia citations without having a Wikipedia page?”</a>. <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101822690106826262">My guess</a> is Heidi Burgiel, co-author of frequently-cited book <em>The Symmetries of Things</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://jmfork.github.io/2048/">Deterministic 2048</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101830138376282978"/>). The next tile is always a 2 at the first available square. It should be possible to describe a strategy that applies to any  board and that provably achieves a score of  but apparently this is not known.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/2019/03/11/incidences-open-problem-part-1/">Adam Sheffer points out that, despite recent advances in incidence geometry, many problems remain open, and sets out on a project to catalog them</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101837928344081808"/>). His starting points are the unit distances problem and incidences with nonlinear algebraic plane curves.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://gizmodo.com/rss-is-better-than-twitter-1833624929">Why you should be keeping up with news and long-form websites using RSS rather than twitter</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101840580734668234"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19529442">via</a>). If you want to incorporate RSS feeds into your Mastodon stream, <a href="https://friend.camp/@darius/100897757870017125">Darius Kazemi’s RSS-to-Mastodon tool</a> looks useful, but I haven’t tried it, because so far I’m happy reading those feeds through NetNewsWire.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2019/03/28/scholars-complain-visa-problems-ahead-international-conference-canada">International Studies Association participants unable to get visas to go to their conference in Toronto</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101847752696450725"/>), a repeat of an issue I posted about for <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/31/linkage.html">NeurIPS in January</a>. According to the story, the proportion of participants with visa issues is similar to recent years when the conference has been in the US. Which is not a great target for Canada to aspire to…</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-31T16:48:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-31T16:48:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-04-08T04:33:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7489</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/03/30/physics-computation-blog-post-round-up/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Physics &amp; Computation Blog Post Round-up</title>
    <summary>In the Fall, Boaz and I co-taught a grad seminar on physics and computation (see here for some of the original press coverage). We were lucky to attract an intrepid group of students from multiple fields, with representatives from computer science, physics, math and biology. As part of the course, we asked our students to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In the Fall, Boaz and I co-taught a <a href="https://www.boazbarak.org/fall18seminar/">grad seminar</a> on physics and computation (see <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/08/06/physics-envy/">here</a> for some of the original press coverage). We were lucky to attract an intrepid group of students from multiple fields, with representatives from computer science, physics, math and biology. As part of the course, we asked our students to give presentations and write expository blog posts on a number of topics at the intersection of computation and physics, including algorithms from statistical physics, quantum area laws, and the firewall paradox. The students worked hard to produce posts that make the physics concepts accessible to a computer science audience, and the result is a nice collection of posts that create a “bridge” from CS to physics.</p>
<p>Here, the aim is to give a (long overdue) table of contents for their posts. Followers of the blog may have noticed a landslide of physics &amp; computation posts around December and January; if you weren’t able to keep up with them all at the time, then here they are, rounded up and organized by topic.</p>
<h2>Statistical Physics</h2>
<h4>Background and intro to phase transitions:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/09/15/statistical-physics-an-introduction-in-two-parts/">Statistical Physics: an introduction in two parts</a> (by Tselil Schramm)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Algorithms from statistical physics: belief propagation and approximate message passing:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/10/20/belief-propagation-and-the-stochastic-block-model/">Belief Propagation and the Stochastic Block Model</a> (by Thomas Orton)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/26/introduction-to-amp-and-the-replica-trick/">Introduction to AMP and the Replica Trick</a> (by Preetum Nakkiran and <span class="qu"><span class="gD">Yueqi </span></span><span class="qu"><span class="gD">Sheng)</span></span></li>
</ul>
<h4>Informational and computational phase transitions:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/16/algorithmic-and-information-theoretic-decoding-thresholds-for-low-density-parity-check-code/">Algorithmic and Information Theoretic Decoding Thresholds for Low density Parity-Check Code</a> (by Jeremy Dohmann, Vanessa Wong, and Venkat Arun)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Proving the existence of phase transitions:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/13/ising-perceptron-under-gaussian-disorder-and-k-nae-sat/">Ising Perceptron under Gaussian Disorder, and k-NAE-SAT</a> (based on a guest lecture by <a href="https://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~nikesun/">Nike Sun</a>, as scribed by Patrick Guo, Vinh-Kha Le, Shyam Narayanan, and David Stoner)</li>
</ul>
<h4> Using convex relaxations to approximate partition functions:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/11/11/approximating-partition-functions/">Approximating Partition Functions</a> (based on a guest lecture by <a href="https://math.mit.edu/~risteski/">Andrej Risteski</a> as scribed by Alex Kelser, Alex Lin, Amil Merchant, and Suproteem Sarkar)</li>
</ul>
<h2>Quantum Computation</h2>
<h4>Background on Quantum Hamiltonians and tensor network representations:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/20/quantum-hamiltonian-complexity/">What is Quantum Hamiltonian Complexity?</a> (by Ben Edelman)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/20/tensor-networks-matrix-product-states-dmrg/">Tensor Networks, Matrix Product States and Density Matrix Renormalization Group</a> (by Fred Zhang)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Area laws:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/18/a-1d-area-law-for-gapped-local-hamiltonians/">A 1D Area Law for Gapped Local Hamiltonians</a> (by Boriana Gjura and Prayaag Venkat)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quantum algorithms:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/23/introduction-to-quantum-walks/">Introduction to Quantum Walks</a> (by Beatrice Nash)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/20/efficient-preparation-of-thermal-states-of-quantum-systems-natural-or-artificial/">Efficient preparation of thermal states of quantum systems: natural or artificial</a> (based on a guest lecture by <a href="http://web.mit.edu/aram/www/">Aram Harrow</a> as scribed by Sinho Chewi, William S. Moses, Tasha Schoenstein, Ary Swaminathan)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/22/quantum-approximate-optimization-algorithm-and-applications/">Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm and Applications</a> (by
<div class="b4">
<div class="dl">
<div class="aIj">
<div class="c5 J-J5-Ji">Amir Karamlou)</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="dp"/>
</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quantum games and quantum PCPs:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/22/towards-quantum-pcp-a-proof-of-the-nlets-theorem/">Towards Quantum PCP: A Proof of the NLETS Theorem</a> (by Abhijit Mudigonda, Richard Wang, and Lisa Yang)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/03/quantum-games/">Quantum Games</a> (by Nilin Abrahamsen, Daniel Alabi, Mitali Bafna, Emil Khabiboulline, and Juspreet Sandhu)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quantum supremacy:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/25/quantum-circuits-and-their-role-in-demonstrating-quantum-supremacy/">Quantum circuits and their role in demonstrating quantum supremacy</a> (by Hikari Sorensen)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quantum error correction:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/07/quantum-error-correction/">Peter Shor on Quantum Error Correction</a> (based on a guest lecture by Peter Shor as scribed by Annie Wei)</li>
</ul>
<h2>Black Holes and the Firewall Paradox</h2>
<p>(See also Boaz’s <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/08/22/black-holes-paradoxes-and-computational-complexity/">introductory post</a>)</p>
<h4>Background on black holes and the Firewall Paradox:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/20/the-firewall-paradox-in-context/">Why physicists care about the Firewall Paradox</a> (by Noah Miller)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/30/black-hole-paradoxes-a-conservative-yet-radical-journey/">Black hole paradoxes: A conservative yet radical journey</a> (by Abhishek Anand and Noah Miller)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Firewall Paradox meets Computational Complexity:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/02/01/black-holes-a-complexity-theory-perspective/">Black Holes, a complexity theory perspective</a> (by Chi-Ning Chou and Parth Mehta)</li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-30T20:20:58Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-30T20:20:58Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>tselilschramm</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:21:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=15708</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Integer Multiplication in NlogN Time</title>
    <summary>A win for multi-variable polynomials Composite crop from src1, src2 David Harvey and Joris van der Hoeven are computational mathematicians. They have just released a paper showing how to multiply two -bit integers in time. A companion paper gives details of a simpler second algorithm that is time pending a widely-believed conjecture about primes. Today […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>A win for multi-variable polynomials</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/harveyvanderhoeven2/" rel="attachment wp-att-15709"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-15709" height="150" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/03/harveyvanderhoeven2.png?w=201&amp;h=150" width="201"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Composite crop from <a href="https://web.maths.unsw.edu.au/~davidharvey/">src1</a>, <a href="https://www.polytechnique.edu/en/content/researchers-lx-international-congress-mathematicians-brazil">src2</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
David Harvey and Joris van der Hoeven are computational mathematicians. They have just released a <a href="https://web.maths.unsw.edu.au/~davidharvey/papers/nlogn/">paper</a> showing how to multiply two <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-bit integers in <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/> time. A companion <a href="http://www.texmacs.org/joris/ffnlogn/ffnlogn-abs.html">paper</a> gives details of a simpler second algorithm that is <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/> time pending a widely-believed conjecture about primes.</p>
<p>
Today we discuss what makes these new results possible.<br/>
<span id="more-15708"/></p>
<p>
The first paper leads off with a nice history of algorithms that beat the <img alt="{O(n^2)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E2%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n^2)}"/>-time method all of us learned in school. Far from being <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2010/10/23/galactic-algorithms/">galactic</a>, the longtime-champion <img alt="{O(n\log n \log\!\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n+%5Clog%5C%21%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n \log\!\log n)}"/> algorithm of Arnold Schönhage and Volker Strassen is a workhorse of the GNU Multiple Precision Library (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_Multiple_Precision_Arithmetic_Library">GMP</a>). The <img alt="{\log\!\log n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog%5C%21%5Clog+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log\!\log n}"/> factor was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Furer's_algorithm">improved</a> by Martin Fürer in 2007 and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1407.3360?context=cs">further</a> in 2014 by Harvey and van der Hoeven with Grégoire Lecerf. Now it is gone altogether.</p>
<p>
Their algorithm is currently not practical, but it is also not yet tuned. At the start of section 5, they note that their estimates take effect for <img alt="{n \geq 2^{d^{12}}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn+%5Cgeq+2%5E%7Bd%5E%7B12%7D%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n \geq 2^{d^{12}}}"/> where they use <img alt="{d = 1,\!729}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd+%3D+1%2C%5C%21729%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d = 1,\!729}"/>. When they note that <img alt="{2^{d^{12}} &gt; 2^{4,\!096}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7Bd%5E%7B12%7D%7D+%3E+2%5E%7B4%2C%5C%21096%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{d^{12}} &gt; 2^{4,\!096}}"/> they don’t mean the numbers need at least <img alt="{4,\!096}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B4%2C%5C%21096%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{4,\!096}"/> bits, rather <img alt="{2^{4,\!096}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7B4%2C%5C%21096%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{4,\!096}}"/> is the number of bits. Since there are only <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/space/a27259/how-many-particles-are-in-the-entire-universe/">about</a> <img alt="{2^{270}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7B270%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{270}}"/> particles in the observable universe, this puts the term <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2010/10/23/galactic-algorithms/">galactic</a> to shame. </p>
<p>
The number <img alt="{1,\!729}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2C%5C%21729%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1,\!729}"/> recalls a famous <a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Hardy-RamanujanNumber.html">story</a> about Godfrey Hardy and Srinivasa Ramanujan. This is not wholly a coincidence. They get a bounding multiplier of <img alt="{36}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B36%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{36}"/> from one place, another factor of <img alt="{6}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B6%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{6}"/> from another, and finally a factor of <img alt="{8}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B8%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{8}"/> giving <img alt="{1,\!728}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2C%5C%21728%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1,\!728}"/> which equals <img alt="{12^3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B12%5E3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{12^3}"/>. Then they just make <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/> be higher by <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/>, setting up <img alt="{1,\!729 = 12^3 + 1^3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2C%5C%21729+%3D+12%5E3+%2B+1%5E3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1,\!729 = 12^3 + 1^3}"/> which happens to equal <img alt="{9^3 + 10^3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B9%5E3+%2B+10%5E3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{9^3 + 10^3}"/>. But there is much flex in the choices and they sketch how to improve the needed bound from <img alt="{1,\!728}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2C%5C%21728%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1,\!728}"/> to just <img alt="{8}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B8%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{8}"/>. They also uncover some new tricks for calculating in certain large finite rings defined via multi-variable polynomials.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Polynomials and Tricks </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
When we heard the news on Tuesday, both of us thought of the famous primality <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AKS_primality_test">test</a> of Manindra Agrawal, Neeraj Kayal, and Nitin Saxena (AKS), which placed deciding primality into deterministic polynomial time. We stated the message as the title of an old <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2011/02/26/polynomials-are-easier-than-integers/">post</a> on other joint work by Kayal: “Polynomials Are Easier Than Integers.” </p>
<p>
The crux of the AKS test is to employ the theorem that for any co-prime <img alt="{(a,N)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28a%2CN%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(a,N)}"/>, the polynomial congruence relation </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  (x + a)^N \equiv x^N + a \pmod{N} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%28x+%2B+a%29%5EN+%5Cequiv+x%5EN+%2B+a+%5Cpmod%7BN%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  (x + a)^N \equiv x^N + a \pmod{N} "/></p>
<p>holds in <img alt="{\mathbb{Z}[x]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{Z}[x]}"/> if and only if <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> is prime. This is tested in the quotient ring <img alt="{\mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^r - 1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx%5D%2F%28x%5Er+-+1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^r - 1)}"/>. The game becomes finding <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> small enough and minimizing the number of <img alt="{a}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a}"/> that need to be checked in order for the body of tests in the quotient ring to be conclusive. </p>
<p>
We take time to note that the case <img alt="{a = N-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba+%3D+N-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a = N-1}"/> is possibly sufficient while testing a small set of <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/>. Agrawal has <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agrawal's_conjecture">conjectured</a> that if <img alt="{(x - 1)^N \equiv x^N - 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x+-+1%29%5EN+%5Cequiv+x%5EN+-+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(x - 1)^N \equiv x^N - 1}"/> modulo both <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> and <img alt="{x^r - 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%5Er+-+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x^r - 1}"/> then either <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> is prime or <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> divides <img alt="{N^2 - 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%5E2+-+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N^2 - 1}"/>. This conjecture is <a href="https://aimath.org/WWN/primesinp/primesinp.pdf">doubted</a> on heuristic counting grounds but it has been verified for <img alt="{N &lt; 10^{12}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN+%3C+10%5E%7B12%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N &lt; 10^{12}}"/> and can be <a href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2009/008.pdf">modified</a> by including the case <img alt="{a = 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba+%3D+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a = 2}"/>. It would improve the polynomial time in the number <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> of bits in <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> from <img alt="{\tilde{O}(n^6)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctilde%7BO%7D%28n%5E6%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\tilde{O}(n^6)}"/> to <img alt="{\tilde{O}(n^3)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctilde%7BO%7D%28n%5E3%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\tilde{O}(n^3)}"/> and also improve the constants. We mention this because Harvey and van der Hoeven have a number-theoretic conjecture that (as shown in their companion paper) improves both their constant on <img alt="{n\log n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5Clog+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n\log n}"/> and the simplicity of the proof.</p>
<p>
The further message of the new papers is added power from giving the polynomials more variables. They use <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/> variables: <img alt="{x_1,\dots,x_{d-1}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_%7Bd-1%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x_1,\dots,x_{d-1}}"/> plus a nominal <img alt="{x_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x_d}"/> that is later substituted by <img alt="{e^{\pi i/r} y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%5E%7B%5Cpi+i%2Fr%7D+y%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e^{\pi i/r} y}"/>. Here <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> is a certain power of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/> and combined with the <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/>-th variable <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/> to build the base ring <img alt="{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R}"/> of complex polynomials in <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/> modulo <img alt="{y^r + 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%5Er+%2B+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y^r + 1}"/>. The other variables are used to mod out by <img alt="{(x_1^{t_1} - 1,\dots,x_{d-1}^{t_{d-1}} - 1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x_1%5E%7Bt_1%7D+-+1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_%7Bd-1%7D%5E%7Bt_%7Bd-1%7D%7D+-+1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(x_1^{t_1} - 1,\dots,x_{d-1}^{t_{d-1}} - 1)}"/> where the <img alt="{t_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_i}"/> are powers of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/> no higher than <img alt="{2r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2r%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2r}"/>. Operations in quotient rings of this type are especially efficient. They are used to emulate operations in <img alt="{\mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^s - 1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx%5D%2F%28x%5Es+-+1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^s - 1)}"/> where <img alt="{s}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s}"/> is a product of primes <img alt="{s_1\cdots s_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_1%5Ccdots+s_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_1\cdots s_d}"/> that are near powers of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/>. The emulation is done via the isomorphism</p>
<p>
<a name="CRT"/></p><a name="CRT">
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^{s_1\cdots s_d} - 1) \cong \mathbb{Z}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{s_1} - 1,\dots,x_d^{s_d} - 1), \ \ \ \ \ (1)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx%5D%2F%28x%5E%7Bs_1%5Ccdots+s_d%7D+-+1%29+%5Ccong+%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5D%2F%28x_1%5E%7Bs_1%7D+-+1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5E%7Bs_d%7D+-+1%29%2C+%5C+%5C+%5C+%5C+%5C+%281%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^{s_1\cdots s_d} - 1) \cong \mathbb{Z}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{s_1} - 1,\dots,x_d^{s_d} - 1), \ \ \ \ \ (1)"/></p>
</a><p><a name="CRT"/> which follows from the Chinese remainder theorem. </p>
<p>
They start with Schönhage and Strassen’s original trick of splitting the two <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-bit integers into <img alt="{\Theta(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CTheta%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Theta(\log n)}"/>-sized pieces so that the problem reduces to multiplying polynomials of degree <img alt="{\Theta(n/\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CTheta%28n%2F%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Theta(n/\log n)}"/> in <img alt="{\mathbb{Z}[x]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{Z}[x]}"/> with coefficients of <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/> size. They use the <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/>-dimensional Discrete Fourier Transform over <img alt="{\mathbb{C}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BC%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{C}}"/> with complex operations that need only <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/> bits of precision individually. This setting also gives leeway for approximative methods in their final algorithm. But first we describe what was evidently their original strategy.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Recursive Strategy </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Their first task in either case is to find <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/>-many distinct primes <img alt="{s_1,\dots,s_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cs_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_1,\dots,s_d}"/> of order <img alt="{(n/\log n)^{1/d}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28n%2F%5Clog+n%29%5E%7B1%2Fd%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(n/\log n)^{1/d}}"/> in magnitude. Now when <img alt="{d = 1,\!729}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd+%3D+1%2C%5C%21729%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d = 1,\!729}"/> the exponent <img alt="{1/d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2Fd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1/d}"/> makes the primes quite small indeed, and the need to find distinct ones already drives <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> up quite high before their algorithm can even go into effect. Moreover, for the approximation to work, the primes need to be congruent to <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/> modulo <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/>. </p>
<p>
Their original strategy—detailed in the companion paper—builds on a <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/1448407">result</a> of Charles Rader to reduce the DFT computation to multiplications in </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \mathbb{C}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{s_1 - 1} - 1,\dots,x_d^{s_d - 1} - 1), " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathbb%7BC%7D%5Bx_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5D%2F%28x_1%5E%7Bs_1+-+1%7D+-+1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5E%7Bs_d+-+1%7D+-+1%29%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \mathbb{C}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{s_1 - 1} - 1,\dots,x_d^{s_d - 1} - 1), "/></p>
<p>where compared to (<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/#CRT">1</a>) they have reduced the exponents by one. Using <img alt="{s_i \equiv 1 \pmod{r}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_i+%5Cequiv+1+%5Cpmod%7Br%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_i \equiv 1 \pmod{r}}"/>, they next reduce this to multiplications in </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \mathbb{C}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{r} - 1,\dots,x_d^{r} - 1). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathbb%7BC%7D%5Bx_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5D%2F%28x_1%5E%7Br%7D+-+1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5E%7Br%7D+-+1%29.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \mathbb{C}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{r} - 1,\dots,x_d^{r} - 1). "/></p>
<p>Then the above-mentioned substitution of <img alt="{x_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x_d}"/> by <img alt="{e^{\pi i/r} y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%5E%7B%5Cpi+i%2Fr%7D+y%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e^{\pi i/r} y}"/> makes them into products over </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  R[x_1,\dots,x_{d-1}]/(x_1^{t_1} - 1,\dots,x_{d-1}^{t_{d-1}} - 1) \qquad\text{with}\qquad R = \mathbb{C}[y]/(y^r + 1). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++R%5Bx_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_%7Bd-1%7D%5D%2F%28x_1%5E%7Bt_1%7D+-+1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_%7Bd-1%7D%5E%7Bt_%7Bd-1%7D%7D+-+1%29+%5Cqquad%5Ctext%7Bwith%7D%5Cqquad+R+%3D+%5Cmathbb%7BC%7D%5By%5D%2F%28y%5Er+%2B+1%29.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  R[x_1,\dots,x_{d-1}]/(x_1^{t_1} - 1,\dots,x_{d-1}^{t_{d-1}} - 1) \qquad\text{with}\qquad R = \mathbb{C}[y]/(y^r + 1). "/></p>
<p>These last products are at last amenable to the usual Fast Fourier Transform trick of applying FFT for each <img alt="{t_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_i}"/> by pretending that <img alt="{y^{2r/t_i}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%5E%7B2r%2Ft_i%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y^{2r/t_i}}"/> is a primitive <img alt="{t_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_i}"/>-th root of unity, multiplying pointwise in <img alt="{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R}"/>, and doing the inverse FFT. Finally the products in <img alt="{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R}"/> can be converted into <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/>-bit integer products, and this sets up the vast recursion from multiplying the original <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-bit integers to a batch of <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/>-bit ones. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Finding Good Primes </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
In order for the recursion to solve to <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/>, they need the values <img alt="{q_i = (s_i - 1)/r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq_i+%3D+%28s_i+-+1%29%2Fr%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q_i = (s_i - 1)/r}"/> to be not too large. Viewing this task from the bottom up, they want to choose a single value <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> and choose small <img alt="{q_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q_i}"/> such that <img alt="{s_i = rq_i + 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_i+%3D+rq_i+%2B+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_i = rq_i + 1}"/> is prime. Since <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> is a power of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/>, there is some resemblance to the harder task of finding Sophie Germain primes, which are also relevant to the AKS algorithm. In this case, however, all they need is a sufficiently small <img alt="{\epsilon &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon &gt; 0}"/> such that:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> For all coprime <img alt="{a,k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%2Ck%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a,k}"/> with <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k}"/> sufficiently large, there is a prime <img alt="{q &lt; k^{1+\epsilon}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq+%3C+k%5E%7B1%2B%5Cepsilon%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q &lt; k^{1+\epsilon}}"/> such that <img alt="{q \equiv a \pmod{k}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq+%5Cequiv+a+%5Cpmod%7Bk%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q \equiv a \pmod{k}}"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This is, however, only known for “<img alt="{\epsilon}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon}"/>” <img alt="{= 4.18}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3D+4.18%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{= 4.18}"/> and the Generalized Riemann Hypothesis is only known to improve the bound to <img alt="{k^{2+\delta}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%5E%7B2%2B%5Cdelta%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k^{2+\delta}}"/> for any <img alt="{\delta &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdelta+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\delta &gt; 0}"/>. The above is conjectured to hold for any <img alt="{\epsilon &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon &gt; 0}"/> but it hasn’t been proved. They currently need it for <img alt="{\epsilon = 1/303}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon+%3D+1%2F303%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon = 1/303}"/>.</p>
<p>
The companion paper uses the conjecture to improve multiplication in the field <img alt="{\mathbb{F}_{p^\ell}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BF%7D_%7Bp%5E%5Cell%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{F}_{p^\ell}}"/> to time <img alt="{O(n\ell \log(p)(\log(n) + \log(\ell) + \log\!\log(p))}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Cell+%5Clog%28p%29%28%5Clog%28n%29+%2B+%5Clog%28%5Cell%29+%2B+%5Clog%5C%21%5Clog%28p%29%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\ell \log(p)(\log(n) + \log(\ell) + \log\!\log(p))}"/>. This uses a single algorithm over any prime <img alt="{p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p}"/> and power <img alt="{\ell}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cell%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\ell}"/>; of course if they are fixed, then this time likewise becomes <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/>. This currently needs <img alt="{\epsilon = 1/2^{1,\!162}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon+%3D+1%2F2%5E%7B1%2C%5C%21162%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon = 1/2^{1,\!162}}"/>. </p>
<p>
The companion <a href="http://www.texmacs.org/joris/ffnlogn/ffnlogn-abs.html">paper</a> has full details of how all this works and many more numerical tricks than we’ve mentioned—a <em>tour de force</em>. Getting the result for integer multiplication unconditionally, however, requires one more major tool in their arsenal. To use it they set up the primes <img alt="{s_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_i}"/> to be slightly below respective powers of 2 <img alt="{t_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_i}"/> (rather than be above a single power of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/> <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> by the aforementioned factors <img alt="{q_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q_i}"/>) while retaining <img alt="{t_1\cdots t_d = O(s_1 \cdots s_d)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_1%5Ccdots+t_d+%3D+O%28s_1+%5Ccdots+s_d%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_1\cdots t_d = O(s_1 \cdots s_d)}"/>. </p>
<p>
Their innovation compared to the translations in the first strategy is that one can still reduce the DFT computation in dimensions <img alt="{s_1,\dots,s_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cs_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_1,\dots,s_d}"/> needing <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/> precision to a complex DFT in dimensions <img alt="{t_1,\dots,t_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_1%2C%5Cdots%2Ct_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_1,\dots,t_d}"/> by employing approximation. Their algorithm is completely deterministic but it employs weights that conform to Gaussian distributions to effect the approximation. The preservation of Gaussians under Fourier transforms enables close enough approximations to be obtained by solving relatively small and easily-specified systems of linear equations. The resulting complex DFT is then massaged in a manner similar to the first strategy. The resulting recursion is not quite as steep—it goes from <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> to <img alt="{n' = n^{1/d + o(1)}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%27+%3D+n%5E%7B1%2Fd+%2B+o%281%29%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n' = n^{1/d + o(1)}}"/>—but it gives </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  M(n) = \frac{Kn}{n'} M(n') + O(n\log n) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++M%28n%29+%3D+%5Cfrac%7BKn%7D%7Bn%27%7D+M%28n%27%29+%2B+O%28n%5Clog+n%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  M(n) = \frac{Kn}{n'} M(n') + O(n\log n) "/></p>
<p>with <img alt="{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{K}"/> and the <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/> term independent of <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/> (indeed, <img alt="{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{K}"/> becomes the aforementioned <img alt="{1,\!729}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2C%5C%21729%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1,\!729}"/>). This gives <img alt="{M(n) = O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%28n%29+%3D+O%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{M(n) = O(n\log n)}"/>. The approximation technique does not work for multiplication in <img alt="{\mathbb{F}_{p^\ell}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BF%7D_%7Bp%5E%5Cell%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{F}_{p^\ell}}"/>, however. As usual, here is where we say to consult the papers for further details—there is a wealth of them.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Will the <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/> time be concretely improvable? Will it tell us anything about the <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2009/02/24/a-conjecture-of-hartmanis/">problem</a> of <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2012/06/15/why-the-hartmanis-stearns-conjecture-is-still-open/">proving</a> a super-linear lower bound? And short of those two goals, what new results will become possible through the multi-variable polynomial techniques they employ?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-29T13:23:44Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-29T13:23:44Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="primes"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="trick"/>
    <category term="algebra"/>
    <category term="Arnold Schonhage"/>
    <category term="asymptotics"/>
    <category term="congruence"/>
    <category term="David Harvey"/>
    <category term="finite fields"/>
    <category term="integer multiplication"/>
    <category term="Joris van der Hoeven"/>
    <category term="Manindra Agrawal"/>
    <category term="Martin Furer"/>
    <category term="Neeraj Kayal"/>
    <category term="Nitin Saxena"/>
    <category term="NlogN time"/>
    <category term="polynomials"/>
    <category term="rings"/>
    <category term="Volker Strassen"/>
    <author>
      <name>KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-04-09T00:20:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
