<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2021-09-01T14:39:26Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/09/01/quics-hartree-postdoctoral-fellowships-at-joint-center-for-quantum-information-and-computer-science-quics-at-quics-university-of-maryland-apply-by-december-1-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/09/01/quics-hartree-postdoctoral-fellowships-at-joint-center-for-quantum-information-and-computer-science-quics-at-quics-university-of-maryland-apply-by-december-1-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>QuICS Hartree Postdoctoral Fellowships at Joint Center for Quantum Information and Computer Science (QuICS) at QuICS/University of Maryland (apply by December 1, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Joint Center for Quantum Information and Computer Science (QuICS, http://quics.umd.edu) is seeking exceptional candidates for the QuICS Hartree Postdoctoral Fellowships in Quantum Information and Computer Science. Applications should be submitted through AcademicJobsOnline at https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/fellowship/19390. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/fellowship/19390 Email: quics-coordinator@umiacs.umd.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Joint Center for Quantum Information and Computer Science (QuICS, <a href="http://quics.umd.edu">http://quics.umd.edu</a>) is seeking exceptional candidates for the QuICS Hartree Postdoctoral Fellowships in Quantum Information and Computer Science. Applications should be submitted through AcademicJobsOnline at <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/fellowship/19390">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/fellowship/19390</a>.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/fellowship/19390">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/fellowship/19390</a><br/>
Email: quics-coordinator@umiacs.umd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-09-01T14:33:08Z</updated>
    <published>2021-09-01T14:33:08Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/09/01/a-postdoc-position-in-machine-learning-focusing-on-applications-in-renewable-energy-systems-at-technion-israe-l-institute-of-technology-apply-by-october-15-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/09/01/a-postdoc-position-in-machine-learning-focusing-on-applications-in-renewable-energy-systems-at-technion-israe-l-institute-of-technology-apply-by-october-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Postdoc Position in Machine Learning, Focusing on Applications in Renewable Energy Systems at Technion—Israe l Institute of Technology (apply by October 15, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The research groups of Shie Mannor, Yoash Levron and Kfir Levy from the Faculty of Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering, offer a postdoctoral position in the field of machine learning, focusing on applications in power systems and renewable energy systems. The objective of the proposed project is to investigate possible applications of XAI in power systems […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The research groups of Shie Mannor, Yoash Levron and Kfir Levy from the Faculty of Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering, offer a postdoctoral position in the field of machine learning, focusing on applications in power systems and renewable energy systems.<br/>
The objective of the proposed project is to investigate possible applications of XAI in power systems and renewable energy systems.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://mlis.technion.ac.il/">https://mlis.technion.ac.il/</a><br/>
Email: yoashl@ee.technion.ac.il</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-09-01T12:00:47Z</updated>
    <published>2021-09-01T12:00:47Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/08/31/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/08/31/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>Finding a stationary point of a smooth function (as can be done, eventually, by gradient descent) is complete for \(\mathsf{PPAD}\cap\mathsf{PLS}\) (\(\mathbb{M}\), via) as Fearnley, Goldberg, Hollender, and Savani write in STOC 2021 best paper “The complexity of gradient descent”. Gradient descent finds local minima quickly in many cases, but can be slow to navigate shallow labyrinthine optimization landscapes; this result suggests that there are unlikely to be much better shortcuts.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p>Finding a stationary point of a smooth function (as can be done, eventually, by gradient descent) is complete for \(\mathsf{PPAD}\cap\mathsf{PLS}\) (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106772538573678641">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/computer-scientists-discover-limits-of-major-research-algorithm-20210817/">via</a>) as Fearnley, Goldberg, Hollender, and Savani write in STOC 2021 best paper “<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.01929">The complexity of gradient descent</a>”. Gradient descent finds local minima quickly in many cases, but can be slow to navigate shallow labyrinthine optimization landscapes; this result suggests that there are unlikely to be much better shortcuts.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyadic_rational">Dyadic rational</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106779193515008360">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), the fractions whose denominators are powers of two. These are among the earliest concepts of fractions to develop in schoolchildren, frequently used in systems of weights and measures, and (because they are the ones with finite binary representations) central to computing. Now a Good Article on Wikipedia.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/20210">Pentagonum pentagonorum</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106789568903344596">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). The space of shapes of convex equiangular pentagons itself forms a right equilateral pentagon in a hyperbolic plane of self-crossing pentagon shapes, and its tiling by edge-reflections corresponds to moves that add or remove a “bowtie” on a pentagon edge. Other choices of fixed angles give other right hyperbolic pentagons, parameterized by a pentagon of pentagons of pentagons. New “short story” by Danny Calegari in the <em>Notices</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/a-deep-math-dive-into-why-some-infinities-are-bigger-than-others/">A deep math dive into why some infinities are bigger than others</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106796347455729012">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2021/08/a-deep-math-dive-into-why-some-infinities-are-bigger-than-others.html">via</a>). Martin Goldstern and Jakob Kellner carefully explore the relations between certain infinite cardinalities, all more than countable but at most the cardinality of the continuum, defined using measure-zero and nowhere-dense subsets of the plane.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Australian Research Council unexpectedly nukes any applicants for Future Fellowships and 
Discovery Early Career Researcher Awards who had the temerity to cite “preprints”, anywhere in their proposals, defined as pre-peer-review versions of journal papers but interpreted more broadly to cover reviewed pre-publication versions, tech reports, white papers, etc: <a href="https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/heartbreak-research-careers-ruined-australian-rule-tweak"><em>Times Higher Education</em></a>, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/education/2021/aug/20/devastating-career-event-scientists-caught-out-by-change-to-australian-research-council-fine-print"><em>Guardian</em></a>, <a href="https://www.researchprofessionalnews.com/rr-news-australia-government-agencies-2021-8-fury-mounts-over-arc-grants/"><em>Research Professional News</em></a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/ARC_Tracker/status/1428120670391603200"><em>ARC Tracker</em></a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106803003708416295">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CSv1fVtjCbX/">A tiling of the plane by center-hinged pairs of equilateral triangles, connected at their corners, expands into a different tiling by stars, hexagons, and diamonds</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106809169136660230">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://www.metafilter.com/192397/Friday-foldy-fun">via</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://nitter.fdn.fr/AngelikiKoutso1/status/1428795625974468623">Euclidean Geometry Street</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@antoinechambertloir/106810914210492431">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), a street in Greece decorated with geometry diagram street art.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.cantorsparadise.com/playing-with-geometry-imo-2021-problem-4-4e534ae98146">Two equal-length quadrilaterals from a tangential quadrilateral</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106826806266178026K">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>): IMO 2021 Problem 4 explained with the help of some dynamic geometry software, by Russell Lim.</p>
  </li>
  <li>While beefing up the Wikipedia article on the handshaking lemma in graph theory  (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106832642233608294">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), I chanced on <a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/topic/Handshaking-lemma/637997">the Semantic Scholar page of “papers important to this topic”, supposedly extracted by artificial intelligence</a>. I see:
    <ul>
      <li>The 3-vertex model in physics</li>
      <li>A relevant review on general topics in graph theory</li>
      <li>Household goods in China</li>
      <li>Sociolinguistics of sexuality</li>
      <li>Paths on meshes (maybe relevant?)</li>
      <li>Workplace trust</li>
      <li>Famous cases of asthma</li>
      <li>Arthropod DNA</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Moral: AI is hard!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://theconversation.com/excel-autocorrect-errors-still-plague-genetic-research-raising-concerns-over-scientific-rigour-166554">Among recent genetics papers using Excel spreadsheets for their data, roughly 30% contained autocorrect errors such as conversion of non-date text to dates, up from 20% in a 2016 study</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106835013253564017">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://retractionwatch.com/2021/08/28">via</a>). “The lesson for researchers is clear: it’s past time to stop using Excel and learn to use more powerful software.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.09832">Progress on universal covers for carpenter’s rules</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106837942716544142">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), small-area diameter-1 shapes into which every polyline with segment lengths ≤ 1 can be folded. The new shape in this preprint by three Jiangs (at least one apparently a home-schooled high-schooler) kind of looks like the Starfleet emblem from Star Trek: a curvy triangle with a concave base and two convex sides. The sides are just involutes of the base; the harder part is finding the right base.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://leosstemhacks.wordpress.com/2018/03/27/np-complete-3rd-grade-math-problems/">NP Complete 3rd Grade Math Problems</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@jhertzli/106836869097887100">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). A worksheet asks students to solve a subset sum problem with 279 valid solutions out of roughly 2 million possibilities. Maybe they expect the kids to code it on a computer?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>My new favorite xkcd: <a href="https://xkcd.com/2509/">some useful geometry formulas</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106849244513165410">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/14614448211023772">Gender, notability, and inequality on Wikipedia</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106853402792027473">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Wikipedia_Signpost/2021-08-29/In_the_media">via</a>). Study by Francesca Tripodi finds that biographies of women on Wikipedia face significantly greater pressure to be deleted than biographies of men, even when factoring out other variables by considering only the biographies that are eventually deemed worthy of inclusion.</li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-31T16:46:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-31T16:46:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T00:12:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-1644972784510347593</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/1644972784510347593/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/08/since-we-will-soon-be-back-in-classroom.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1644972784510347593" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1644972784510347593" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/08/since-we-will-soon-be-back-in-classroom.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Since we will soon be back in the classroom, how was Zoom? Anything you want to maintain?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>UMCP will have all classes on campus this Fall. There is a Mask Mandate. All students and faculty have to get vaccinated unless they have a health or religious exception. 92% are vaccinated, which I interpret as people are NOT abusing the exceptions (though I still wish it was higher, and it may go higher). (ADED LATER- right after I posted this I got an email saying that UMCP is now up to 97%).  Those NOT vaccinated have to get tested - I think twice a week. </p><p>Now that we are back in the live-classroom, here are some thoughts about teaching on zoom. </p><p>I taught on zoom:</p><p>Spring 2020: The last half of both Ramsey Theory and Automata Theory(Reg, CFG,P,NP,Dec,Undec)</p><p>Fall 2021:  Cryptography </p><p>Spring 2021: Honors Discrete Math and Automata theory</p><p><br/></p><p>a) I taught in the usual time slot but I recorded the lecture so those who could not make it (more common during the pandemic) could still see it. Attendance was low, verbal interaction was low, but chat-interaction was very good. Looking into if we can do a chat in an in-person class. I was recording lectures before the pandemic and will keep doing so.</p><p>b) My exams were open-notes, open-book, open-web. That cuts down on ways they can cheat, though they can still phone-a-friend. Or ask their cat.  Unusual-but-correct answers can happen, as I discussed in <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/07/a-table-for-matrix-mortality-what-i.html#comment-form">this blog</a>.</p><p>c) I gave my muffin talk a few times on zoom. In person it goes very well as my enthusiasm is contagious.  On Zoom that affect is dampened so the audience was more sedate.  I gave it as a special lecture to High School students and to my REU students. Note that it was NOT part of a class so the usual motivation to learn it to do the HW is gone. Hence its more important they be excited about it. </p><p>d) In person I carefully make sure that I wear a funny T-shirt every day, and its a diff one, and usually a math one to (if possible) match the topic. On Zoom I did not bother, though I sometimes used wallpaper to match the topic. </p><p>e) I had to make up slides for Aut theory and for some of Discrete Math. For Crypto I already had slides. I like the slides I made up and will use them in the future. But see next point. </p><p>f) In Discrete Math I went  faster than usual- perhaps because its on slides, perhaps because there were less questions since it was on zoom, perhaps because Emily my  TA was so awesome that they had less questions. (She is very interested in education and did a guest post about the pandemic and education <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/04/a-guest-blog-on-pandemics-affect-on.html">here</a>.) As a result I actually learned and presented the proofs that (1) the e is irrational (my slides are <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/users/gasarch/COURSES/250/S21/slides/etalk.pdf">here</a>) and that Liouville numbers are transcendental (my slides are <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/users/gasarch/COURSES/250/S21/slides/ltalk.pdf">here</a>). While I enjoyed learning those theorems and I think the students understood them on some level, I will slow down next time.</p><p>g) Ramsey Theory: It is impossible to teach the Poly VDW theorem on slides, so I had to omit that part of the course. </p><p>h) Bottom Line: Did the students learn more? less? the same? My impression is that the students learned about the same, but really really didn't like it. And thats legit- that is NOT just students complaining. </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-31T15:34:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-31T15:34:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T10:35:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5777</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5777" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5777#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5777" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">“The Chair”: A Straussian interpretation</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">[Warning: spoilers follow!] Last week Dana and I watched the full first season of The Chair, the Netflix drama that stars Sandra Oh as Ji-Yoon Kim, incoming chairwoman of the English department at the fictional Pembroke University. As the rave reviews promised, I found the show to be brilliantly written and acted. At times, The […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p/>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img alt="" src="https://www.scottaaronson.com/thechair.jpg"/></figure></div>



<p><strong>[Warning: spoilers follow!]</strong></p>



<p>Last week Dana and I watched the full first season of <a href="https://www.netflix.com/title/81206259"><em>The Chair</em></a>, the Netflix drama that stars Sandra Oh as Ji-Yoon Kim, incoming chairwoman of the English department at the fictional Pembroke University.  As the rave reviews promised, I found the show to be brilliantly written and acted.  At times, <em>The Chair</em> made me think about that <em>other</em> academia-centered sitcom, <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Big_Bang_Theory">The Big Bang Theory</a></em>, which I freely confess I also enjoyed.  But <em>The Chair</em> is much more highbrow (and more political), it’s about the humanities rather than STEM, and it’s mostly about academics who are older than the ones in <em>Big Bang</em>, both biologically and professionally.</p>



<p>I wouldn’t call <em>The Chair</em> “realistic”: the sets, stuffed with imposing bookshelves, paintings of great scholars, etc., look like how a TV producer might imagine university buildings, rather than the relatively humdrum reality.  But in less than three hours, the show tackles a staggering number of issues that will be recognizable and relevant to anyone in academia: cratering enrollments, a narrow-minded cost-cutting dean, a lack of free time and a desperate search for childcare, a tenure case that turns into a retention case, a woke scandal (about which more later), a faculty revolt against Ji-Yoon culminating in a vote of no confidence, and much more.  There’s also an elaborate side plot involving the actor (and real-life former literary scholar) David Duchovny, who portrays himself, being invited to lecture at Pembroke, which is <em>not</em> the sort of thing most academics have experience with, but which I suppose many viewers will enjoy.</p>



<p>The show is written at a high enough level that its stumbles are those of a daring acrobat.  In the main narrative arc of the first season, the writers set themselves an absurdly ambitious (and, I think, laudable) goal: namely, to dramatize a conflict between a free-spirited professor, and woke students trying to cancel that professor for a classroom “microaggression,” in a way that fully empathizes with both sides.  I don’t know if the show actually succeeds at this, but that’s partly because I don’t know if it’s <em>possible</em> to succeed.</p>



<p>To start with some background: in Pembroke’s English department, there are old, traditionalist white males, who give lectures extolling the Great Men of Literature, and who apparently still wield considerable power.  Meanwhile, critical theorists are presented as young, exciting upstarts bravely challenging the status quo.  People with recent experience of English departments should correct me if I’m wrong, but my sense is that this is pretty anachronistic—i.e., that the last powerful traditionalists in humanities departments were routed by the 80s or 90s at the latest, so that students in the Twitter-and-smartphone era (when <em>The Chair</em> is set) would be about as likely to encounter them as they would professors sitting around in charcoal suits smoking pipes.</p>



<p>There were also some of what felt to me like … intersectional oversights?  Ji-Yoon, being Korean-American, is repeatedly approached by Black female students and faculty as a “fellow woman of color,” with whom they can commiserate about the entrenched power of the department’s white males.  The show never examines how woke discourse has increasingly reclassified Asian-Americans as “white-adjacent”—as, for example, in the battles over gifted and magnet programs or admissions to Harvard.  Likewise, woke students are shown standing arm-in-arm with Pembroke’s Jewish community, to denounce (what we in the audience know to be) a phantom antisemitic incident.  Left unexplored is how, in the modern woke hierarchy, Jews have become just another kind of privileged white person (worse, of course, if they have ties to Israel).</p>



<p>This brings me to the first season’s central conflict, which revolves around Bill Dobson, a handsome middle-aged white male professor who’s revered as the department’s greatest genius on the basis of his earlier work, but who, after the death of his wife, is now washed-up, flippant, and frequently drunk or high.  In one class session, while lecturing about intellectuals who found the strength to resist fascism despite their own nihilistic impulses, Bill makes a Nazi salute and shouts “Heil Hitler!,” as a theatrical reminder to the students about the enormity of what those intellectuals were fighting.  Alas, a woke student captures that moment on their smartphone camera and shares it on social media.  The clip of Bill making the Heil salute goes viral, shorn of all exculpatory context.  Soon, crowds of students are waving placards and screaming “No Nazis at Pembroke!” outside the English building.  In a desperate effort to make his PR crisis go away, the dean initiates termination proceedings against Bill—the principles of academic freedom and even Bill’s tenure be damned.  Ji-Yoon, of course, as Bill’s chair, is caught smack in the middle of this.  It’s complicated even further by Ji-Yoon’s and Bill’s romantic feelings for each other, and further still by Bill’s role as the babysitter of Ji-Yoon’s adopted daughter.</p>



<p>As all of this unfolds, the show seems immensely interested in pinning the blame on Bill’s “tragic flaws,” minor though they seemed to me—mostly just pride and unseriousness.  (E.g., trying to lampoon the absurd charge of Nazism, Bill offhandedly mentions that he’s always wanted to visit Hitler’s mountain retreat, and on another occasion belts out “Springtime for Hitler” from <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Producers_(1967_film)">The Producers</a></em>.)  The woke students, by contrast, are portrayed as earnest, understandably upset, and legitimately terrified about hate crimes on campus.  If they, too, have opportunistic motives to attack Bill, the show never examines them.</p>



<p>In one sentence, then, here’s my beef with <em>The Chair</em>: its script portrays a mob, step by step, destroying an innocent man’s life over nothing, and yet it wants me to feel the mob’s pain, and be disappointed in its victim for mulishly insisting on his innocence (even though he <em>is</em>, in fact, innocent).</p>



<p>With real-life woke controversies, there often lingers the question of whether the accused <em>might really be</em> a racist, fascist, sexual predator, or whatever else, adequate proof or no.  What’s different here is that we <em>know</em> that Bill Dobson is none of those things, we <em>know</em> he’s decent to his core, because the writers have painstakingly shown us that.  And yet, in a weird narrative pretzel, we’re nevertheless supposed to be mad at him, and to sympathize with the campaign to cancel him.</p>



<p>A casual perusal of other reviews of <em>The Chair</em> told me that these reactions were far from universal.  <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=the+chair+reviews&amp;oq=the+chair+reviews&amp;aqs=chrome.0.0i67i131i433j0i131i433i512l2j0i512l7.2011j0j4&amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;ie=UTF-8">Here</a>, for example, is what one viewer wrote:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>I can appreciate that this is probably close to the reality that most women/of color experience in higher education. I enjoyed watching the scenes with Joan and Yaz [two female professors] the most but the rest was a drag. I couldn’t understand why Ji-Yoon was into Bill, or why <em>anyone</em> was into Bill. I found him to be an insufferable man-baby. That is such a turn off. So she’d put him straight but then still be pining for him. He wreaked [sic] of entitled, white male, tenured privilege and never showed any contrition for his actions or even awareness of their impact. i’m so tired of the “brilliant <strong>_</strong>” being used to justify coddling someone. And for the rest of the stuffy old patriarchal farts– boot them out! They weren’t good teachers and weren’t able to meet the needs of today’s students.</p></blockquote>



<p>I asked myself: <em>did this person watch the same show?</em>  It’s like, the script couldn’t possibly have been clearer about Bill’s character, the fact that he’s the polar opposite of the woke students’ mental construct.   And yet, if the show had drawn an unambiguous corollary from Bill’s goodness—namely, that the effort to cancel him is a moral travesty—then <em>The Chair</em> itself might have been denounced as conservative (or at least classical liberal) propaganda, and those who’d otherwise form its core viewership wouldn’t have watched.</p>



<p>So, if I were a literary critic like the ones on the show, I might argue that <em>The Chair</em> begs for a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persecution_and_the_Art_of_Writing">Straussian</a> interpretation.  Sure, there’s an “overt” reading, wherein Bill Dobson is done in by his own hubris, or wherein it’s a comedy of errors with no one to blame.  But then there’s also an “esoteric” reading, wherein Bill is the victim of an extremely specific modern-day collective insanity, one that future generations might look back on with little more ambivalence than we look back on McCarthyism.  The writers of <em>The Chair</em> might <em>hint</em> at this latter reading, through their sympathetic portrayal of Bill and the obviousness of the injustice done to him, but they can never make it too explicit, because of the political and cultural constraints under which they themselves operate.</p>



<p>Under this theory, it presumably falls to those slightly outside the world portrayed in <em>The Chair</em>—like, let’s imagine, a theoretical computer science blogger who himself was denounced for woke heresies to the point where he has little more to lose in that direction—to make the esoteric reading explicit.  Unless and until, of course, a second season comes along to undermine that reading entirely.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-31T07:45:45Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-31T07:45:45Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Obviously I'm Not Defending Aaronson"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T14:32:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13113</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13113" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>BDD-Based Algorithm for SCC Decomposition of Edge-Coloured Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Nikola Beneš, Luboš Brim, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pastva:Samuel.html">Samuel Pastva</a>, David Šafránek <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.13113">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Edge-coloured directed graphs provide an essential structure for modelling
and computing complex problems arising in many scientific disciplines. The size
of edge-coloured graphs appearing in practice can be enormous in the number of
both vertices and colours. An important fundamental problem that needs to be
solved over edge-coloured graphs is detecting strongly connected components.
The problem becomes challenging for large graphs with a large number of
colours.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we describe a novel symbolic algorithm that computes all the
monochromatic strongly connected components of an edge-coloured graph. In the
worst case, the algorithm performs $O(p \cdot n \cdot \log n)$ symbolic steps,
where $p$ is the number of colours and $n$ is the number of vertices. We
evaluate the algorithm using an experimental implementation based on Binary
Decision Diagrams (BDDs) and large (up to $2^{48}$) coloured graphs produced by
models appearing in systems biology.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:52:58Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13110</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13110" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A New Rational Approach to the Square Root of 5</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Su:Shenghui.html">Shenghui Su</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zheng:Jianhua.html">Jianhua Zheng</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lv:Shuwang.html">Shuwang Lv</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.13110">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, authors construct a new type of sequence which is named an
extra-super increasing sequence, and give the definitions of the minimal super
increasing sequence {a[0], ..., a[l]} and minimal extra-super increasing
sequence {z[0], ...,[z]l}. Discover that there always exists a fit n which
makes (z[n] / z[n-1] - a[n] / a[n-1])= PHI, where PHI is the golden ratio
conjugate with a finite precision able to be expressed by computers. Further,
derive the formula radic(5) = 2(z[n] / z[n-1] - a[n] / a[n-1]) + 1, where n
corresponds to the demanded precision. Experiments demonstrate that the
approach to radic(5) through a ratio difference is more smooth and expeditious
than through a Taylor power series, and convince the authors that lim{n to
infinity} (z[n] / z[n-1] - a[n] / a[n-1]) = PHI holds.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:48:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13094</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13094" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An outer totalistic weakly universal cellular automaton in the dodecagrid with four states</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Margenstern:Maurice.html">Maurice Margenstern</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.13094">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we prove that there is an outer totalistic weakly universal
cellular automaton in the dodecagrid, the tessellation {5,3,4} of the
hyperbolic 3D space, with four states. It is the first result in such a
context.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T23:08:20Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13086</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13086" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A New Lever Function with Adequate Indeterminacy</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Su:Shenghui.html">Shenghui Su</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Luo:Ping.html">Ping Luo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lv:Shuwang.html">Shuwang Lv</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xu:Maozhi.html">Maozhi Xu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.13086">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The key transform of the REESSE1+ asymmetrical cryptosystem is Ci = (Ai * W ^
l(i)) ^ d (% M) with l(i) in Omega = {5, 7, ..., 2n + 3} for i = 1, ..., n,
where l(i) is called a lever function. In this paper, the authors give a
simplified key transform Ci = Ai * W ^ l(i) (% M) with a new lever function
l(i) from {1, ..., n} to Omega = {+/-5, +/-6, ..., +/-(n + 4)}, where "+/-"
means the selection of the "+" or "-" sign. Discuss the necessity of the new
l(i), namely that a simplified private key is insecure if the new l(i) is a
constant but not one-to-one function. Further, expound the sufficiency of the
new l(i) from four aspects: (1) indeterminacy of the new l(i), (2) insufficient
conditions for neutralizing the powers of W and W ^-1 even if Omega = {5, 6,
..., n + 4}, (3) verification by examples, and (4) running times of the
continued fraction attack and W-parameter intersection attack which are the two
most efficient of the probabilistic polytime attack algorithms so far. Last,
the authors elaborate the relation between a lever function and a random
oracle.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:50:57Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13076</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13076" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Extending Partial Representations of Circular-Arc Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Jiří Fiala, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rutter:Ignaz.html">Ignaz Rutter</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Stumpf:Peter.html">Peter Stumpf</a>, Peter Zeman <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.13076">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The partial representation extension problem generalizes the recognition
problem for classes of graphs defined in terms of vertex representations. We
exhibit circular-arc graphs as the first example of a graph class where the
recognition is polynomially solvable while the representation extension problem
is NP-complete. In this setting, several arcs are predrawn and we ask whether
this partial representation can be completed.
</p>
<p>We complement this hardness argument with tractability results of the
representation extension problem on various subclasses of circular-arc graphs,
most notably on all variants of Helly circular-arc graphs. In particular, we
give linear-time algorithms for extending normal proper Helly and proper Helly
representations. For normal Helly circular-arc representations we give an
$O(n^3)$-time algorithm.
</p>
<p>Surprisingly, for Helly representations, the complexity hinges on the
seemingly irrelevant detail of whether the predrawn arcs have distinct or
non-distinct endpoints: In the former case the previous algorithm can be
extended, whereas the latter case turns out to be NP-complete. We also prove
that representation extension problem of unit circular-arc graphs is
NP-complete.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:53:40Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13061</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13061" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A New Test for Hamming-Weight Dependencies</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Blackman:David.html">David Blackman</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vigna:Sebastiano.html">Sebastiano Vigna</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.13061">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We describe a new statistical test for pseudorandom number generators
(PRNGs). Our test can find bias induced by dependencies among the Hamming
weights of the outputs of a PRNG, even for PRNGs that pass state-of-the-art
tests of the same kind from the literature, and in particular for generators
based on F_2-linear transformations such as the dSFMT, xoroshiro128+, and
WELL512.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T23:04:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13060</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13060" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Further Improvement on Approximating TTP-2</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhao:Jingyang.html">Jingyang Zhao</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xiao:Mingyu.html">Mingyu Xiao</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.13060">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Traveling Tournament Problem (TTP) is a hard but interesting sports
scheduling problem inspired by Major League Baseball, which is to design a
double round-robin schedule such that each pair of teams plays one game in each
other's home venue, minimizing the total distance traveled by all $n$ teams
($n$ is even). In this paper, we consider TTP-2, i.e., TTP with one more
constraint that each team can have at most two consecutive home games or away
games. Due to the different structural properties, known algorithms for TTP-2
are different for $n/2$ being odd and even. For odd $n/2$, the best known
approximation ratio is about $(1+12/n)$, and for even $n/2$, the best known
approximation ratio is about $(1+4/n)$. In this paper, we further improve the
approximation ratio from $(1+4/n)$ to $(1+3/n)$ for $n/2$ being even.
Experimental results on benchmark sets show that our algorithm can improve
previous results on all instances with even $n/2$ by $1\%$ to $4\%$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T23:03:47Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12976</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12976" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximating Pandora's Box with Correlations</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Shuchi Chawla, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gergatsouli:Evangelia.html">Evangelia Gergatsouli</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/McMahan:Jeremy.html">Jeremy McMahan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tzamos:Christos.html">Christos Tzamos</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12976">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Pandora's Box problem asks to find a search strategy over $n$
alternatives given stochastic information about their values, aiming to
minimize the sum of the search cost and the value of the chosen alternative.
Even though the case of independently distributed values is well understood,
our algorithmic understanding of the problem is very limited once the
independence assumption is dropped.
</p>
<p>Our work aims to characterize the complexity of approximating the Pandora's
Box problem under correlated value distributions. To that end, we present a
general reduction to a simpler version of Pandora's Box, that only asks to find
a value below a certain threshold, and eliminates the need to reason about
future values that will arise during the search. Using this general tool, we
study two cases of correlation; the case of explicitly given distributions of
support $m$ and the case of mixtures of $m$ product distributions.
</p>
<p>$\bullet$ In the first case, we connect Pandora's Box to the well studied
problem of Optimal Decision Tree, obtaining an $O(\log m)$ approximation but
also showing that the problem is strictly easier as it is equivalent (up to
constant factors) to the Uniform Decision Tree problem.
</p>
<p>$\bullet$ In the case of mixtures of product distributions, the problem is
again related to the noisy variant of Optimal Decision Tree which is
significantly more challenging. We give a constant-factor approximation that
runs in time $n^{ \tilde O( m^2/\varepsilon^2 ) }$ for $m$ mixture components
whose marginals on every alternative are either identical or separated in TV
distance by $\varepsilon$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T23:05:21Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12893</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12893" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tight Guarantees for Static Threshold Policies in the Prophet Secretary Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Arnosti:Nick.html">Nick Arnosti</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Ma:Will.html">Will Ma</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12893">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the prophet secretary problem, $n$ values are drawn independently from
known distributions, and presented in random order. A decision-maker must
accept or reject each value when it is presented, and may accept at most $k$
values in total. The objective is to maximize the expected sum of accepted
values.
</p>
<p>We study the performance of static threshold policies, which accept the first
$k$ values exceeding a fixed threshold (or all such values, if fewer than $k$
exist). We show that using an optimal threshold guarantees a $\gamma_k = 1 -
e^{-k}k^k/k!$ fraction of the offline optimal solution, and provide an example
demonstrating that this guarantee is tight. We also provide simple algorithms
that achieve this guarantee. The first sets a threshold such that the expected
number of values exceeding the threshold is equal to $k$, and offers a
guarantee of $\gamma_k$ if $k \geq 5$. The second sets a threshold so that $k
\cdot \gamma_k$ values are accepted in expectation, and offers a guarantee of
$\gamma_k$ for all $k$. To establish these guarantees, we prove a result about
sums of independent Bernoulli random variables, which extends a classical
result of Hoeffding (1956) and is of general interest.
</p>
<p>Finally, we note that our algorithms can be implemented in settings with
restricted information about agents' values. This makes them practical in
settings such as the allocation of COVID-19 vaccines.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T23:02:26Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12879</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12879" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Parameterizing the Permanent: Hardness for $K_8$-minor-free graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Curticapean:Radu.html">Radu Curticapean</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xia:Mingji.html">Mingji Xia</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12879">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the 1960s, statistical physicists discovered a fascinating algorithm for
counting perfect matchings in planar graphs. Valiant later showed that the same
problem is #P-hard for general graphs. Since then, the algorithm for planar
graphs was extended to bounded-genus graphs, to graphs excluding $K_{3,3}$ or
$K_{5}$, and more generally, to any graph class excluding a fixed minor $H$
that can be drawn in the plane with a single crossing. This stirred up hopes
that counting perfect matchings might be polynomial-time solvable for graph
classes excluding any fixed minor $H$. Alas, in this paper, we show #P-hardness
for $K_{8}$-minor-free graphs by a simple and self-contained argument.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12840</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12840" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Exact algorithms for maximum weighted independent set on sparse graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Huang:Sen.html">Sen Huang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xiao:Mingyu.html">Mingyu Xiao</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Xiaoyu.html">Xiaoyu Chen</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12840">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The maximum independent set problem is one of the most important problems in
graph algorithms and has been extensively studied in the line of research on
the worst-case analysis of exact algorithms for NP-hard problems. In the
weighted version, each vertex in the graph is associated with a weight and we
are going to find an independent set of maximum total vertex weight. In this
paper, we design several reduction rules and a fast exact algorithm for the
maximum weighted independent set problem, and use the measure-and-conquer
technique to analyze the running time bound of the algorithm. Our algorithm
works on general weighted graphs and it has a good running time bound on sparse
graphs. If the graph has an average degree at most 3, our algorithm runs in
$O^*(1.1443^n)$ time and polynomial space, improving previous running time
bounds for the problem in cubic graphs using polynomial space.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:55:18Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12812</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12812" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linking disjoint segments into a simple polygon is hard</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jiang:Rain.html">Rain Jiang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jiang:Kai.html">Kai Jiang</a>, Minghui Jiang <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12812">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Deciding whether a family of disjoint line segments in the plane can be
linked into a simple polygon (or a simple polygonal chain) by adding segments
between their endpoints is NP-hard.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12779</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12779" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Parameterizations of Logarithmic-Space Reductions, Stack-State Complexity of Nonuniform Families of Pushdown Automata, and a Road to the LOGCFL$\subseteq$LOGDCFL/poly Question</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yamakami:Tomoyuki.html">Tomoyuki Yamakami</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12779">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The complexity class LOGCFL (resp., LOGDCFL) consists of all languages that
are many-one reducible to context-free (resp., deterministic context-free)
languages using logarithmic space. These complexity classes have been studied
over five decades in connection to parallel computation since they are located
between Nick's classes $\mathrm{NC}^1$ and $\mathrm{NC}^2$. In contrast, the
state complexity of nonuniform finite-automaton families was first discussed in
the 1970s and it has been extensively explored lately for various
finite-automata families. We extend this old subject to the stack-state
complexity (i.e., the total number of inner states plus simultaneously pushable
stack symbol series) of nonuniform families of various pushdown automata. We
introduce reasonable "parameterizations" of LOGCFL and LOGDCFL and apply them
as a technical tool to establish a close connection between the
LOGCFL$\subseteq$LOGDCFL/poly question and the polynomial stack-state
complexity of nonuniform families of two-way pushdown automata. We also discuss
the precise computational complexity of polynomial-size one-way pushdown
automata.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:40:13Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12751</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12751" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Second-Order Finite Automata</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Melo:Alexsander_Andrade_de.html">Alexsander Andrade de Melo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Oliveira:Mateus_de_Oliveira.html">Mateus de Oliveira Oliveira</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12751">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Traditionally, finite automata theory has been used as a framework for the
representation of possibly infinite sets of strings. In this work, we introduce
the notion of second-order finite automata, a formalism that combines finite
automata with ordered decision diagrams, with the aim of representing possibly
infinite {\em sets of sets} of strings. Our main result states that
second-order finite automata can be canonized with respect to the second-order
languages they represent. Using this canonization result, we show that sets of
sets of strings represented by second-order finite automata are closed under
the usual Boolean operations, such as union, intersection, difference and even
under a suitable notion of complementation. Additionally, emptiness of
intersection and inclusion are decidable.
</p>
<p>We provide two algorithmic applications for second-order automata. First, we
show that several width/size minimization problems for deterministic and
nondeterministic ODDs are solvable in fixed-parameter tractable time when
parameterized by the width of the input ODD. In particular, our results imply
FPT algorithms for corresponding width/size minimization problems for ordered
binary decision diagrams (OBDDs) with a fixed variable ordering. Previously,
only algorithms that take exponential time in the size of the input OBDD were
known for width minimization, even for OBDDs of constant width. Second, we show
that for each $k$ and $w$ one can count the number of distinct functions
computable by ODDs of width at most $w$ and length $k$ in time
$h(|\Sigma|,w)\cdot k^{O(1)}$, for a suitable $h:\mathbb{N}\times
\mathbb{N}\rightarrow \mathbb{N}$. This improves exponentially on the time
necessary to explicitly enumerate all such functions, which is exponential in
both the width parameter $w$ and in the length $k$ of the ODDs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:39:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12687</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12687" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Visible Rank and Codes with Locality</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Alrabiah:Omar.html">Omar Alrabiah</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Guruswami:Venkatesan.html">Venkatesan Guruswami</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12687">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We propose a framework to study the effect of local recovery requirements of
codeword symbols on the dimension of linear codes, based on a combinatorial
proxy that we call \emph{visible rank}. The locality constraints of a linear
code are stipulated by a matrix $H$ of $\star$'s and $0$'s (which we call a
"stencil"), whose rows correspond to the local parity checks (with the
$\star$'s indicating the support of the check). The visible rank of $H$ is the
largest $r$ for which there is a $r \times r$ submatrix in $H$ with a unique
generalized diagonal of $\star$'s. The visible rank yields a field-independent
combinatorial lower bound on the rank of $H$ and thus the co-dimension of the
code.
</p>
<p>We prove a rank-nullity type theorem relating visible rank to the rank of an
associated construct called \emph{symmetric spanoid}, which was introduced by
Dvir, Gopi, Gu, and Wigderson~\cite{DGGW20}. Using this connection and a
construction of appropriate stencils, we answer a question posed in
\cite{DGGW20} and demonstrate that symmetric spanoid rank cannot improve the
currently best known $\widetilde{O}(n^{(q-2)/(q-1)})$ upper bound on the
dimension of $q$-query locally correctable codes (LCCs) of length $n$.
</p>
<p>We also study the $t$-Disjoint Repair Group Property ($t$-DRGP) of codes
where each codeword symbol must belong to $t$ disjoint check equations. It is
known that linear $2$-DRGP codes must have co-dimension $\Omega(\sqrt{n})$. We
show that there are stencils corresponding to $2$-DRGP with visible rank as
small as $O(\log n)$. However, we show the second tensor of any $2$-DRGP
stencil has visible rank $\Omega(n)$, thus recovering the $\Omega(\sqrt{n})$
lower bound for $2$-DRGP. For $q$-LCC, however, the $k$'th tensor power for
$k\le n^{o(1)}$ is unable to improve the $\widetilde{O}(n^{(q-2)/(q-1)})$ upper
bound on the dimension of $q$-LCCs by a polynomial factor.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:40:47Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12658</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12658" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Clusters in Markov Chains via Singular Vectors of Laplacian Matrices</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cole:Sam.html">Sam Cole</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kirkland:Steve.html">Steve Kirkland</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12658">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Suppose that $T$ is a stochastic matrix. We propose an algorithm for
identifying clusters in the Markov chain associated with $T$. The algorithm is
recursive in nature, and in order to identify clusters, it uses the sign
pattern of a left singular vector associated with the second smallest singular
value of the Laplacian matrix $I-T.$ We prove a number of results that justify
the algorithm's approach, and illustrate the algorithm's performance with
several numerical examples.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:52:27Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12628</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12628" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Planar Straight-line Realizations of 2-Trees with Prescribed Edge Lengths</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Alegr=iacute=a:Carlos.html">Carlos Alegría</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Borrazzo:Manuel.html">Manuel Borrazzo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lozzo:Giordano_Da.html">Giordano Da Lozzo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Battista:Giuseppe_Di.html">Giuseppe Di Battista</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Frati:Fabrizio.html">Fabrizio Frati</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Patrignani:Maurizio.html">Maurizio Patrignani</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12628">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study a classic problem introduced thirty years ago by Eades and Wormald.
Let $G=(V,E,\lambda)$ be a weighted planar graph, where $\lambda: E \rightarrow
\mathbb{R}^+$ is a length function. The Fixed Edge-Length Planar Realization
problem (FEPR for short) asks whether there exists a planar straight-line
realization of $G$, i.e., a planar straight-line drawing of $G$ where the
Euclidean length of each edge $e \in E$ is $\lambda(e)$.
</p>
<p>Cabello, Demaine, and Rote showed that the FEPR problem is NP-hard, even when
$\lambda$ assigns the same value to all the edges and the graph is
triconnected. Since the existence of large triconnected minors is crucial to
the known NP-hardness proofs, in this paper we investigate the computational
complexity of the FEPR problem for weighted $2$-trees, which are $K_4$-minor
free. We show its NP-hardness, even when $\lambda$ assigns to the edges only up
to four distinct lengths. Conversely, we show that the FEPR problem is
linear-time solvable when $\lambda$ assigns to the edges up to two distinct
lengths, or when the input has a prescribed embedding. Furthermore, we consider
the FEPR problem for weighted maximal outerplanar graphs and prove it to be
linear-time solvable if their dual tree is a path, and cubic-time solvable if
their dual tree is a caterpillar. Finally, we prove that the FEPR problem for
weighted $2$-trees is slice-wise polynomial in the length of the longest path.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:56:44Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12500</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12500" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Positive Planar Satisfiability Problems under 3-Connectivity Constraints</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hasan:Md=_Manzurul.html">Md. Manzurul Hasan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mondal:Debajyoti.html">Debajyoti Mondal</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rahman:Md=_Saidur.html">Md. Saidur Rahman</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12500">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A 3-SAT problem is called positive and planar if all the literals are
positive and the clause-variable incidence graph (i.e., SAT graph) is planar.
The NAE 3-SAT and 1-in-3-SAT are two variants of 3-SAT that remain NP-complete
even when they are positive. The positive 1-in-3-SAT problem remains
NP-complete under planarity constraint, but planar NAE 3-SAT is solvable in
$O(n^{1.5}\log n)$ time. In this paper we prove that a positive planar NAE
3-SAT is always satisfiable when the underlying SAT graph is 3-connected, and a
satisfiable assignment can be obtained in linear time. We also show that
without 3-connectivity constraint, existence of a linear-time algorithm for
positive planar NAE 3-SAT problem is unlikely as it would imply a linear-time
algorithm for finding a spanning 2-matching in a planar subcubic graph. We then
prove that positive planar 1-in-3-SAT remains NP-complete under the
3-connectivity constraint, even when each variable appears in at most 4
clauses. However, we show that the 3-connected planar 1-in-3-SAT is always
satisfiable when each variable appears in an even number of clauses.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12486</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12486" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Renting Servers in the Cloud: The Case of Equal Duration Jobs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Masoori:Mahtab.html">Mahtab Masoori</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Narayanan:Lata.html">Lata Narayanan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pankratov:Denis.html">Denis Pankratov</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12486">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Renting servers in the cloud is a generalization of the bin packing problem,
motivated by job allocation to servers in cloud computing applications. Jobs
arrive in an online manner, and need to be assigned to servers; their duration
and size are known at the time of arrival. There is an infinite supply of
identical servers, each having one unit of computational capacity per unit of
time. A server can be rented at any time and continues to be rented until all
jobs assigned to it finish. The cost of an assignment is the sum of durations
of rental periods of all servers. The goal is to assign jobs to servers to
minimize the overall cost while satisfying server capacity constraints. We
focus on analyzing two natural algorithms, NextFit and FirstFit, for the case
of jobs of equal duration. It is known that the competitive ratio of NextFit
and FirstFit are at most 3 and 4 respectively for this case. We prove a tight
bound of 2 on the competitive ratio of NextFit. For FirstFit, we establish a
lower bound of 2.519 on the competitive ratio, even when jobs have only two
distinct arrival times. For the case when jobs have arrival times 0 and 1 and
duration 2, we show a lower bound of 1.89 and an upper bound of 2 on the strict
competitive ratio of FirstFit. Finally, using the weight function technique, we
obtain stronger results for the case of uniform servers.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T23:02:42Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12477</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12477" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An explicit vector algorithm for high-girth MaxCut</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Jessica K. Thompson, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Parekh:Ojas.html">Ojas Parekh</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Marwaha:Kunal.html">Kunal Marwaha</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12477">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We give an approximation algorithm for MaxCut and provide guarantees on the
average fraction of edges cut on $d$-regular graphs of girth $\geq 2k$. For
every $d \geq 3$ and $k \geq 4$, our approximation guarantees are better than
those of all other classical and quantum algorithms known to the authors. Our
algorithm constructs an explicit vector solution to the standard semidefinite
relaxation of MaxCut and applies hyperplane rounding. It may be viewed as a
simplification of the previously best known technique, which approximates
Gaussian wave processes on the infinite $d$-regular tree.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T22:53:15Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12464</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2108.12464" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Bottleneck Convex Subsets: Finding $k$ Large Convex Sets in a Point Set</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1630368000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Durocher:Stephane.html">Stephane Durocher</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Keil:J=_Mark.html">J. Mark Keil</a>, Saeed Mehrabi, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mondal:Debajyoti.html">Debajyoti Mondal</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2108.12464">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Chv\'{a}tal and Klincsek (1980) gave an $O(n^3)$-time algorithm for the
problem of finding a maximum-cardinality convex subset of an arbitrary given
set $P$ of $n$ points in the plane. This paper examines a generalization of the
problem, the Bottleneck Convex Subsets problem: given a set $P$ of $n$ points
in the plane and a positive integer $k$, select $k$ pairwise disjoint convex
subsets of $P$ such that the cardinality of the smallest subset is maximized.
Equivalently, a solution maximizes the cardinality of $k$ mutually disjoint
convex subsets of $P$ of equal cardinality. We show the problem is NP-hard when
$k$ is an arbitrary input parameter, we give an algorithm that solves the
problem exactly, with running time polynomial in $n$ when $k$ is fixed, and we
give a fixed-parameter tractable algorithm parameterized in terms of the number
of points strictly interior to the convex hull.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/127</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/127" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-127 |  Small Circuits Imply Efficient Arthur-Merlin Protocols | 

	Michael Ezra, 

	Ron D. Rothblum</title>
    <summary>The inner product function $\langle x,y \rangle = \sum_i x_i y_i \bmod 2$ can be easily computed by a (linear-size) ${AC}^0(\oplus)$ circuit: that is, a constant depth circuit with AND, OR and parity (XOR) gates. But what if we impose the restriction that the parity gates can only be on the bottom most layer (closest to the input)? Namely, can the inner product function be computed by an ${AC}^0$ circuit composed with a single layer of parity gates? This seemingly simple question is an important open question at the frontier of circuit lower bound research.
    
    In this work, we focus on a minimalistic version of the above question. Namely, whether the inner product function cannot be \emph{approximated} by a small $DNF$ augmented with a single layer of parity gates. Our main result shows that the existence of such a circuit would have unexpected implications for interactive proofs, or more specifically, for interactive variants of the Data Streaming and Communication Complexity models. In particular, we show that the existence of such a small (i.e., polynomial-size) circuit yields:
    
    \begin{enumerate}
        \item An $O(d)$-message protocol in the Arthur-Merlin Data Streaming model for every $n$-variate, degree $d$ polynomial (over $\mathbb{GF}(2)$), using only $\widetilde{O}\left(d\right)\cdot\log(n)$ communication and space complexity. In particular, this gives an AM$[2]$ Data Streaming protocol for a variant of the well-studied triangle counting problem, with poly-logarithmic communication and space complexities.
       
        \item A $2$-message communication complexity protocol for any sparse (or low degree) polynomial, and for any function computable by an ${AC}^0(\oplus)$ circuit. Specifically, for the latter, we obtain a protocol with communication complexity that is poly-logarithmic in the size of the ${AC}^0(\oplus)$ circuit.
    \end{enumerate}</summary>
    <updated>2021-08-30T21:34:58Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-30T21:34:58Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/08/30/multiple-faculty-positions-in-computer-science-and-engineering-at-ohio-state-university-apply-by-september-15-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/08/30/multiple-faculty-positions-in-computer-science-and-engineering-at-ohio-state-university-apply-by-september-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Multiple Faculty Positions in Computer Science and Engineering at Ohio State University (apply by September 15, 2021)</title>
    <summary>We seek 20 faculty appointments at all seniority levels and in all research areas, with emphasis on theory and algorithms, quantum computing, AI/ML, human-centric computing, robotics, HPC/systems, networking/communications, graphics/visualization, cybersecurity/privacy, CSE + health/life sciences, computing for social good, data science/analytics, computational science, computing education Website: https://cse.osu.edu/faculty-recruiting Email: rountev.1@osu.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We seek 20 faculty appointments at all seniority levels and in all research areas, with emphasis on theory and algorithms, quantum computing, AI/ML, human-centric computing, robotics, HPC/systems, networking/communications, graphics/visualization, cybersecurity/privacy, CSE + health/life sciences, computing for social good, data science/analytics, computational science, computing education</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://cse.osu.edu/faculty-recruiting">https://cse.osu.edu/faculty-recruiting</a><br/>
Email: rountev.1@osu.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-30T18:41:37Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-30T18:41:37Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2021-08-29-the-private-set-intersection-psi-protocol-of-the-apple-csam-detection-system/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2021-08-29-the-private-set-intersection-psi-protocol-of-the-apple-csam-detection-system/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Private Set Intersection (PSI) Protocol of the Apple CSAM Detection System</title>
    <summary>In this post, we will discuss the cryptographic construction used in Apple’s new system for detecting CSAM - Child Sexual Abuse Material. This cryptographic construction implements a new variant of PSI - Private Set Intersection. While a lot of attention has been paid to the broad implications of this system,...</summary>
    <updated>2021-08-29T21:55:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-29T21:55:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T01:39:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/126</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/126" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-126 |  Quantum Algorithms for Variants of Average-Case Lattice Problems via Filtering | 

	Qipeng Liu, 

	Yilei Chen, 

	Mark Zhandry</title>
    <summary>We show polynomial-time quantum algorithms for the following problems: 
(*) Short integer solution (SIS) problem under the infinity norm, where the public matrix is very wide, the modulus is a polynomially large prime, and the bound of infinity norm is set to be half of the modulus minus a constant. 
(*) Extrapolated dihedral coset problem (EDCP) with certain parameters. 
(*) Learning with errors (LWE) problem given LWE-like quantum states with polynomially large moduli and certain error distributions, including bounded uniform distributions and Laplace distributions.

The SIS, EDCP, and LWE problems in their standard forms are as hard as solving lattice problems in the worst case. However, the variants that we can solve are not in the parameter regimes known to be as hard as solving worst-case lattice problems. Still, no classical or quantum polynomial-time algorithms were known for those variants.

Our algorithms for variants of SIS and EDCP use the existing quantum reductions from those problems to LWE, or more precisely, to the problem of solving LWE given LWE-like quantum states. Our main contributions are introducing a filtering technique and solving LWE given LWE-like quantum states with interesting parameters.</summary>
    <updated>2021-08-29T07:01:12Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-29T07:01:12Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/125</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/125" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-125 |  The Exact Complexity of Pseudorandom Functions and Tight Barriers to Lower Bound Proofs | 

	Zhiyuan Fan, 

	Jiatu Li, 

	Tianqi Yang</title>
    <summary>How much computational resource do we need for cryptography? This is an important question of both theoretical and practical interests. In this paper, we study the problem on pseudorandom functions (PRFs) in the context of circuit complexity. Perhaps surprisingly, we prove extremely tight upper and lower bounds in various circuit models.

* In general $B_2$ circuits, assuming the existence of PRFs, PRFs can be constructed in $2n + o(n)$ size, simplifying and improving the $O(n)$ bound by Ishai et al. (STOC 2008). We show that such construction is almost optimal by giving an unconditional $2n-O(1)$ lower bound.

* In logarithmic depth circuits, assuming the existence of $NC^1$ PRFs, PRFs can be constructed in $2n + o(n)$ size and $(1+\epsilon) \log n$ depth simultaneously.

* In constant depth linear threshold circuits, assuming the existence of $TC^0$ PRFs, PRFs can be constructed with wire complexity $n^{1+O(1.61^{-d})}$. We also give an $n^{1+\Omega(c^{-d})}$ wire complexity lower bound for some constant $c$.

The upper bounds are proved with generalized Levin's trick and novel constructions of "almost" universal hash functions; the lower bound for general circuits is proved via a tricky but elementary wire-counting argument; and the lower bound for $TC^0$ circuits is proved by extracting a "black-box" property of $TC^0$ circuits from the "white-box" restriction lemma of Chen, Santhanam, and Srinivasan (Theory Comput. 2018). As a byproduct, we prove unconditional tight upper and lower bounds for "almost" universal hashing, which we believe to have independent interests.

Following Natural Proofs by Razborov and Rudich (J. Comput. Syst. Sci. 1997), our results make progress in realizing the difficulty to improve known circuit lower bounds which recently becomes significant due to the discovery of several "bootstrapping results". In $TC^0$, this reveals the limitation of the current restriction-based methods; in particular, it brings new insights in understanding the strange phenomenon of "sharp threshold results" such as the one presented by Chen and Tell (STOC 2019).</summary>
    <updated>2021-08-29T03:10:52Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-29T03:10:52Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/124</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/124" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-124 |  On the Complexity of Two-Party Differential Privacy | 

	Noam Mazor, 

	Iftach Haitner, 

	Jad Silbak, 

	Eliad Tsfadia</title>
    <summary>In distributed differential privacy, the parties perform analysis over their joint data while preserving the privacy for both datasets. Interestingly, for a few fundamental two-party functions such as inner product and Hamming distance, the accuracy of the distributed solution lags way behind what is achievable in the client-server setting. McGregor, Mironov, Pitassi, Reingold, Talwar, and Vadhan [FOCS ’10] proved that this gap is inherent, showing upper bounds on the accuracy of (any) distributed solution for these functions. These limitations can be bypassed when settling for computational differential privacy, where the data is differentially private only in the eyes of a computationally bounded observer, using public-key cryptography primitives.

We prove that the use of public-key cryptography is necessary for bypassing the limitation of McGregor et al., showing that a non-trivial solution for the inner-product, or the Hamming distance, implies the existence of a key-agreement protocol. Our bound implies a combinatorial proof for the fact that non-Boolean inner product of independent (strong) Santha-Vazirani sources is a good condenser. We obtain our main result by showing that the inner-product of a (single, strong) SV source with a uniformly random seed is a good condenser, even when the seed and source are dependent.</summary>
    <updated>2021-08-29T01:09:35Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-29T01:09:35Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-7677986234153291067</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/7677986234153291067/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=7677986234153291067" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/7677986234153291067" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/7677986234153291067" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2021/08/nterview-with-concur-2021-tot-award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Interview with CONCUR 2021 ToT Award Recipients: David Janin and Igor Walukiewicz</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This is the fourth and last instalment of the series of interviews with the 2021 CONCUR Test-of-Time Award recipients, which I have conducted with Nathalie Bertrand and Nobuko Yoshida's great help. (See <a href="https://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2021/06/interview-with-concur-2021-tot-award.html" target="_blank">here</a>, <a href="https://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2021/08/interview-with-concur-2021-tot-award.html" target="_blank">here</a> and <a href="https://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2021/08/interview-with-concur-2021-tot-award_23.html" target="_blank">there</a> for the previous ones.) In it, I interviewed <a href="https://www.labri.fr/perso/janin/" target="_blank">David Jani</a>n and <a href="https://www.labri.fr/perso/igw/" target="_blank">Igor Walukiewicz</a>. </p><p>I thank David and Igor for their very stimulating answers to my questions and for painting such a rich picture of the context for their award-winning work and of the subsequent developments related to it. Enjoy!<b/></p><p>Note: The interview has been slightly edited for clarity and to correct some small typos. Thanks to <a href="http://www-sop.inria.fr/members/Ilaria.Castellani/" target="_blank">Ilaria Castellani</a> for pointing out several typos that had escaped my attention. <b><br/></b></p><p><b>Luca:</b> You receive the CONCUR ToT Award 2021 for your paper <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/3-540-61604-7_60" target="_blank">On the Expressive Completeness of the Propositional mu-Calculus with respect to Monadic Second Order Logic</a>, which appeared at CONCUR 1996. In that article, you showed what I consider to be a fundamental result, namely that the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modal_%CE%BC-calculus" target="_blank">mu-calculus</a> and the bisimulation-invariant fragment of  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monadic_second-order_logic" target="_blank">monadic second-order logic (MSOL)</a>  have the same expressiveness over transition systems. Could you tell us how you came to study that question and why do you think that such a natural problem hadn't been answered before your paper? </p><p><b>David and Igor:</b>At that time we were interested in automata characterizations of the expressive power of MSOL and the mu-calculus. In 1988 <a href="https://www.mimuw.edu.pl/~niwinski/" target="_blank">Damian Niwinski</a> has shown that over binary trees the mu-calculus and MSOL are expressively equivalent. When it appeared, the result was quite surprising, even unexpected.  The two logics are not equivalent on unranked trees where the number of children of a node is not  fixed. In consequence, the logics are not equivalent over the class of all transition systems. </p><p>In 1983 van Benthem showed that modal logic is equivalent to the bisimulation-invariant fragment of first-order logic. When we have learned about this result we<br/>have realized that our automata models can be used to prove a similar statement<br/>for the mu-calculus. <br/><br/>The method of van Benthem could not be applied to MSOL, the automata based<br/>method looks like the only way to prove the result. <br/><br/><b>Luca:</b> I am interested in how research collaborations start, as I like to tell "research-life stories" to PhD students and young researchers. Could you tell us how you started your collaboration?<br/><br/><b>David:</b> I came to meet Igor when he was visiting Bordeaux in fall 93, presenting his first completeness result on a proof system for the mu-calculus (LICS 93). I was myself starting a PhD considering modal logic for specifying (various forms of) nondeterminism in connection with (power)domain theory (FST&amp;TCS 93).<br/><br/>We eventually met again in Auvergnes (center of France) for the Logic Colloquium in summer 94. There, spending time in the park nearby the conference venue or walking around the volcanoes, we elaborated a notion of nondeterministic automata for the modal mu-calculus. This result can be seen as extending the notion of "disjunctive" normal form from propositional logic to the modal mu-calculus. I remember that Igor later used this result for his second completeness result for <a href="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/~kozen/" target="_blank">Kozen</a>’s proposed proof system for the mu-calculus (LICS 95). Thanks to Igor, this was for me the occasion to learn in depth the link between mu-calculus and tree automata.<br/><br/>Incidentally, <a href="https://staff.science.uva.nl/j.vanbenthem/" target="_blank">Johan van Benthem</a> was also attending this Logic Colloquium and we both attend his lecture about the bisimulation-invariant fragment of FO. Although we did not yet realize we could generalize his result to MSO, this surely increased our own understanding of logic.<br/><br/>Our first result (Automata for the mu-calculus) was presented at MFCS in 95 in Prague, where Igor and I met again. It could have been there, or a little later, that we eventually postulated our bisimulation-invariance result. However, proof arguments were only found later while exchanging emails. It was a bit amazing for me that we could discuss that way across Europe: email started to be heavily used only in the late 80's. In my head, Poland was far, far away from France.<br/><br/>Yet our collaboration was eventually in the line of an  ongoing collaboration<br/>between Warsaw and Bordeaux, involving researcher like Arnold (my supervisor)<br/>and Niwinski (Igor's mentor), both major specialists in the area of automata and<br/>logics. Somehow, as a followup, together with Aachen (<a href="https://logic.rwth-aachen.de/People/Graedel/" target="_blank">Grädel</a> and <a href="https://www.lics.rwth-aachen.de/cms/LICS/Der-Lehrstuhl/Team/Dozierende/~ocwi/Wolfgang-Thomas/lidx/1/" target="_blank">Thomas</a>) and<br/>many other sites, the GAMES European network was later created, and, almost at<br/>the same time, Igor came to Bordeaux as a CNRS researcher.<br/><br/><b>Luca:</b> As you mentioned earlier, van Bentham has <a href="https://pure.uva.nl/ws/files/3800551/1170_12194y.pdf" target="_blank">shown</a> that modal logic has the same expressive power as the bisimulation-invariant fragment of first-order logic. In some sense, one may consider your main result as the extension of van Bentham's theorem to a setting with fixed-points. Could you briefly describe at a high level the challenges that fixed-points created in your work? To your mind, what was the main technical achievement or technique in your paper?<br/><br/><b>David and Igor:</b> Sure our result is similar to van Benthem's, and, as mentioned<br/>above, his own presentation in 93 was very inspiring. However, his proof relies<br/>on compactness of first-order logic and cannot be adapted to monadic<br/>second-order logic. In our proof, we have used automata-theoretic techniques. <br/><br/>In our previous works we had developed automata models for MSOL and the<br/>mu-calculus on unranked trees. Every transition system is bisimulation invariant<br/>to a tree obtained by the unfolding of the transition system. Crucially for our<br/>result, it is also equivalent to a tree where every subtree is duplicated<br/>infinitely many times. A short pumping argument shows that on such trees the two automata models are equivalent. <br/><br/><b>Luca:</b> Did any of your subsequent research build explicitly on the results and the techniques you developed in your award-winning paper? Is there any result obtained by other researchers that builds on your work and that you like in particular?<br/><br/><b>David and Igor: </b>Around that time Marco Hollenberg and Giovana D'Agostino used our automata-theoretic methods to show the uniform interpolation property for the mu-calculus. <br/><br/>In collaboration with Giacomo Lenzi (postdoc in Bordeaux from Pisa), David<br/>considered the bisimulation-invariant fragment of various levels of the monadic<br/>quantifier alternation hierarchy. It turns out that monadic Sigma_1 corresponds to reachability properties and monadic Sigma_2 corresponds to Büchi properties, respectively the first and second levels of the mu-calculus hierarchy. <br/><br/>It could be the case that all mu-calculus can be translated into monadic<br/>Sigma_3 formulas -- this is true when restricting to deterministic transition<br/>systems. However, with nondeterminism, such a result seems difficult to achieve. <br/><br/>Incidentally, Giacomo and David also proved that adding limited counting capacity<br/>to modalities yields a fixed-point calculus equivalent to the unraveling invariant<br/>fragment of MSO (LICS 2001).  <br/><br/>In 1999, in collaboration with Erich Grädel, Igor has used similar techniques to define and study guarded fixed-point logic. Subsequently, several other fixed-point logics of this kind were proposed with the most expressive one probably being guarded negation logic with fixed points of Bárány, ten Cate, and Segoufin from 2015.  These works all use automata-theoretic methods to some extent. <br/><br/><b>Luca:</b> Your paper was written while Igor was at BRICS at the University of Aarhus. Igor, what was it like to be at BRICS@Aarhus at that time? What role do<br/>you think centres like BRICS played and can play in the development of theoretical computer science? Do you think that your stay at BRICS had a<br/>positive impact on your future career?<br/><br/><b>Igor:</b> My stay at BRICS had definitively a beneficial impact on me. At that time BRICS was one of the most active centers world wide in theoretical computer science. Being able to see and talk to so many different people, being exposed<br/>to so many different ideas, was very enriching. BRICS was a meeting place <br/>allowing scientists to have a better and larger vision of our field. BRICS contributed to the development of many people involved, as well as to the excellence of Aarhus, and even Denmark as a whole, in our field.<br/><br/><b>Luca:</b> I have been brought up in the concurrency-theory tradition and I feel that bisimulation-invariant properties are the interesting ones over transition systems. Do you think that we actually "need" logics that allow one to specify properties of transition systems that are not bisimulation invariant?<br/><br/><b>David:</b> That was the idea indeed and the mu-calculus is the good logic for that. From a mathematical perspective, bisimulation is a fairly natural definition. In some sense, bisimulation equivalence is a greatest co-congruence.<br/><br/>However, I always suspected that bisimulation is too fine grained as an equivalence for concurrency. When modeling realistic systems, nondeterminism arises either as controllable (angelic) or uncontrollable (demonic) choice. In this case, the right equivalence to be considered is simulation equivalence.<br/><br/>The funny thing is that David Park, who "invented" bisimulation, was actually studying equivalence of J.R. Büchi's deterministic string automata where, because of determinism, bisimulation turns out to be equivalent to simulation equivalence. It is only after Matthew Hennessy and Robin Milner's work in concurrency that bisimulation was applied to nondeterministic behaviors.<br/><br/><b>Igor:</b> In the context of XML and semistructured data, bisimulation is not relevant. One of the prominent queries in XPATH is whether a value appears twice -- that is clearly not a bisimulation-invariant property. So while XPATH looks very close to PDL or the mu-calculus, many techniques and questions are very different. The other context that comes to mind is controller synthesis, where we ask for a<br/>transition system of a specific shape, for example, with self-loops on certain actions. Such self loops represent invisibility of the action to the controller. <br/><br/><b>Luca:</b> What are the research topics that you find most interesting right now? Is there any specific problem in your current field of interest that you'd like to see solved?<br/><br/><b>David: </b>In Logic for Computer Science, there have always been two kinds of approaches: model theory that eventually led to model checking and proof theory that eventually led to typed programming languages.<br/><br/>Twenty years later, aiming at designing and implementing real concurrent systems, especially for interactive arts, I realized that the latter approach was<br/>(at least for me) a lot more effective. Building concurrent systems by synchronizing arbitrary sub-systems sounded for me like unstructured programming; it was essentially unmaintainable. Monads and linear types, among<br/>many other approaches in typed functional programming, surely offered interesting<br/>alternatives to process calculi approaches.<br/><br/><b>Igor:</b> In the context of the paper we discuss here, I am surprised by developments around the model-checking problem for the mu-calculus. After some years of relative calm, Calude, Jain, Khoussainov, Li and Stephan have made an important breakthrough in 2017. Yet, despite big activity after this result, the research on the problem seems to have hit one more barrier. Another old prominent problem is decidability of the alternation hierarchy for the mu-calculus. The problem is: given a formula and a number of alternations between the least and the greatest fixed-points, decide if there is an  equivalent formula with this number of alternations. Even when the number of alternations is fixed we do not know the answer. Among others, Thomas Colcombet and Christof Loeding have done very interesting work on this subject.<br/><br/><b>Luca:</b> What advice would you give to a young researcher who is keen to start working on topics related to automata theory and logic in computer science? <br/><br/><b>David:</b> From the distance, our result sounds to me as a combination of both technique and imagination. Technique for mastering known results and imagination for finding original open problems, especially between research fields that are not (yet) known to be deeply related. As a matter of fact, I felt lucky finding such a fresh open problem that was (probably) a lot easier to solve than many other well-known hard problems.<br/><br/>Technique comes from hard work. It is obviously essential but somehow easy to teach and evaluate in academia. Imagination comes from curiosity. It is still essential but a lot more difficult to teach. So young researchers must develop by themselves their own imagination and curiosity.<br/><br/>In the automata-theory branch of logic in computer science, the remaining open<br/>problems seem fairly hard, so I believe that it is the imagination of young researchers that will make the difference for setting up new interesting directions of research, especially those who are ready to look aside, towards other areas of<br/>logic in computer science and, because it can be a considerable source of<br/>motivation, funny applications.<br/><br/><b>Igor:</b> Naturally, the field is much broader these days than it was 25 years ago. It is<br/>crucial to master some techniques. For this, working on variations of already solved problems is a good method. Yet, I think it is important to escape<br/>the cycle of constant modifications of existing problems and their solutions. <br/>I would suggest that, at some moment, one should find an important open<br/>problem that one is passionate about and should spend a considerable effort on<br/>it. I admit that this is a matter of a taste, personality, and having a sufficiently<br/>comfortable situation to afford such a risk. Another good option is to look at frontiers with other areas: distributed computing, semantics, control theory, security. <br/><br/></p><br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-28T12:27:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-28T12:27:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T09:08:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5769</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5769" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5769#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5769" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Please cheer me up</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Update: Come to think of it, let’s circle back to the thing about kids under 13 getting banned from taking the SAT, as a ridiculous unintended consequence of some federal regulation. I wonder whether this is a campaign this blog could spearhead that would have an actual chance of making a positive difference in the […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><br/><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update: </span></strong>Come to think of it, let’s circle back to the thing about kids under 13 getting banned from taking the SAT, as a ridiculous unintended consequence of some federal regulation.  I wonder whether this is a campaign this blog could spearhead that would have <strong>an actual chance of making a positive difference in the world (!!)</strong>, rather than just giving me space to express myself, to vent my impotent rage at the tragic failures of our civilization and the blankfaces who sleep soundly despite knowing that they caused those failures.  What if, like, a whole bunch of us wrote to the College Board, or whatever federal agency enforces the regulation that the College Board is worried about, and we asked them whether a solution might be found in which parents gave permission on the web form for their under-13s to take the SAT, given how memorable this opportunity was for many of us, how it was a nerd rite of passage, and how surely none of us have any wish to deny that opportunity to the next generation, so let’s work together to solve this?</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>I’m depressed that, all over the world, the values of the Enlightenment are humiliated and in retreat, while the values of the Taliban are triumphant.  The literal Taliban of course, but also a thousand mini-Talibans of every flavor, united in their ideological certainty.</p>



<p>I’m depressed that now and for the future, the image of the United States before the world—<em>deservedly</em> so—is one of desperate Afghans plunging to their deaths from the last airplanes out of Kabul.  I’m depressed that, while this historic calamity was set in motion by Donald Trump, the president who bears direct, immediate moral responsibility for it is the one I voted for.  And knowing what I know now, I’d <em>still</em> have voted for him—but with an ashen face.</p>



<p>I’m depressed that, on social media, the same people who seven years ago floridly denounced me, because, while explaining how as a young person I overcame the urge to suicide and finally achieved some semblance of a normal life, I made a passing reference to a vanished culture of arranged marriages, to which I seemed better-adapted than to the world of today—these very same people are the ones sagely resigned to millions of Afghan women and girls<em> actually</em> forced into unwanted marriages, tortured, and raped, who explain that there’s nothing the US can or should do about this, even that it was folly to imagine we could impose parochial Western values, like women’s rights, on a culture that doesn’t want them.  These are the people who saw fit to lecture me on my feminist failings.</p>



<p>I’m depressed that there’s an <em>exceedingly</em> good chance that both of my kids will get covid, as they’ve returned to school and preschool in Austin, TX, where the Delta variant is raging out of control, new reports of cases among the kids’ schoolmates come almost every day, Daniel has been quarantined at home for the past week because of one such case, there’s no vaccination mandate (and a looming battle over mask mandates), and—crucially, tragically, incredibly—<strong>the FDA has not only slow-walked approval of covid vaccines for children under 12, but has pushed back the approval <em>even further</em> than it previously planned, ignoring <a href="https://www.fox43.com/article/news/local/fda-covid-19-vaccine-children-under-12-pfizer-aap-moderna/521-cb2d3d7e-c08e-4920-a0e8-92b81a4d6e90">unprecedented public objections</a> from the American Academy of Pediatrics.</strong>  The FDA blankfaces have done this in spite of the reality, obvious to anyone with eyes and a brain, that they’re thereby consigning thousands of children to their deaths, that whatever ultra-rare risks the vaccine poses to children are infinitesimal compared to the overwhelming benefit.</p>



<p>Since I worry that I wasn’t clear enough, how about this: in a just world, the FDA in its current form would be dismantled, and <s>all those who needlessly delayed the delivery of covid vaccines to children would be tried for manslaughter</s> [while I still think the case for authorizing covid vaccines for kids right now is <em>overwhelmingly</em> clear, I hereby retract this particular remark, which was based on a factor 5-10 overestimate of the covid mortality risk for kids—for more, see <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5769#comment-1907100">this comment</a>].  The blankfaces have <em>already</em> killed more people through pointlessly delaying the approval of covid vaccines than their agency could plausibly have saved through its entire history: do they need to take the children as well?  As far as I’m concerned, those who defend the status quo—those who meet the on-the-ground reality of overflowing pediatric hospitals with obfuscatory words about procedures and best practices and the need for yet more data—are no better either morally or intellectually than the anti-vaxx conspiracy theorists, their rightly-reviled cousins.</p>



<p>As icing on the cake, I’m depressed that the College Board is no longer administering the SAT to children under 13, apparently because of federal regulations—-which means that Johns Hopkins CTY’s famed <a href="https://cty.jhu.edu/testing/study-exceptional-talent-set">Study of Exceptional Talent</a>, a program that made a big difference in my life three decades ago, has been suspended indefinitely.  Imagine being a nerdy 11-year-old in 2021: no more tracking, no more gifted programs, no more magnet schools, no more acceleration, no <em>getting vaccinated against deadly disease</em> (!!), … oh, and if perchance you felt the urge to take the SAT, just to prove that you could outscore the grownups who decided to impose all this on you, then no, you’re no longer allowed to do that either.</p>



<p>The one bright spot in the endlessly bleak picture is that Daniel, my 4-year-old son, now plays a pretty mean chess game, if not quite at the level of <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5171">Beth Harmon</a>.  Having just learned the rules a few months ago, Daniel now gives me and Dana (admittedly, no one would mistake either of us for Magnus Carlsen) extremely competitive matches; just yesterday he beat several adults in a park.  Daniel has come to spend much of his free time (and now that he’s quarantined, he has a lot) playing chess against his iPad and watching chess videos.  To be clear, he has very little emotional maturity <em>even for a 4-year-old</em>, and unlike me at the same age, he has no overwhelming passion for numbers or counting, but with chess I’ve finally found a winner.  Now I just need to hope that they don’t ban chess-playing for children under 13.</p>



<p>So that’s it, it’s off my chest.  Commenters: what else have you got that might cheer me up?</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-27T19:47:44Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-27T19:47:44Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Obviously I'm Not Defending Aaronson"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Rage Against Doofosity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2021-08-31T14:32:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19067</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/26/great-go-glitchy-grammar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Great Go, Glitchy Grammar</title>
    <summary>If there are sentient beings on other planets, then they play Go.—Emanuel Lasker, chess world champion ACM Prize in Computing source David Silver, the 2019 ACM Computing Prize winner, is highlighted this month in the main journal of the ACM—the Communications of the ACM. He is featured in the “Last Byte” article at the end. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>If there are sentient beings on other planets, then they play Go.—Emanuel Lasker, chess world champion</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/26/great-go-glitchy-grammar/davidsilver/" rel="attachment wp-att-19069"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-19069" height="150" src="https://i2.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/davidsilver.png?resize=150%2C150&amp;ssl=1" width="150"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">ACM Prize in Computing <a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/730838">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
David Silver, the 2019 ACM Computing Prize winner, is highlighted this month in the main journal of the ACM—the Communications of the ACM. He is featured in the “Last Byte” <a href="https://m-cacm.acm.org/magazines/2021/9/255049-playing-with-and-against-computers/fulltext">article</a> at the end. </p>
<p>
Today we discuss one aspect of the article in regard to machine assistance.</p>
<p>
The article highlights his work on computer programs that play Go, under the title “Playing With, and Against, Computers.” Silver led a Google DeepMind project that used learning methods to make the program <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AlphaGo">AlphaGo</a>, which beat the many-times world Go champion Lee Sedol in March 2016.  </p>
<p>
The victory was only the beginning; subsequent iterations of the algorithm have been able to learn without any human data or prior knowledge except the rules of the game and, eventually, without even knowing the rules.  Very impressive. The versions that Silver refers to include <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AlphaGo_Zero">AlphaGo Zero</a> and finally <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AlphaZero">AlphaZero</a>. We covered the 2016 match <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2016/03/11/stonefight-at-the-goke-corral/">here</a> and discussed AlphaZero <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2017/12/17/truth-from-zero/">here</a>.  See also this <a href="https://nikcheerla.github.io/deeplearningschool/2018/01/01/AlphaZero-Explained/">explanation</a> of AlphaZero.</p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/26/great-go-glitchy-grammar/gogame/" rel="attachment wp-att-19070"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19070" height="168" src="https://i2.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/gogame.png?resize=300%2C168&amp;ssl=1" width="300"/></a></p>
<p/><h2> The Last Article </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Each month the last article is special. It starts on the last page <img alt="{p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> of the month’s publication. Then it continues to page <img alt="{p-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and so on. All the other articles go from <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> to <img alt="{q+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and so on. On the website it gives the pages as “120-ff”; maybe the hyphen is a minus sign to invert the sense of <em>ff</em> as “following folios.”</p>
<p>
The article is also always in the form of an interview: a series of questions and answers by the person being highlighted. This month the author, Leah Hoffmann, asks Silver questions about his work on Go playing programs. </p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/26/great-go-glitchy-grammar/lh/" rel="attachment wp-att-19072"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19072" height="144" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/lh.jpg?resize=120%2C144&amp;ssl=1" width="120"/></a></p>
<p/><h2> One Question </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
About midway through the interview, Hoffmann poses the following:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <b>Eventually, you built a system that learned to play Go on a smaller, nine-by-nine sized board.</b> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Silver answered:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> We had some successes in the early days on the small-sized boards. Our system did learn, through these very principled trial-and-error reinforcement learning techniques, to associate different patterns with whether they would lead to winning or losing the game. Then I started collaborating Sylvain Gelly at the University of Paris on a project called MoGo, which became the first nine-by-nine Go championship program. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
What is wrong with his answer? What is interesting about this answer, from a Google point of view? Any thoughts before you turn the page? Well, posts do not have pages on the blog, so we’ll use a section heading as divider.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Our Answer </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The answer is that the response is not correct grammar. Do you see? It should be:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Then I started collaborating <b>with</b> Sylvain Gelly at the University of Paris on a project <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
We find it fun to see an article about robotic methods that can play the world’s best Go, yet misses a chance to discover a simple grammatical error. There are lots of programs, free ones even, that catch this one. (Microsoft Word 2016, however, seems not to.)</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> A Google Fix? </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
This gave us the idea of seeing whether existing Google tools could fix it automatically. </p>
<p>
One available tool is Google Translate, and this recalled the idea of our old <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2010/11/12/can-we-translate-english-to-english/">post</a> titled, “Can We Translate English To English?” That idea, which I (Ken writing this part) occasionally use when communicating with chess officials in many countries, is to try repeated translations into the target language until you get one that translates back to English the way you want it. Here, we have freedom to use any language <em>L</em> as the intermediary. </p>
<p>
Using just the last sentence in the quote, here is what I get when I translate into <em>L</em> and then back. People used to write in Latin even for fellow speakers of their first language, so I tried Latin:</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/26/great-go-glitchy-grammar/golatin/" rel="attachment wp-att-19074"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-19074" height="76" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/GoLatin.jpg?resize=600%2C76&amp;ssl=1" width="600"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Latin inserted a missing preposition, but not the right one. Thinking of a language with similar richness of grammar to Latin but more native speakers who are currently alive (so that Google gains more data year over year), I tried Russian:</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/26/great-go-glitchy-grammar/gorussian/" rel="attachment wp-att-19078"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-19078" height="87" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/GoRussian.jpg?resize=600%2C87&amp;ssl=1" width="600"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
This got the main part right, except for ‘y’ coming back as ‘i’, but wobbled on the second half—which is frankly a mouthful in English. To multiply the number of native speakers by 10, I went to Chinese. Google offers the choice of “Traditional” or “Simplified” Chinese, but coming back is the same:</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/26/great-go-glitchy-grammar/gochinese/" rel="attachment wp-att-19079"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-19079" height="68" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/GoChinese.jpg?resize=600%2C68&amp;ssl=1" width="600"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Going via Chinese got “with” but lost the specificity of “collaborating” and also messed up the second half. So I tried completely the opposite idea: an artificial language with zero native speakers and a limited vocabulary—Esperanto.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/26/great-go-glitchy-grammar/goesperanto/" rel="attachment wp-att-19080"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-19080" height="76" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/GoEsperanto.jpg?resize=600%2C76&amp;ssl=1" width="600"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Suddenly it is perfect. What is curious is that the Esperanto puts no preposition between “kunlabori” and Sylvain Gelly, who looks like a direct object the same as in the mistaken English original. But Google knows to insert the extra “with” on coming back. </p>
<p>
We’ll invite you to have fun trying other languages. Among ones I tried, only Italian and Portuguese matched the exactness of the correction via Esperanto. But all of them fixed the issue of “with.”</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Does this show a commonality among human languages in their entirety that can help us improve our experiences with any one of them?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-26T19:38:07Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-26T19:38:07Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="AlphaGo"/>
    <category term="AlphaZero"/>
    <category term="CACM"/>
    <category term="David Silver"/>
    <category term="Google Translate"/>
    <category term="grammar"/>
    <category term="interview"/>
    <category term="Last Byte"/>
    <category term="Leah Hoffmann"/>
    <category term="natural language processing"/>
    <category term="translation"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/08/26/assistant-professor-tenure-track-and-professor-positions-in-computer-science-at-ist-austria-apply-by-october-29-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/08/26/assistant-professor-tenure-track-and-professor-positions-in-computer-science-at-ist-austria-apply-by-october-29-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor (tenure-track) and Professor positions in Computer Science at IST Austria (apply by October 29, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Institute of Science and Technology Austria (IST Austria) invites applications for several open positions in all areas of computer science. IST Austria values diversity and is committed to equal opportunities. We strive to increase the number of women, particularly in fields where they are underrepresented, and therefore we strongly encourage female researchers to apply. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Institute of Science and Technology Austria (IST Austria) invites applications for several open positions in all areas of computer science.</p>
<p>IST Austria values diversity and is committed to equal opportunities. We strive to increase the number of women, particularly in fields where they are underrepresented, and therefore we strongly encourage female researchers to apply.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://ist.ac.at/en/jobs/faculty/">https://ist.ac.at/en/jobs/faculty/</a><br/>
Email: faculty.recruiting@ist.ac.at</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-26T15:24:23Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-26T15:24:23Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-542741463481169013</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/542741463481169013/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/08/the-long-road.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/542741463481169013" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/542741463481169013" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/08/the-long-road.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Long Road</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><i>Guest blogger Varsha Dani tells us why it's never too late.</i></p><p>This week, I am starting as an Assistant Professor at RIT and I am super excited about it. What's the big deal, you are probably thinking. Don't lots of people get hired in tenure track positions every year? Sure. But the difference in my case is that I got my Ph.D. in 2008. </p><div>Why didn't I look for a position right away? There were a number of reasons. I was burned out. I was going to have a baby. The job market was not particularly good that year. I would have had a two-body problem. And most importantly, I thought it was just going to be a short break. I thought that there was no rush...</div><div><br/></div><div>What did I do in those intervening years? A lot of things. I spent a lot of time with my kids, including part home-schooling them for some time. I found some new interests, both in Math and CS and outside. I found new collaborators and did some research in new areas, just for fun. Sometimes I was funded for it through grants, but mostly I wasn't. I wrote a lot of Computer Science and some math materials for Brilliant.org. I organized math clubs at my kids' elementary and middle schools. I hiked. I wrote <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/06/on-chain-letters-and-pandemics.html">poetry</a>. I never intended nearly 13 years to go by, but somehow they did.  At some point I remembered that I had meant to take a short break, not to give up on being an academic altogether. But by then it seemed too late. At the beginning of my meant-to-be-short hiatus, I used to jokingly refer to myself as a "scholar at large" but by the time a decade had gone by I had started to feel extremely isolated and being a scholar for its own sake was not something to joke about anymore.  Each year I rolled the job-search dice, but with each passing year it seemed more and more futile to do so, and more and more of an imposition to ask people to write recommendations for me. And then, out of the blue, last year, I found a whole community of independent researchers who, like me, were pursuing their scholarly interests despite not being employed to do so, and who felt unapologetically unembarrassed, even proud of it.  And, even more out of the blue, this year I got an offer. And now, this Fall, I am actually doing it. I am actually an academic! To be honest, I feel more than a little trepidation about it, mixed in with the excitement. </div><div><br/></div><div>So why am I telling you this? Partly to celebrate. Partly to publicly thank my spouse, who has been extremely supportive of all my decisions (and all my actions that were born of indecision) over many years. Partly to give a shout-out to the wonderful folks at the <a href="http://ronininstitute.org/">Ronin Institute</a> who helped me remember that we do science (and computer science) because we love it, not because it pays the bills. Ironically, I believe I needed to be reminded of that before I could get a job! But mostly, I'm writing this to reach out to anyone out there who thinks that their decisions have led to a one-way street they no longer want to be on. It may be hard, and there are, of course, no guarantees, but you won't know whether you can turn around, unless you try. </div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-25T20:07:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-25T20:07:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T10:35:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19054</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/24/a-negative-comment-on-negations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Negative Comment on Negations</title>
    <summary>Always turn a negative situation into a positive situation—Michael Jordan (MJ) src Michael I. Jordan of the University of California, Berkeley, is a pioneer of AI that few outside of his field recognize. “He’s known as the Michael Jordan of machine learning,” quips Oren Etzioni, director of the Seattle-based Allen Institute. Today, Ken and I […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Always turn a negative situation into a positive situation—Michael Jordan (<a href="https://www.azquotes.com/quote/150625">MJ</a>)</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/24/a-negative-comment-on-negations/mij/" rel="attachment wp-att-19056"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-19056" height="135" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/mij.png?resize=135%2C135&amp;ssl=1" width="135"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2"><a href="https://ds.cs.umass.edu/external-advisory-board">src</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Michael I. Jordan of the University of California, Berkeley, is a pioneer of AI that few outside of his field recognize. “He’s known as the Michael Jordan of machine learning,” quips Oren Etzioni, director of the Seattle-based Allen Institute.</p>
<p>
Today, Ken and I discuss some linkage between machine learning and computational complexity theory.<br/>
<span id="more-19054"/></p>
<p>
The quip by Etzioni runs longer—see <a href="https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/04/who-s-michael-jordan-computer-science-new-tool-ranks-researchers-influence">this</a>. The Allen Institute’s <a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/">Semantic Scholar</a> project aims to achieve content-based associative search for academic publications, so one can search for X that are close to a topic Y you have defined. They created an “influence graph” for millions of academic publications that goes well beyond citation counts. The graph’s most influential computer science paper was one by Jordan.</p>
<p>
Neither Jordan has ever worked in complexity theory. Somehow, I thought the above is relevant to complexity theory. It got me thinking about MIJ and his connection to machine learning (ML). This is connected to complexity theory again, and so <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> </p>
<p>
My thoughts converged on how the notion of <em>monotone</em> plays in both fields. Influence strikes us as naturally monotone—“negative influence” is still influence—and building the graph is a kind of positively weighted transitive closure. Many ML algorithms work by monotonically increasing an objective function, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expectation-maximization_algorithm">expectation-maximization</a> as expounded by MIJ. Non-monotone components such as negative (inhibiting) neural links and <a href="http://www.optimization-online.org/DB_FILE/2014/08/4488.pdf">line</a>–<a href="https://www.caam.rice.edu/~yzhang/caam565/L1_reg/BB-step.pdf">search</a> add-ons to gradient descent are employed, but when and to what extent are they critical? We think negation is critical in complexity theory, but maybe not so much. Here are my thoughts.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Upper Bounds and Lower Bounds </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/24/a-negative-comment-on-negations/easy/" rel="attachment wp-att-19057"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19057" height="252" src="https://i2.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/easy.png?resize=338%2C252&amp;ssl=1" width="338"/></a></p>
<p>
Complexity theory is all about how hard is it to solve some problem. How hard is it to decide if a number is a prime? How hard is it to find a factor of a composite number? How hard is to color a graph with three colors? And so on.</p>
<p>
There are two issues: </p>
<p>
<b>Upper Bounds</b> Find an algorithm for the problem that is more efficient in some manner. Often in number of steps, but can be in other measures of complexity like memory used or amount of randomness and so on.</p>
<p>
<b>Lower Bounds</b> Show that no algorithm for the problem is more efficient in some manner. For example, show that no algorithm can solve the problem is fewer than a certain number of steps.</p>
<p>
The first is an <img alt="{\exists}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cexists%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> problem; the second is a <img alt="{\forall}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cforall%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. An upper bound is proving there exists an algorithm that is efficient enough. You job is to present an algorithm that solves the problem. A lower bound is proving all algorithms that solve the problem, must take more steps than allowed. </p>
<p>
There is something about <img alt="{\exists}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cexists%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> that is fundamentally simpler than <img alt="{\forall}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cforall%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. An upper bound requires you to design an algorithm that works in some clever manner. The algorithm must exploit some trick about the problem that is powerful. For example to decide if a number is a prime, do not try all possible factors. Rather use a key consequence of a number being a prime: use the value of the number raised to a high power. </p>
<p>
The lower bound requires you to show that there is no algorithm that operates more efficiently that a certain bound. You must show that being too fast, for example, makes you wrong.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Negations </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
One approach to lower bounds is via Boolean complexity. The idea is that any computation can be done with <img alt="{AND}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BAND%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, <img alt="{OR}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BOR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, and <img alt="{NOT}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BNOT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. But, if we leave out <img alt="{NOT}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BNOT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, some computations cannot be done. However: </p>
<p>
Suppose that you wish to show that something cannot be computed efficiently. An obvious first step is to explain what operations are needed to compute it at all. Once you fix on operations that are enough, you can then focus on the question of whether the given operations can <em>efficiently</em> compute it.</p>
<p>
Suppose you wish to show that it will take a long time to get from A to another location B. How can you prove this? You might measure how long the distance is between A and B. Then if you know that you must drive a car from A to B, a lower bound is simple: How fast can the car go at maximum and argue that the time is therefore at least </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \frac{\mathit{Distance}(A,B)}{M}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cfrac%7B%5Cmathit%7BDistance%7D%28A%2CB%29%7D%7BM%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>Here M is the maximum speed the car goes.</p>
<p>
Suppose that Distance is <img alt="{100}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B100%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> <i>miles</i> and the car can go at most <img alt="{40}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B40%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> miles per hour. Then a simple calculation is that it must take at least  	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \frac{100}{40} = 2.5 \text{ hours.}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cfrac%7B100%7D%7B40%7D+%3D+2.5+%5Ctext%7B+hours.%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>Of course it could be higher if sometimes you go slower—perhaps you have to stop now and then for traffic lights. 	</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Monotone Circuits </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
There are many theorems like <a href="https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~eva/Gap.Between.Monotone.NonMonotone.Circuit.Complexity.is.Exponential.pdf">this</a>: </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 1</b> <em> Any monotone circuit that computes <img alt="{F(X)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF%28X%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> correctly has size at least exponential in <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> . </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
These theorems are often hard to prove and require clever methods, but there are now tons of them. The field of complexity continues to extend and refine these theorems.</p>
<p>
This feeds in to the approach of showing <img alt="{\mathsf{P &lt; NP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BP+%3C+NP%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> via Boolean circuit complexity. That is, to show that for some particular <img alt="{\mathsf{NP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BNP%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-complete problem, any Boolean computation for it requires a super-polynomial number of gates. A big idea is to build off the monotone lower bound results by moderately adding negation. </p>
<p>
But there is a big issue: it takes only order <img alt="{\log n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> negations to make the results fail. We <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2017/08/17/on-the-edge-of-eclipses-and-pnp/">covered</a> some recent <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2020/06/16/pnp/">attempts</a> by Norbert Blum to make this kind of idea work, but they do not seem to have established a new <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/08/10/p-vs-np-proof-claims/">base camp</a> for this approach, beyond <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF01978380">previously</a>–<a href="http://people.cs.uchicago.edu/~razborov/files/clique.pdf">known</a> <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0304397586901222">results</a> and <a href="file://C:/Users/KWRegan/Downloads/TR16-188.pdf">more</a>–<a href="https://theoryofcomputing.org/articles/v016a013/">recent</a> <a href="https://sol.sbc.org.br/index.php/ctd/article/view/15761">advances</a>.</p>
<p>
This failure led many to think that negations are somehow the “final frontier.” But we do not agree with this either. We feel that negations are not the critical issue.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Slice Issue—Again </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The key is the concept of <em>slice</em>. A slice of <img alt="{\{0,1\}^n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%7B0%2C1%5C%7D%5En%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is a subset <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> that has all the elements the same weight. That is, its member binary strings have the same number of <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>s.</p>
<p>
There are many theorems like <a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/abs/10.1137/0215037?journalCode=smjcat">this</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 2</b> <em> Any monotone circuit that computes <img alt="{F(X)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF%28X%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> correctly has size polynomial in <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. Provided it only need work on some slice of <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
For a simple insight, suppose we want to say that a given bit <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> of a string <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. If we are promised that <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> belongs to a slice with <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>s, then we can do this with a monotone function: one saying that bits <img alt="{1\dots i-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%5Cdots+i-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and <img alt="{i+1\dots n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%2B1%5Cdots+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> collectively have at least <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>s. </p>
<p>
For an example of how slices show that negations cannot be the issue, consider factoring of <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> bit numbers. This requires perhaps super polynomial size circuits. But note that if we fix factoring to <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-bit numbers that have <img alt="{n/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>‘s, say, then it becomes a function on a slice. And it is easy to see that a computation without any negations is at most order <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> bigger. Thus negations cannot be the secret to factoring. This is the key insight.</p>
<p>
We still have not said anything new. This insight says that strong lower bounds on monotone complexity for slice functions will give lower bounds for general circuits. But we still do not know how to get such bounds. We have shifted around the side of the mountain, but the resulting “Slice Gap” seems to block ascent as before.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Climbing Mount ML </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
This is what has me thinking about whether machine learning can supply new insight. </p>
<p>
Here is a simple old story of what I mean. One of the limits on the simple neural model of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perceptron">perceptrons</a> that was shown a half-century ago by Marvin Minsky and Seymour Papert is that they cannot compute the binary XOR function. This <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perceptrons_(book)#The_XOR_affair">led</a> people to expect that small assemblages of perceptrons would be similarly powerless. But it only takes three layers of perceptrons to compute XOR. The point is, a small control structure over monotone can replace the free use of negation.</p>
<p>
To go deeper—into deep learning for instance—we’ve peeked at the <a href="https://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~shais/UnderstandingMachineLearning/understanding-machine-learning-theory-algorithms.pdf">book</a> <em>Understanding Machine Learning: From Theory to Algorithms</em> by Shai Shalev-Shwartz and Shai Ben-David. The latter we know for some <a href="https://www.cs.technion.ac.il/users/wwwb/cgi-bin/tr-get.cgi/1991/CS/CS0699.revised.pdf">work</a> on Boolean circuits and P=NP. The nub is more easily approached via a 2014 <a href="http://lear.inrialpes.fr/workshop/osl2015/slides/osl2015_shalev_shwartz.pdf">talk</a> by the former, titled “On the Computational Complexity of Deep Learning,” and his 2016 <a href="https://www.ima.umn.edu/2015-2016/SW5.16-19.16/24770">followup</a>. One point is that “theoretically weak” structures perform well when requirements of worst-case correctness and realizability are lifted—and the details make us wonder about possible parallels to the case of slices.  The point also prompts us to ask:</p>
<blockquote><p>
What control structures, or intermediate operations short of full negation, create practically powerful algorithms that are still theoretically nearly as weak as monotone?  Can researching them help us close the gap on lower bounds?
</p></blockquote>
<p>
To go wider, it seems that both we humans and ML algorithms perform well at many tasks using largely monotone components. Can they help give an account relevant to complexity of what power necessarily comes from non-monotone components? We note caveats expressed by MIJ in a much-noted 2014 <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/machinelearning-maestro-michael-jordan-on-the-delusions-of-big-data-and-other-huge-engineering-efforts">interview</a> for <em>IEEE Spectrum</em> about generalizing from brain function to ML practice, but our intent is to look for particulars.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Can machine learning help us understand the power of monotone functions?  </p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-25T02:07:10Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-25T02:07:10Z</published>
    <category term="algorithms"/>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="circuits"/>
    <category term="complexity"/>
    <category term="deep learning"/>
    <category term="lower bounds"/>
    <category term="machine learning"/>
    <category term="Michael I. Jordan"/>
    <category term="monotone"/>
    <category term="slice"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/123</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/123" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-123 |  On public-coin zero-error randomized communication complexity | 

	Hamed Hatami, 

	Ben Davis, 

	William Pires, 

	Ran Tao, 

	Hamza Usmani</title>
    <summary>We prove that for every Boolean function, the public-coin zero-error randomized communication complexity and the  deterministic communication complexity are polynomially equivalent.</summary>
    <updated>2021-08-24T22:39:39Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-24T22:39:39Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/08/24/phd-postdoc-at-tu-munich-apply-by-september-30-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/08/24/phd-postdoc-at-tu-munich-apply-by-september-30-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PhD / Postdoc at TU Munich (apply by September 30, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The group of Theoretical Foundations of Artificial Intelligence at Technical University of Munich invites applications for the position of a full-time research position (PhD or Postdoc) for conducting research in the computational/statistical learning theory, specifically generalisation and consistency of neural networks. Website: https://portal.mytum.de/jobs/wissenschaftler/NewsArticle_20210727_120151/index_html Email: ghoshdas@in.tum.de</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The group of Theoretical Foundations of Artificial Intelligence at Technical University of Munich invites applications for the position of a full-time research position (PhD or Postdoc) for conducting research in the computational/statistical learning theory, specifically generalisation and consistency of neural networks.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://portal.mytum.de/jobs/wissenschaftler/NewsArticle_20210727_120151/index_html">https://portal.mytum.de/jobs/wissenschaftler/NewsArticle_20210727_120151/index_html</a><br/>
Email: ghoshdas@in.tum.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-08-24T12:13:56Z</updated>
    <published>2021-08-24T12:13:56Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-09-01T14:37:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
