<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-12-19T14:21:50Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4450" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Quantum Dominance, Hegemony, and Superiority</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Yay! I’m now a Fellow of the ACM. Along with my fellow new inductee Peter Shor, who I hear is a real up-and-comer in the quantum computing field. I will seek to use this awesome responsibility to steer the ACM along the path of good rather than evil. Also, last week, I attended the Q2B […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Yay!  I’m <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/news/2019/professor-scott-aaronson-named-acm-fellow">now</a> a Fellow of the ACM.  Along with my <a href="https://www.acm.org/media-center/2019/december/fellows-2019">fellow new inductee</a> Peter Shor, who I hear is a real up-and-comer in the quantum computing field.  I will seek to use this awesome responsibility to steer the ACM along the path of good rather than evil.</p>



<p>Also, last week, I attended the <a href="https://q2b.qcware.com/">Q2B</a> conference in San Jose, where a central theme was the outlook for practical quantum computing in the wake of the first clear demonstration of quantum computational supremacy.  Thanks to the folks at <a href="https://qcware.com/">QC Ware</a> for organizing a fun conference (full disclosure: I’m QC Ware’s Chief Scientific Advisor).  I’ll have more to say about the actual scientific things discussed at Q2B in future posts.</p>



<p>None of that is why you’re here, though.  You’re here because of the battle over “quantum supremacy.”</p>



<p>A week ago, my good friend and <a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/the-talk-3">collaborator</a> Zach Weinersmith, of <a href="http://smbc-comics.com/">SMBC Comics</a>, put out a <a href="http://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/classical">cartoon</a> with a dark-curly-haired scientist named “Dr. Aaronson,” who’s revealed on a hot mic to be an evil “quantum supremacist.”  Apparently a rush job, this cartoon is far from Zach’s finest work.  For one thing, if the character is supposed to be me, why not draw him as me, and if he isn’t, why call him “Dr. Aaronson”?  In any case, I learned from talking to Zach that the cartoon’s timing was purely coincidental: Zach didn’t even <em>realize</em> what a hornet’s-nest he was poking with this.</p>



<p>Ever since John Preskill <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1203.5813">coined</a> it in 2012, “quantum supremacy” has been an awkward term.  Much as I admire John Preskill’s wisdom, brilliance, generosity, and good sense, in physics as in everything else—yeah, “quantum supremacy” is not a term I would’ve coined, and it’s certainly not a hill I’d choose to die on.  Once it had gained common currency, though, I sort of took a liking to it, mostly because I realized that I could mine it for dark one-liners in my talks.</p>



<p>The thinking was: even as white supremacy was making its horrific resurgence in the US and around the world, here we were, physicists and computer scientists and mathematicians of varied skin tones and accents and genders, coming together to pursue a different and better kind of supremacy—a small reflection of the better world that we still believed was possible.  You might say that we were <strong>reclaiming</strong> the word “supremacy”—which, after all, just means a state of being supreme—for something non-sexist and non-racist and inclusive and good.</p>



<p>In the world of 2019, alas, perhaps it was inevitable that people wouldn’t leave things there.</p>



<p>My first intimation came a month ago, when <a href="https://twitter.com/LeonieMueck?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor">Leonie Mueck</a>—someone who I’d gotten to know and like when she was an editor at <em>Nature</em> handling quantum information papers—emailed me about her view that our community should abandon the term “quantum supremacy,” because of its dark overtones, and potential to make women and minorities uncomfortable in our field.  She advocated using “quantum advantage” instead.</p>



<p>So I sent Leonie back a friendly reply, explaining that, as the father of a math-loving 6-year-old girl, I understood and shared her concerns—but also, that I didn’t know an alternative term that really worked.</p>



<p>See, it’s like this.  Preskill meant “quantum supremacy” to refer to a <em>momentous event</em> that seemed likely to arrive in a matter of years: namely, the moment when programmable quantum computers would first outpace the ability of the fastest classical supercomputers on earth, running the fastest algorithms known by humans, to simulate what the quantum computers were doing (at least on special, contrived problems).  And … “the historic milestone of quantum advantage”?  It just doesn’t sound right.  Plus, as many others pointed out, the term “quantum advantage” is already used to refer to … well, quantum <em>advantages</em>, which might fall well short of supremacy.</p>



<p>But one could go further.  Suppose we did switch to “quantum advantage.”  Couldn’t that term, too, remind vulnerable people about the unfair advantages that some groups have over others?  Indeed, while “advantage” is certainly subtler than “supremacy,” couldn’t that make it all the more insidious, and therefore dangerous?</p>



<p>Oblivious though I sometimes am, I realized Leonie would be unhappy if I offered that, because of my wholehearted agreement, I would henceforth never again call it “quantum supremacy,” but only “quantum superiority,” “quantum dominance,” or “quantum hegemony.”</p>



<p>But maybe you now see the problem.  What word does the English language provide to describe one thing <em>decisively beating or</em> <em>being better than</em> a different thing for some purpose, and which <em>doesn’t</em> have any unsavory connotations?</p>



<p>I’ve heard “quantum ascendancy,” but that makes it sound like we’re a UFO cult—waiting to ascend, like ytterbium ions caught in a laser beam, to a vast quantum computer in the sky.</p>



<p>Or “quantum inimitability” (that is, inability to imitate using a classical computer), but who can pronounce that?</p>



<p>Today, my brilliant former student <a href="https://ewintang.com/">Ewin Tang</a> (yes, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3880">that one</a>) relayed to me a suggestion by Kevin Tian: “quantum eclipse” (that is, the moment when quantum computers first eclipse classical ones for some task).  But would one want to speak of a “quantum eclipse experiment”?  And shouldn’t we expect that, the cuter and cleverer the term, the harder it will be to use unironically?</p>



<p>In summary, while someone <em>might</em> think of a term so inspired that it immediately supplants “quantum supremacy” (and while I welcome suggestions), I currently regard it as an open problem.</p>



<p>Anyway, evidently dissatisfied with my response, last week Leonie teamed up with 13 others to publish a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03781-0">letter in <em>Nature</em></a>, which was originally entitled “Supremacy is for racists—use ‘quantum advantage,'” but whose title I see has now been changed to the milder “Instead of ‘supremacy’ use ‘quantum advantage.'”  Leonie’s co-signatories included four of my good friends and colleagues: Alan Aspuru-Guzik, Helmut Katzgraber, Anne Broadbent, and Chris Granade (the last of whom got started in the field by helping me edit <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Quantum-Computing-since-Democritus-Aaronson/dp/0521199565"><em>Quantum Computing Since Democritus</em></a>).</p>



<p>Their letter says:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>The community claims that quantum supremacy is a technical term with a specified meaning.  However, any technical justification for this descriptor could get swamped as it enters the public arena after the intense media coverage of the past few months.</p><p>In our view, ‘supremacy’ has overtones of violence, neocolonialism and racism through its association with ‘white supremacy’.  Inherently violent language has crept into other branches of science as well — in human and robotic spaceflight, for example, terms such as ‘conquest’, ‘colonization’ and ‘settlement’ evoke the <em>terra nullius</em> arguments of settler colonialism and must be contextualized against ongoing issues of neocolonialism.</p><p>Instead, quantum computing should be an open arena and an inspiration for a new generation of scientists.</p></blockquote>



<p>When I did an “Ask Me Anything” session, as the closing event at Q2B, <a href="https://www.sckaiser.com/">Sarah Kaiser</a> asked me to comment on the <em>Nature</em> petition.  So I repeated what I’d said in my emailed response to Leonie—running through the problems with each proposed alternative term, talking about the value of reclaiming the word “supremacy,” and mostly just trying to diffuse the tension by getting everyone laughing together.  Sarah later <a href="https://twitter.com/crazy4pi314/status/1205288610297069568">tweeted</a> that she was “really disappointed” in my response.</p>



<p>Then the <em>Wall Street Journal</em> got in on the action, with a brief <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/achieving-quantum-wokeness-11576540808">editorial</a> (warning: paywalled) mocking the <em>Nature</em> petition:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>There it is, folks: Mankind has hit quantum wokeness.  Our species, akin to Schrödinger’s cat, is simultaneously brilliant and brain-dead.  We built a quantum computer and then argued about whether the write-up was linguistically racist.</p><p>Taken seriously, the renaming game will never end.  First put a Sharpie to the Supremacy Clause of the U.S. Constitution, which says federal laws trump state laws.  Cancel Matt Damon for his 2004 role in “The Bourne Supremacy.”  Make the Air Force give up the term “air supremacy.”  Tell lovers of supreme pizza to quit being so chauvinistic about their toppings.  Please inform Motown legend Diana Ross that the Supremes are problematic.</p><p>The quirks of quantum mechanics, some people argue, are explained by the existence of many universes.  How did we get stuck in this one? </p></blockquote>



<p>Steven Pinker also weighed in, with a linguistically-informed <a href="https://twitter.com/sapinker/status/1206662965614825472">tweetstorm</a>:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>This sounds like something from The Onion but actually appeared in Nature … It follows the wokified stigmatization of other innocent words, like “House Master” (now, at Harvard, Residential Dean) and “NIPS” (Neural Information Processing Society, now NeurIPS).  It’s a familiar linguistic phenomenon, a lexical version of Gresham’s Law: bad meanings drive good ones out of circulation.  Examples: the doomed “niggardly” (no relation to the n-word) and the original senses of “cock,” “ass,” “prick,” “pussy,” and “booty.”  Still, the prissy banning of words by academics should be resisted.  It dumbs down understanding of language: word meanings are conventions, not spells with magical powers, and all words have multiple senses, which are distinguished in context.  Also, it makes academia a laughingstock, tars the innocent,  and does nothing to combat actual racism &amp; sexism.</p></blockquote>



<p>Others had a stronger reaction.  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curtis_Yarvin">Curtis Yarvin</a>, better known as Mencius Moldbug, is one of the founders of “neoreaction” (and a significant influence on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Bannon">Steve Bannon</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Anton">Michael Anton</a>, and other Trumpists).  Regulars might remember that Yarvin argued with me in <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em>‘s comment section, under a <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3167">post</a> in which I denounced Trump’s travel ban and its effects on my Iranian PhD student.  Since then, Yarvin has sent me many emails, which have ranged from long to <em>extremely</em> long, and whose message could be summarized as: “[labored breathing] Abandon your liberal Enlightenment pretensions, young Nerdwalker.  Come over the Dark Side.”</p>



<p>After the “supremacy is for racists” letter came out in <em>Nature</em>, though, Yarvin sent me his shortest email ever.  It was simply a link to the letter, along with the comment “I knew it would come to this.”</p>



<p>He meant: “What more proof do you need, young Nerdawan, that this performative wokeness is a cancer that will eventually infect everything you value—even totally apolitical research in quantum information?  And by extension, that my whole worldview, which warned of this, is fundamentally correct, while your faith in liberal academia is naïve, and will be repaid only with backstabbing?”</p>



<p>In a subsequent email, Yarvin predicted that in two years, the whole community will be saying “quantum advantage” instead of “quantum supremacy,” and in five years I’ll be saying “quantum advantage” too.  As Yarvin <a href="https://www.unqualified-reservations.org/2009/01/gentle-introduction-to-unqualified/">famously wrote</a>: “Cthulhu may swim slowly.  But he only swims left.”</p>



<p>So what do I <em>really</em> think about this epic battle for (and against) supremacy?</p>



<p>Truthfully, half of me just wants to switch to “quantum advantage” right now and be done with it.  As I said, I know some of the signatories of the <em>Nature</em> letter to be smart and reasonable and kind.  They don’t wish to rid the planet of everyone like me.  They’re not Amanda Marcottes or Arthur Chus.  Furthermore, there’s little I despise more than a meaty scientific debate devolving into a pointless semantic one, with brilliant friend after brilliant friend getting sucked into the vortex (“you too?”).  I’m strongly in the Pinkerian camp, which holds that words are just arbitrary designators, devoid of the totemic power to dictate thoughts.  So if friends and colleagues—even just a few of them—tell me that they find some word I use to be offensive, why not just be a <em>mensch</em>, apologize for any unintended hurt, switch words midsentence, and continue discussing the matter at hand?</p>



<p>But then the other half of me wonders: once we’ve ceded an open-ended veto over technical terms that remind anyone of anything bad, <em>where does it stop?</em>  How do we ever certify a term as kosher?  At what point do we all get to stop arguing and laugh together? </p>



<p>To make things concrete, look back at <a href="https://twitter.com/crazy4pi314/status/1205288610297069568">Sarah Kaiser’s Twitter thread</a>—the one where she expresses disappointment in me.  Below her tweet, someone remarks that, besides “quantum supremacy,” the word “ancilla” (as in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ancilla_bit">ancilla qubit</a>, a qubit used for intermediate computation or other auxiliary purposes) is problematic as well.  Here’s Sarah’s response:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>I agree, but I wanted to start by focusing on the obvious one, Its harder for them to object to just one to start with, then once they admit the logic, we can expand the list</p></blockquote>



<p>(What would Curtis Yarvin say about that?)</p>



<p>You’re probably now wondering: what’s wrong with “ancilla”?  <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.06768">Apparently</a>, in ancient Rome, an <a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/ancilla">“ancilla”</a> was a female slave, and indeed that’s the Latin root of the English adjective <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/ancillary">“ancillary”</a> (as in “providing support to”).  I confess that I hadn’t known that—had you?  Admittedly, once you <em>do</em> know, you might never again look at a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Controlled_NOT_gate">Controlled-NOT gate</a>—pitilessly flipping an ancilla qubit, subject only to the whims of a nearby control qubit—in quite the same way.</p>



<p>(Ah, but the ancilla can fight back against her controller!  And she does—in the Hadamard basis.)</p>



<p>The thing is, if we’re gonna play this game: what about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creation_and_annihilation_operators">annihilation operators</a>?  Won’t those need to be … annihilated from physics?</p>



<p>And what about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unitary_matrix">unitary matrices</a>?  Doesn’t their very name negate the multiplicity of perspectives and cultures?</p>



<p>What about Dirac’s oddly-named <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bra%E2%80%93ket_notation">bra/ket notation</a>, with its limitless potential for puerile jokes, about the “bra” vectors displaying their contents horizontally and so forth?  (Did you just smile at that, you hateful pig?)</p>



<p>What about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermitian_adjoint">daggers</a>?  Don’t we need a less violent conjugate tranpose?</p>



<p>Not to beat a dead horse, but once you hunt for examples, you realize that the whole dictionary is shot through with domination and brutality—that you’d have to massacre the English language to take it out.  There’s nothing special about math or physics in this respect.</p>



<p>The same half of me also thinks about my friends and colleagues who oppose claims of quantum supremacy, or even the quest for quantum supremacy, on various <em>scientific</em> grounds.  I.e., either they don’t think that the Google team achieved what it said, or they think that the task wasn’t hard enough for classical computers, or they think that the entire goal is misguided or irrelevant or uninteresting.</p>



<p>Which is fine—these are precisely the arguments we <em>should </em>be having—except that I’ve personally seen some of my respected colleagues, while arguing for these positions, opportunistically tack on ideological objections to the term “quantum supremacy.”  Just to goose up their case, I guess.  And I confess that every time they did this, it made me want to keep saying “quantum supremacy” from now till the end of time—<em>solely to deny these colleagues a cheap and unearned “victory,” one they apparently felt they couldn’t obtain on the merits alone.</em>  I realize that this is childish and irrational.</p>



<p>Most of all, though, the half of me that I’m talking about thinks about Curtis Yarvin and the <em>Wall Street Journal</em> editorial board, cackling with glee to see their worldview so dramatically confirmed—as theatrical wokeness, that self-parodying modern monstrosity, turns its gaze on (of all things) quantum computing research.  More red meat to fire up the base—or at least that sliver of the base nerdy enough to care.  And the left, as usual, walks right into the trap, sacrificing its credibility with the outside world to pursue a runaway virtue-signaling spiral.</p>



<p>The same half of me thinks: do we <em>really</em> want to fight racism and sexism?  Then let’s work together to assemble a broad coalition that can defeat Trump.  And Jair Bolsonaro, and Viktor Orbán, and all the other ghastly manifestations of humanity’s collective lizard-brain.  Then, if we’re really fantasizing, we could liberalize the drug laws, and get contraception and loans and education to women in the Third World, and stop the systematic disenfranchisement of black voters, and open up the world’s richer, whiter, and higher-elevation countries to climate refugees, and protect the world’s remaining indigenous lands (those that didn’t burn to the ground this year).</p>



<p>In this context, the trouble with obsessing over terms like “quantum supremacy” is not merely that it diverts attention, while contributing nothing to fighting the world’s actual racism and sexism.  The trouble is that the obsessions are <em>harmful</em>.  For they make academics—along with progressive activists—look silly.  They make people think that we must not have meant it when we talked about the existential urgency of climate change and the world’s other crises.  They pump oxygen into right-wing echo chambers.</p>



<p>But it’s worse than ridiculous, because of the message that I fear is received by many outside the activists’ bubble.  When you <em>say</em> stuff like “[quantum] supremacy is for racists,” what’s <em>heard</em> might be something more like:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“Watch your back, you disgusting supremacist.  Yes, <em>you</em>.  You claim that you mentor women and minorities, donate to good causes, try hard to confront the demons in your own character?  Ha!  None of that counts for anything with us.  You’ll never be with-it enough to be our ally, so don’t bother trying.  We’ll see to it that you’re never safe, not even in the most abstruse and apolitical fields.  We’ll comb through your words—even words like ‘ancilla qubit’—-looking for any that we can cast as offensive by our opaque and ever-shifting standards.  And once we find some, we’ll have it within our power to end your career, and you’ll be reduced to groveling that we don’t.  Remember those popular kids who bullied you in second grade, giving you nightmares of social ostracism that persist to this day?  We plan to achieve what even those bullies couldn’t: to shame you with the full backing of the modern world’s moral code.  See, we’re the <em>good guys</em> of this story.  It’s goodness itself that’s branding you as racist scum.”</p></blockquote>



<p>In short, I claim that the message—not the message <em>intended</em>, of course, by anyone other than a Chu or a Marcotte or a SneerClubber, but the message <em>received</em>—is basically a Trump campaign ad.  I claim further that our civilization’s current self-inflicted catastrophe will end—i.e., the believers in science and reason and progress and rule of law will claw their way back to power—when, and only when, a generation of activists emerges that understands these dynamics as well as <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/31/us/politics/obama-woke-cancel-culture.html">Barack Obama</a> did.</p>



<p>Wouldn’t it be awesome if, five years from now, I could say to Curtis Yarvin: <em>you were wrong</em>?  If I could say to him: <em>my colleagues and I still use the term ‘quantum supremacy’ whenever we care to, and none of us have been cancelled or ostracized for it—so maybe you should revisit your paranoid theories about Cthulhu and the Cathedral and so forth</em>?  If I could say: <em>quantum computing researchers now have bigger fish to fry than arguments over words—like moving beyond quantum supremacy to the first useful quantum simulations, as well as the race for scalability and fault-tolerance</em>?  And even: <em>progressive activists now have bigger fish to fry too—like retaking actual power all over the world</em>?</p>



<p>Anyway, as I said, that’s how half of me feels.  The other half is ready to switch to “quantum advantage” or any other serviceable term and get back to doing science.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-19T09:17:02Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-19T09:17:02Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Obviously I'm Not Defending Aaronson"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T13:24:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08805</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08805" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Pseudospectral Shattering, the Sign Function, and Diagonalization in Nearly Matrix Multiplication Time</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576713600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Banks:Jess.html">Jess Banks</a>, Jorge Garza Vargas, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kulkarni:Archit.html">Archit Kulkarni</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Srivastava:Nikhil.html">Nikhil Srivastava</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.08805">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We exhibit a randomized algorithm which given a square $n\times n$ complex
matrix $A$ with $\|A\| &lt; 1$ and $\delta&gt;0$, computes with high probability
invertible $V$ and diagonal $D$ such that $$\|A-VDV^{-1}\|\le \delta $$ and
$\|V\|\|V^{-1}\| \le O(n^{2.5}/\delta)$ in $O(T_{MM}\&gt;(n)\log^2(n/\delta))$
arithmetic operations on a floating point machine with $O(\log^4(n/\delta)\log
n)$ bits of precision. Here $T_{MM}\&gt;(n)$ is the number of arithmetic
operations required to multiply two $n\times n$ complex matrices numerically
stably, with $T_{MM}\,\,(n)=O(n^{\omega+\eta}\&gt;\&gt;)$ for every $\eta&gt;0$, where
$\omega$ is the exponent of matrix multiplication. The algorithm is a variant
of the practical spectral bisection algorithm in numerical linear algebra
(Beavers and Denman, 1974). This running time is optimal up to polylogarithmic
factors, in the sense that verifying that a given similarity diagonalizes a
matrix requires at least matrix multiplication time. It significantly improves
best previously provable running times of $O(n^9/\delta^2)$ arithmetic
operations for diagonalization of general matrices (Armentano et al., 2018),
and (w.r.t. dependence on $n$) $O(n^3)$ arithmetic operations for Hermitian
matrices (Parlett, 1998).
</p>
<p>The proof rests on two new ingredients. (1) We show that adding a small
complex Gaussian perturbation to any matrix splits its pseudospectrum into $n$
small well-separated components. This implies that the eigenvalues of the
perturbation have a large minimum gap, a property of independent interest in
random matrix theory. (2) We rigorously analyze Roberts' 1970 Newton iteration
method for computing the matrix sign function in finite arithmetic, itself an
open problem in numerical analysis since at least 1986. This is achieved by
controlling the evolution the iterates' pseudospectra using a carefully chosen
sequence of shrinking contour integrals in the complex plane.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08674</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08674" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dynamic Toolbox for ETRINV</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576713600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Abrahamsen:Mikkel.html">Mikkel Abrahamsen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Miltzow:Tillmann.html">Tillmann Miltzow</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.08674">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Recently, various natural algorithmic problems have been shown to be $\exists
\mathbb{R}$-complete. The reduction relied in many cases on the $\exists
\mathbb{R}$-completeness of the problem ETR-INV, which served as a useful
intermediate problem. Often some strengthening and modification of ETR-INV was
required. This lead to a cluttered situation where no paper included all the
previous details. Here, we give a streamlined exposition in a self-contained
manner. We also explain and prove various universality results regarding
ETR-INV. These notes should not be seen as a research paper with new results.
However, we do describe some refinements of earlier results which might be
useful for future research. We plan to extend and update this exposition as
seems fit.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08482</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08482" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hardness of Network Satisfaction for Relation Algebras with Normal Representations</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576713600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bodirsky:Manuel.html">Manuel Bodirsky</a>, Simon Knäuer <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.08482">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the computational complexity of the general network satisfaction
problem for a finite relation algebra $A$ with a normal representation $B$. If
$B$ contains a non-trivial equivalence relation with a finite number of
equivalence classes, then the network satisfaction problem for $A$ is NP-hard.
As a second result, we prove hardness if $B$ has domain size at least three and
contains no non-trivial equivalence relations but a symmetric atom $a$ with a
forbidden triple $(a,a,a)$, that is, $a \not\leq a \circ a$. We illustrate how
to apply our conditions on two small relation algebras.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08322</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08322" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Finding Effective Geo-Social Group for Impromptu Activity with Multiple Demands</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576713600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Lu.html">Lu Chen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Chengfei.html">Chengfei Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhou:Rui.html">Rui Zhou</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xu:Jiajie.html">Jiajie Xu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Jianxin.html">Jianxin Li</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.08322">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Geo-social group search aims to find a group of people proximate to a
location while socially related. One of the driven applications for geo-social
group search is organizing an impromptu activity. This is because the social
cohesiveness of a found geo-social group ensures a good communication
atmosphere and the spatial closeness of the geo-social group reduces the
preparation time for the activity. Most existing works treat geo-social group
search as a problem that finds a group satisfying a single social constraint
while optimizing the spatial proximity. However, when an impromptu activity has
additional demands on attendees, e.g., the activity requires that the attendees
have certain set of skills, the existing works cannot find an effective
geo-social group efficiently. In this paper, we study how to find a group that
is most proximate to a query location while satisfying multiple constraints.
Specifically, the multiple constraints on which we focus include social
constraint, size constraint and keyword constraint. We propose a novel search
framework which first effectively narrows down the search space with
theoretical guarantees and then efficiently finds the optimum result. Although
our model considers multiple constraints, novel techniques devised in this
paper ensure that search cost is equivalent to parameterized constant times of
one time social constraint checking on a vastly restricted search space. We
conduct extensive experiments on both real and semi-synthetic datasets for
demonstrating the efficiency of the proposed search algorithm. To evaluate the
effectiveness, we conduct two case studies on real datasets, demonstrating the
superiority of our proposed model.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-19T02:21:42Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08277</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08277" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Testing Membership for Timed Automata</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576713600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lassaigne:Richard.html">Richard Lassaigne</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rougemont:Michel_de.html">Michel de Rougemont</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.08277">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a timed automata which admits thick components and a timed word $x$, we
present a tester which decides if $x$ is in the language of the automaton or if
$x$ is $\epsilon$-far from the language, using finitely many samples taken from
the weighted time distribution $\mu$ associated with an input $x$. We introduce
a distance between timed words, the {\em timed edit distance}, which
generalizes the classical edit distance. A timed word $x$ is $\epsilon$-far
from a timed language if its relative distance to the language is greater than
$\epsilon$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08258</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08258" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Xor Filters: Faster and Smaller Than Bloom and Cuckoo Filters</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576713600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Graf:Thomas_Mueller.html">Thomas Mueller Graf</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lemire:Daniel.html">Daniel Lemire</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.08258">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Bloom filter provides fast approximate set membership while using little
memory. Engineers often use these filters to avoid slow operations such as disk
or network accesses. As an alternative, a cuckoo filter may need less space
than a Bloom filter and it is faster. Chazelle et al. proposed a generalization
of the Bloom filter called the Bloomier filter. Dietzfelbinger and Pagh
described a variation on the Bloomier filter that can be used effectively for
approximate membership queries. It has never been tested empirically, to our
knowledge. We review an efficient implementation of their approach, which we
call the xor filter. We find that xor filters can be faster than Bloom and
cuckoo filters while using less memory. We further show that a more compact
version of xor filters (xor+) can use even less space than highly compact
alternatives (e.g., Golomb-compressed sequences) while providing speeds
competitive with Bloom filters.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08066</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08066" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Putting Ridesharing to the Test: Efficient and Scalable Solutions and the Power of Dynamic Vehicle Relocation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576713600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Danassis:Panayiotis.html">Panayiotis Danassis</a>, Marija Sakota, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Filos=Ratsikas:Aris.html">Aris Filos-Ratsikas</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Faltings:Boi.html">Boi Faltings</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.08066">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Ridesharing is a coordination problem in its core. Traditionally it has been
solved in a centralized manner by ridesharing platforms. Yet, to truly allow
for scalable solutions, we needs to shift from traditional approaches, to
multi-agent systems, ideally run on-device. In this paper, we show that a
recently proposed heuristic (ALMA), which exhibits such properties, offers an
efficient, end-to-end solution for the ridesharing problem. Moreover, by
utilizing simple relocation schemes we significantly improve QoS metrics, by up
to 50%.
</p>
<p>To demonstrate the latter, we perform a systematic evaluation of a diverse
set of algorithms for the ridesharing problem, which is, to the best of our
knowledge, one of the largest and most comprehensive to date. Our evaluation
setting is specifically designed to resemble reality as closely as possible. In
particular, we evaluate 12 different algorithms over 12 metrics related to
global efficiency, complexity, passenger, driver, and platform incentives.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=18781</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/18/abel-in-jerusalem-sunday-january-12-2020-and-other-events/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Abel in Jerusalem – SUNDAY, January 12, 2020, and other events</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I would like to report on seven eight mathematical events taking place in Jerusalem, the Tel Aviv area, and Haifa in the next few weeks. (Probably I missed quite a few other mathematical events, feel free to update in the … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/18/abel-in-jerusalem-sunday-january-12-2020-and-other-events/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I would like to report on <del>seven</del> eight mathematical events taking place in Jerusalem, the Tel Aviv area, and Haifa in the next few weeks. (Probably I missed quite a few other mathematical events, feel free to update in the comment section.)</p>
<p>1. <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/event/abel-jerusalem">Abel in Jerusalem: Sunday, January 12, 2020, 09:45-19:00</a>, featuring: <strong>Christopher Hacon, Ulrike Tillmann, Claire Voisin, and François Labourie</strong>.</p>
<p>2. <a href="http://ias.huji.ac.il/SchoolCSE4">Winter School: The Mathematics of Quantum computing</a> (starting  Dec. 15, 2019, <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1OcFzE1PHxBN4l87sOQB033FZLTgY934GHxnpVKi3NaM/edit">program</a>): The Rabin lecture by <strong>Boaz Barak</strong> Monday Dec 16 14:00 CS building;  and also including <strong>a panel/debate on quantum supremacy</strong> moderated by <strong>Sandy Irani</strong>, Dec. 19 , 2019 16:00 CS building. (I am one of the seven panelists and for an introduction to my stance, see <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tau-theory-fest/home">this post</a>.) There are great videotaped lectures! <span style="color: #ff6600;">Important massage</span>: Most lectures are in IIAS, at Feldman building. In the first days the lecture rooms were completely full but from today some seats are available!</p>
<p>3. <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tau-theory-fest/home">TAU Theory Fest  December 29, 2019  – January, 3, 2020.</a> Great line of speakers, and various workshops.</p>
<p>4. <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/boolean-functions/home">Boolean function day, Friday, January 3, 2020,</a> featuring <strong>Esty Kelman, Noam Lifschitz, Renan Gross, Ohad Klein, and Naomi Kirshner</strong>.</p>
<p>5. <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/node/92491">Zabrodsky’s lecture, <strong>Paul Seidel</strong>, December 19, 23, 24 2019, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem.</a> (See <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/14/old-lecture-notes-by-alex-zabrodsky/">this previous post</a>.)</p>
<p>6. <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/node/96554">Dvoretzky’s lectures, <strong>Sylvia Serfaty</strong>,  January 15,16, 2020, the Hebrew University of Jerusalem</a>. (See this post about <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/12/26/lior-aryeh-and-michael/">Aryeh Dvoretzky</a>.)</p>
<p>7. <a href="https://cms-math.net.technion.ac.il/prof-sergei-tabachnikov/">Distinguished lectures by <strong>Sergey Tabachnikov</strong>, January, 6, 8, 9 the Technion.</a></p>
<p>8. <a href="http://u.math.biu.ac.il/~schiff/wrkshpam25.html?fbclid=IwAR1kxSI4W9M1wCS0ebNUzF3d200d4QnYRRIlml4Y6bobjhn9fECgpufp44c">The Twenty-fifth Israeli Mini-Workshop in Applied and Computational Mathematics</a>, Wednesday December 25. Bar-Ilan University. Great line of speakers.</p>
<h2>Abel In Jerusalem, Sunday, January 12, 2020.</h2>
<p>The Einstein Institute of mathematics is happy to host the Abel in Jerusalem Conference. The location of the conference in Manchester House, Lecture Hall 2. Each year the Abel Committee holds a symposium where members of the Abel Committee and some of the world’s top mathematicians will be speaking. “Abel in Jerusalem” will be the 10th one-day conference with lectures aimed at a mathematically educated and interested audience, with the objective of increasing public awareness of mathematics and of the Abel Prize.</p>
<p>The day starts (09:40) with opening remarks by <strong>Hans Petter Graver</strong>, President of the Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters, followed by lectures by  <strong>Christopher Hacon</strong> (University of Utah) 10:00-11:00; <strong>Ulrike Tillmann</strong> (Oxford University) 11:30-12:30; <strong>Claire Voisin</strong> (Collège de France) 14:30-15:30; and <strong>François Labourie</strong> (Université Côte d’Azur) 16:00-17:00. Participation, including lunch, and reception at the King David Hotel is free but registration is needed. Organizers: <strong>Gil Kalai</strong> and <strong>Tamar Ziegler</strong>; For more detail <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/event/abel-jerusalem">see this page</a>. If you are interested in attending please <a href="https://forms.gle/fEL7KgQxE8hHtb9q8" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="">register here</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/abelinj.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18866" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/abelinj.png?w=640"/></a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-18T06:08:07Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-18T06:08:07Z</published>
    <category term="Algebra"/>
    <category term="Analysis"/>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Conferences"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <category term="Updates"/>
    <category term="Christopher Hacon"/>
    <category term="Claire Voisin"/>
    <category term="Fran&#xE7;ois Labourie"/>
    <category term="Ulrike Tillmann"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08045</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08045" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the I/O complexity of hybrid algorithms for Integer Multiplication</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576627200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Stefani:Lorenzo_De.html">Lorenzo De Stefani</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.08045">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Almost asymptotically tight lower bounds are derived for the I/O complexity
$IO\left(n,M\right)$ of a general class of hybrid algorithms computing the
product of two integers, each represented with $n$ digits in a given base $s$,
in a two-level storage hierarchy with $M$ words of fast memory, with different
digits stored in different memory words. The considered hybrid algorithm
combine the Toom-Cook-$k$ (or Toom-$k$) fast integer multiplication approach
with computational complexity $\Theta\left(c_kn^{\log_k
\left(2k-1\right)}\right)$, and "standard" integer multiplication algorithms
which compute $\Omega\left(n^2\right)$ digit multiplications.
</p>
<p>We present an $\Omega\left(\left(n/\max\{M,n_0\}\right)^{\log_k
\left(2k-1\right)}\left(\max\{1,n_0/M\}\right)^2M\right)$ lower bound for the
I/O complexity a class of "uniform, non-stationary" hybrid algorithms when
executed in a two-level storage hierarchy with $M$ words of fast memory, where
$n_0$ denotes the threshold size of sub-problems which are computed using
standard algorithms with algebraic complexity $\Omega\left(n^2\right)$.
</p>
<p>The lower bound is derived for the more general class of "non-uniform,
non-stationary" hybrid algorithms which allow recursive calls to have a
different structure, even when they refer to the multiplication of integers of
the same size and in the same recursive level including those where the value
of $k$ is allowed to vary with the level of recursion. As some hybrid
algorithms from this class execute a number of I/O operations that is within a
$O\left(k^2\right)$ multiplicative term of the corresponding lower bounds, the
proposed lower bounds are almost asymptotically tight and indeed tight for
constant values of $k$.
</p>
<p>Extensions of the lower bounds for a parallel model with $P$ processors are
also discussed.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-18T23:21:02Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08032</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08032" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Monotone 3-Sat-(2,2) is NP-complete</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576627200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/D=ouml=cker:Janosch.html">Janosch Döcker</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.08032">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We show that Monotone 3-Sat remains NP-complete if (i) each clause contains
exactly three distinct variables, (ii) each clause is unique, i.e., there are
no duplicates of the same clause, and (iii), amongst the clauses, each variable
appears unnegated exactly twice and negated exactly twice. Darmann and D\"ocker
[6] recently showed that this variant of Monotone 3-Sat is either trivial or
NP-complete. In the first part of the paper, we construct an unsatisfiable
instance which answers one of their open questions (Challenge 1) and places the
problem in the latter category.
</p>
<p>Then, we adapt gadgets used in the construction to (1) sketch two reductions
that establish NP-completeness in a more direct way, and (2), to show that
$\forall\exists$ 3-SAT remains $\Pi_2^P$-complete for quantified Boolean
formulas with the following properties: (a) each clause is monotone (i.e., no
clause contains an unnegated and a negated variable) and contains exactly three
distinct variables, (b) each universal variable appears exactly once unnegated
and exactly once negated, (c) each existential variable appears exactly twice
unnegated and exactly twice negated, and (d) the number of universal and
existential variables is equal. Furthermore, we show that the variant where (b)
is replaced with (b') each universal variable appears exactly twice unnegated
and exactly twice negated, and where (a), (c) and (d) are unchanged, is
$\Pi_2^P$-complete as well. Thereby, we improve upon two recent results by
D\"ocker et al. [8] that establish $\Pi_2^P$-completeness of these variants in
the non-monotone setting.
</p>
<p>We also discuss a special case of Monotone 3-Sat-(2,2) that corresponds to a
variant of Not-All-Equal Sat, and we show that all such instances are
satisfiable.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-18T23:20:29Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07992</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07992" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Power of Programs over Monoids in J</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576627200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grosshans:Nathan.html">Nathan Grosshans</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.07992">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The model of programs over (finite) monoids, introduced by Barrington and
Th{\'e}rien, gives an interesting way to characterise the circuit complexity
class $\mathsf{NC^1}$ and its subclasses and showcases deep connections with
algebraic automata theory. In this article, we investigate the computational
power of programs over monoids in $\mathbf{J}$, a small variety of finite
aperiodic monoids. First, we give a fine hierarchy within the class of
languages recognised by programs over monoids from $\mathbf{J}$, based on the
length of programs but also some parametrisation of $\mathbf{J}$. Second, and
most importantly, we make progress in understanding what regular languages can
be recognised by programs over monoids in $\mathbf{J}$. We show that those
programs actually can recognise all languages from a class of restricted
dot-depth one languages, using a non-trivial trick, and conjecture that this
class suffices to characterise the regular languages recognised by programs
over monoids in $\mathbf{J}$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-18T23:20:44Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07957</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07957" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximating MIS over equilateral $B_1$-VPG graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576627200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lahiri:Abhiruk.html">Abhiruk Lahiri</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mukherjee:Joydeep.html">Joydeep Mukherjee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Subramanian:C=_R=.html">C. R. Subramanian</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.07957">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present an approximation algorithm for the maximum independent set (MIS)
problem over the class of equilateral $B_1$-VPG graphs. These are intersection
graphs of $L$-shaped planar objects % (and their rotations by multiples of
$90^o$) with both arms of each object being equal. We obtain a $36(\log
2d)$-approximate algorithm running in $O(n(\log n)^2)$ time for this problem,
where $d$ is the ratio $d_{max}/d_{min}$ and $d_{max}$ and $d_{min}$ denote
respectively the maximum and minimum length of any arm in the input equilateral
$L$-representation of the graph. In particular, we obtain $O(1)$-factor
approximation of MIS for $B_1$-VPG -graphs for which the ratio $d$ is bounded
by a constant. % formed by unit length $L$-shapes. In fact, algorithm can be
generalized to an $O(n(\log n)^2)$ time and a $36(\log 2d_x)(\log
2d_y)$-approximate MIS algorithm over arbitrary $B_1$-VPG graphs. Here, $d_x$
and $d_y$ denote respectively the analogues of $d$ when restricted to only
horizontal and vertical arms of members of the input. This is an improvement
over the previously best $n^\epsilon$-approximate algorithm \cite{FoxP} (for
some fixed $\epsilon&gt;0$), unless the ratio $d$ is exponentially large in $n$.
In particular, $O(1)$-approximation of MIS is achieved for graphs with
$\max\{d_x,d_y\}=O(1)$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-18T23:20:20Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07820</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07820" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Balancing the Tradeoff Between Clustering Value and Interpretability</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576627200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saisubramanian:Sandhya.html">Sandhya Saisubramanian</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Galhotra:Sainyam.html">Sainyam Galhotra</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zilberstein:Shlomo.html">Shlomo Zilberstein</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.07820">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Graph clustering groups entities -- the vertices of a graph -- based on their
similarity, typically using a complex distance function over a large number of
features. Successful integration of clustering approaches in automated
decision-support systems hinges on the interpretability of the resulting
clusters. This paper addresses the problem of generating interpretable
clusters, given features of interest that signify interpretability to an
end-user, by optimizing interpretability in addition to common clustering
objectives. We propose a $\beta$-interpretable clustering algorithm that
ensures that at least $\beta$ fraction of nodes in each cluster share the same
feature value. The tunable parameter $\beta$ is user-specified. We also present
a more efficient algorithm for scenarios with $\beta\!=\!1$ and analyze the
theoretical guarantees of the two algorithms. Finally, we empirically
demonstrate the benefits of our approaches in generating interpretable clusters
using four real-world datasets. The interpretability of the clusters is
complemented by generating simple explanations denoting the feature values of
the nodes in the clusters, using frequent pattern mining.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07673</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07673" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Finding the Mode of a Kernel Density Estimate</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576627200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lee:Jasper_C=_H=.html">Jasper C. H. Lee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Jerry.html">Jerry Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Musco:Christopher.html">Christopher Musco</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Phillips:Jeff_M=.html">Jeff M. Phillips</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tai:Wai_Ming.html">Wai Ming Tai</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.07673">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given points $p_1, \dots, p_n$ in $\mathbb{R}^d$, how do we find a point $x$
which maximizes $\frac{1}{n} \sum_{i=1}^n e^{-\|p_i - x\|^2}$? In other words,
how do we find the maximizing point, or mode of a Gaussian kernel density
estimation (KDE) centered at $p_1, \dots, p_n$? Given the power of KDEs in
representing probability distributions and other continuous functions, the
basic mode finding problem is widely applicable. However, it is poorly
understood algorithmically. Few provable algorithms are known, so practitioners
rely on heuristics like the "mean-shift" algorithm, which are not guaranteed to
find a global optimum. We address this challenge by providing fast and provably
accurate approximation algorithms for mode finding in both the low and high
dimensional settings. For low dimension $d$, our main contribution is to reduce
the mode finding problem to a solving a small number of systems of polynomial
inequalities. For high dimension $d$, we prove the first dimensionality
reduction result for KDE mode finding, which allows for reduction to the low
dimensional case. Our result leverages Johnson-Lindenstrauss random projection,
Kirszbraun's classic extension theorem, and perhaps surprisingly, the
mean-shift heuristic for mode finding.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07629</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07629" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Learning Mixtures of Linear Regressions in Subexponential Time via Fourier Moments</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576627200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Sitan.html">Sitan Chen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Jerry.html">Jerry Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Song:Zhao.html">Zhao Song</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.07629">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the problem of learning a mixture of linear regressions (MLRs).
An MLR is specified by $k$ nonnegative mixing weights $p_1, \ldots, p_k$
summing to $1$, and $k$ unknown regressors $w_1,...,w_k\in\mathbb{R}^d$. A
sample from the MLR is drawn by sampling $i$ with probability $p_i$, then
outputting $(x, y)$ where $y = \langle x, w_i \rangle + \eta$, where
$\eta\sim\mathcal{N}(0,\varsigma^2)$ for noise rate $\varsigma$. Mixtures of
linear regressions are a popular generative model and have been studied
extensively in machine learning and theoretical computer science. However, all
previous algorithms for learning the parameters of an MLR require running time
and sample complexity scaling exponentially with $k$.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we give the first algorithm for learning an MLR that runs in
time which is sub-exponential in $k$. Specifically, we give an algorithm which
runs in time $\widetilde{O}(d)\cdot\exp(\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{k}))$ and outputs
the parameters of the MLR to high accuracy, even in the presence of nontrivial
regression noise. We demonstrate a new method that we call "Fourier moment
descent" which uses univariate density estimation and low-degree moments of the
Fourier transform of suitable univariate projections of the MLR to iteratively
refine our estimate of the parameters. To the best of our knowledge, these
techniques have never been used in the context of high dimensional distribution
learning, and may be of independent interest. We also show that our techniques
can be used to give a sub-exponential time algorithm for learning mixtures of
hyperplanes, a natural hard instance of the subspace clustering problem.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07600</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07600" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Trapezoidal Sketch: A Sketch Structure for Frequency Estimation of Data Streams</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576627200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Ning.html">Ning Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Zhaoxin.html">Zhaoxin Zhang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Du:Wan.html">Wan Du</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Alex_X=.html">Alex X. Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Rui.html">Rui Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yuan:Xin.html">Xin Yuan</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.07600">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The sketch is one of the typical and widely used data structures for
estimating the frequencies of items in data streams. However, since the counter
sizes in the traditional rectangular-structure sketch (rstructure sketch) are
the same, it is hard to achieve small space usage, high capacity (i.e., the
maximum counter size of the sketch), and high estimation accuracy
simultaneously. Moreover, when considering the high skewness of data streams,
this will become even worse [15]. Therefore, in this paper, we firstly propose
the trapezoidal-structure sketch (t-structure sketch). In the t-structure
sketch, different from the r-structure sketch, the counter sizes in different
layers are different. Based on this innovation, the low space usage and high
capacity can be achieved simultaneously in the t-structure sketch. Then, based
on the basic t-structure sketch, we propose the space saving t-structure sketch
and the capacity improvement t-structure sketch, and analyze the properties of
these two t-structure sketches. Finally, considering the estimation accuracy in
the original version of the t-structure sketch is slightly worse than that in
the r-structure sketch, we propose the probabilistic based estimation error
reducing algorithm to improve the estimation accuracy in t-structure sketch.
Compared with the CM sketch, CU sketch, C sketch, and A sketch, the simulation
results show that the performances on space usage, capacity, and estimation
accuracy are improved successfully by t-structure sketch.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-18T23:21:03Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07599</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.07599" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Game Theory based Joint Task Offloading and Resources Allocation Algorithm for Mobile Edge Computing</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1576627200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yan:Jianen.html">Jianen Yan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Ning.html">Ning Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Zhaoxin.html">Zhaoxin Zhang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Alex_X=.html">Alex X. Liu</a>, Jose Fernan Martinez, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yuan:Xin.html">Xin Yuan</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.07599">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Mobile edge computing (MEC) has emerged for reducing energy consumption and
latency by allowing mobile users to offload computationally intensive tasks to
the MEC server. Due to the spectrum reuse in small cell network, the inter-cell
interference has a great effect on MEC performances. In this paper, for
reducing the energy consumption and latency of MEC, we propose a game theory
based approach to join task offloading decision and resources allocation
together in the MEC system. In this algorithm, the offloading decision, the CPU
capacity adjustment, the transmission power control, and the network
interference management of mobile users are regarded as a game. In this game,
based on the best response strategy, each mobile user makes their own utility
maximum rather than the utility of the whole system. We prove that this game is
an exact potential game and the Nash equilibrium (NE) of this game exists. For
reaching the NE, the best response approach is applied. We calculate the best
response of these three variables. Moreover, we investigate the properties of
this algorithm, including the convergence, the computational complexity, and
the Price of anarchy (PoA). The theoretical analysis shows that the inter-cell
interference affects on the performances of MEC greatly. The NE of this game is
Pareto efficiency. Finally, we evaluate the performances of this algorithm by
simulation. The simulation results illustrate that this algorithm is effective
in improving the performances of the multi-user MEC system.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-12-18T23:38:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-12-18T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/17/faculty-position-in-algorithms-and-complexity-at-university-of-edinburgh-apply-by-january-31-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/17/faculty-position-in-algorithms-and-complexity-at-university-of-edinburgh-apply-by-january-31-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty Position in Algorithms and Complexity at University of Edinburgh (apply by January 31, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The School of Informatics at the University of Edinburgh invites applicants for Lecturer (“Assistant Professor”), and Reader (“Associate Professor”) in Algorithms and Complexity for Optimisation. For a full advert for the post, and how to apply, please see the link below. Website: https://www.vacancies.ed.ac.uk/pls/corehrrecruit/erq_jobspec_version_4.jobspec?p_id=050688 Email: kousha@inf.ed.ac.uk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The School of Informatics at the University of Edinburgh invites applicants for Lecturer (“Assistant Professor”), and Reader (“Associate Professor”) in Algorithms and Complexity for Optimisation.</p>
<p>For a full advert for the post, and how to apply, please see the link below.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.vacancies.ed.ac.uk/pls/corehrrecruit/erq_jobspec_version_4.jobspec?p_id=050688">https://www.vacancies.ed.ac.uk/pls/corehrrecruit/erq_jobspec_version_4.jobspec?p_id=050688</a><br/>
Email: kousha@inf.ed.ac.uk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-17T18:42:14Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-17T18:42:14Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16469</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/15/an-ancient-conjecture-on-primes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Ancient Conjecture on Primes</title>
    <summary>After 50 years we still are baffled by the primes. Cornell faculty album source Juris Hartmanis needs no introduction. But we can note this long interview last February by the Heidelberg Laureate Foundation. His sister, Astrid Ivask, was a world–recognized poet. Today Ken and I wish to discuss one of his old conjectures. We have […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>After 50 years we still are baffled by the primes.</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hartmaniswhiteboard-1.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16473" height="200" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hartmaniswhiteboard-1.png?w=134&amp;h=200" width="134"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Cornell faculty album <a href="https://digital.library.cornell.edu/catalog/ss:547397">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Juris Hartmanis needs no introduction. But we can note this long <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AxbKu7MrqA4">interview</a> last February by the Heidelberg Laureate Foundation. His sister, Astrid Ivask, was a <a href="https://www.worldliteraturetoday.org/blog/literary-tributes/tribute-astrid-ivask-literary-light">world</a>–<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astrid_Ivask">recognized</a> poet.</p>
<p>
Today Ken and I wish to discuss one of his old conjectures.</p>
<p>
We have previously discussed one of his conjectures <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2009/02/24/a-conjecture-of-hartmanis/">here</a>. The conjecture we are interested in his one made in his joint <a href="https://ecommons.cornell.edu/handle/1813/5864">paper</a> with Herbert Shank titled, “On the Recognition of Primes by Automata.”</p>
<p>
Shank once wrote a paper <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-symbolic-logic/article/on-the-undecidability-of-finite-planar-cubic-graphs1/84518469D4AF1774ADE070EBA56601C9">On the undecidability of finite planar cubic graphs</a> with Solomon Garfunkel. I, Dick, liked this paper because it honestly pointed out that a predecessor paper by them was erroneous:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> In the March, 1971 issue of this Journal (JSL) a paper of ours was published purporting to prove the hereditary undecidability of the first-order theory of finite planar graphs. The proof presented there contains an error which is unfortunately “unfixable” by the methods of that paper. The theorem however is true and we demonstrate here a generalization to finite cubic (exactly three edges at each vertex) planar graphs. The method involves coding the halting problem for a Turing machine into the theory of these graphs by considering special printouts of computations. Let us first consider a discussion of the aforementioned mistake and see what can be learned from it <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\dots}"/> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Primality Space Conjecture </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Hartmanis and Shank (HS) asked the following conjecture—over fifty years ago—about testing whether an integer is a prime number: </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  01,11,101,111,1101,1011,10001, \dots " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++01%2C11%2C101%2C111%2C1101%2C1011%2C10001%2C+%5Cdots+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  01,11,101,111,1101,1011,10001, \dots "/></p>
<p>We’ve written them in binary notation with the ones’ place first—just the way to give numbers on the input tape of a Turing machine. No error in their Turing representation here—just their brilliant conjecture connecting space to number theory: Suppose that primality is computed in space <img alt="{S(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S(n)}"/>. Then 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  S(n) \ge cn, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++S%28n%29+%5Cge+cn%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  S(n) \ge cn, "/></p>
<p>for some <img alt="{c&gt;0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%3E0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c&gt;0}"/>. That is, any primality test must take linear space. </p>
<p>
As usual, space is the measure of how much storage the algorithm must use. The input tape is read-only and does count against the storage bound. The famous AKS primality test showed that whether a given <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-bit number <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> is prime can be determined in <img alt="{n^{O(1)}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7BO%281%29%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n^{O(1)}}"/> time but did not improve the linear upper bound on space, which HS showed by trivial means: Try all possible divisors between <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/> and <img alt="{\sqrt{x}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7Bx%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{x}}"/>. The arithmetic and loop for this method can all be conducted in <img alt="{O(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n)}"/> space.</p>
<p>
What is some intuition for this conjecture? Why insist the space be <em>linear</em> when <img alt="{n^{1-\epsilon}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7B1-%5Cepsilon%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n^{1-\epsilon}}"/> space is plenty—given that polynomial time could still be equal to logspace? Well, suppose <img alt="{S(n) \ll n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%28n%29+%5Cll+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S(n) \ll n}"/> and consider the integers <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> from <img alt="{2^{n-1}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7Bn-1%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{n-1}}"/> to <img alt="{2^n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5En%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^n}"/>, that is all having <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> bits in binary notation. The number of machine configurations apart from the content <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> of the input tape is at most:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<img alt="{2^{O(S(n))}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7BO%28S%28n%29%29%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{O(S(n))}}"/> possible contents of the <img alt="{S(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S(n)}"/> worktape cells, times <p/>
</li><li>
<img alt="{n+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n+1}"/> input head positions, times <img alt="{S(n)+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%28n%29%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S(n)+1}"/> or so worktape head positions, times <p/>
</li><li>
the finite number of states.
</li></ul>
<p>
This is <img alt="{\ll N = 2^n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cll+N+%3D+2%5En%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\ll N = 2^n}"/>. In fact, it is <img alt="{\ll \frac{N}{n} = \frac{N}{\ln N}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cll+%5Cfrac%7BN%7D%7Bn%7D+%3D+%5Cfrac%7BN%7D%7B%5Cln+N%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\ll \frac{N}{n} = \frac{N}{\ln N}}"/> which is asymptotically the number of those <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> that are prime according to the Prime Number Theorem. This means that the vast majority of prime numbers have <em>no</em> worktape configuration that is unique to their accepting computation, not even close. Thus each configuration would be shared with many other primes—and most would be shared with many non-primes as well. Whereas many non-primes are composite for the same reason—such as all strings beginning with <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0}"/> being even—the intuition is that each prime has its distinct track of reasons that ought not to come together with other primes.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Less Space </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The HS paper notes that since the set of primes is not regular, it needs at least order-of <img alt="{\log\log(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog%5Clog%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log\log(n)}"/> space. This is a weak lower bound. </p>
<p>
Both the bound and the above intuition become sharper if we require that the input tape be <em>one-way</em> as well as read-only: its head cannot go left to re-read lower-order bits. Every non-regular language requires order-of <img alt="{\log(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log(n)}"/> space by such 1-way machines. </p>
<p>
If we write the prime numbers in unary notation—that is, <img alt="{\{0^m : m \text{ is prime}\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%7B0%5Em+%3A+m+%5Ctext%7B+is+prime%7D%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\{0^m : m \text{ is prime}\}}"/>—then we can prove they cannot be recognized by a machine <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{M}"/> in <img alt="{o(\log m)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bo%28%5Clog+m%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{o(\log m)}"/> space. Having the input tape be unary makes the whole computation depend on the configuration of <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{M}"/> as described above. In consequence, <img alt="{L(M)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%28M%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L(M)}"/> has infinite arithmetic progressions of accepted strings. But by the celebrated theorem of Gustav Dirichlet, each such progression contains infinitely many primes as well as infinitely-many non-primes.  </p>
<p>
Scaling back from unary to binary seems to scale the space up to linear, so perhaps this result supports the HS conjecture. HS make related observations about log space and the density of the primes in the paper.  On the other hand, polynomial time could still be equal to logspace (with two-way input tape), which would make their conjecture wrong. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Another Prime Conjecture </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We believe that the HS conjecture is hard, is related to some interesting questions, and could be false. That is, there might be some way to check that a number is prime in <img alt="{o(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bo%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{o(n)}"/> space. Proving lower bounds on space remains, after many decades, hopeless.</p>
<p>
Here is a related conjecture. Using the same binary representation as above—where <img alt="{1011}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1011%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1011}"/> is 13 and <img alt="{10001}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B10001%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{10001}"/> is 17—Jeffrey Shallit has <a href="https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/~shallit/Talks/bc4.pdf">asked</a> whether we can determine whether a given finite automaton accepts <i>some</i> input so that it is a prime number. We believe it is still open. Let’s assume for the moment that it is true. Then we can solve some open questions in number theory related to primes. This problem unlike the HS is worth some money. For example, the above would pay 50 British pounds—about $66.62. </p>
<p>
Jeff points out that if the above is decidable then one can solve the famous problem: Are there any Fermat primes that are not known? Recall a Fermat prime is one of the form 	 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  2^{2^{\ell}} + 1. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++2%5E%7B2%5E%7B%5Cell%7D%7D+%2B+1.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  2^{2^{\ell}} + 1. "/></p>
<p>The largest one known is </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  2^{2^{4}} + 1 = 65,\!537." class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++2%5E%7B2%5E%7B4%7D%7D+%2B+1+%3D+65%2C%5C%21537.&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  2^{2^{4}} + 1 = 65,\!537."/></p>
<p>All such primes match the regular expression <img alt="{10^*1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B10%5E%2A1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{10^*1}"/> in binary notation, which is easy for a finite automaton to recognize. This expression matches numbers of the form <img alt="{2^k + 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5Ek+%2B+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^k + 1}"/>, but as we discussed <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/06/01/almost-fermat-primes/">here</a>, they can be prime only when <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k}"/> is a power of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/>.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Why are simple complexity questions about primes so hard? Why indeed?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-15T22:46:56Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T22:46:56Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="primes"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="complexity"/>
    <category term="conjecture"/>
    <category term="Hartmanis"/>
    <category term="Herbert Shank"/>
    <category term="space complexity"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-asynchrony-uncommitted-lower-bound/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-asynchrony-uncommitted-lower-bound/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The FLP Impossibility, Asynchronous Consensus Lower Bound via Uncommitted Configurations</title>
    <summary>In this third post, we conclude with the celebrated Fischer, Lynch, and Paterson impossibility result from 1985. It is the fundamental lower bound for consensus in the asynchronous model. Theorem 1 (FLP85): Any protocol $\mathcal{P}$ solving consensus in the asynchronous model that is resilient to even just one crash failure...</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-15T17:15:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T17:15:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Ittai Abraham</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T07:22:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-synchrony-uncommitted-lower-bound/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-synchrony-uncommitted-lower-bound/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Synchronous Consensus Lower Bound via Uncommitted Configurations</title>
    <summary>In this second post, we show the fundamental lower bound on the number of rounds for consensus protocols in the synchronous model. Theorem 1: Any protocol solving consensus in the synchronous model that is resilient to $t$ crash failures must have an execution with at least $t+1$ rounds. Bad news:...</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-15T17:05:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T17:05:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Ittai Abraham</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T07:22:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-consensus-model-for-FLP/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-consensus-model-for-FLP/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Consensus Lower Bounds via Uncommitted Configurations</title>
    <summary>In this series of three posts, we discuss two of the most important consensus lower bounds: Lamport, Fischer [1982]: any protocol solving consensus in the synchronous model that is resilient to $t$ crash failures must have an execution with at least $t+1$ rounds. Fischer, Lynch, and Patterson [1983, 1985]: any...</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-15T17:03:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T17:03:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Ittai Abraham</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T07:22:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/12/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/12/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>Figures show 11,000 academics have left UK universities in the three years since the Brexit referendum.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/education/2019/dec/01/lib-dems-brexit-brain-drain-eu-academics">Figures show 11,000 academics have left UK universities in the three years since the Brexit referendum</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2019-12-02/american-computer-expert-arrested-north-korea-talk-cryptocurrency">US arrests an American computer scientist for giving a talk at a conference</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103242730915859586"/>). It was in North Korea, on cryptocurrency, but from the story doesn’t appear to have covered anything that isn’t widely known elsewhere.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Mathematicians get riled up about mandatory diversity statements and recommendations that above-average contributions to diversity be used as a hard filter for all faculty job candidates (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103248639071738786"/>, <a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2019/11/19/mathematician-comes-out-against-mandatory-diversity-statements-while-others-say-they">via</a>, <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@pkra/103237286846736065">via2</a>, <a href="https://cybre.space/@zardoz/103310868212435260">via3</a>): <a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/201911/rnoti-p1778.pdf">Abigail Thompson sees mandated loyalty to political positions (such as prioritizing diversity) as anti-academic freedom</a>, kicking off the debate. <a href="https://ilaba.wordpress.com/2019/12/01/diversity-statements/">Izabella Laba disagrees but prefers institutional action to lip-service statements of good intentions</a> and argues that unrealistic expectations on faculty (like that they all be simultaneously outstanding in teaching, research, and now also diversity) can backfire by favoring the kind of male faculty member who takes advantage of an unpaid wife as his assistant. <a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/202001/rnoti-o1.pdf">Many others weigh in</a> in the letters to the editor of the <em>Notices</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.chronicle.com/article/5-Ways-to-Welcome-Women-to/247541">Five ways to welcome women to computer science</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103256355399857427"/>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://theaggie.org/2019/12/05/yuval-peres-math-professor-with-series-of-sexual-misconduct-allegations-levied-against-him-gives-lecture-at-uc-davis/">Davis student newspaper provides thorough roundup of sexual harassment charges against Yuval Peres</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103259258824223410"/>). They missed the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Sockpuppet_investigations/Pedantisch/Archive">side drama of sockpuppets and meatpuppets cleaning this from his Wikipedia article</a>, though, or maybe omitted it for lack of evidence connecting it to Peres himself. This is sad. Why would someone with so much to give to the field be so self-destructive and so destructive of the lives and careers of others around him?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>More stupid commercial journal publisher tricks (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103264128297632805"/>): Wiley won’t honor my institutional subscription unless I enable third-party cookies in my browser. So I can</p>

    <ol>
      <li>
        <p>decrease my browser security on all sites,</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>not read papers by László Babai on J. Graph Theory,</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>ask my librarian for a copy, making much more work and delay for all but maybe letting the publisher know how much negative value-added they’re providing, or</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>become a pirate.</p>
      </li>
    </ol>

    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sci-Hub">Sci-Hub</a> to the rescue! Yo ho!</p>

    <p>Also while I’m picking on Wiley, how did <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/cpe.5484">He et al., “A polynomial‐time algorithm for simple undirected graph isomorphism”</a> ever pass peer review for their journal <em>Concurrency and Computation, Practice and Experience</em>, or even a basic sanity check that it has a coherent topic that fits the mission of the journal?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/roots-of-unity/the-surprising-link-between-recreational-math-and-undecidability/">The surprising link between recreational math and undecidability</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103267941967518229"/>). Evelyn Lamb describes how a seemingly isolated fact about Fibonacci numbers () led to Matiyasevich’s solution to Hilbert’s 10th problem, that there is no general algorithm for solving Diophantine equations.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.maureeneppstein.com/mve_journal/?p=2028">My mother has a new book of poetry coming out</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103273857130169711"/>). I think this is her fifth, after Earthward (Finishing Line Press, 2014), Rogue Wave at Glass Beach (March Street Press, 2009), Quickening (March Street Press, 2007), and A Place Called Home (Monday Press, 1995).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Osculating_circles_of_the_Archimedean_spiral.svg">This image by Adam Majewski</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103279309793264877"/>) shows the osculating circles of an Archimedean spiral. The spiral itself is not shown, but you can see it anyway, where the circles become dense.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Osculating circles of the Archimedean spiral" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/archimedean-osculation.svg"/></p>

    <p>It is not unusual that the circles nest. By the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tait%E2%80%93Kneser_theorem">Tait–Kneser theorem</a> this happens whenever the curvature along a curve is monotonic. And on most smooth curves, the curvature is monotonic except at a small number of points called vertices.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://chalkdustmagazine.com/front-page-banner/constructing-the-cover-of-issue-10/">Chalkdust magazine provides a compass-and-straightedge construction for the girih pattern on the cover of a recent issue</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103284659404495472"/>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://twitter.com/textfiles/status/1204428311553642496">How archive.org preserves the history of the web, and why you should care</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103291205125122328"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21764592">via</a>). Meanwhile, <a href="https://modsandmembersblog.wordpress.com/2019/12/08/verizon-yahoo-bad-form/">Verizon sabotages efforts to archive Yahoo Groups content, in the face of their plans to shut much of it down</a> (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21737696">via</a>, <a href="https://boingboing.net/2019/12/08/oath-makes-you-swear-2.html">via2</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://randomascii.wordpress.com/2019/12/08/on2-again-now-in-wmi/"> in Windows Management Instrumentation</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103299014968956821"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21743424">via</a>). This is why understanding algorithm analysis is important: even when the constant factors are very small (here, a nine-instruction loop), quadratic time can mean significant delays. The post also introduces “Dawson’s first law of computing:  is the sweet spot of badly scaling algorithms: fast enough to make it into production, but slow enough to make things fall down once it gets there.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Two recently-posted geometry puzzles (neither of which I have seriously attempted to answer (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103304781327067493"/>):</p>

    <ol>
      <li>
        <p><a href="https://discrete-notes.github.io/polygon%20problem">If you expand a convex polygon along one coordinate axis while leaving the other coordinate unchanged, can the original polygon always fit into the expanded copy (perhaps with some rotation or translation)?</a></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/can-you-solve-a-particularly-prismatic-puzzle/">How many different integer rectangular cuboids have (ignoring units) volume = surface area?</a></p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/permutations/">John Baez collects more than you wanted to know about the statistics of random permutations</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103310641851251562"/>). The really pretty ones are Part 3 puzzle 8: What is the probability that a chosen element of an -element permutation lies in a cycle of length ? And part 6 puzzle 7 (don’t ask me how the numbering works): What is the expected number of -cycles in a random -element permutation?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://wild.maths.org/folding-fractions">Folding fractions</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103314218243317735"/>). There’s a standard compass-and-straightedge construction for dividing a line segment evenly into a given number of smaller segments, and origami folding constructions are (depending on the model of what is allowed) at least as powerful, so it shouldn’t be surprising that you can fold arbitrary even subdivisions of the side of an origami square. But this construction of  from  by Kazuo Haga is particularly elegant.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-15T15:41:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T15:41:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-12-16T00:37:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/182</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/182" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-182 |  The Limitations of Few Qubits: One-way and Two-way Quantum Finite Automata and the Group Word Problem | 

	Zachary Remscrim</title>
    <summary>The two-way finite automaton with quantum and classical states (2QCFA), defined by Ambainis and Watrous, is a model of quantum computation whose quantum part is extremely limited; however, as they showed, 2QCFA are surprisingly powerful: a 2QCFA with only a single-qubit can recognize the language $L_{pal}=\{w \in \{a,b\}^*:w \text{ is a palindrome}\}$ with bounded-error in expected exponential time. We prove that their result essentially cannot be improved upon: a 2QCFA (of any finite size) cannot recognize $L_{pal}$ with bounded-error in expected time $2^{o(n)}$, on inputs of length $n$. To our knowledge, this is the first example of a language that can be recognized with bounded-error by a 2QCFA in exponential time but not in subexponential time. A key tool in our result is a generalization to 2QCFA of a technical lemma that was used by Dwork and Stockmeyer to prove a lower bound on the expected running time of any two-way probabilistic finite automaton that recognizes a non-regular language with bounded-error. 

Furthermore, we prove strong lower bounds on the expected running time of any 2QCFA that recognizes a group word problem with bounded-error. In a recent paper, we showed that 2QCFA can recognize, with bounded-error, a broad class of group word problems in expected exponential time, and a more narrow class of group word problems in expected polynomial time. As a consequence, we can now exhibit a large family of natural languages that can be recognized with bounded-error by a 2QCFA in expected exponential time, but not in expected subexponential time. Moreover, we obtain significant progress towards a precise classification of those group word problems that can be recognized with bounded-error in expected polynomial time by a 2QCFA.

We also consider the one-way measure-once quantum finite automaton (1QFA), defined by Moore and Crutchfield, as well as a natural generalization to one-way measure-once finite automata with quantum and classical states (1QCFA). We precisely classify those groups whose word problem may be recognized with positive one-sided error (for both the bounded-error and unbounded-error cases) by a 1QFA or 1QCFA with any particular number of quantum states and any particular number of classical states; we also obtain partial results in the negative one-sided error case. As an immediate corollary, we show that allowing a 1QFA or 1QCFA to have even a single additional quantum or classical state enlarges the class of languages that may be recognized with positive one-sided error (of either type).</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-15T06:18:59Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T06:18:59Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/181</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/181" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-181 |  A Separator Theorem for Hypergraphs and a CSP-SAT Algorithm | 

	Navid Talebanfard, 

	Michal Koucky, 

	Vojtech Rodl</title>
    <summary>We show that for every $r \ge 2$ there exists $\epsilon_r &gt; 0$ such that any $r$-uniform hypergraph on $m$ edges with bounded vertex degree has a set of at most $(\frac{1}{2} - \epsilon_r)m$ edges the removal of which breaks the hypergraph into connected components with at most $m/2$ edges. We use this to give a satisfiability algorithm for $n$-variable $(d, k)$-CSPs in which every variable appears in at most $r$ constraints in time $d^{(1 - \epsilon_r)n}$ where $\epsilon_r$ depends only on $r$, provided that $k$ is small enough as a function of $m$. We will also show that unsatisfiable $(2, k)$-CSPs with variable frequency $r$ can be refuted in tree-like resolution in size $2^{(1 - \epsilon_r)n}$. Furthermore for Tseitin formulas on graphs with degree at most $k$ (which are $(2, k)$-CSPs) we give a deterministic algorithm finding such a refutation.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-13T14:39:31Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-13T14:39:31Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7376087648863245436</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7376087648863245436/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/why-is-there-no-all-encompassing-term.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7376087648863245436" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7376087648863245436" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/why-is-there-no-all-encompassing-term.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Why is there no all-encompassing term for a course on Models of Computation?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In my <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/what-do-you-call-your-ugrad-non.html">last blog post</a> I asked my readers to leave comments saying what the name of the course that has some of Regular Languages, Context Free Languages  Decideability, P, NP (any maybe other stuff) in it.  I suspected there would be many different names and their were. I was able to put all but 6 into 4 equivalence classes. So that's 10 names. Thats a lot  especially compared to<br/>
<br/>
(Introduction to) Algorithms<br/>
<br/>
and<br/>
<br/>
(Introduction to) Cryptography<br/>
<br/>
which I suspect have far fewer names. One commenter pointed out that the reason for the many different names is that there are many versions of the course. That's not quite an explanation since there are also many different versions of Cryptography---at UMCP  crypto is cross listed in THREE departments (CS, Math, EE) and its taught by 6 or so different people who don't talk to each other (I am one of them). I think Algorithms is more uniform across colleges.<br/>
<br/>
I think that terms Algorithms and Cryptography are both rather broad and can accommodate many versions of the courses, whereas no term seems to be agreed upon to encompass the DFA etc course.<br/>
Even saying DFA etc is not quite right since some of the courses spend little or even no time on DFA's.<br/>
<br/>
Below is a list of all the names I got and some comments. Note that some schools appear twice since they have two courses along these lines.<br/>
<br/>
-----------------------------------------<br/>
TITLE: (Introduction to) Theory of Computation:<br/>
<br/>
Swarthmore:                                            Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
UCSD:                                                     Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
Saint Michaels:                                        Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
Univ of Washington: Introduction to the Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
Waterloo:                  Introduction to the Theory of Computing<br/>
<br/>
COMMENT: Theory of Computation could have been the term that encompasses all of these courses. I speculate that it didn't catch on since it sounds too much like computability theory which is only one part of the course.<br/>
<br/>
------------------------<br/>
TITLE: Formal Languages and XXX<br/>
<br/>
CMU:                                                Formal Languages, Automata, and Computability<br/>
<br/>
Florida Tech:                                    Formal Languages and Automata Theory<br/>
<br/>
UC-Irvine:                                        Formal Languages and Automata Theory<br/>
<br/>
Univ of Chicago:    Introduction to Formal Languages<br/>
<br/>
University of Bucharest:                 Formal Language and Automata<br/>
<br/>
TU Darmstadt:                                Formal Foundations of CS I: Automata, Formal Languages, and Decidability<br/>
<br/>
TUK Germany:                               Formal Languages and Computability<br/>
<br/>
COMMENT: The title makes it sound like they don't cover P and NP. I do not know if thats true; however, I speculate that, it could never be the encompassing term.<br/>
<br/>
Spell Check things Automata and Computability are not words, but I've googled them and they seem to be words.<br/>
<br/>
--------------------------<br/>
TITLE: Computability/Decidability and Complexity/Intractability<br/>
<br/>
Reed College: Computability and Complexity<br/>
<br/>
Caltech:          Decidability and Intractability<br/>
<br/>
COMMENT: The title makes it sound like they don't cover regular or context free languages. I do not know if that's true; however, I speculate that, since the terms sound that way, they never caught on as the general term.<br/>
<br/>
Spellecheck thinks that neither Decidability nor Decideability is a word. Google seems to say that I should leave out the e, so I will.<br/>
<br/>
------------------------------<br/>
TITLE:  Blah MODELS Blah<br/>
<br/>
Tel-Aviv (a long time ago) Computational Models<br/>
<br/>
UIUC:                               Algorithms and Models of Computation (also has some algorithms in it)<br/>
<br/>
Waterloo:                                                   Models of Computation (enriched version)<br/>
<br/>
COMMENT: Models of Computation sounds like a good name for the course! Too bad it didn't catch on.  It would also be able to withstand changes in the content like more on parallelism or more on communication complexity.<br/>
<br/>
------------------------------<br/>
TITLE: MISC<br/>
<br/>
CMU:                                          Great Ideas in Theoretical Computer Science<br/>
<br/>
UCLouvain (Belgium)                Calculabilite (Computability)<br/>
<br/>
Moscow Inst. of  Phy. and Tech.: Mathematical logic and Theory of Algorithms<br/>
<br/>
Portland State University:            Computational Structures<br/>
<br/>
Germany:                                     Informatik III (Not all of Germany)<br/>
<br/>
Univ of Chicago:                         Introduction to Complexity<br/>
<br/>
COMMENT: All of these terms are to narrow to have served as a general term.<br/>
<div>
<br/></div>
<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-12T20:24:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-12T20:24:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T05:51:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/12/postdoc-at-university-of-illinois-at-chicago-apply-by-december-31-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/12/postdoc-at-university-of-illinois-at-chicago-apply-by-december-31-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at University of Illinois at Chicago (apply by December 31, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The MSCS department has an opening for a 3-year postdoc in the “Foundations of Data Science” under its newly received TRIPODS grant. All areas of TCS related to data science (broadly interpreted) will be considered. The position carries a teaching load of 1 graduate course per year and a competitive salary. For more information on […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The MSCS department has an opening for a 3-year postdoc in the “Foundations of Data Science” under its newly received TRIPODS grant.</p>
<p>All areas of TCS related to data science (broadly interpreted) will be considered. The position carries a teaching load of 1 graduate course per year and a competitive salary.</p>
<p>For more information on UIC’s TRIPODS center, visit: <a href="https://tripods.uic.edu/">https://tripods.uic.edu/</a></p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.mathjobs.org/jobs/jobs/15259">https://www.mathjobs.org/jobs/jobs/15259</a><br/>
Email: lreyzin@uic.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-12T17:34:01Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-12T17:34:01Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/12/faculty-position-in-quantum-information-at-harvard-university-apply-by-december-15-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/12/faculty-position-in-quantum-information-at-harvard-university-apply-by-december-15-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty position in Quantum Information at Harvard University (apply by December 15, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The Harvard Quantum Initiative, Departments of Physics, Chemistry and the SEAS areas of Computer Science and Electrical Engineering seek to appoint a tenure-track professor in the broad theoretical domain of quantum information. Areas of interest may include but are not limited to quantum algorithms, communication, complexity, control, and the physics of quantum information systems. Website: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Harvard Quantum Initiative, Departments of Physics, Chemistry and the SEAS areas of Computer Science and Electrical Engineering seek to appoint a tenure-track professor in the broad theoretical domain of quantum information. Areas of interest may include but are not limited to quantum algorithms, communication, complexity, control, and the physics of quantum information systems.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicpositions.harvard.edu/postings/9396">https://academicpositions.harvard.edu/postings/9396</a><br/>
Email: cploucha@fas.harvard.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-12T15:18:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-12T15:18:19Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/12/faculty-at-iowa-state-university-apply-by-january-13-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/12/faculty-at-iowa-state-university-apply-by-january-13-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty at Iowa State University (apply by January 13, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at Iowa State University seeks applicants for a faculty position at the rank of tenure-track Assistant Professor or tenured Associate Professor. We are specifically looking for experts in artificial intelligence, AI decision theory, foundations of machine learning, algorithmic foundations for data science, and algorithmic game theory. Website: https://isu.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/IowaStateJobs/job/Ames-IA/Assistant-or-Associate-Professor-of-Computer-Science_R1252 Email: mkcrum@iastate.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at Iowa State University seeks applicants for a faculty position at the rank of tenure-track Assistant Professor or tenured Associate Professor. We are specifically looking for experts in artificial intelligence, AI decision theory, foundations of machine learning, algorithmic foundations for data science, and algorithmic game theory.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://isu.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/IowaStateJobs/job/Ames-IA/Assistant-or-Associate-Professor-of-Computer-Science_R1252">https://isu.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/IowaStateJobs/job/Ames-IA/Assistant-or-Associate-Professor-of-Computer-Science_R1252</a><br/>
Email: mkcrum@iastate.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-12T15:16:10Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-12T15:16:10Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/12/postdoc-at-the-chinese-university-of-hong-kong-apply-by-january-15-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/12/postdoc-at-the-chinese-university-of-hong-kong-apply-by-january-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at The Chinese University of Hong Kong (apply by January 15, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Institute of Theoretical Computer Science and Communications at CUHK is offering positions for postdoctoral fellows whose expertise is in complexity theory, algorithms, information theory, coding theory, cryptography, and other theoretical topics in related areas. The position is for 12 months, renewable for another 12 months subject to satisfactory progress. Website: http://www.itcsc.cuhk.edu.hk/Openings.html Email: itcsc@cuhk.edu.hk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Institute of Theoretical Computer Science and Communications at CUHK is offering positions for postdoctoral fellows whose expertise is in complexity theory, algorithms, information theory, coding theory, cryptography, and other theoretical topics in related areas. The position is for 12 months, renewable for another 12 months subject to satisfactory progress.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://www.itcsc.cuhk.edu.hk/Openings.html">http://www.itcsc.cuhk.edu.hk/Openings.html</a><br/>
Email: itcsc@cuhk.edu.hk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-12T06:49:34Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-12T06:49:34Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/09/tenure-track-faculty-at-university-of-illinois-at-chicago-apply-by-january-13-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/09/tenure-track-faculty-at-university-of-illinois-at-chicago-apply-by-january-13-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure-Track Faculty at University of Illinois at Chicago (apply by January 13, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Mathematics (MSCS) department at UIC is looking for a tenure-track assistant professor to join the “Mathematical Computer Science” group. All areas of theoretical computer science will be considered. You can learn more about our TCS group on https://theory.cs.uic.edu/. Website: http://mathjobs.org/jobs/jobs/15229 Email: lreyzin@uic.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Mathematics (MSCS) department at UIC is looking for a tenure-track assistant professor to join the “Mathematical Computer Science” group. All areas of theoretical computer science will be considered.</p>
<p>You can learn more about our TCS group on <a href="https://theory.cs.uic.edu/.">https://theory.cs.uic.edu/.</a></p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://mathjobs.org/jobs/jobs/15229">http://mathjobs.org/jobs/jobs/15229</a><br/>
Email: lreyzin@uic.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-09T21:51:01Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-09T21:51:01Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://theorydish.blog/?p=1541</id>
    <link href="https://theorydish.blog/2019/12/09/quantum-dna-sequencing-the-ultimate-hardness-hypothesis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum DNA sequencing &amp; the ultimate hardness hypothesis</title>
    <summary>Longest common subsequence (LCS) and edit distance (ED) are fundamental similarity measures of interest to genomic applications (insertions/deletions/substitutions are a pretty good proxy for both mutations and read errors). The fastest known algorithms for computing the LCS/ED between two -character strings run in nearly quadratic time. Breakthroughs in fine-grained complexity [BI18][AHWW16] from the last few years provide some nice formal barriers further progress: in particular, substantially faster algorithms would refute NC-SETH, the hypothesis that given an NC circuit with input bits,  deciding if the circuit has any satisfying assignment requires time. (Note that this is a weaker, aka safer, hypothesis than the standard SETH.)   Quantum algorithms for edit distance? One way to try to circumvent the computational barriers is by approximation algorithms (see my blog post). A different approach is to go with quantum algorithms: Grover’s search can solve NC-SAT in time. Even those of us less skeptic than Gil Kalai can probably agree that quadratic quantum speedups won’t be practical anytime soon. But in theory, I find the question of whether we can design subquadratic quantum algorithms for edit distance very interesting (see also [BEG+18]). Alas, even with the power of quantum computers we don’t know any truly [...]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Longest common subsequence (LCS) and edit distance (ED) are fundamental similarity measures of interest to genomic applications (insertions/deletions/substitutions are a pretty good proxy for both mutations and read errors). The fastest known algorithms for computing the LCS/ED between two <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n"/>-character strings run in nearly quadratic time. Breakthroughs in fine-grained complexity <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1412.0348">[BI18]</a><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1511.06022">[AHWW16]</a> from the last few years provide some nice formal barriers further progress: in particular, substantially faster algorithms would refute <em>NC-SETH</em>, the hypothesis that given an NC circuit with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n"/> input bits,  deciding if the circuit has any satisfying assignment requires <img alt="2^{(1-o(1))n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2%5E%7B%281-o%281%29%29n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="2^{(1-o(1))n}"/> time. (Note that this is a weaker, aka safer, hypothesis than the standard SETH.)</p>
<p> </p>
<h2>Quantum algorithms for edit distance?</h2>
<p>One way to try to circumvent the computational barriers is by approximation algorithms (see my <a href="https://theorydish.blog/2018/07/20/approximating-edit-distance/">blog post</a>). A different approach is to go with quantum algorithms: Grover’s search can solve NC-SAT in <img alt="2^{n/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2%5E%7Bn%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="2^{n/2}"/> time. Even those of us less skeptic than <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/11/13/gils-collegial-quantum-supremacy-skepticism-faq/">Gil Kalai</a> can probably agree that quadratic quantum speedups won’t be practical anytime soon. But in theory, I find the question of whether we can design subquadratic quantum algorithms for edit distance very interesting (see also <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.04178">[BEG+18]</a>).</p>
<p>Alas, even with the power of quantum computers we don’t know any truly subquadratic algorithms for computing LCS/ED. On the other hand, it is not clear how to rule out even linear-time algorithms. A few weeks ago, Buhrman, Patro, and Speelman, posted a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.05686">paper</a> that gives a <img alt="n^{3/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B3%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n^{3/2}"/> quantum <em>query complexity </em>lower bound for LCS/ED.</p>
<blockquote><p>Open Problem: Close the <img alt="n^{3/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B3%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n^{3/2}"/> vs <img alt="n^2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n^2"/> gap for quantum query complexity of ED/LCS.</p></blockquote>
<p>What is “query complexity” of ED/LCS? Buhrman et al. consider the following query model: In LCS, we want a <strong>maximum monotone matching</strong> between the characters of the two strings, where we can match two characters if they’re identical. Now suppose that in the query complexity problem we still want to find a maximum monotone matching, but instead of the character-equality graph (which is a union of disjoint cliques), we have an arbitrary bipartite graph, and <strong>given a pair of vertices, the oracle tells you if there is an edge between them</strong>.</p>
<p>This model may seem a bit counter-intuitive at first since the graphs may not correspond to any pair of strings; and indeed other models have been considered before <a href="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=321922">[UAH76]</a><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1005.4033">[AKO10]</a>. But it turns out that this model is well-motivated by the NC-SETH lower bound (see discussion below).</p>
<p> </p>
<h2>The ultimate hardness hypothesis</h2>
<p>What does the <img alt="n^{3/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B3%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n^{3/2}"/> query complexity lower bound mean for algorithms on actual strings? Instead of a black box oracle, our algorithms have access to an NC-circuit that implements it. Intuitively, we don’t know how to do very much with white box circuits, so it seems plausible to hypothesize that the running time will be lower bound by the query complexity. In some sense, this is a special case of the following <em>ultimate hardness hypothesis </em>that unifies a lot of the computational hardness assumptions that we like to assume but have no idea how to prove (e.g. P!=NP, P!=BQP, NC-SETH, FP!=PPAD, etc):</p>
<blockquote><p>[Ultimate Hardness Hypothesis] For every problem, the white-box computational complexity is lower bounded by the black-box query complexity.”</p></blockquote>
<p>In communication complexity similar statements are known and are called simulation/lifting theorems (see e.g. <a href="https://theory.stanford.edu/~mika/thesis.pdf">Mika’s thesis</a>). For computational complexity, there are obvious counter examples such as “decide if the oracle can be implemented by a small circuit”. So it only makes sense to continue to assume the ultimate hardness hypothesis for “reasonable problems” instead of “every problem”.</p>
<p>But Burhman et al. identify the following variant of the ultimate hardness hypothesis which I find very interesting. It is defined with respect to a function <img alt="T:\{0,1\}^{2^n} \rightarrow \{0,1\}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=T%3A%5C%7B0%2C1%5C%7D%5E%7B2%5En%7D+%5Crightarrow+%5C%7B0%2C1%5C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="T:\{0,1\}^{2^n} \rightarrow \{0,1\}"/> which takes as input the truth-table of a circuit and outputs True or False. Roughly, they hypothesize that:</p>
<blockquote><p>[Burhman et al.-QSETH, paraphrased] For <em>every</em> <img alt="T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=T&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="T"/>, deciding if <img alt="T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=T&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="T"/> is true or false is as hard whether we’re given the actual circuit, or only the guarantee that the oracle is implemented by a small circuit”</p></blockquote>
<p>At a first read, I thought that arguments a-la impossibility of obfuscation <a href="https://www.iacr.org/archive/crypto2001/21390001.pdf">[BGI+01]</a> should refute this hypothesis, but a few weeks later I still don’t know how to prove it. Do you?</p>
<p> </p>
<h2>A tip for the upcoming holidays</h2>
<p>During my postdoc, I worked on the quantum query complexity of ED/LCS with Shalev Ben-David, Rolando La Placa, and John Wright. I was a bit bummed to find out that we got scooped by Buhrman et al, but I know of at least 3 other groups that were also scooped by the same paper, so at least we’re in good company <img alt="&#x1F642;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f642.png" style="height: 1em;"/></p>
<p>At the time, a fellow postdoc from Psychology asked me what I was working on. I resisted the temptation to try to explain the various quantum variants of NC-SETH, and instead told him I was working on “DNA sequencing with quantum computers”. His reaction was priceless. Regardless of what you’re actually working on, try this line during the holidays when your relatives ask you about your work.</p>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-09T18:20:46Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-09T18:20:46Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>aviad.rubinstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://theorydish.blog</id>
      <logo>https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/cropped-nightdish1.jpg?w=32</logo>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Stanford's CS Theory Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Theory Dish</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:21:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-693865784966232415</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/693865784966232415/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/what-do-you-call-your-ugrad-non.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/693865784966232415" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/693865784966232415" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/what-do-you-call-your-ugrad-non.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What do you call your ugrad non-algorithms theory course?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am in the process of reviewing<br/>
<br/>
<i>                     What can be computed: A Practical Guide to the Theory of Computation</i><br/>
<i>                     by John MacCormick</i><br/>
<br/>
<br/>
and I need YOUR help for the first SENTENCE.  I began by saying<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
                    This is a text book for a course on <i>Formal Language Theory</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
but then I realized that this is not what we call the course at UMCP. Then I got to thinking: what do other schools call it? I have the following so far:<br/>
<br/>
UMCP: Elementary Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
Harvard: Introduction to Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
MIT: Automata, Computability, and, Complexity<br/>
<br/>
Clark: Automata Theory<br/>
<br/>
(My spellcheck does not think Automata is a word. Also Computability. Usually I listen to my spellcheckers, but I checked and YES, I spelled them right.)<br/>
<br/>
For some other schools I either hit a place I needed an account, or I just got titles without a description so I could not be sure.<br/>
<br/>This is where YOU come in!<br/>
<br/>
Please leave comments with your school and the title of the course at your school that covers a reasonable overlap with: Regular Sets, Context Free Sets, Decidable and Undecidble and r.e. sets, P, NP, perhaps other complexity classes, and NP-completeness. Its FINE if your answer is one of the above ones, or one of the other comments--- I plan to later set this up as a pigeonhole principle problem.<br/>
<br/>
I suspect that courses in algorithms are called <i>Algorithms </i>or <i>Introduction to Algorithms.</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
I suspect that courses in cryptography are called <i>Cryptography </i><i> </i>or <i>Intro to Cryptography.</i><br/>
<br/>
<br/>
Why does the non-algorithm, non-crypto theory course have more names?<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<i><br/></i>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-09T04:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-09T04:00:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T05:51:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16454</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/08/hctor-garcia-molina-1953-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Héctor Garcia-Molina, 1953–2019</title>
    <summary>We all lost a great person Cropped from Mexican NotiCyTI obit Héctor Garcia-Molina died just before Thanksgiving. He was a computer scientist and Professor in both the Departments of Computer Science and Electrical Engineering at Stanford University. Today Ken and I write in sadness about his passing and to express some personal appreciations. We at […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>We all lost a great person</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/29-11-19-molina.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16456" height="180" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/29-11-19-molina.jpg?w=165&amp;h=180" width="165"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Cropped from Mexican NotiCyTI <a href="https://noticyti.com/politica-cyt-i/742-muere-h%C3%A9ctor-garc%C3%ADa-molina,-el-mexicano-que-contribuy%C3%B3-al-estrellato-de-google-y-cisco.html">obit</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Héctor Garcia-Molina <a href="https://news.stanford.edu/2019/12/06/hector-garcia-molina-influential-computer-scientist-database-expert-dies-65/">died</a> just before Thanksgiving. He was a computer scientist and Professor in both the Departments of Computer Science and Electrical Engineering at Stanford University.</p>
<p>
Today Ken and I write in sadness about his passing and to express some personal appreciations.<br/>
<span id="more-16454"/></p>
<p>
We at GLL have talked about him before. See <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2015/03/08/lint-for-math/">this</a> for his story about the fun of using an IBM mainframe for teaching. Or see <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2011/11/03/whos-afraid-of-arrows-paradox/">this</a> for a story about Héctor and meetings.</p>
<p>
I, Dick, had the pleasure to have worked with him, while we were both faculty at Princeton in the 1980’s and beyond.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> His Clock </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Héctor was the chair of the Stanford Computer Science Department from January 2001 to December 2004. Stanford then rotated the chair so all took their turn. I know that he “hated” being an administrator in general. But of course being a team player he took his turn. </p>
<p>
One way to see his real feelings about being a chair was to look at the clock his students constructed for him. The clock was a digital timer that counted down the seconds that remained in his term as the chair. It started at roughly 126227808. I am sure he did fine, but the clock was a statement. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> His Worst Paper </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
While Héctor was at Princeton we worked together on a project—the <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2010/05/20/sorting-out-chess-endgames/">MMM</a> project. It led to one of his least cited papers—a 1984 <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/1676454">paper</a> with me and Jacobo Valdes. OK, it has 48 citations according to IEEE. The idea of the project was to use memory rather than processors to speed up computations. He was a joy to work with: he was careful, and thoughtful, and just fun to work with on any project. </p>
<p>
We did write a second <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=AMrcBwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA565&amp;lpg=PA565&amp;dq=The+Massive+Memory+Machine+Project&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=_QFT07G56P&amp;sig=ACfU3U0-KV060yO3PHRllCnj3Y5o10BX-w&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwj7o67o-abmAhXHwFkKHRfzDs4Q6AEwDXoECAkQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=The Massive Memory Machine Project&amp;f=false">paper</a> with Richard Cullingford instead of Valdes, which Héctor presented at a meeting on knowledge-based management systems. The above Google Books link goes to the end with a <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=AMrcBwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA565&amp;lpg=PA565&amp;dq=The+Massive+Memory+Machine+Project&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=_QFT07G56P&amp;sig=ACfU3U0-KV060yO3PHRllCnj3Y5o10BX-w&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwj7o67o-abmAhXHwFkKHRfzDs4Q6AEwDXoECAkQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=The Massive Memory Machine Project&amp;f=false">discussion</a> in which a simple issue was raised—we paraphrase:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Won’t it take forever just to write all zeros to the memory? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Héctor had a scientist’s answer: the project was still not at the prototype stage so he didn’t know. He said the project should be viewed as a scientific experiment to find out. Maybe he also had an inkling that what was coming was a decade of breakthroughs in CPU design and parallel/pipeline processing after all. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> His Predictions </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Héctor was unparalleled at seeing the future. I always thought that one of his abilities, one that set him apart, was his ability to predict directions of research. This allowed him, and his students, to write early papers in research areas before they became hot. This is one of the talents that made him so amazing.</p>
<p>
I recall way before the world wide web was created he had students working on adding links to documents. I recall a talk by one of his students at Princeton that discussed what we now call URLs. One question that was raised during the talk was: How were the links going to be created? There was a lively discussion about this. Could they be created automatically? If not why would people take the time to create the links? Indeed.</p>
<p>
Héctor saw that links would be created. That people would take the effort to create them. I must admit that he was right, and he saw the future better than most. I wish I had a fraction of his ability to see directions like he did.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Guiding Students </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Héctor told me that when he first got to Stanford the fund managers and investors roamed the halls. They would ask anyone they could if they had an idea for a company or a startup. It was a constant issue that Héctor had to deal with. They were continually trying to steal away students. </p>
<p>
He told me he felt like he was the head of an abbey and was always having to protect his charges within the walls.</p>
<p>
When the impetus came from within it was different. Of course, Héctor was the advisor of Sergey Brin at the time he and Larry Page conceived Google. Brin and Page found that their search engine prototypes were so good the dataflow was constantly straining Stanford’s machines. They needed to scrounge for more disks and processors to mount their servers. Héctor already oversaw the Stanford Digital Libraries Project and he <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2018/09/04/8-surprising-facts-you-might-not-know-about-googles-early-days.html">arranged</a> for funds to purchase spare parts for the data servers. </p>
<p>
It is interesting that in this 2001 <a href="https://sigmod.org/publications/interviews/pdf/hector-final1.pdf">interview</a> in the <em>SIGMOD Record</em>, Héctor did not have a high opinion of the industrial side of his area:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Again, I don’t think industry really does very much research. They come up with an idea and they try to sell it. If it was a good idea, maybe they will make money. Even if it was a bad idea, if they have good marketing people, they might still make money and we never know … I don’t think they have an advantage over [academics] in testing the ideas and evaluating them and performing measurements and really understanding what are the right techniques. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
In the same interview, he had sage advice for students after completing their PhDs and during the tenure process, mainly on the side of not trying to play the system but focus on doing what you love.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Stanford Home Team </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Héctor had been a graduate student at Stanford. So his return there as a professor was a kind of homecoming. He was a home-team player in many senses. One of them is shown by this photo:</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hector-garcia-molina-sports.jpg"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-16457" height="200" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hector-garcia-molina-sports.jpg?w=300&amp;h=200" width="300"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Stanford University obituary <a href="https://news.stanford.edu/2019/12/06/hector-garcia-molina-influential-computer-scientist-database-expert-dies-65/">source</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
He was a registered Stanford sports photographer. He also taught a course at Stanford on photography. We don’t know if he had special insights on detecting “deepfake” photos and videos. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Our condolences go to all his family. Héctor you will be missed. You are missed. </p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-08T23:27:02Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-08T23:27:02Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="databases"/>
    <category term="Hector Garcia-Molina"/>
    <category term="memorial"/>
    <category term="memory machines"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/08/assistant-professor-position-tenure-track-at-hse-university-moscow-apply-by-january-12-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/08/assistant-professor-position-tenure-track-at-hse-university-moscow-apply-by-january-12-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor Position (Tenure Track) at HSE University, Moscow (apply by January 12, 2020)</title>
    <summary>HSE University, Faculty of Computer Science invites applications for full-time, tenure-track positions of Assistant Professor in all areas of computer science including but not limited to programming language theory, software engineering, system programming, algorithms, computation complexity, bioinformatics, artificial intelligence, and machine learning, etc. Website: https://iri.hse.ru/computer_science2020 Email: s.karapetyan@hse.ru</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>HSE University, Faculty of Computer Science invites applications for full-time, tenure-track positions of Assistant Professor in all areas of computer science including but not limited to programming language theory, software engineering, system programming, algorithms, computation complexity, bioinformatics, artificial intelligence, and machine learning, etc.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://iri.hse.ru/computer_science2020">https://iri.hse.ru/computer_science2020</a><br/>
Email: s.karapetyan@hse.ru</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-08T19:52:48Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-08T19:52:48Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/180</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/180" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-180 |  Covering Codes for Insertions and Deletions | 

	Andreas Lenz, 

	Cyrus Rashtchian, 

	Paul Siegel, 

	Eitan Yaakobi</title>
    <summary>A covering code is a set of codewords with the property that the union of balls, suitably defined, around these codewords covers an entire space. Generally, the goal is to find the covering code with the minimum size codebook. While most prior work on covering codes has focused on the Hamming metric, we consider the problem of designing covering codes defined in terms of  insertions and  deletions. First, we provide new sphere-covering lower bounds on the minimum possible size of such codes. Then, we provide new existential upper bounds on the size of optimal covering codes for a single insertion or a single deletion that are tight up to a constant factor. Finally, we derive improved upper bounds for covering codes using $R\geq 2$ insertions or deletions. We prove that codes exist with density that is only a factor $O(R \log R)$ larger than the lower bounds for all fixed $R$. In particular, our upper bounds have an optimal dependence on the word length, and we achieve asymptotic density matching the best known bounds for Hamming distance covering codes.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-08T09:03:55Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-08T09:03:55Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/07/postdoctoral-fellowship-at-bocconi-university-apply-by-december-15-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/07/postdoctoral-fellowship-at-bocconi-university-apply-by-december-15-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral Fellowship at Bocconi University (apply by December 15, 2019)</title>
    <summary>Two postdoctoral positions, each for one year renewable to a second, are available to work in Luca Trevisan’s group at Bocconi University on topics related to average-case analysis of algorithms, approximation algorithms, and combinatorial constructions. The positions have a very competitive salary and relocation benefits. Funding for travel is available. Website: https://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/3ecc85da-ac66-46ac-9db7-09ac0ef9b715/Call-2ADR-01B1-Bidsa-Erc.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&amp;CVID=mUjaHAv Email: L.Trevisan@unibocconi.it</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Two postdoctoral positions, each for one year renewable to a second, are available to work in Luca Trevisan’s group at Bocconi University on topics related to average-case analysis of algorithms, approximation algorithms, and combinatorial constructions.</p>
<p>The positions have a very competitive salary and relocation benefits. Funding for travel is available.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/3ecc85da-ac66-46ac-9db7-09ac0ef9b715/Call-2ADR-01B1-Bidsa-Erc.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&amp;CVID=mUjaHAv">https://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/3ecc85da-ac66-46ac-9db7-09ac0ef9b715/Call-2ADR-01B1-Bidsa-Erc.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&amp;CVID=mUjaHAv</a><br/>
Email: L.Trevisan@unibocconi.it</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-07T23:11:27Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-07T23:11:27Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4279</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/12/07/postdoc-position-at-bocconi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc Position at Bocconi</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am recruiting for two postdoctoral positions, each for one year renewable to a second, to work with me at Bocconi University on topics related to average-case analysis of algorithms, approximation algorithms, and combinatorial constructions. The positions have a very … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/12/07/postdoc-position-at-bocconi/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I am recruiting for two postdoctoral positions, each for one year renewable to a second, to work with me at Bocconi University on topics related to average-case analysis of algorithms, approximation algorithms, and combinatorial constructions. </p>
<p>The positions have a very competitive salary and relocation benefits. Funding for travel is available.</p>
<p>Application information is at <a href="https://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/3ecc85da-ac66-46ac-9db7-09ac0ef9b715/Call-2ADR-01B1-Bidsa-Erc.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&amp;CVID=mUjaHAv">this link</a>. The deadline  is <b>December 15</b>. If you apply, please also send me an email (L.Trevisan at unibocconi.it) to let me know.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-07T23:07:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-07T23:07:19Z</published>
    <category term="theory"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/179</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/179" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-179 |  Towards Optimal Separations between Quantum and Randomized Query Complexities | 

	Avishay Tal</title>
    <summary>The query model offers a concrete setting where quantum algorithms are provably superior to randomized algorithms. Beautiful results by Bernstein-Vazirani, Simon,  Aaronson, and others presented partial Boolean functions that can be computed by quantum algorithms making much fewer queries compared to their randomized analogs. To date, separations of $O(1)$ vs. $\sqrt{N}$ between quantum and randomized query complexities remain the state-of-the-art (where $N$ is the input length), leaving open the question of whether $O(1)$ vs. $N^{1/2+\Omega(1)}$ separations are possible?

We answer this question in the affirmative. Our separating problem is a variant of the Aaronson-Ambainis $k$-fold Forrelation problem. We show that our variant:
(1) Can be solved by a quantum algorithm making $2^{O(k)}$ queries to the inputs.
(2) Requires at least $\tilde{\Omega}(N^{2(k-1)/(3k-1)})$ queries for any randomized algorithm.

For any constant $\varepsilon&gt;0$, this gives a  $O(1)$  vs. $N^{2/3-\varepsilon}$ separation between the quantum and randomized query complexities of partial Boolean functions. 

Our proof is Fourier analytical and uses new bounds on the Fourier spectrum of classical decision trees, which could be of independent interest. 

Looking forward, we conjecture that the Fourier bounds could be further improved in a precise manner, and show that such conjectured bounds imply optimal $O(1)$ vs. $N^{1-\varepsilon}$ separations between the quantum and randomized query complexities of partial Boolean functions.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-07T14:25:04Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-07T14:25:04Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-19T14:20:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
