<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-01-24T23:28:47Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/24/faculty-at-uc-san-diego-apply-by-february-15-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/24/faculty-at-uc-san-diego-apply-by-february-15-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>faculty at UC San Diego (apply by February 15, 2019)</title>
    <summary>Apply to be an Assistant Professor, with a focus on Algorithmic Approaches to Socially Innovative Product Architectures and Business Models. This is a joint search by the Computer Science department and the Rady business school. Website: https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF01987 Email: slovett@ucsd.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Apply to be an Assistant Professor, with a focus on Algorithmic Approaches to Socially Innovative Product Architectures and Business Models. This is a joint search by the Computer Science department and the Rady business school.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF01987">https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF01987</a><br/>
Email: slovett@ucsd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-24T18:10:56Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-24T18:10:56Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7530001663397385709</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7530001663397385709/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/machine-learning-and-wind-turbines.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7530001663397385709" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7530001663397385709" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/machine-learning-and-wind-turbines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Machine Learning and Wind Turbines</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;">
<a href="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-IwXAr_ptgYo/XEYxZWFiAzI/AAAAAAABmPw/6t_lphNZigA3sXSix1MpcmKNANZFiGkawCLcBGAs/s1600/Turbines.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="180" src="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-IwXAr_ptgYo/XEYxZWFiAzI/AAAAAAABmPw/6t_lphNZigA3sXSix1MpcmKNANZFiGkawCLcBGAs/s320/Turbines.png" width="320"/></a></div>
<br/>
My daughter Molly spent six weeks on an environmental program in China last summer. When she got back she had to do a report on machine learning and wind turbines used for clean energy generation. What does machine learning have to do with wind turbines? Plenty it turns out and it tell us a lot about the future of programming.<br/>
<br/>
Sudden changes in wind can cause damage to the blades of the turbine. Maintenance is very expensive especially for turbines in the sea and a broken turbine generates no electricity. To catch these changes ahead of time you can mount a Lidar on top of the turbine.<br/>
<br/>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;">
<a href="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-9LFv8FGZNG8/XEYxYFyCYDI/AAAAAAABmPs/TLY7-bfPWhMWjRLl8Jn9ixXrTBa_sAk7ACLcBGAs/s1600/Turbine%2BLidar.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="180" src="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-9LFv8FGZNG8/XEYxYFyCYDI/AAAAAAABmPs/TLY7-bfPWhMWjRLl8Jn9ixXrTBa_sAk7ACLcBGAs/s320/Turbine%2BLidar.jpg" width="320"/></a></div>
<br/>
The Lidar can detect wind gusts from about 100 meters ahead, giving about 10 seconds to react. In that time you can rotate the blades, or the whole turbine itself to minimize any damage. Here's a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j5zLp6UuC70">video</a> describing the situation.<br/>
<br/>
<center>

</center>
<br/>
How do you do the computations to convert the Lidar data into accurate representations of wind gusts and then how to best adjust for them? You could imagine some complex fluid dynamics computation, which gets even more complex when you several wind turbines in front of each other. Instead you can use the massive amount of data you have collected by sensors on the turbine and the Lidar information and train a neural network. Training takes a long time but a trained network can quickly determine a good course of action. Now neural networks can always make mistakes but unlike self-driving cars, a mistake won't kill anyone, just possibly cause more damage. Since on average you can save considerable maintenance costs, using ML here is a big win.<br/>
<br/>
I've obviously over simplified the above but I really like this example. This is not an ML solution to a standard AI question like image recognition or playing chess. Rather we are using ML to make a difficult computation tractable mostly by using ML on available data and that changes how we think about programming complex tasks.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-24T13:58:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-24T13:58:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>https://plus.google.com/101693130490639305932</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>https://plus.google.com/101693130490639305932</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T22:52:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1054</id>
    <link href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1054" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Prophet inequality and auction design</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Suppose you want to sell a car and there are 10 agents willing to buy it. You are not sure how much they could pay but for each of them you know a probability distribution of how high the offer … <a href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1054">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Suppose you want to sell a car and there are 10 agents willing to buy it. You are not sure how much they could pay but for each of them you know a probability distribution of how high the offer will be. For example, a car salon would always pay 10K  but some person might offer 5K or 15K with equal probability. The best you could do is to first negotiate with all of them and then pick the highest bid. Unfortunately, you cannot do so - after seeing each offer you must irrevocably choose either to sell the car or to refuse the offer. What is the best strategy to maximize your revenue in this case?</p>
<p>In turns out that this is a well-studied optimization problem with a simple strategy that guarantees you can (on expectation) earn at least half as much as a hypothetical prophet, who knows all the bids in advance. This result is known as the prophet inequality. What is more surprising, this strategy would work even if you are a car retailer and want to sell five cars. Moreover, you might want to have some constraints, for example you do not want to sell two cars to buyers from the same city, or have multiple kinds of cars with different evaluations, and you can always guarantee an expected revenue comparable to the one of the prophets.</p>
<p>This problem not only exploits beautiful math but also has important applications in internet ad display. Actually, whenever you type a query into a web search engine, the ad system performs this kind of car-selling game with the ad suppliers, who offer different bids for their ad to be displayed to you.</p>
<p>Here is a link to our recent work with new developments in this theory: <a href="http://ieee-focs.org/FOCS-2018-Papers/pdfs/59f790.pdf">http://ieee-focs.org/FOCS-2018-Papers/pdfs/59f790.pdf</a></p>
<p>Michał Włodarczyk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-24T10:21:58Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-24T10:21:58Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Renata Czarniecka</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl</id>
      <link href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>University of Warsaw</subtitle>
      <title>Banach's Algorithmic Corner</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07928</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07928" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximate k-Cover in Hypergraphs: Efficient Algorithms, and Applications</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1548288000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nguyen:Hung.html">Hung Nguyen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Thai:Phuc.html">Phuc Thai</a>, My Thai, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vu:Tam.html">Tam Vu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dinh:Thang.html">Thang Dinh</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.07928">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a weighted hypergraph $\mathcal{H}(V, \mathcal{E} \subseteq 2^V, w)$,
the approximate $k$-cover problem seeks for a size-$k$ subset of $V$ that has
the maximum weighted coverage by \emph{sampling only a few hyperedges} in
$\mathcal{E}$. The problem has emerged from several network analysis
applications including viral marketing, centrality maximization, and landmark
selection. Despite many efforts, even the best approaches require $O(k n \log
n)$ space complexities, thus, cannot scale to, nowadays, humongous networks
without sacrificing formal guarantees. In this paper, we propose BCA, a family
of algorithms for approximate $k$-cover that can find $(1-\frac{1}{e}
-\epsilon)$-approximation solutions within an \emph{$O(\epsilon^{-2}n \log n)$
space}. That is a factor $k$ reduction on space comparing to the
state-of-the-art approaches with the same guarantee. We further make BCA more
efficient and robust on real-world instances by introducing a novel adaptive
sampling scheme, termed DTA.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-24T23:24:20Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07906</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07906" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>How Many Passengers Can We Serve with Ride-sharing?</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1548288000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tan:Zeren.html">Zeren Tan</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.07906">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Ride-sharing can reduce traffic congestion and thus reduce gas emissions and
save travel time. However, transportation system with ride-sharing is currently
inefficient due to low occupancy rate, high travel demand and some other
factors. Existing literature did not consider ride-sharing with multi-request
grouped in one trip. In our paper, we firstly proposed a graph-based algorithm
that can obtain an approximation solution in polynomial time and then proposed
an exact algorithm to solve this problem with maximizing the number of
passenegers served in $O(1.2312^{|\mathcal{E}|})$ time.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-24T23:22:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07904</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07904" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Solving unconstrained 0-1 polynomial programs through quadratic convex reformulation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1548288000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Elloumi:Sourour.html">Sourour Elloumi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lambert:Am=eacute=lie.html">Amélie Lambert</a>, Arnaud Lazare <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.07904">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We propose a solution approach for the problem (P) of minimizing an
unconstrained binary polynomial optimization problem. We call this method PQCR
(Polynomial Quadratic Convex Reformulation). The resolution is based on a
3-phase method. The first phase consists in reformulating (P) into a quadratic
program (QP). For this, we recursively reduce the degree of (P) to two, by use
of the standard substitution of the product of two variables by a new one. We
then obtain a linearly constrained binary program. In the second phase, we
rewrite the quadratic objective function into an equivalent and parametrized
quadratic function using the equality x 2 i = x i and new valid quadratic
equalities. Then, we focus on finding the best parameters to get a quadratic
convex program which continuous relaxation's optimal value is maximized. For
this, we build a semidefinite relaxation (SDP) of (QP). Then, we prove that the
standard linearization inequalities, used for the quadratization step, are
redundant in (SDP) in presence of the new quadratic equalities. Next, we deduce
our optimal parameters from the dual optimal solution of (SDP). The third phase
consists in solving (QP *), the optimal reformulated problem, with a standard
solver. In particular, at each node of the branch-and-bound, the solver
computes the optimal value of a continuous quadratic convex program. We present
computational results on instances of the image restoration problem and of the
low autocorrelation binary sequence problem. We compare PQCR with other
convexification methods, and with the general solver Baron 17.4.1 [39]. We
observe that most of the considered instances can be solved with our approach
combined with the use of Cplex [24].
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-24T23:22:12Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07825</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07825" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the Power of Symmetric Linear Programs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1548288000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Atserias:Albert.html">Albert Atserias</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dawar:Anuj.html">Anuj Dawar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Ochremiak:Joanna.html">Joanna Ochremiak</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.07825">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider families of symmetric linear programs (LPs) that decide a
property of graphs (or other relational structures) in the sense that, for each
size of graph, there is an LP defining a polyhedral lift that separates the
integer points corresponding to graphs with the property from those
corresponding to graphs without the property. We show that this is equivalent,
with at most polynomial blow-up in size, to families of symmetric Boolean
circuits with threshold gates. In particular, when we consider polynomial-size
LPs, the model is equivalent to definability in a non-uniform version of
fixed-point logic with counting (FPC). Known upper and lower bounds for FPC
apply to the non-uniform version. In particular, this implies that the class of
graphs with perfect matchings has polynomial-size symmetric LPs while we obtain
an exponential lower bound for symmetric LPs for the class of Hamiltonian
graphs. We compare and contrast this with previous results (Yannakakis 1991)
showing that any symmetric LPs for the matching and TSP polytopes have
exponential size. As an application, we establish that for random, uniformly
distributed graphs, polynomial-size symmetric LPs are as powerful as general
Boolean circuits. We illustrate the effect of this on the well-studied
planted-clique problem.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-24T23:20:48Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07809</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07809" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A randomized strategy in the mirror game</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1548288000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Feige:Uriel.html">Uriel Feige</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.07809">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Alice and Bob take turns (with Alice playing first) in declaring numbers from
the set $[1,2N]$. If a player declares a number that was previously declared,
that player looses and the other player wins. If all numbers are declared
without repetition, the outcome is a tie. If both players have unbounded memory
and play optimally, then the game will be tied. Garg and Schneider [ITCS 2019]
showed that if Alice has unbounded memory, then Bob can secure a tie with $\log
N$ memory, whereas if Bob has unbounded memory, then Alice needs memory linear
in $N$ in order to secure a tie.
</p>
<p>Garg and Schneider also considered an {\em auxiliary matching} model in which
Alice gets as an additional input a random matching $M$ over the numbers
$[1,2N]$, and storing this input does not count towards the memory used by
Alice. They showed that is this model there is a strategy for Alice that ties
with probability at least $1 - \frac{1}{N}$, and uses only $O(\sqrt{N} (\log
N)^2)$ memory. We show how to modify Alice's strategy so that it uses only
$O((\log N)^3)$ space.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-24T23:24:54Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07609</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07609" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faster parameterized algorithm for Cluster Vertex Deletion</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1548288000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tsur:Dekel.html">Dekel Tsur</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.07609">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the Cluster Vertex Deletion problem the input is a graph $G$ and an
integer $k$. The goal is to decide whether there is a set of vertices $S$ of
size at most $k$ such that the deletion of the vertices of $S$ from $G$ results
a graph in which every connected component is a clique. We give an algorithm
for Cluster Vertex Deletion whose running time is $O^*(1.811^k)$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-24T23:21:57Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07530</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1901.07530" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Minimum--Entropy Couplings and their Applications</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1548288000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cicalese:Ferdinando.html">Ferdinando Cicalese</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gargano:Luisa.html">Luisa Gargano</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vaccaro:Ugo.html">Ugo Vaccaro</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.07530">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given two discrete random variables $X$ and $Y,$ with probability
distributions ${\bf p}=(p_1, \ldots , p_n)$ and ${\bf q}=(q_1, \ldots , q_m)$,
respectively, denote by ${\cal C}({\bf p}, {\bf q})$ the set of all couplings
of ${\bf p}$ and ${\bf q}$, that is, the set of all bivariate probability
distributions that have ${\bf p}$ and ${\bf q}$ as marginals. In this paper, we
study the problem of finding a joint probability distribution in ${\cal C}({\bf
p}, {\bf q})$ of \emph{minimum entropy} (equivalently, a coupling that
\emph{maximizes} the mutual information between $X$ and $Y$), and we discuss
several situations where the need for this kind of optimization naturally
arises. Since the optimization problem is known to be NP-hard, we give an
efficient algorithm to find a joint probability distribution in ${\cal C}({\bf
p}, {\bf q})$ with entropy exceeding the minimum possible at most by {1 bit},
thus providing an approximation algorithm with an additive gap of at most 1
bit. Leveraging on this algorithm, we extend our result to the problem of
finding a minimum--entropy joint distribution of arbitrary $k\geq 2$ discrete
random variables $X_1, \ldots , X_k$, consistent with the known $k$ marginal
distributions of the individual random variables $X_1, \ldots , X_k$. In this
case, our algorithm has an { additive gap of at most $\log k$ from optimum.}
</p>
<p>We also discuss several related applications of our findings and {extensions
of our results to entropies different from the Shannon entropy.}
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-24T23:22:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/23/postdoctoral-fellow-at-carnegie-mellon-university-apply-by-february-28-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/23/postdoctoral-fellow-at-carnegie-mellon-university-apply-by-february-28-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral Fellow at Carnegie Mellon University (apply by February 28, 2019)</title>
    <summary>Postdoctoral Position at the computer science department, CMU. Hosted by Venkatesan Gurusawami and Pravesh Kothari. Start Date: Fall 2019 (Flexible) Application Deadline: Feb 28, 2019 (earlier applications encouraged). To apply, send CV, a research statement and arrange for 2 letters of recommendation to be set to be sent to bcook@cs.cmu.edu with subject line mentioning “CMU […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Postdoctoral Position at the computer science department, CMU. Hosted by Venkatesan Gurusawami and Pravesh Kothari. Start Date: Fall 2019 (Flexible)<br/>
Application Deadline: Feb 28, 2019 (earlier applications encouraged).</p>
<p>To apply, send CV, a research statement and arrange for 2 letters of recommendation to be set to be sent to bcook@cs.cmu.edu with subject line mentioning “CMU theory postdoc.”</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~kothari/theory-postdoc.html">https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~kothari/theory-postdoc.html</a><br/>
Email: kothari@cs.princeton.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-23T22:24:07Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-23T22:24:07Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/22/postdoc-at-charles-university-in-prague-apply-by-february-28-2019-2/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/22/postdoc-at-charles-university-in-prague-apply-by-february-28-2019-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at Charles University in Prague (apply by February 28, 2019)</title>
    <summary>Several one‐year post‐doc positions are available at the Computer Science Institute of Charles University, with a possibility of one-year extension. The positions are in areas of algorithms, cryptography, computational complexity, combinatorics and graph theory. Starting date is in Fall 2019, and can be negotiated. Website: https://iuuk.mff.cuni.cz/~koucky/iuuk-postdocs.html Email: koucky@iuuk.mff.cuni.cz</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Several one‐year post‐doc positions are available at the Computer Science Institute of Charles University, with a possibility of one-year extension. The positions are in areas of algorithms, cryptography, computational complexity, combinatorics and graph theory. Starting date is in Fall 2019, and can be negotiated.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://iuuk.mff.cuni.cz/~koucky/iuuk-postdocs.html">https://iuuk.mff.cuni.cz/~koucky/iuuk-postdocs.html</a><br/>
Email: koucky@iuuk.mff.cuni.cz</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-22T12:38:31Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-22T12:38:31Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/22/phd-student-at-charles-university-in-prague-apply-by-february-28-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/22/phd-student-at-charles-university-in-prague-apply-by-february-28-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PhD student at Charles University in Prague (apply by February 28, 2019)</title>
    <summary>Positions for PhD students are available at the Computer Science Institute of Charles University within the framework of the project “Efficient approximation algorithms and circuit complexity” funded by the Grant Agency of the Czech Republic. Applications are invited from candidates who have strong background in theoretical computer science or discrete mathematics. Starting date: Fall 2019. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Positions for PhD students are available at the Computer Science Institute of Charles University within the framework of the project “Efficient approximation algorithms and circuit complexity” funded by the Grant Agency of the Czech Republic. Applications are invited from candidates who have strong background in theoretical computer science or discrete mathematics. Starting date: Fall 2019.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://iuuk.mff.cuni.cz/~koucky/EPAC/positions.html">https://iuuk.mff.cuni.cz/~koucky/EPAC/positions.html</a><br/>
Email: koucky@iuuk.mff.cuni.cz</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-22T12:36:30Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-22T12:36:30Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/22/postdoc-at-charles-university-in-prague-apply-by-february-28-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/22/postdoc-at-charles-university-in-prague-apply-by-february-28-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at Charles University in Prague (apply by February 28, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The position is supported by a five year project “EPAC: Efficient approximation algorithms and circuit complexity” funded by the Grant Agency of the Czech Republic. The project is focused on approximation algorithms in fine-grained and parameterized complexity and on lower bound techniques. Starting date is in Fall 2019, and can be negotiated. Website: https://iuuk.mff.cuni.cz/~koucky/EPAC/ Email: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The position is supported by a five year project “EPAC: Efficient approximation algorithms and circuit complexity” funded by the Grant Agency of the Czech Republic. The project is focused on approximation algorithms in fine-grained and parameterized complexity and on lower bound techniques. Starting date is in Fall 2019, and can be negotiated.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://iuuk.mff.cuni.cz/~koucky/EPAC/">https://iuuk.mff.cuni.cz/~koucky/EPAC/</a><br/>
Email: koucky@iuuk.mff.cuni.cz</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-22T12:33:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-22T12:33:00Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3377</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/01/22/guest-post-like-a-swarm-of-locusts-vijay-vazirani/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Guest post: “Like a Swarm of Locusts…” (Vijay Vazirani)</title>
    <summary>  [The following guest post was written by Vijay Vazirani.]           What the cutting locust left, the swarming locust has eaten. What the swarming locust left, the hopping locust has eaten, and what the hopping locust left, the destroying locust has eaten. Joel 1:4 A few years ago, while attending a […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em><img align="RIGHT" alt="My Picture" border="1" class=" alignleft" height="161" src="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~vazirani/Vijay2.png" width="135"/></em></p>
<p> </p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><em>[The following guest post was written by Vijay Vazirani.] </em></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><em> </em></p>
<p> </p>
<blockquote><p><em>What the cutting locust left, the swarming locust has eaten. What the swarming locust left, the hopping locust has eaten, and what the hopping locust left, the destroying locust has eaten.</em></p>
<p style="text-align: right;">Joel 1:4</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A few years ago, while attending a Dagstuhl program on Equilibrium Computation, I embarked on one of the traditional long hikes through the beautiful woods surrounding Schloss Dagstuhl and happened to be walking next to a senior member of the Operations Research community. In no time we got immersed in a lively discussion on the style of research going on in Algorithmic Game Theory. We both agreed that the progress made in a matter of a few years was nothing short of phenomenal. At this point, my colleague remarked that AGT was no exception and that when TCS researchers enter a new area, they go in with such energies and enthusiasm that in no time not only is all low hanging fruit gone but in fact the entire area is devoid of any reasonable open problems! “They attack the area like swarms of locusts devouring foliage in biblical lands, consuming not only fruit and leaves but even shrubs and twigs,” he added. “Yes, and only sh*t is left behind!” I chimed in.</p>
<p>As AGT is reaching that stage, with researchers yearning for new issues/problems for their students and their own research and grant proposals, there is a reprieve emerging on the horizon: a program at Simons on “<a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/programs/market2019">Online and Matching-Based Market Design</a>” in Fall 2019.</p>
<p>This is by no means a new area. In fact, the first such market, for matching medical residents to hospitals, dates back to 1920s, well before the classic — and by now Nobel Prize winning — work of Gale and Shapley on the stable matching problem, which provided the canonical algorithm for this market. In recent years, the advent of the Internet and the relocation of our most important activities to online platforms have led to an explosion of such marketplaces (for examples, see the Simons web page) and they have been occupying an ever-increasing fraction of our economy.</p>
<p>AGT, CS and Economics have already had a massive impact via these markets. My own experience comes from Google’s multi-billion dollar Adwords market in which sophisticated algorithmic ideas have also played a central role, e.g., see the Simons talk “<a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/talks/vijay-vazirani-4-30-18">Google’s AdWords Market: How Theory Influenced Practice</a>“.</p>
<p>Clearly, the stakes are high. There is a real opportunity of extending the already existing highly inter-disciplinary theory in substantial ways and making an even bigger impact. Considering this and the enthusiasm of the researchers who have agreed to be participants in this program, Federico Echenique, Nicole Immorlica and I have launched the project of publishing a comprehensive volume of contributed chapters on this topic. More information on this will be coming soon.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-21T22:24:51Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-21T22:24:51Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>robertkleinberg</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:26:54Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=15597</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/01/21/a-simple-fact/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Simple Fact</title>
    <summary>Can we find a simplest proof? Composite crop from src1, src2 Joseph Wedderburn and Leonard Dickson proved Wedderburn’s “Little” Theorem: that every finite ring with the zero-product property is a field. Which of them proved it first is hard to tell. Today we discuss the issue of finding simple proofs for simple facts—not just Wedderburn’s […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Can we find a simplest proof?</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/01/wedderburndickson.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-15598" height="142" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/01/wedderburndickson.png?w=193&amp;h=142" width="193"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Composite crop from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Wedderburn">src1</a>, <a href="http://www.ams.org/about-us/presidents/14-dickson">src2</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Joseph Wedderburn and Leonard Dickson proved Wedderburn’s “Little” Theorem: that every finite ring with the zero-product property is a field. Which of them proved it first is hard to tell.</p>
<p>
Today we discuss the issue of finding simple proofs for simple facts—not just Wedderburn’s theorem but the zero-product property on which it leans.</p>
<p>
Dickson was a professor at the University of Chicago when Wedderburn visited on a Carnegie Fellowship in 1904–05. To <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wedderburn's_little_theorem#History">judge</a> <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=0CApaWJwry8C&amp;pg=PA318&amp;lpg=PA318&amp;dq=In+pursuit+of+the+finite+division+algebra+theorem+and+beyond&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=esoyfvVJAl&amp;sig=ACfU3U0N05-c467jVhDz1ElYLcsE4e_9Og&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjRvPv41_3fAhVOnuAKHdy3DgcQ6AEwBXoECAIQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=In pursuit of the finite division algebra theorem and beyond&amp;f=false">from</a> <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=O7R-DwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA105&amp;lpg=PA105&amp;dq=wedderburn+dickson+proofs&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=VdkQrceyrN&amp;sig=ACfU3U3u7Qn3ibDSszBPg0AitsrXUNUZpA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwixkqzl0f3fAhWMTt8KHVo9DVgQ6AEwBnoECAUQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=wedderburn dickson proofs&amp;f=false">several</a> <a href="https://api.research-repository.uwa.edu.au/portalfiles/portal/9699048/BambergPenttilaRevised.pdf">sources</a>, what happened is that Wedderburn first claimed a proof. Dickson did not believe the <em>result</em> and tried to build a counterexample. Instead he found a lemma that convinced him it was true and used it to give a simpler proof. They gave back-to-back presentations on 20 January, 1905, Wedderburn wrote up his paper with his proof and two more based on the lemma, which Wedderburn ascribed to an earlier paper by George Birkhoff and Harry Vandiver. Dickson wrote a paper with his approach, saying in a footnote:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> First proved by Wedderburn … Following my simpler proof above, and using the same lemma, Wedderburn constructed two further simpler proofs. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
However, Wedderburn’s first proof was found to have a gap. As <a href="https://www.math.uni-bielefeld.de/lag/man/099.pdf">detailed</a> by Michael Adam and Birte Specht, the gap was a statement that was not false <em>per se</em> but whose vague argument used only properties from a class of weaker structures in which it can fail. So:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Who first proved the theorem? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Other Proofs, Other Properties </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Our sources linked above differ on whether the gap was noticed at the time or anytime before Emil Artin remarked on it in 1927. Artin didn’t discuss the gap but gave his own proof instead. There <a>seems</a> <a href="https://www.theoremoftheday.org/Docs/WedderburnShamil.pdf">to</a> <a href="https://ysharifi.wordpress.com/2011/09/24/wedderburns-little-theorem-1/">be</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wedderburn's_little_theorem#Proof">consensus</a> that the “proof from the Book” was <a href="http://www.math.leidenuniv.nl/~hfinkeln/seminarium/eindige_delingsring_is_lichaam.pdf">given</a> by Ernst Witt four years later in 1931. But two other proofs, <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2311457?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents">by</a> Israel Herstein and <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/glasgow-mathematical-journal/article/grouptheoretic-proof-of-a-theorem-of-maclaganwedderburn/7BBA5D9EA9EDEE000BAE4859EDE64DA6">by</a> Hans Zassenhaus, receive prominent mention. </p>
<p>
As our sources attest, interest in finding other proofs continues. The surprise in the theorem, which is that finiteness and the zero-product property force the multiplication to be commutative, informs what happens in other mathematical structures. Proofs that draw on results about these structures create connections among many areas. The shortest proof drawing on deeper results was a two-page <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2312328">paper</a> in the summer 1964 <em>Monthly</em> by Theodore Kaczynski (of <a href="https://www.fbi.gov/history/famous-cases/unabomber">ill</a> <a href="https://www.biography.com/news/unabomber-ted-kaczynski-today">note</a>). We won’t try to compare all these proofs, but will try to flip the question by focusing on the other property involved—the zero-product property:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> If <img alt="{a \cdot b = 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba+%5Ccdot+b+%3D+0%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a \cdot b = 0}"/> then <img alt="{a = 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba+%3D+0%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a = 0}"/> or <img alt="{b = 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb+%3D+0%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b = 0}"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Given a ring <img alt="{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R}"/> with this property, how easy is it to prove? If <img alt="{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R}"/> has inverses then it is immediate, else multiplying both sides of <img alt="{a\cdot b = 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%5Ccdot+b+%3D+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a\cdot b = 0}"/> by <img alt="{a^{-1}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%5E%7B-1%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a^{-1}}"/> in front and <img alt="{b^{-1}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%5E%7B-1%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b^{-1}}"/> in back would yield the contradiction <img alt="{1 = 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1+%3D+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1 = 0}"/>. And we know if <img alt="{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R}"/> is finite then this property makes it a field. So our quest for a different angle leads us to thinking about infinite rings. </p>
<p>
Incidentally, a ring with the zero-product property is called a <em>domain</em>. If the multiplication is commutative then it is an <em>integral domain</em>, though Serge Lang preferred the term <em>entire ring</em>. Our example goes beyond the integers though.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> No Zero-Divisors I </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
A natural example that arises is the ring of integer polynomials over multiple variables. Thus for two variables <img alt="{x,y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%2Cy%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x,y}"/> the elements of this ring are 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \sum_{i,j} c_{ij}x^{i}y^{j}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Csum_%7Bi%2Cj%7D+c_%7Bij%7Dx%5E%7Bi%7Dy%5E%7Bj%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \sum_{i,j} c_{ij}x^{i}y^{j}. "/></p>
<p>It is easy to see that they form a ring with the usual high school rules for adding and multiplying polynomials. The ring is an integral domain in general.</p>
<p>
To show this, we claim that it has no zero-divisors. Suppose that it does: let <img alt="{f(x,y) \cdot g(x,y) = 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29+%5Ccdot+g%28x%2Cy%29+%3D+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y) \cdot g(x,y) = 0}"/>. Then let 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  f(x,y) = \sum_{k} f_{k}(x) y^{k}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++f%28x%2Cy%29+%3D+%5Csum_%7Bk%7D+f_%7Bk%7D%28x%29+y%5E%7Bk%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  f(x,y) = \sum_{k} f_{k}(x) y^{k}, "/></p>
<p>and 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  g(x,y) = \sum_{k} g_{k}(x) y^{k}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++g%28x%2Cy%29+%3D+%5Csum_%7Bk%7D+g_%7Bk%7D%28x%29+y%5E%7Bk%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  g(x,y) = \sum_{k} g_{k}(x) y^{k}. "/></p>
<p>Assume that the maximum degree in <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/> for <img alt="{f(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y)}"/> is <img alt="{df}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bdf%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{df}"/> and is <img alt="{dg}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bdg%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{dg}"/> for <img alt="{g(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bg%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{g(x,y)}"/>. Then <img alt="{f_{df}(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_%7Bdf%7D%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_{df}(x)}"/> and <img alt="{g_{df}(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bg_%7Bdf%7D%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{g_{df}(x)}"/> are both non-zero polynomials in one variable. It is clear by induction that <img alt="{f_{df}(x) \cdot g_{dg}(x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf_%7Bdf%7D%28x%29+%5Ccdot+g_%7Bdg%7D%28x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f_{df}(x) \cdot g_{dg}(x)}"/> is not zero. This proves the claim.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> No Zero-Divisors II </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The trouble with the above property of polynomials is that it is only about formal objects. In many applications to computer science we want to view polynomials as objects that can be evaluated. So a natural issue is a slightly different property: Suppose that <img alt="{F(x,y,\dots)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF%28x%2Cy%2C%5Cdots%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{F(x,y,\dots)}"/> and <img alt="{G(x,y,\dots)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%28x%2Cy%2C%5Cdots%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G(x,y,\dots)}"/> are two integral polynomials. Suppose further that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  F(a,b,\dots) \cdot G(a,b,\dots) = 0, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++F%28a%2Cb%2C%5Cdots%29+%5Ccdot+G%28a%2Cb%2C%5Cdots%29+%3D+0%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  F(a,b,\dots) \cdot G(a,b,\dots) = 0, "/></p>
<p>for all integers <img alt="{a,b,\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%2Cb%2C%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a,b,\dots}"/>. Then it clearly must be the case that either <img alt="{F=0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF%3D0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{F=0}"/> identically or <img alt="{G=0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%3D0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G=0}"/> identically. Right?</p>
<p>
The trouble is that this seems to be obvious but how do we prove that it is true? Note, it must be the case that some use of the fact that <img alt="{F}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{F}"/> and <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> are polynomials. The fact is not true for more complex functions. For example, 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \cos(\pi x) \cdot \sin(\pi x) = 0, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Ccos%28%5Cpi+x%29+%5Ccdot+%5Csin%28%5Cpi+x%29+%3D+0%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \cos(\pi x) \cdot \sin(\pi x) = 0, "/></p>
<p>for all integers <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/>. But neither the function <img alt="{\cos(\pi x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccos%28%5Cpi+x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\cos(\pi x)}"/> nor <img alt="{\sin(\pi x)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csin%28%5Cpi+x%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sin(\pi x)}"/> is identically zero for all integers.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> A Proof </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Here is a relatively simple proof of the fact. It uses the famous Schwarz-Zippel (SZ) Theorem. See <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2009/11/30/the-curious-history-of-the-schwartz-zippel-lemma/">here</a> for our discussion of the theorem. </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 1</b> <em> Let <img alt="{P}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P}"/> be in <img alt="{\mathbb{F}[x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_n]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BF%7D%5Bx_1%2Cx_2%2C%5Cldots%2Cx_n%5D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{F}[x_1,x_2,\ldots,x_n]}"/> be a non-zero polynomial of total degree <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/> over a field <img alt="{\mathbb{F}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BF%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{F}}"/>. Let <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S}"/> be a finite subset of <img alt="{\mathbb{F}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BF%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{F}}"/> and let <img alt="{r_{1},\dots,r_{n}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br_%7B1%7D%2C%5Cdots%2Cr_%7Bn%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r_{1},\dots,r_{n}}"/> be selected at random independently and uniformly from <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S}"/>. Then 	</em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \Pr[P(r_1,r_2,\ldots,r_n)=0] \leq \frac{d}{|S|}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5CPr%5BP%28r_1%2Cr_2%2C%5Cldots%2Cr_n%29%3D0%5D+%5Cleq+%5Cfrac%7Bd%7D%7B%7CS%7C%7D.+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \Pr[P(r_1,r_2,\ldots,r_n)=0] \leq \frac{d}{|S|}. "/></p>
</em><p><em/>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
The S-Z lemma of course has manifest applications throughout complexity theory. Often it is used in design of randomized algorithms. What we found interesting is that here we use it for a different purpose: to prove a structural property of polynomials.</p>
<p>
Back to our fact. Assume that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  F(a,b) \cdot G(a,b) = 0, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++F%28a%2Cb%29+%5Ccdot+G%28a%2Cb%29+%3D+0%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  F(a,b) \cdot G(a,b) = 0, "/></p>
<p>for all integers <img alt="{a \in S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba+%5Cin+S%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a \in S}"/> and <img alt="{b \in S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb+%5Cin+S%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b \in S}"/> for some finite set. Now either <img alt="{F(a, b)=0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF%28a%2C+b%29%3D0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{F(a, b)=0}"/> or <img alt="{G(a, b)=0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%28a%2C+b%29%3D0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G(a, b)=0}"/> must be true for at least one half of the values in <img alt="{S \times S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS+%5Ctimes+S%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S \times S}"/>. Assume that it is <img alt="{F}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{F}"/>. Then by the S-Z theorem it must be that <img alt="{F=0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF%3D0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{F=0}"/> always if the set <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S}"/> is large enough. Therefore, the fact is proved.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Is there a simpler proof of this key fact? Is it possible to find an easier reference in the literature of this basic fact of polynomials? We have yet to discover one—any help would be appreciated.</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-21T18:37:22Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-21T18:37:22Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Teaching"/>
    <category term="algebra"/>
    <category term="fields"/>
    <category term="history of mathematics"/>
    <category term="Joseph Wedderburn"/>
    <category term="Leonard Dickson"/>
    <category term="polynomials"/>
    <category term="rings"/>
    <category term="Schwartz-Zippel"/>
    <category term="Wedderburn's Little Theorem"/>
    <category term="zero divisors"/>
    <category term="zero-product property"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:26:56Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-800609330387332388</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/800609330387332388/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/acm-prize-and-some-thoughts-on-godel.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/800609330387332388" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/800609330387332388" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/acm-prize-and-some-thoughts-on-godel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>ACM prize and some thoughts on the Godel Prize</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><br/>
<br/>
As Lance Tweeted, and I will re-iterate, nominations for the following prizes<br/>
are due soon and you can nominate people <a href="https://sigact.org/articles/prizes.html">here</a><br/>
<br/>
Godel Prize for outstanding paper in TCS. (Godel mentioned P vs NP in a letter to Von Neumann. I've heard it said that its too bad they didn't work on it-- either it would be solved or we'd know its hard. Frankly, I think enough smart people have worked on it that we already know its hard.)<br/>
<br/>
Knuth Prize for outstanding contributions to foundations of Computer Science. (its a greater honor to have a prize  named after you in your lifetime then to win a prize!)<br/>
<br/>
Dijkstra Prize (I wonder if having `ijk' in his name inspired him to work in algorithms)<br/>
<br/>
Kanellakis Theory and Practice Award.<br/>
<br/>
Lawler Award for Humanitarian Contributions within CS and Informatics.<br/>
<br/>
ACM Distinguished Service Award<br/>
<br/>
Danny Lewin Best Student Paper Award (best student paper at STOC)<br/>
<br/>
The Best Paper award (Best paper at STOC, Best paper at FOCS)<br/>
<br/>
(The last two I doubt you can nominate someone for.)<br/>
<br/>
A few thoughts on the Godel Prize:<br/>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
1) You can win the Godel Prize twice and some people have: Goldwasser, Hastad, Arora, Szegedy, Spielman, Teng. Spielman-Teng have won it as a team twice.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
2) GLAD there is no limit to how many can win. If a paper has a lot of people on it (and this has happened) then FINE, they're all winners! According to The Big Bang Theory (the TV show, not the theory) in Physics at most 3 can win a Nobel Prize in Physics for the same breakthrough in a given year. The show itself shows how stupid the policy is.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
3) I either knew and forgot or never knew that DPDA Equiv is decidable! Glad to now it just in time for teaching Automata theory this spring.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
4) Looking over the list reminded me that there are some papers in the intersection of those I want to read and those I am able to read! Though not many. Most I want to read but they seem hard.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
5) The Kanellakis award is for theory that is PRACTICAL. Could someone win a Godel AND a Kannellakis award for the same paper (or set of papers). I found one sort-of case ( (a) below) and one definite case ( (b) below).</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
a) Moshe and Wolpert won the 2000 Godel Prize for Temporal Logic and Finite Automata (I should also read that before my class starts)</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
Holtzmann, Kurshan, Vardi, and Wolpert won the 2005 Kanellakis prize for Formal Verification Tools.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
I assume the two works are related.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
b) Freund and Schapire won the 2003 Godel Prize and the 2004 Kanellakis Award, both for their work on boosting in Machine Learning.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
6) Why is it the  Godel <i>Prize </i>and the Kanellakis <i>Award? </i>What is the diff between a prize and an award? A quick Google Search says that an Award is a token of effort and merit, while a Prize is something you win in a competition. I doubt that applies. I suspect they are called Prize and Award from historical accident. Does anyone know?</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-20T22:44:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-20T22:44:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>https://plus.google.com/101693130490639305932</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T22:52:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/008</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/008" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-008 |  Efficiently factoring polynomials modulo $p^4$ | 

	Ashish Dwivedi, 

	Rajat Mittal, 

	Nitin Saxena</title>
    <summary>Polynomial factoring has famous practical algorithms over fields-- finite, rational \&amp; $p$-adic. However, modulo prime powers it gets hard as there is non-unique factorization and a combinatorial blowup ensues. For example, $x^2+p \bmod p^2$ is irreducible, but $x^2+px \bmod p^2$ has exponentially many factors! We present the first randomized poly($\deg f, \log p$) time algorithm to factor a given univariate integral $f(x)$ modulo $p^k$, for a prime $p$ and $k \leq 4$. Thus, we solve the open question of factoring modulo $p^3$ posed in (Sircana, ISSAC'17). 

Our method reduces the general problem of factoring $f(x) \bmod p^k$ to that of {\em root finding} in a related polynomial $E(y) \bmod\langle p^k, \varphi(x)^\ell \rangle$ for some irreducible $\varphi \bmod p$. We could efficiently solve the latter for $k\le4$, by incrementally transforming $E(y)$. Moreover, we discover an efficient and strong generalization of Hensel lifting to lift factors of $f(x) \bmod p$ to those  $\bmod\ p^4$ (if possible). This was previously unknown, as the case of repeated factors of $f(x) \bmod p$ forbids classical Hensel lifting.</summary>
    <updated>2019-01-20T09:00:53Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-20T09:00:53Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:26:44Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7400</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/20/the-firewall-paradox-in-context/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Why physicists care about the Firewall Paradox</title>
    <summary>[Guest post by Noah Miller – a Harvard Physics Ph.D student that took our seminar. Noah’s webpage contains wonderful and extensive notes that can be of interest to computer scientists. –Boaz] (The following blog post serves as an introduction to the following notes:) Black Holes, Hawking Radiation, and the Firewall There are many different types of “theoretical physicists.” There are theoretical […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>[Guest post by </em><a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/noahmiller"><em>Noah Miller</em></a><em> – a Harvard Physics Ph.D student that took our seminar. Noah’s webpage contains wonderful and extensive notes that can be of interest to computer scientists. –Boaz]</em></p>



<p/>



<p>(The following blog post serves as an introduction to the following notes:)</p>



<p><a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/files/noahmiller/files/firewall.pdf">Black Holes, Hawking Radiation, and the Firewall</a></p>



<p>There are many different types of “theoretical physicists.” There are theoretical astrophysicists, theoretical condensed matter physicists, and even theoretical biophysicists. However, the general public seems to be most interested in the exploits of what you might call “theoretical high energy theorists.” (Think Stephen Hawking.)</p>



<p>The holy grail for theoretical high energy physicists (who represent only a small fraction of all physicists) would be to find a theory of quantum gravity. As it stands now, physicists have two theories of nature: quantum field theory (or, more specifically, the “Standard Model”) and Einstein’s theory of general relativity. Quantum field theory describes elementary particles, like electrons, photons, quarks, gluons, etc. General relativity describes the force of gravity, which is really just a consequence of the curvature of spacetimes. </p>



<p>Sometimes people like to say that quantum field theory describes “small stuff” like particles, while general relativity describes “big stuff” like planets and stars. This is maybe not the best way to think about it, though, because planets and stars are ultimately just made out of a bunch of quantum particles.</p>



<p>Theoretical physicists are unhappy with having two theories of nature. In order to describe phenomena that depend on both quantum field theory and general relativity, the two theories must be combined in an “ad hoc” way. A so-called “theory of everything,” another name for the currently unknown theory of “quantum gravity,” would hypothetically be able to describe all the phenomena we know about. Just so we’re all on the same page, they don’t even have a fuly worked out hypothesis. (“String theory,” a popular candidate, is still not even a complete “theory” in the normal sense of the word, although it could become one eventually.)</p>



<p>So what should these high energy theoretical physicists do if they want to discover what this theory of quantum gravity is? For the time being, nobody can think up an experiment that would be sensitive to quantum gravitation effects which is feasible with current technology. We are limited to so-called “thought experiments.”</p>



<p>This brings us to Hawking radiation. In the 1970’s, Stephen Hawking considered what would happen to a black hole once quantum field theory was properly taken into account. (Of course, this involved a bit of “ad hoc” reasoning, as mentioned previously.) Hawking found that, much to everybody’s surprise, the black hole evaporated, realeasing energy in the form of “Hawking radiation” (mostly low energy photons). More strangely, this radiation comes out exactly in the spectrum you would expect from something “hot.” For example, imagine heating a piece of metal. At low temperatures, it emits low energy photons invisible to the human eye. Once it gets hotter, it glows red, then yellow, then perhaps eventually blue. The spectrum of light emitted follows a very specific pattern. Amazingly, Hawking found that the radiation which black holes emit follow the exact same pattern. By analogy, they have a temperature too!</p>



<p>This is more profound than you might realize. This is because things which have an temperature should also have an “entropy.” You see, there are two notions of “states” in physics: “microstates” and “macrostates.” A microstate gives you the complete physical information of what comprises a physical system. For example, imagine you have a box of gas, which contains many particles moving in a seemingly random manner. A “microstate” of this box would be a list of all the positions and momenta of every last particle in that box. This would be impossible to measure in pratice. A “macrostate,” on the other hand, is a set of microstates. You may not know what the exact microstate your box of gas is in, but you can measure macroscopic quantities (like the total internal energy, volume, particle number) and consider the set of all possible microstates with those measured quantities.</p>



<p>The “entropy” of a macrostate is the logarithm of the number of possible microstates. If black holes truly are thermodynamic systems with some entropy, that means there should be some “hidden variables” or microstates to the black hole that we currently don’t understand. Perhaps if we understood the microstates of the black hole, we would be much closer to understanding quantum gravity!</p>



<p>However, Hawking also discovered something else. Because the black hole is radiating out energy, its mass will actually decrease as time goes on. Eventually, it should disappear entirely. This means that the information of what went into the black hole will be lost forever.</p>



<p>Physicists did not like this, however, because it seemed to them that the information of what went into the black hole should never be lost. Many physicists believe that the information of what went into the black hole should somehow be contained in the outgoing Hawking radiation, although they do not currently understand how. According to Hawking’s original calculation, the Hawking radiation only depends on a parameters of the black hole (like its mass) and have nothing to do with the many finer details on what went in, the exact “microstate” of what went in.</p>



<p>However, physicists eventually realized a problem with the idea that the black hole releases its information in the form of outgoing Hawking radiation. The problem has to do with quantum mechanics. In quantum mechanics, it is impossible to clone a qubit. That means that if you threw a qubit in a black hole and then waited for it to eventually come out in the form of Hawking radiation, then the qubit could no longer be “inside” the black hole. However, if Einstein is to be believed, you should also be able to jump into the black hole and see the qubit on the inside. This seems to imply that the qubit is cloned, as it is present on both the inside and outside of the black hole.</p>



<p>Physicists eventually came up with a strange fix called “Black Hole Complementarity” (BHC). According to BHC, according to people outside the black hole, the interior does not exist. Also, according to people who have entered the black hole, the outside ceases to exist. Both descriptions of the world are “correct” because once someone has entered the black hole, they will be unable to escape and compare notes with the person on the outside.</p>



<p>Of course, it must be emphasized that BHC remains highly hypothetical. People have been trying to poke holes in it for a long time. The largest hole is the so called “Firewall Paradox,” first proposed in 2012. Essentially, the Firewall paradox tries to show that the paradigm of BHC is self-contradictory.  In fact, it was able to use basic quantum mechanics to show that, under some reasonable assumptions, the interior of the black hole <em>truly</em> doesn’t exist, and that anyone who tries to enter would be fried at an extremely hot “firewall!” Now, I don’t think most physicists actually believe that black holes really have a firewall (although this might depend on what day of the week you ask them). The interesting thing about the Firewall paradox is that it derives a seemingly crazy result from seemingly harmless starting suppositions. So these suppositions would have to be tweaked in the theory of quantum gravity order to get rid of the firewall.</p>



<p>This is all to say that all this thinking about black holes really might help physicists figure out something about quantum gravity. (Then again, who can really say for sure.)</p>



<p>If you would like to know more about the Firewall paradox, I suggest you read my notes, pasted at the top of this post!</p>



<p>The goal of the notes was to write an introduction to the Black Hole Information Paradox and Firewall Paradox that could be read by computer scientists with no physics background.</p>



<p>The structure of the notes goes as follows:</p>



<ol><li>Special relativity</li><li>General relativity</li><li>Quantum Field Theory (in which I ambitiously tell you what QFT actually is!)</li><li>Statistical Mechanics (this is the best part)</li><li>Hawking radiation</li><li>The information paradox</li></ol>



<p>Because the information paradox touches on all areas of physics, I thought it was necessary to take “zero background, infinite intelligence” approach, introducing the all the necessary branches of physics (GR, QFT, Stat Mech) in order to understand what the deal with Hawking radiation really is, and why physicists think it is so important. I think it is safe to say that if you read these notes, you’ll learn a non-trivial amount of physics.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-20T06:00:25Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-20T06:00:25Z</published>
    <category term="physics"/>
    <category term="cs229r"/>
    <author>
      <name>noahmiller5490</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/18/postdoc-at-ut-austin-apply-by-february-5-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/18/postdoc-at-ut-austin-apply-by-february-5-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at UT Austin (apply by February 5, 2019)</title>
    <summary>UT Austin invites applications for a Postdoctoral Fellow in theoretical computer science for the 2019-20 academic year to work with David Zuckerman. Research interests should overlap with his: pseudorandomness, computational complexity, coding theory, and more. Applications will be considered until the position is filled, but review of applicants will begin on February 5. Website: https://utaustin.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/UTstaff/job/UT-MAIN-CAMPUS/Postdoctoral-Fellow_R_00001518 […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>UT Austin invites applications for a Postdoctoral Fellow in theoretical computer science for the 2019-20 academic year to work with David Zuckerman. Research interests should overlap with his: pseudorandomness, computational complexity, coding theory, and more. Applications will be considered until the position is filled, but review of applicants will begin on February 5.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://utaustin.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/UTstaff/job/UT-MAIN-CAMPUS/Postdoctoral-Fellow_R_00001518">https://utaustin.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/UTstaff/job/UT-MAIN-CAMPUS/Postdoctoral-Fellow_R_00001518</a><br/>
Email: diz@utexas.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-18T16:52:08Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-18T16:52:08Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://thmatters.wordpress.com/?p=1263</id>
    <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2019/01/18/sigact-award-deadlines/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>SIGACT Award deadlines</title>
    <summary>From the SIGACT executive committee: The deadlines to submit nominations for the Gödel Prize, Knuth Prize, and SIGACT Distinguished Service Award are coming soon. Calls for nominations for all three awards can be found at the links below. Note that March 1 is now the permanent deadline for SIGACT Distinguished Service Award nominations, this year […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>From the SIGACT executive committee:</p>
<p>The deadlines to submit nominations for the Gödel Prize, Knuth Prize, and SIGACT Distinguished Service Award are coming soon. Calls for nominations for all three awards can be found at the links below. Note that March 1 is now the permanent deadline for SIGACT Distinguished Service Award nominations, this year and in future years.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://sigact.org/prizes/g%C3%B6del/g%C3%B6del_call19.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Gödel Prize</a>: deadline <strong>February 15, 2019</strong></li>
<li><a href="https://sigact.org/prizes/knuth/knuth19.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Knuth Prize</a>: deadline <strong>February 15, 2019</strong></li>
<li><a href="https://sigact.org/prizes/service.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">SIGACT Distinguished Service Award</a>: deadline <strong>March 1, every year (including 2019)</strong><br/>
<em>Those who intend to submit a nomination for the Distinguished Service Award are strongly encouraged to inform the Selection Committee Chair at least two weeks in advance.</em></li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-18T14:37:13Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-18T14:37:13Z</published>
    <category term="awards"/>
    <category term="Deadlines"/>
    <author>
      <name>shuchic</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://thmatters.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theory Matters</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3375</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/01/18/upcoming-nomination-deadlines-godel-knuth-and-sigact-distinguished-service-award/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Upcoming Nomination Deadlines: Gödel, Knuth, and SIGACT Distinguished Service Award</title>
    <summary>The deadlines to submit nominations for the Gödel Prize, Knuth Prize, and SIGACT Distinguished Service Award are coming soon. Calls for nominations for all three awards can be found at the links below. Note that March 1 is now the permanent deadline for SIGACT Distinguished Service Award nominations, this year and in future years. Gödel […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div>
<p>The deadlines to submit nominations for the Gödel Prize, Knuth Prize, and SIGACT Distinguished Service Award are coming soon. Calls for nominations for all three awards can be found at the links below. Note that March 1 is now the permanent deadline for SIGACT Distinguished Service Award nominations, this year and in future years.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://sigact.org/prizes/g&#xF6;del/g&#xF6;del_call19.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Gödel Prize</a>: deadline <strong>February 15, 2019</strong></li>
<li><a href="https://sigact.org/prizes/knuth/knuth19.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Knuth Prize</a>: deadline <strong>February 15, 2019</strong></li>
<li><a href="https://sigact.org/prizes/service.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">SIGACT Distinguished Service Award</a>: deadline <strong>March 1, every year (including 2019)</strong><br/>
<em>Those who intend to submit a nomination for the Distinguished Service Award are strongly encouraged to inform the Selection Committee Chair at least two weeks in advance.</em></li>
</ul>
<div class="yj6qo"/>
<div class="adL"/>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-18T03:35:08Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-18T03:35:08Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>robertkleinberg</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:26:54Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/17/orientations-infinite-graphs</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/17/orientations-infinite-graphs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Orientations of infinite graphs</title>
    <summary>An orientation of an undirected graph is the directed graph that you get by assigning a direction to each edge. Several kinds of orientations have been studied. For instance, in a graph with even vertex degrees, an Eulerian orientation makes the numbers of incoming and outgoing degrees equal at each vertex. In a bridgeless graph, a strong orientation makes the resulting directed graph strongly connected. In finite connected graphs, every Eulerian orientation is strong, but that is untrue in infinite graphs. Consider, for instance, the graph of unit distances on the integers, which is Eulerian (every vertex has degree two) but has no strong orientation (every edge is a bridge). Even when a strong orientation exists, an Eulerian orientation might not be strong: the graph of distance-1 and distance-2 integers, with the orientation from smaller to larger numbers, is Eulerian but not strong. So when does an Eulerian strong orientation exist? The answer turns out to be: whenever the obvious obstacles are not present. Every bridgeless connected even-degree infinite graph has an Eulerian strong orientation.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>An <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orientation_(graph_theory)">orientation</a> of an undirected graph is the directed graph that you get by assigning a direction to each edge. Several kinds of orientations have been studied. For instance, in a graph with even vertex degrees, an Eulerian orientation makes the numbers of incoming and outgoing degrees equal at each vertex. In a bridgeless graph, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strong_orientation">strong orientation</a> makes the resulting directed graph strongly connected. In finite connected graphs, every Eulerian orientation is strong, but that is untrue in infinite graphs. Consider, for instance, the graph of unit distances on the integers, which is Eulerian (every vertex has degree two) but has no strong orientation (every edge is a bridge). Even when a strong orientation exists, an Eulerian orientation might not be strong: the graph of distance-1 and distance-2 integers, with the orientation from smaller to larger numbers, is Eulerian but not strong. So when does an Eulerian strong orientation exist? The answer turns out to be: whenever the obvious obstacles are not present. Every bridgeless connected even-degree infinite graph has an Eulerian strong orientation.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="For infinite graphs, Eulerian orientations might not be strong" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/euler-not-strong.svg"/></p>

<p>To prove this, we can use a convenient tool for dealing with infinite orientations by looking only at finite graphs, a result of Rado from 1949 that is simultaneously a predecessor and generalization of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_Bruijn%E2%80%93Erd%C5%91s_theorem_(graph_theory)">De Bruijn–Erdős theorem on graph colorings</a>. Suppose each element in some infinite set  has a finite set of labels, and we choose an assignment of labels for each finite subset of . These choices may be inconsistent with each other, so there may be no way of labeling all of  consistently with all of the choices. But Rado proved (assuming the axiom of choice) that there exists a global labeling that, on every finite subset, is consistent with the assignment to one of its finite supersets. Another way of thinking about this is that if certain finite patterns must be avoided, and every finite subset has a labeling that avoids them, then some global labeling will also avoid them.<sup id="fnref:rado"><a class="footnote" href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/17/orientations-infinite-graphs.html#fn:rado">1</a></sup> The De Bruijn–Erdős theorem is the case where the elements are vertices, the labels are colors, and the patterns to be avoided are pairs of equal color on adjacent vertices. In our case the set elements will be edges, the labels will be which way to orient each edge, and the choice of assignment will be some way of defining a “good” orientation for finite subgraphs.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Graph vertices can be labeled by color; edges, by orientation" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/graph-labels.svg"/></p>

<p>So suppose we’re given a finite subgraph  of an infinite 2-edge-connected even-degree graph. What kind of orientation on  should we look for? A complication is that  might have bridges or odd-degree vertices. So we’ll try to come as close as we can to what we want, an Eulerian strong orientation, while taking those deficiencies into account. Let’s define a good orientation of  to be an orientation that is almost Eulerian, in that at each vertex the in-degree and out-degree differ by at most one, and almost strong, in that each edge of  that belongs to an undirected cycle also belongs to a directed cycle. Another way of stating the almost strong condition is that the strongly connected components of the oriented graph should coincide with the 2-edge-connected components, or blocks, of the undirected graph.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="A good orientation of a graph" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/good-orientation.svg"/></p>

<p>The existence of a good orientation of an arbitrary finite undirected graph (also having some other stronger properties) was proven in the 1960s by Nash-Williams.<sup id="fnref:nw"><a class="footnote" href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/17/orientations-infinite-graphs.html#fn:nw">2</a></sup> But now Rado’s method proves that every infinite graph also has a good orientation. If we find a global orientation that’s nearly-Eulerian on a supergraph of the star of neighbors of every vertex, then it must be nearly-Eulerian. And if it’s almost strong on a supergraph of every cycle, then it must be almost strong. This proves the theorem that a bridgeless connected even-degree infinite graph has an Eulerian strong orientation, because every good orientation in these graphs must be Eulerian and strong. Nash-Williams already considered the infinite case of his orientation theorem, but wrote that the details were too heavy to include. Perhaps he didn’t know about Rado’s theorem (despite it being published in the same journal), which makes the extension from finite to infinite easy.</p>

<p>The same method of extending finite to infinite orientations can also be used to study notions of graph sparseness including <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arboricity">arboricity</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Degeneracy_(graph_theory)">degeneracy</a>, and pseudoarboricity. Historically the pseudoarboricity of infinite graphs was first. A graph has pseudoarboricity at most  if it can be oriented so that each vertex has out-degree  (or equivalently if it can be partitioned into subgraphs each with out-degree one). In the 1950 paper in which he first announced the De Bruijn–Erdős theorem, Erdős used it to prove that, when such an orientation is given, the resulting graph can be -colored.<sup id="fnref:e"><a class="footnote" href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/17/orientations-infinite-graphs.html#fn:e">3</a></sup> But he didn’t write about the conditions under which such an orientation exists. Rado’s theorem shows that they are the same as in the finite case: an outdegree- orientation exists if and only if every finite -vertex subgraph has at most  edges.</p>

<p>A graph has degeneracy at most  if it has an acyclic orientation so that each vertex has out-degree . Unlike in the finite case, infinite graphs with low degeneracy might have high minimum degree; for instance, there exist graphs with degeneracy one in which all vertices have infinite degree. A finite -degenerate graph can be -colored greedily, and the De Bruijn–Erdős theorem shows that even in the infinite case such a coloring exists. Rado’s theorem shows that infinite graphs with pseudoarboricity  are -degenerate, and that a graph is -degenerate if and only if every finite subgraph has a vertex with degree at most . As in the case of Eulerian strong orientations, this involves checking the orientation only on two kinds of finite subgraphs, stars and cycles.</p>

<p>Arboricity is based on forests and there are multiple incompatible definitions of infinite forests. But the one we want to use is that a forest is a 1-degenerate graph. A graph has arboricity  if its edges can be partitioned into  forests. This is clearly at least as large as the degeneracy (no Rado needed). Rado’s theorem shows that infinite graphs with arboricity  are -degenerate, and that a graph has arboricity at most  if and only if every finite -vertex subset has at most  edges.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:rado">
      <p>Rado, R. (1949), “<a href="https://doi.org/10.4153/cjm-1949-031-1">Axiomatic treatment of rank in infinite sets</a>”, <em>Canad. J. Math.</em> 1: 337–343. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/17/orientations-infinite-graphs.html#fnref:rado">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:nw">
      <p>Nash-Williams, C. St. J. A. (1960), “<a href="https://doi.org/10.4153/cjm-1960-049-6">On orientations, connectivity and odd-vertex-pairings in finite graphs</a>”, <em>Canad. J. Math.</em>, 12: 555–567; —— (1969), “Well-balanced orientations of finite graphs and unobtrusive odd-vertex-pairings”, <em>Recent Progress in Combinatorics (Proc. Third Waterloo Conf. on Combinatorics, 1968)</em>, New York: Academic Press, pp. 133–149. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/17/orientations-infinite-graphs.html#fnref:nw">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:e">
      <p>Erdős, P. (1950), “<a href="https://users.renyi.hu/~p_erdos/1950-13.pdf">Some remarks on set theory</a>”, <em>Proc. AMS</em>, 1: 127–141. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/17/orientations-infinite-graphs.html#fnref:e">↩</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101435740463423422">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-17T20:39:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-17T20:39:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-01-18T04:45:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8539994327270054973</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/8539994327270054973/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/the-cost-of-privacy.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8539994327270054973" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8539994327270054973" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/the-cost-of-privacy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Cost of Privacy</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody>
<tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-8HqZkaSkvdw/XD82UgwmqHI/AAAAAAABmMQ/6zYMalG9fXUS5OF28uajL8MOiXo6igmaACLcBGAs/s1600/iphone.jpeg" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="182" src="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-8HqZkaSkvdw/XD82UgwmqHI/AAAAAAABmMQ/6zYMalG9fXUS5OF28uajL8MOiXo6igmaACLcBGAs/s200/iphone.jpeg" width="200"/></a></td></tr>
<tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">Billboard at 2019 CES</td></tr>
</tbody></table>
<br/>Computer scientists tend to obsess about privacy and we've had a privacy/security debate for decades now. But now machine learning has really given us a whole new spin on what privacy protects and takes away.<br/>
<div>
<br/>
I take an open approach and basically allow Google to know everything about my life. Google knows where I've been--sometimes my Pixel asks me which store in a shopping center I visited and I give up that info. Google knows who I communicate with, what websites I visit, what music and movies I listen to and watch, all my photos, what temperature makes me comfortable and so on.<br/>
<br/>
What do I get? A Google ecosystem that knows me sometimes better than I know myself. Google works best when it learns and integrates. I get asked to download maps for trips Google knows I'm about to take. I have Google assistant throughout my house, in my phone, in my car and it tailor answers and sometimes even the questions that I need answers to. If anything I wish there was further integration, like Google Voice should ring my office phone only when I'm in the office.<br/>
<br/>
Georgia Tech now forces us to use Microsoft Exchange for email. Outlook is not a bad email program but its capabilities, especially for search, does not work as well and think of all that unused knowledge.<br/>
<br/>
I trust Google to keep my information safe, with a random password and 2-factor encryption and even if someone would manage to break in they would find I'm a pretty boring person with an unhealthy obsession of opera (the musical form not the browser).<br/>
<br/>
Doesn't work for everyone and companies should make it easy to keep your info secure. But I say go use your machine learning on me and find ways to make my life easier and more fun, and sure send me some targeted ads as payment. The Internets will find a way to discover you anyway, might as well take advantage. </div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-17T17:45:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-17T17:45:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>https://plus.google.com/101693130490639305932</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>https://plus.google.com/101693130490639305932</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T22:52:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/007</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/007" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-007 |  Lower Bounds for Linear Decision Lists | 

	Arkadev Chattopadhyay, 

	Meena Mahajan, 

	Nikhil Mande, 

	Nitin Saurabh</title>
    <summary>We demonstrate a lower bound technique for linear decision lists, which are decision lists where the queries are arbitrary linear threshold functions.
We use this technique to prove an explicit lower bound by showing that any linear decision list computing the function $MAJ \circ XOR$ requires size $2^{0.18 n}$.  This completely answers an open question of Tur{\'a}n and Vatan [FoCM'97]. We also show that the spectral classes $PL_1, PL_\infty$, and the polynomial threshold function classes $\widehat{PT}_1, PT_1$,  are incomparable to linear decision lists.</summary>
    <updated>2019-01-17T16:40:39Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-17T16:40:39Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:26:44Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/17/dimea-days-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/17/dimea-days-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>DIMEA Days 2019</title>
    <summary>June 12-13, 2019 Brno, Czech Republic https://www.fi.muni.cz/research/dimea/days19.html Registration deadline: March 31, 2019</summary>
    <updated>2019-01-17T10:51:30Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-17T10:51:30Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:28:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/17/gdansk-summer-school-of-advanced-science-on-algorithms-for-discrete-optimization/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/17/gdansk-summer-school-of-advanced-science-on-algorithms-for-discrete-optimization/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Gdańsk Summer School of Advanced Science on Algorithms for Discrete Optimization</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">July 6-12, 2019 Gdansk, Poland https://eti.pg.edu.pl/advanced-science-on-algorithms/advanced-science The school aims at providing an opportunity for graduate and undergraduate students as well as young researchers to get together and attend advanced courses and talks on current topics in the field of algorithms and data structures for discrete optimization problems. During 8 days of the school, 6 advanced … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/17/gdansk-summer-school-of-advanced-science-on-algorithms-for-discrete-optimization/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Gdańsk Summer School of Advanced Science on Algorithms for Discrete Optimization</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-17T10:51:24Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-17T10:51:24Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:28:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/17/nice-summer-school-on-random-walks-and-complex-networks/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/17/nice-summer-school-on-random-walks-and-complex-networks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Nice summer school on random walks and complex networks</title>
    <summary>July 8-19, 2019 Nice, France https://math.unice.fr/~dmitsche/Summerschool/Summerschool.html Registration deadline: May 1, 2019 This 2-week-summer school aims to explain concepts on random walks and random models for complex networks at a level suitable for second year master students and PhD students in mathematics and theoretical computer science.</summary>
    <updated>2019-01-17T10:51:20Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-17T10:51:20Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:28:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/006</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/006" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-006 |  Upper Bounds on Communication in terms of Approximate Rank | 

	Anna Gal, 

	Ridwan Syed</title>
    <summary>We show that any Boolean function with approximate rank $r$ can be computed by bounded error quantum protocols without prior entanglement of complexity $O( \sqrt{r} \log r)$. In addition, we show that any Boolean function with approximate rank $r$ and discrepancy $\delta$ can be computed by deterministic protocols of complexity $O(r)$, and private coin bounded error randomized protocols of complexity $O((\frac{1}{\delta})^2 + \log r)$. Our results yield lower bounds on approximate rank. We also obtain a strengthening of Newman's theorem with respect to approximate rank.</summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T22:58:33Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-16T22:58:33Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:26:44Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/005</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/005" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-005 |  An Exponential Lower Bound on the Sub-Packetization of MSR Codes | 

	Omar Alrabiah, 

	Venkatesan Guruswami</title>
    <summary>An $(n,k,\ell)$-vector MDS code is a $\mathbb{F}$-linear subspace of $(\mathbb{F}^\ell)^n$ (for some field $\mathbb{F}$) of dimension $k\ell$, such that any $k$ (vector) symbols of the codeword suffice to determine the remaining $r=n-k$ (vector) symbols. The length $\ell$ of each codeword symbol is called the sub-packetization of the code. Such a code is called minimum storage regenerating (MSR), if any single symbol of a codeword can be recovered by downloading $\ell/r$ field elements (which is known to be the least possible) from each of the other symbols.

MSR codes are attractive for use in distributed storage systems, and by now a variety of ingenious constructions of MSR codes are available. However, they all suffer from exponentially large sub-packetization of at least $r^{k/r}$. Our main result is an almost tight lower bound showing that for an MSR code, one must have $\ell \ge \exp(\Omega(k/r))$. Previously, a lower bound of $\approx \exp(\sqrt{k/r})$, and a tight lower bound for a restricted class of optimal access MSR codes, were known. Our work settles a key question concerning MSR codes that has received much attention, with a short proof hinging on one key definition that is somewhat inspired by Galois theory.</summary>
    <updated>2019-01-16T18:36:24Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-16T18:36:24Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:26:44Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/16/motwani-postdoctoral-fellowship-at-stanford-computer-science-apply-by-december-21-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/16/motwani-postdoctoral-fellowship-at-stanford-computer-science-apply-by-december-21-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Motwani Postdoctoral Fellowship at Stanford Computer Science (apply by December 21, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The theory group at Stanford invites applications for the Motwani postdoctoral fellowship in theoretical computer science. Information and application instructions below. Applications will be accepted until the positions are filled, but review of applicants will begin after Jan 21. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/13134 Email: theory.stanford@gmail.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The theory group at Stanford invites applications for the Motwani postdoctoral fellowship in theoretical computer science. Information and application instructions below.</p>
<p>Applications will be accepted until the positions are filled, but review of applicants will begin after Jan 21.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/13134">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/13134</a><br/>
Email: theory.stanford@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-16T18:32:56Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-16T18:32:56Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/9th-phd-summer-school-in-discrete-mathematics/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/9th-phd-summer-school-in-discrete-mathematics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>9th PhD Summer School in Discrete Mathematics</title>
    <summary>June 30 – July 6, 2019 Rogla, Slovenia https://conferences.famnit.upr.si/event/12/ The summer school will offer two mini-courses: “Combinatorial limits and their applications in extremal combinatorics” and “Coxeter groups”, as well as invited talks and student talks</summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:09:50Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T23:09:50Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:28:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/5th-algorithmic-and-enumerative-combinatorics-summer-school-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/5th-algorithmic-and-enumerative-combinatorics-summer-school-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>5th Algorithmic and Enumerative Combinatorics Summer School 2019</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">July 29 – August 2, 2019 Hagenberg, Austria https://www3.risc.jku.at/conferences/aec2019/index.html n the spirit of the AEC2014, AEC2015, AEC2016 and AEC2018, the goal of this summer school is to put forward the interplay between the fields of Enumerative Combinatorics, Analytic Combinatorics, and Algorithmics. This is a very active research area, which, aside from the three fields fueling … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/5th-algorithmic-and-enumerative-combinatorics-summer-school-2019/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">5th Algorithmic and Enumerative Combinatorics Summer School 2019</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:09:30Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T23:09:30Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:28:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/spring-school-and-workshop-on-polytopes/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/spring-school-and-workshop-on-polytopes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Spring School and Workshop on Polytopes</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">March 11-15, 2019 Bochum, Germany https://www.rub.de/polytopes2019/ Registration deadline: February 11, 2019 The Spring School is designed for advanced bachelor, master and PhD students. The aim is to prepare the participants in such a way that they can follow the lectures of the subsequent workshop. It consists of three crash courses: Geometry of Polytopes, Monday (2x2h) … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/15/spring-school-and-workshop-on-polytopes/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Spring School and Workshop on Polytopes</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-15T23:08:56Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T23:08:56Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:28:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>For the new year, I’ve decided to try to get back into taking photos more frequently, and to make it lower-overhead I’m making individual Mastodon posts for some of them rather than writing a longer blog post for every batch of photos. So that’s why you see a couple of those images inline here.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>For the new year, I’ve decided to try to get back into taking photos more frequently, and to make it lower-overhead I’m making individual Mastodon posts for some of them rather than writing a longer blog post for every batch of photos. So that’s why you see a couple of those images inline here.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://community.wolfram.com/groups/-/m/t/1579272">Fitting in</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@shonk/101320172170027222"/>). Animated GIF of 124 disks packed (supposedly optimally) on a sphere and then steregraphically projected to the plane, by Clayton Shonkwiler.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://twitter.com/BrunoLevy01/status/1080085027210309632">More animated GIFs of fluids with splashy frothy surfaces</a> by Bruno Levy (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101349213452607605"/>). The fluids are modeled as power diagrams of systems of discrete points and simulated using methods from <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1605.00568">arXiv:1605.00568</a>.
See follow-up tweets for source code and long explanatory video.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/help/stats/2018_by_area/index">Lots of charts and plots of the growth of arXiv.org through 2018</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101355877277070622"/>). In the area I moderate (cs.DS, algorithms and data structures) the number of preprints grew from 1597 in 2017 to 1767 in 2018, but this was a little below the 14% growth rate for arXiv overall, and was far outpaced by the rapid growth in cs.CV (computer vision), cs.LG (machine learning), and cs.CL (natural language processing).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.fortbraggalleywayart.org/the-fish-mural.html">Matsya And The Great Deluge</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101361278765845519"/>). Street art from Fort Bragg illustrating an ancient Indian folk tale.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/mfb/MatsyaAndTheGreatDeluge.html"><img alt="&quot;Matsya And The Great Deluge&quot; street art in Fort Bragg, California" src="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/mfb/MatsyaAndTheGreatDeluge-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;"/></a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.metafilter.com/178580/Orange-Peels-and-Fresnel-Integrals-Train-Sets-The-Urinal-Problem">Orange peels and fresnel integrals! Train sets! The urinal problem!</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101366435174480182"/>). Metafilter discovers <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@esoterica">Interesting Esoterica</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/1.9781611975482"><em>Proceedings of the Thirtieth Annual ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA 2019)</em></a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101373871420970067"/>). My favorite talk from the first day of SODA was “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/1.9781611975482.27">Extremal and probabilistic results for order types</a>” (Jie Han, Yoshiharu Kohayakawa, Marcelo T. Sales, and Henrique Stagni).
Its main results are
    <ol>
      <li>the probability that a random point set has a specific order type is upper and lower bounded by functions of the smallest size of a grid containing the order type, and</li>
      <li>every nontrivial hereditary property of point sets has probability  of being true of random point sets.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-iran-demographer-arrests-20190107-story.html">Iran arrests demographers, the latest target amid an escalating crackdown on academics and activists</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101379517186873559"/>). One of the two arrestees is an Iranian-Australian dual citizen; the other is director of the Iranian National Institute of Population Research. The apparent reason for the arrest is that their research contradicted a political narrative of Iranian hardliners according to which Iran is suffering a population crash and must increase fertility.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The first sighting of one of my Wikipedia illustrations in a SODA talk goes to Michał Włodarczyk’s “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/1.9781611975482.104">Losing treewidth by separating subsets</a>” (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101389040748549759"/>). It concerns removing few graph vertices to reach a subgraph with some desired property. If the optimal solution removes  vertices and graphs with the property have treewidth , then his solution removes  vertices and takes the same time as exactly solving  subproblems of size .</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2019/01/analco-sosa-soda-post.html">Michael Mitzenmacher blogs about SODA, SOSA, ALENEX, and ANALCO</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101390458273110460"/>).
Michael was PC co-chair of <a href="https://simplicityinalgorithms.com/">SOSA</a>, which I was skeptical about (shouldn’t all the best algorithms be simple?), but the session I attended favorably impressed me. Here’s an example, a simple algorithm for <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1501.07460">2-approximating maximum genus oriented graph embedding</a>: greedily remove 2-edge paths while preserving connectivity. .</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pubs/EppRee-SODA-19-slides.pdf">My SODA talk slides on finding laminar 3-vertex separators</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101396845733518307"/>). At the talk, someone asked about finding a maximum set of laminar 3-separators. It’s NP-complete: use Uehara’s “<a href="https://www.jaist.ac.jp/~uehara/pdf/triangle.pdf">NP-complete problems on a 3-connected cubic graph and their applications</a>” to find cubic planar graphs whose -separators are vertex neighborhoods (so laminar separators = neighbors of independent vertices) in which maximum independent set is hard.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Spotted on the Cambridge University Press display table at SODA (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101402305412043483"/>):</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/soda-books/index.html"><img alt="Forbidden Configurations in Discrete Geometry on display alongside other Cambridge University Press books" src="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/soda-books/books-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;"/></a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://codeparade.itch.io/marblemarcher">Marble Marcher</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101407478247456589"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=18805717">via</a>). A game of guiding a marble across a dynamically changing fractal surface. The key is to use the recursive structure of the fractal to make a data structure that can handle the interactions between the marble and the fractal surface quickly enough to run in realtime.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://thehighergeometer.wordpress.com/2019/01/13/some-serious-open-access-journals-in-mathematics/">A list of (respectable) open access journals in mathematics</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101410796814360458"/>). <a href="http://jgaa.info/">JGAA</a> and <a href="http://jocg.org/">JoCG</a> not yet listed but maybe soon?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.metafilter.com/178755/Space-filling-curves-the-hard-way">Wacław Szpakowski’s space-filling curve art</a> (<a href="https://mastodon.social/@joshmillard/101415993062003559"/>).</p>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_Bruijn%E2%80%93Erd%C5%91s_theorem_(graph_theory)">The De Bruijn–Erdős theorem</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101421411362488773"/>): when all finite subgraphs of an infinite graph are -colorable, so is the whole graph. Now a Good Article on Wikipedia.</li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-15T22:07:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T22:07:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-01-18T04:45:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4048</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4048" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4048#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4048" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">The Winding Road to Quantum Supremacy</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Greetings from QIP’2019 in Boulder, Colorado! Obvious highlights of the conference include Urmila Mahadev’s opening plenary talk on her verification protocol for quantum computation (which I blogged about here), and Avishay Tal’s upcoming plenary on his and Ran Raz’s oracle separation between BQP and PH (which I blogged about here). If you care, here are […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Greetings from <a href="https://jila.colorado.edu/qip2019/">QIP’2019</a> in Boulder, Colorado!  Obvious highlights of the conference include Urmila Mahadev’s opening plenary talk on her verification protocol for quantum computation (which I blogged about <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3697">here</a>), and Avishay Tal’s upcoming plenary on his and Ran Raz’s oracle separation between BQP and PH (which I blogged about <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3827">here</a>).  If you care, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/talks/online.ppt">here</a> are the slides for the talk I just gave, on the paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1802.09025">“Online Learning of Quantum States”</a> by me, Xinyi Chen, Elad Hazan, Satyen Kale, and Ashwin Nayak.  Feel free to ask in the comments about what else is going on.</p>



<p>I returned a few days ago from my whirlwind Australia tour, which included Melbourne and Sydney; a Persian wedding that happened to be held next to a pirate ship (the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MY_Steve_Irwin">Steve Irwin</a>, used to harass whalers and adorned with a huge Jolly Roger); meetings and lectures graciously arranged by friends at <a href="https://www.uts.edu.au/">UTS</a>; a quantum computing lab tour personally conducted by 2018 “Australian of the Year” <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michelle_Simmons">Michelle Simmons</a>; three meetups with readers of this blog (or more often, readers of the <em>other</em> Scott A’s blog who graciously settled for the discount Scott A); and an excursion to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grampians_National_Park">Grampians National Park</a> to see wild kangaroos, wallabies, koalas, and emus.</p>



<p>But the thing that happened in Australia that provided the actual occassion for this post is this: I was interviewed by Adam Ford in Carlton Gardens in Melbourne, about quantum supremacy, AI risk, Integrated Information Theory, whether the universe is discrete or continuous, and to be honest I don’t remember what else.  You can watch the first segment, the one about the prospects for quantum supremacy, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=1&amp;v=BvVciA5iXH4">here on YouTube</a>.  My only complaint is that Adam’s video camera <em>somehow</em> made me look like an out-of-shape slob who needs to hit the gym or something.</p>



<p><strong><font color="red">Update (Jan. 16):</font></strong> Adam has now posted a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=397&amp;v=cscRdv57oRQ">second video on YouTube</a>, wherein I talk about my <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/papers/giqtm3.pdf">“Ghost in the Quantum Turing Machine”</a> paper, my critique of Integrated Information Theory, and more.</p>



<p>And now Adam has posted <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gi67h6v-6fc">yet a third segment</a>, in which I talk about small, lighthearted things like existential threats to civilization and the prospects for superintelligent AI.</p>



<p>And a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WjuuO1HnOR4">fourth</a>, in which I talk about whether reality is discrete or continuous.</p>



<p>Related to the “free will / consciousness” segment of the interview: the biologist Jerry Coyne, whose blog <a href="https://whyevolutionistrue.wordpress.com/">“Why Evolution Is True”</a> I’ve intermittently enjoyed over the years, yesterday <a href="https://whyevolutionistrue.wordpress.com/2019/01/15/a-computer-scientist-finds-the-question-of-free-will-uninteresting-for-bad-reasons/">announced my existence to his readers</a>, with a post that mostly criticizes my views about free will and predictability, as I expressed them years ago in a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fp02OJVGG20">clip that’s on YouTube</a> (at the time, Coyne hadn’t seen GIQTM or my other writings on the subject).  Coyne also took the opportunity to poke fun at this weird character he just came across whose “life is devoted to computing” and who even mistakes tips for change at airport smoothie stands.  Some friends here at QIP had a good laugh over the fact that, for the world beyond theoretical computer science and quantum information, this is what 23 years of research, teaching, and writing apparently boil down to: an 8.5-minute video clip where I spouted about free will, and also my having been arrested once in a comic mix-up at Philadelphia airport.  Anyway, since then I had a very pleasant email exchange with Coyne—someone with whom I find myself in agreement much more often than not, and who I’d love to have an extended conversation with sometime despite the odd way our interaction started.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-15T18:51:16Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T18:51:16Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-01-18T14:51:09Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-4806966094683791166</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/4806966094683791166/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/do-we-ever-only-care-about-decision.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/4806966094683791166" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/4806966094683791166" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/do-we-ever-only-care-about-decision.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>do we ever only care about the decision problem? I know of only one case of that</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(I had been thinking of this for a post then Lance's post on <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/search-versus-decision.html">search versus decision</a> inspired me to write up these thoughts.)<br/>
<br/>
When teaching NP-completeness we often say<br/>
<br/>
<i>The problem we really care about is, for example, given a weighted graph and two vertices s and t, find the optimal way to go from s to t while hitting every node. But its cleaner mathematically to look at the decision problem:</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
<i>{ (G,s,t,C) : there is a Ham Path from s to t that costs \le C }</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
<i>The search and decision are poly time equivalent, so its fine to just look at the decision. Indeed- if our interest in in lower bounds then clearly if Decision is hard then Find is Hard.</i><br/>
<br/>
But here are some questions about search vs decision in general, not just with regard to P vs NP.<br/>
<br/>
1) Is there ever a case where the real world actually cares about the decision version? I can think of just one- given a number is it PRIME is used in Crypto. The real world does not need the witness that its prime (or similar).  They  just want a prime.  Any other cases?<br/>
<br/>
2) How far apart can search and decision be? NP-decision and NP-search they are poly equivalent. In other domains can they be very far apart? For example, is FINDING a k-clique or k-ind set in a graph on 2^{2k} vertices require roughly n^k steps (go through all k-sets) or can we do much better? I suspect this is unknown but would be delighted if a commenter tells me otherwise.<br/>
<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-15T16:21:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T16:21:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>https://plus.google.com/101693130490639305932</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T22:52:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://bit-player.org/?p=2108</id>
    <link href="http://bit-player.org/2019/glaubers-dynamics" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://bit-player.org/2019/glaubers-dynamics#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://bit-player.org/2019/glaubers-dynamics/feed/atom" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Glauber’s dynamics</title>
    <summary type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Roy J. Glauber, Harvard physics professor for 65 years, longtime Keeper of the Broom at the annual Ig Nobel ceremony, and winner of a non-Ig Nobel, has died at age 93. Glauber is known for his work in quantum optics; … <a href="http://bit-player.org/2019/glaubers-dynamics">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Roy J. Glauber, Harvard physics professor for 65 years, longtime Keeper of the Broom at the annual <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ig_Nobel_Prize">Ig Nobel</a> ceremony, and winner of a non-Ig Nobel, has died at age 93. Glauber is known for his work in quantum optics; roughly speaking, he developed a mathematical theory of the laser at about the same time that device was invented, circa 1960. His two main papers on the subject, published in <em>Physical Review</em> in 1963, did not meet with instant acclaim; the Nobel committee’s recognition of their worth came more than 40 years later, in 2005. A third paper from 1963, titled “<a href="https://aip.scitation.org/doi/10.1063/1.1703954">Time-dependent statistics of the Ising model</a>,” also had a delayed impact. It is the basis of a modeling algorithm now called Glauber dynamics, which is well known in the cloistered community of statistical mechanics but deserves wider recognition.</p>
<p>Before digging into the dynamics, however, let us pause for a few words about the man himself, drawn largely from the obituaries in the <em><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/08/obituaries/roy-j-glauber-dead.html">New York Times</a></em> and the <a href="https://www.thecrimson.com/article/2019/1/3/roy-glauber-harvard-professor-obituary/"><em>Harvard Crimson</em></a>.</p>
<p>Glauber was a member of the first class to graduate from the Bronx High School of Science, in 1941. From there he went to Harvard, but left in his sophomore year, at age 18, to work in the theory division at Los Alamos, where he helped calculate the critical mass of fissile material needed for a bomb. After the war he finished his degree at Harvard and went on to complete a PhD under Julian Schwinger. After a few brief adventures in Princeton and Pasadena, he was back at Harvard in 1952 and never left. A poignant aspect of his life is mentioned briefly in a <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3149897/">2009 interview</a>, where Glauber discusses the challenge of sustaining an academic career while raising two children as a single parent.</p>
<hr/>
<p>Here’s a glimpse of Glauber dynamics in action. Click the <em>Go</em> button, then try fiddling with the slider.</p>
<div id="glauber-viz" style="width: 600px; margin: 15px auto;">
	<canvas height="600px" id="glauber-canvas" width="600px"/><p/>
<div id="glauber-controls" style="display: flex; margin: auto;">
		<output class="slider-output" for="glauber-slider" id="glauber-temp" style="font-family: sans-serif; font-style: bold; margin: auto 10px;">3.00</output><br/>
		<input id="glauber-slider" max="5.0" min="0.01" step="0.01" style="width: 300px; margin: auto 10px;" type="range" value="3.00"/><br/>
		<button id="glauber-go-button" style="width: 50px; margin: 10px;">Go</button>
	</div>
</div>
<p class="indent">In the computer program that drives this animation, the slider controls a variable representing temperature. At high temperature (slide the control all the way to the right), you’ll see a roiling, seething mass of colored squares, switching rapidly and randomly between light and dark shades. There are no large-scale or long-lived structures. Occasionally the end point is not a monochromatic field. Instead the panel is divided into broad stripes—horizontal, vertical, or diagonal. This is an artifact of the finite size of the lattice and the use of wraparound boundary conditions. On an infinite lattice, the stripes would not occur.At low temperature (slide to the left), the tableau congeals into a few writhing blobs of contrasting color. Then the minority blobs are likely to evaporate, and you’ll be left with an unchanging, monochromatic panel. Between these extremes there’s some interesting behavior. Adjust the slider to a temperature near 2.27 and you can expect to see persistent fluctuations at all possible scales, from isolated individual blocks to patterns that span the entire array.</p>
<p>What we’re looking at here is a simulation of a model of a ferromagnet—the kind of magnet that sticks to the refrigerator. The model was introduced almost 100 years ago by Wilhelm Lenz and his student Ernst Ising. They were trying to understand the thermal behavior of ferromagnetic materials such as iron. If you heat a block of magnetized iron above a certain temperature, called the Curie point, it loses all traces of magnetization. Slow cooling below the Curie point allows it to spontaneously magnetize again, perhaps with the poles in a different orientation. The onset of ferromagnetism at the Curie point is an abrupt phase transition.</p>
<p>Lenz and Ising created a <a href="http://bit-player.org/bph-publications/AmSci-2000-09-Hayes-Ising.pdf">stripped-down model of a ferromagnet</a>. In the two-dimensional version shown here, each of the small squares represents the spin vector of an unpaired electron in an iron atom. The vector can point in either of two directions, conventionally called <em>up</em> and <em>down</em>, which for graphic convenience are represented by two contrasting colors. There are \(100 \times 100 = 10{,}000\) spins in the array. This would be a minute sample of a real ferromagnet. On the other hand, the system has \(2^{10{,}000}\) possible states—quite an enormous number.</p>
<p>The essence of ferromagnetism is that adjacent spins “prefer” to point in the same direction. To put that  more formally: The energy of neighboring spins is lower when they are parallel, rather than antiparallel. <img alt="four possible orientations of two spins (up up, up down, down up, down down), with their corresponding energies" border="0" class="alignright" height="111" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/Ising-spin-pairs.png" style="margin-bottom: 0px;" width="262"/>For the array as a whole, the energy is minimized if all the spins point the same way, either up or down. Each spin contributes a tiny magnetic moment. When the spins are parallel, all the moments add up and the system is fully magnetized.</p>
<p>If energy were the only consideration, the Ising model would always settle into a magnetized configuration, but there is a countervailing influence: Heat tends to randomize the spin directions. At infinite temperature, thermal fluctuations completely overwhelm the spins’ tendency to align, and all states are equally likely. Because the vast majority of those \(2^{10{,}000}\) configurations have nearly equal numbers of <em>up</em> and <em>down</em> spins, the magnetization is negligible. At zero temperature, nothing prevents the system from condensing into the fully magnetized state. The interval between these limits is a battleground where energy and entropy contend for supremacy. Clearly, there must be a transition of some kind. For Lenz and Ising in the 1920s, the crucial question was whether the transition comes at a sharply defined critical temperature, as it does in real ferromagnets. A more gradual progression from one regime to the other would signal the model’s failure to capture important aspects of ferromagnet physics.</p>
<p>In his doctoral dissertation Ising investigated the one-dimensional version of the model—a chain or ring of spins, each one holding hands with its two nearest neighbors. The result was a disappointment: He found no abrupt phase transition. And he speculated that the negative result would also hold in higher dimensions. The Ising model seemed to be dead on arrival.</p>
<p>It was revived a decade later by Rudolf Peierls, who gave suggestive evidence for a sharp transition in the two-dimensional lattice. Then in 1944 Lars Onsager “solved” the two-dimensional model, showing that the phase transition does exist. The phase diagram looks like this:</p>
<p><img alt="Graph of the gagnetization v temperature phase diagram for the Ising model." border="0" class="centered" height="566" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/magnetization-v-temperature.png" width="640"/></p>
<p>As the system cools, the salt-and-pepper chaos of infinite temperature evolves into a structure with larger blobs of color, but the <em>up</em> and <em>down</em> spins remain balanced on average (implying zero magnetization) down to the critical temperature \(T_C\). At that point there is a sudden bifurcation, and the system will follow one branch or the other to full magnetization at zero temperature.</p>
<hr/>
<p>If a model is classified as <em>solved</em>, is there anything more to say about it? In this case, I believe the answer is yes. The solution to the two-dimensional Ising model gives us a prescription for calculating the probability of seeing any given configuration at any given temperature. That’s a major accomplishment, and yet it leaves much of the model’s behavior unspecified. The solution defines the probability distribution at equilibrium—after the system has had time to settle into a statistically stable configuration. It doesn’t tell us anything about how the lattice of spins reaches that equilibrium when it starts from an arbitrary initial state, or how the system evolves when the temperature changes rapidly.</p>
<p>It’s not just the solution to the model that has a few vague spots. When you look at the finer details of how spins interact, the model itself leaves much to the imagination. When a spin reacts to the influence of its nearest neighbors, and those neighbors are also reacting to one another, does everything happen all at once? Suppose two antiparallel spins both decide to flip at the same time; they will be left in a configuration that is still antiparallel. It’s hard to see how they’ll escape repeating the same dance over and over, like people who meet head-on in a corridor and keep making mirror-image evasive maneuvers. This kind of standoff can be avoided if the spins act sequentially rather than simultaneously. But if they take turns, how do they decide who goes first?</p>
<p>Within the intellectual traditions of physics and mathematics, these questions can be dismissed as foolish or misguided. After all, when we look at the procession of the planets orbiting the sun, or at the colliding molecules in a gas, we don’t ask who takes the first step; the bodies are all in continuous and simultaneous motion. Newton gave us a tool, calculus, for understanding such situations. If you make the steps small enough, you don’t have to worry so much about the sequence of marching orders.</p>
<p>However, if you want to write a computer program simulating a ferromagnet (or simulating planetary motions, for that matter), questions of sequence and synchrony cannot be swept aside. With conventional computer hardware, “let everything happen at once” is not an option. The program must consider each spin, one at a time, survey the surrounding neighborhood, apply an update rule that’s based on both the state of the neighbors and the temperature, and then decide whether or not to flip. Thus the program must choose a sequence in which to visit the lattice sites, as well as a sequence in which to visit the neighbors of each site, and those choices can make a difference in the outcome of the simulation. So can other details of implementation. Do we look at all the sites, calculate their new spin states, and then update all those that need to be flipped? Or do we update each spin as we go along, so that spins later in the sequence will see an array already modified by earlier actions? The original definition of the Ising model is silent on such matters, but the programmer must make a commitment one way or another.</p>
<p>This is where Glauber dynamics enters the story. Glauber presented a version of the Ising model that’s somewhat more explicit about how spins interact with one another and with the “heat bath” that represents the influence of temperature. It’s a theory of Ising <em>dynamics</em> because he describes the spin system not just at equilibrium but also during transitional stages. I don’t know if Glauber was the first to offer an account of Ising dynamics, but the notion was certainly not commonplace in 1963.</p>
<hr/>
<p>There’s no evidence Glauber was  thinking of his method as an algorithm suitable for computer implementation. The subject of simulation doesn’t come up in his 1963 paper, where his primary aim is to find analytic expressions for the distribution of <em>up</em> and <em>down</em> spins as a function of time. (He did this only for the one-dimensional model.) Nevertheless, Glauber dynamics offers an elegant approach to programming an interactive version of the Ising model. Assume we have a lattice of \(N\) spins. Each spin \(\sigma\) is indexed by its coordinates \(x, y\) and takes on one of the two values \(+1\) and \(-1\). Thus flipping a spin is a matter of multiplying \(\sigma\) by \(-1\). The algorithm for a updating the lattice looks like this:</p>
<blockquote><p class="undent">Repeat \(N\) times:</p>
<ol style="margin-bottom: 0px;">
<li>Choose a spin \(\sigma_{x, y}\) at random.</li>
<li>Sum the values of the four neighboring spins, \(S = \sigma_{x+1, y} + \sigma_{x-1, y} + \sigma_{x, y+1} + \sigma_{x, y-1}\). The possible values of \(S\) are \(\{-4, -2, 0, +2, +4\}\).</li>
<li>Calculate \(\Delta E = 2 \, \sigma_{x, y} \, S\), the change in interaction energy if \(\sigma_{x, y}\) were to flip.</li>
<li>If \(\Delta E \lt 0\), set \(\sigma_{x, y} = -\sigma_{x, y}\).</li>
<li>Otherwise, set \(\sigma_{x, y} = -\sigma_{x, y}\) with probability \(\exp(-\Delta E/T)\), where \(T\) is the temperature.</li>
</ol>
<p class="undent">Display the updated lattice.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Step 4 says: If flipping a spin will reduce the overall energy of the system, flip it. Step 5 says: Even if flipping a spin raises the energy, go ahead and flip it in a randomly selected fraction of the cases. The probability of such spin flips is the Boltzmann factor \(\exp(-\Delta E/T)\). This quantity goes to \(0\) as the temperature \(T\) falls to \(0\), so that energetically unfavorable flips are unlikely in a cold lattice. The probability approaches \(1\) as \(T\) goes to infinity, which is why the model is such a seething mass of fluctuations at high temperature.</p>
<p>(If you’d like to take a look at real code rather than pseudocode—namely the JavaScript program running the simulation above—it’s <a href="https://github.com/bit-player/glauber">on GitHub</a>.)</p>
<p>Glauber dynamics belongs to a family of methods called Markov chain Monte Carlo algorithms (MCMC). The <a href="http://bit-player.org/bph-publications/AmSci-2013-03-Hayes-Markov.pdf">idea of Markov chains</a> was an innovation in probability theory in the early years of the 20th century, extending classical probability to situations where the the next event depends on the current state of the system. <a href="http://bit-player.org/bph-publications/AmSci-1993-03-Hayes-random-numbers.pdf">Monte Carlo algorithms</a> emerged at post-war Los Alamos, not long after Glauber left there to resume his undergraduate curriculum. He clearly kept up with the work of Stanislaw Ulam and other former colleagues in the Manhattan Project.</p>
<p>Within the MCMC family, the distinctive feature of Glauber dynamics is choosing spins at random. The obvious alternative is to march methodically through the lattice by columns and rows, examining every spin in turn. <img alt="Blinking checkerboard" border="0" class="alignleft" height="" src="http://bit-player.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/blinking-checkerboard.png" style="margin-bottom: 0px;" width="210"/>That procedure can certainly be made to work, but it requires care in implementation. At low temperature the Ising process is very nearly deterministic, since unfavorable flips are extremely rare. When you combine a deterministic flip rule with a deterministic path through the lattice, it’s easy to get trapped in recurrent patterns. For example, a subtle bug yields the same configuration of spins on every step, shifted left by a single lattice site, so that the pattern seems to slide across the screen. Another spectacular failure gives rise to a blinking checkerboard, where every spin is surrounded by four opposite spins and flips on every time step. Avoiding these errors requires much fussy attention to algorithmic details. (My personal experience is that the first attempt is never right.)</p>
<p>Choosing spins by throwing random darts at the lattice turns out to be less susceptible to clumsy mistakes. Yet, at first glance, the random procedure seems to have hazards of its own. In particular, choosing 10,000 spins at random from a lattice of 10,000 sites does <em>not</em> guarantee that every site will be visited once. On the contrary, a few sites will be sampled six or seven times, and you can expect that 3,679 sites (that’s \(1/e \times 10{,}000)\) will not be visited at all. Doesn’t that bias distort the outcome of the simulation? No, it doesn’t. After many iterations, all the sites will get equal attention.</p>
<p>The nasty bit in all Ising simulation algorithms is updating pairs of adjacent sites, where each spin is the neighbor of the other. Which one goes first, or do you try to handle them simultaneously? The column-and-row ordering maximizes exposure to this problem: Every spin is a member of such a pair. Other sequential algorithms—for example, visiting all the black squares of a checkerboard followed by all the white squares—avoid these confrontations altogether, never considering two adjacent spins in succession. Glauber dynamics is the Goldilocks solution. Pairs of adjacent spins do turn up as successive elements in the random sequence, but they are rare events. Decisions about how to handle them have no discernible influence on the outcome.</p>
<hr/>
<p>Years ago, I had several opportunities to meet Roy Glauber. Regrettably, I failed to take advantage of them. Glauber’s office at Harvard was in the Lyman Laboratory of Physics, a small isthmus building connecting two larger halls. In the 1970s I was a frequent visitor there, pestering people to write articles for <em>Scientific American</em>. It was fertile territory; for a few years, the magazine found more authors per square meter in Lyman Lab than anywhere else in the world. But I never knocked on Glauber’s door. Perhaps it’s just as well. I was not yet equipped to appreciate what he had to say.</p>
<p>Now I can let him have the last word. This is from the introduction to the paper that introduced Glauber dynamics:</p>
<blockquote><p>If the mathematical problems of equilibrium statistical mechanics are great, they are at least relatively well-defined. The situation is quite otherwise in dealing with systems which undergo large-scale changes with time. The principles of nonequilibrium statistical mechanics remain in largest measure unformulated. While this lack persists, it may be useful to have in hand whatever precise statements can be made about the time-dependent hehavior of statistical systems, however simple they may be.</p></blockquote>
<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-15T12:30:26Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T12:30:26Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://bit-player.org" term="computing"/>
    <category scheme="http://bit-player.org" term="physics"/>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Hayes</name>
      <uri>http://bit-player.org</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://bit-player.org/feed/atom</id>
      <link href="http://bit-player.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://bit-player.org/feed/atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">An amateur's outlook on computation and mathematics</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">bit-player</title>
      <updated>2019-01-17T16:22:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/15/faculty-positions-at-all-levels-at-tu-eindhoven-apply-by-march-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/01/15/faculty-positions-at-all-levels-at-tu-eindhoven-apply-by-march-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>faculty positions (at all levels) at TU Eindhoven (apply by March 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Mathematics and Computer Science at TU Eindhoven is looking for new faculty members to expand its academic staff. We welcome applications in all areas of computer science and at all levels, ranging from (tenure-track) assistant professor to full professor. Website: https://jobs.tue.nl/en/vacancy/faculty-members-computer-science-assistant-associate-and-full-professor-level-418993.html Email: M.T.d.Berg@tue.nl</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Mathematics and Computer Science at TU Eindhoven is looking for new faculty members to expand its academic staff. We welcome applications in all areas of computer science and at all levels, ranging from (tenure-track) assistant professor to full professor.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://jobs.tue.nl/en/vacancy/faculty-members-computer-science-assistant-associate-and-full-professor-level-418993.html">https://jobs.tue.nl/en/vacancy/faculty-members-computer-science-assistant-associate-and-full-professor-level-418993.html</a><br/>
Email: M.T.d.Berg@tue.nl</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-01-15T08:57:36Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-15T08:57:36Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:27:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/14/summer-school-on-geometric-and-algebraic-combinatorics/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/14/summer-school-on-geometric-and-algebraic-combinatorics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Summer School on Geometric and Algebraic Combinatorics</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">June 17-28, 2019 Paris, France http://gac-school.imj-prg.fr/ Submission deadline: March 27, 2019 Registration deadline: March 27, 2019 This two-week summer school will present an overview of a selection of topics in the crossroads between geometry, algebra, and combinatorics. It will consist of four one-week mini-courses given by leading experts, complemented with supervised exercise sessions, lectures by … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/01/14/summer-school-on-geometric-and-algebraic-combinatorics/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Summer School on Geometric and Algebraic Combinatorics</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-01-14T14:09:57Z</updated>
    <published>2019-01-14T14:09:57Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-01-24T23:28:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
