<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2022-05-27T06:38:29Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=22716</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/05/26/waging-war-on-quantum/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum Computers: A Brief Assessment of Progress in the Past Decade</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Waging War On Quantum – A Forbes Article by Arthur Herman Arthur Herman is a popular Historian and a senior fellow at the Hudson Institute. On Forbes Magazine he “comments on quantum computing and AI and American national security”, and … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/05/26/waging-war-on-quantum/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div class="article-headline-container">
<div class="header-content-container">
<h2 class="fs-headline speakable-headline font-base font-size should-redesign"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Waging War On Quantum</span> – A Forbes Article by Arthur Herman</h2>
</div>
</div>
<div class="top-contrib-block">
<div class="contribs">
<div class="contrib-container top-contrib bottom-padding">
<div class="fs-author-group-wrapper">
<div class="contrib-byline"/>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_L._Herman">Arthur Herman</a> is a popular Historian and a senior fellow at the Hudson Institute. On Forbes Magazine he “comments on quantum computing and AI and American national security”, and his recent Forbes article <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/arthurherman/2022/05/19/waging-war-on-quantum/?sh=2044c5318896">Waging War on Quantum</a> (thanks, Alexander Vlasov) starts as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #993300;"><em><strong>Quantum computing will never work. Keeping enough qubits stable long enough to do any significant calculating or processing, is a mathematical impossibility. The whole idea that one day quantum computers will discover new miracle drugs, or crack public encryption systems, is a mirage. Even worse, it’s a hoax.</strong></em></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #993300;"><em><strong>That’s been the message from so-called quantum skeptics for a decade or more, including physicists like Gil Kalai of Hebrew University and Mikhail Dyakonov of the University of Montepellier—all in spite of the fact that quantum computers have continued to grow in sophistication and qubit power. Most experts now agree it’s not a question if a large-scale quantum will emerge that can break into public encryption systems using Shor’s algorithm, but </strong></em><strong>when</strong><em><strong>.”</strong></em></span></p></blockquote>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">The first paragraph gives a reasonable description of my views, however I <strong>never</strong> referred to the whole idea of quantum computing as a hoax. </span><span style="color: #0000ff;"><span style="color: #000000;">Regarding the second paragraph, it is indeed correct that quantum computers have continued to grow in sophistication and qubit power, however <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02499">my theory</a> (based on a computational complexity argument) is that progress for reducing the error rate will reach a wall and that recent progress merely approaches this limit. Let me elaborate a little on the development of the past decade as I see it</span>.<br/>
</span></p>
<p>Before moving to my assessment I would like to note that Arthur Herman’s offers an outrageous conclusion to his article. He suggests that skepticism of quantum computers (and of the company <a href="https://ionq.com/">IonQ</a>) puts the skeptics’ countries at risk. In my opinion, the militant rhetoric of the title and of the conclusion is very inappropriate.</p>
<h2>Assessment of progress in the past decade</h2>
<p>The past quantum computing decade is characterized both by notable progress, adjustment of expectations, larger investments, much enthusiasm, and some hype. The overall picture is unclear and might be clearer 5-10 years from now.</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;">The following picture (click to enlarge) describes the shift in the community view over the last decade (as I see it).</span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/05/2010-2020d.png"><img alt="2010-2020d" class="alignnone  wp-image-22721" height="308" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/05/2010-2020d.png?w=724&amp;h=308" width="724"/></a></p>
<p>On the left you can see David DiVincenzo’s famous 7-steps road map to quantum computers. DiVincenzo put forward these steps in his 2000 paper  <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0002077">The physical implementation of quantum computation</a>,  and the above picture on the left is a graphic description of these steps in a <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.1231930">2013 review paper</a> by Michel Devoret and Rob Schoelkopf.  The caption under the Figure asserts that <span style="color: #0000ff;">“Superconducting qubits are the only solid-state implementation at the third stage, and they now aim at reaching the fourth stage (green arrow). In the domain of atomic physics and quantum optics, the third stage had been previously attained by trapped ions and by Rydberg atoms. No implementation has yet reached the fourth stage, where a logical qubit can be stored, via error correction, for a time substantially longer than the decoherence time of its physical qubit components.”</span> The fourth step “logical memory with (substantial) longer lifetime than physical qubits” looked to many like a near term goal ten years ago.</p>
<p>One important development of the last ten years was to introduce building NISQ computers and achieving “quantum supremacy” (and related tasks like high “quantum volume”) as an intermediate goal towards DiVincenzo’s step four. (See the picture on the right.) Of course, there is nothing wrong with setting intermediate goals, we do it all the time and this can be very fruitful.</p>
<p>For me, from the skeptical point of view, these intermediate goals were an opportunity, allowing me to present a <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/12/29/the-argument-against-quantum-computers-a-very-short-introduction/">clear computational theoretic argument</a> for why “quantum supremacy” is out of reach and to connect the problem with the theory of noise-sensitivity and noise-stability and with Fourier methods that I and my colleagues developed in the 90s.</p>
<p>Adding the intermediate goal of quantum supremacy also represented a much slower time-table than what people previously anticipated. For example, nine years ago in 2013  John Martinis <a href="https://youtu.be/7Pok08VvkeU">gave a lecture</a> at <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2013/04/12/qstart/">QSTART</a>,  the opening conference of our HUJI quantum science center. At that time, John expected to have the ability of building distance-3 and distance-5 surface codes within a few years and the tasks of demonstrating logical gates and of logical qubits with <img alt="10^{-15}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=10%5E%7B-15%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> error rates some years later. John also mentioned the ability to control 20 qubits within one month (to this Ray Laflamme commented that it is going to be a long month). All these targets are today still out of reach. It is undisputed that considerably lower noise rates are required even for achieving distance-3 surface codes and it is still not possible to have good control of 20-qubit (and perhaps even 10-qubit) quantum computation.</p>
<p>Of course, John Martinis himself was the leader of the Google efforts towards “quantum supremacy” which are now being carefully evaluated, and his vision and technology from 2013 was important for the Sycamore NISQ experiments. Let me mention that Google’s fantastic “quantum supremacy” claims were <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/03/10/amazing-feng-pan-and-pan-zhang-announced-a-way-to-spoof-classically-simulate-the-googles-quantum-supremacy-circuit/">largely (but not fully) refuted</a>.</p>
<p>There was a similar level of optimism from various other researchers. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_J._Schoelkopf#Schoelkopf.27s_law">It was expected</a> that coherence time would increase by a factor of ten every three years and there was a proposed “<a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/does-nevens-law-describe-quantum-computings-rise-20190618/">double exponential law</a>” prediction for the classical computational power required to simulate quantum devices as time proceeds.  I personally don’t regard these specific claims as hype but rather as (at times, over-the-top) reasoned optimism, but both the reasoning and the predictions themselves should carefully be examined.</p>
<p>NISQ computers are interesting, and they allow interesting quantum physics experiments. Herman asserts that <strong><em>“quantum hybrid systems are making the qubit revolution something that’s happening now, not just a distant dream” </em></strong>and this echoes hopes of several researchers in academia and industry. My analysis asserts that NISQ computers are, from the computational complexity perspective, primitive classical computational devices with inherent chaotic behavior, and therefore, I don’t see how hybrid systems and the interface with conventional computers would turn them into useful computational devices. (They can still be useful for quantum physics experimentation.)</p>
<p>Let me repeat: slower progress than anticipated is very common, setting new intermediate goals is both common and welcome. By themselves they do not imply that the target of “<em><strong>large-scale quantum computers that can break into public encryption systems using Shor’s algorithm” </strong></em>is unrealistic, and indeed many experts in the field believe that it is a matter of time for this ultimate goal to be reached. My view is different, I try to explain my argument to other experts, and to offer experimental predictions and theoretical implications. There are good reasons to hope that the matter will be tested experimentally in the years to come, but my assessment is that the experimental picture from the past decade <strong>is not clear</strong>.</p>
<h2>IonQ, trapped ion quantum computation, and Elon Musk</h2>
<p>Herman’s article was triggered by a 183-page document written by a group called “Scorpion Capital.” The document attacks Maryland-based quantum computer company IonQ and among various concerns it also briefly mentions my and Michel Dyakonov’s positions about quantum computers.  I myself share the common view that ion-trap methods for quantum computers form a major avenue and that Chris Monroe (a co-founder of IonQ) is a major player in this direction. I don’t know much about IonQ’s specific efforts, but I would expect that large scale investment is required to put ion-trap methods to test and I personally would like to see it being tested. So I would be quite pleased to see <strong>Elon Musk</strong> deciding to buy IonQ or the Israeli trapped ion QC company of <a href="https://www.weizmann.ac.il/complex/ozeri/welcome-weizmann-trapped-ions-lab">Roee Ozeri</a> (or both) <img alt="&#x1F642;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f642.png" style="height: 1em;"/> and to make  trapped ion technology his quantum computing signature. Incidentally, the comment section of my 2018 <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/gil-kalais-argument-against-quantum-computers-20180207/">Quanta Magazine interview</a> presented an interesting exchange between Monroe and me (starting <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/gil-kalais-argument-against-quantum-computers-20180207/#comment-4559220424">here</a>).</p>
<h3>A few more remarks:</h3>
<p>1) Herman’s article raises several other interesting issues like when (and if) is the appropriate time to transfer to “post quantum cryptography” protocols.</p>
<p>2) There are a few researchers skeptical of quantum computers that actually conduct research and write papers (and books) about it. (There are others that regard the idea as absurd nonsense of absolutely no interest.) A notable researcher who wrote several important papers in the skeptical direction since the late 90s is Robert Alicki from the University of Gdansk.</p>
<p>3) Here is Herman’s crazy conclusion: “No one is saying the Scorpion Capital short-sellers are in Chinese pay, or that skeptics like Dyakonov and Kalai are knowingly putting their countries at risk. But waging war on the U.S. quantum industry can have serious consequences, unless quantum companies and labs show that they are not intimidated, and reassure the public that the quantum future doesn’t rest on hype but significant achievements—achievements that will make our country and our world safer, stronger, and more confident about our future as a whole.”</p>
<p>4) I changed the title to reflect the main topic of the post.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-26T09:13:54Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-26T09:13:54Z</published>
    <category term="Quantum"/>
    <category term="Arthur Herman"/>
    <category term="IonQ"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/080</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/080" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-080 |  QBF Merge Resolution is powerful but unnatural | 

	Meena Mahajan, 

	Gaurav Sood</title>
    <summary>The Merge Resolution proof system (M-Res) for QBFs, proposed by Beyersdorff et al. in 2019, explicitly builds partial strategies inside refutations. The original motivation for this approach was to overcome the limitations encountered in long-distance Q-Resolution proof system (LD-Q-Res), where the syntactic side-conditions, while prohibiting all unsound resolutions, also end up prohibiting some sound resolutions. However, while the advantage of M-Res over many other resolution-based QBF proof systems was already demonstrated, a comparison with LD-Q-Res itself had remained open. In this paper, we settle this question. We show that M-Res has an exponential advantage over not only LD-Q-Res, but even over LQU$^+$-Res and IRM, the most powerful among currently known resolution-based QBF proof systems. Combining this with results from Beyersdorff et al. 2020, we conclude that M-Res is incomparable with LQU-Res and LQU$^+$-Res.

Our proof method reveals two additional and curious features about M-Res: (i) MRes is not closed under restrictions, and is hence not a natural proof system, and (ii) weakening axiom clauses with existential variables provably yields an exponential advantage over M-Res without weakening. We further show that in the context of regular derivations, weakening axiom clauses with universal variables provably yields an exponential advantage over M-Res without weakening. These results suggest that MRes is better used with weakening, though whether M-Res with weakening is closed under restrictions remains open. We note that even with weakening, M-Res continues to be simulated by eFrege $+ $ $\forall$red (the simulation of ordinary M-Res was shown recently by Chew and Slivovsky).</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T01:31:41Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-26T01:31:41Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12943</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12943" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Transitions from P to NP-hardness: the case of the Linear Ordering Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Elorza:Anne.html">Anne Elorza</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hernando:Leticia.html">Leticia Hernando</a>, Jose A. Lozano <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12943">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper we evaluate how constructive heuristics degrade when a problem
transits from P to NP-hard. This is done by means of the linear ordering
problem. More specifically, for this problem we prove that the objective
function can be expressed as the sum of two objective functions, one of which
is associated with a P problem (an exact polynomial time algorithm is proposed
to solve it), while the other is associated with an NP-hard problem. We study
how different constructive algorithms whose behaviour only depends on
univariate information perform depending on the contribution of the P or
NP-hard components of the problem. A number of experiments are conducted with
reduced dimensions, where the global optimum of the problems is known, giving
different weights to the NP-hard component, while the weight of the P component
is fixed. It is observed how the performance of the constructive algorithms
gets worse as the weight given to the NP-hard component increases.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:37:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12932</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12932" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Prime Holdout Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Max Milkert, Alex Ruchti, Josiah Yoder <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12932">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper introduces prime holdout problems, a problem class related to the
Collatz conjecture. After applying a linear function, instead of removing a
finite set of prime factors, a holdout problem specifies a set of primes to be
retained. A proof that all positive integers converge to 1 is given for both a
finite and an infinite holdout problem. It is conjectured that finite holdout
problems cannot diverge for any starting value, which has implications for
divergent sequences in the Collatz conjecture.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:39:10Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12850</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12850" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Universal Error Measure for Input Predictions Applied to Online Graph Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Giulia Bernardini, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lindermayr:Alexander.html">Alexander Lindermayr</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Marchetti=Spaccamela:Alberto.html">Alberto Marchetti-Spaccamela</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Megow:Nicole.html">Nicole Megow</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Stougie:Leen.html">Leen Stougie</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sweering:Michelle.html">Michelle Sweering</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12850">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We introduce a novel measure for quantifying the error in input predictions.
The error is based on a minimum-cost hyperedge cover in a suitably defined
hypergraph and provides a general template which we apply to online graph
problems. The measure captures errors due to absent predicted requests as well
as unpredicted actual requests; hence, predicted and actual inputs can be of
arbitrary size. We achieve refined performance guarantees for previously
studied network design problems in the online-list model, such as Steiner tree
and facility location. Further, we initiate the study of learning-augmented
algorithms for online routing problems, such as the traveling salesperson
problem and dial-a-ride problem, where (transportation) requests arrive over
time (online-time model). We provide a general algorithmic framework and we
give error-dependent performance bounds that improve upon known worst-case
barriers, when given accurate predictions, at the cost of slightly increased
worst-case bounds when given predictions of arbitrary quality.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:41:11Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12828</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12828" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Asymptotic $\left(\frac{4}{3}+\varepsilon\right)$-Approximation for the 2-Dimensional Vector Bin Packing Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kulik:Ariel.html">Ariel Kulik</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mnich:Matthias.html">Matthias Mnich</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Shachnai:Hadas.html">Hadas Shachnai</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12828">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the $2$-Dimensional Vector Bin Packing Problem (2VBP), a
generalization of classic Bin Packing that is widely applicable in resource
allocation and scheduling. In 2VBP we are given a set of items, where each item
is associated with a two-dimensional volume vector. The objective is to
partition the items into a minimal number of subsets (bins), such that the
total volume of items in each subset is at most $1$ in each dimension.
</p>
<p>We give an asymptotic $\left(\frac{4}{3}+\varepsilon\right)$-approximation
for the problem, thus improving upon the best known asymptotic ratio of
$\left(1+\ln \frac{3}{2}+\varepsilon\right)\approx 1.406$ due to Bansal, Elias
and Khan (SODA 2016). Our algorithm applies a novel Round&amp;Round approach which
iteratively solves a configuration LP relaxation for the residual instance and
samples a small number of configurations based on the solution for the
configuration LP. For the analysis we derive an iteration-dependent upper bound
on the solution size for the configuration LP, which holds with high
probability. To facilitate the analysis, we introduce key structural properties
of 2VBP instances, leveraging the recent fractional grouping technique of
Fairstein et al. (ESA 2021).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:39:19Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12821</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12821" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The complexity of blocking (semi)total dominating sets with edge contractions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Galby:Esther.html">Esther Galby</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12821">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the problem of reducing the (semi)total domination number of
graph by one by contracting edges. It is known that this can always be done
with at most three edge contractions and that deciding whether one edge
contraction suffices is an $\mathsf{NP}$-hard problem. We show that for every
fixed $k \in \{2,3\}$, deciding whether exactly $k$ edge contractions are
necessary is $\mathsf{NP}$-hard and further provide for $k=2$ complete
complexity dichotomies on monogenic graph classes.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12799</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12799" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>SAT Preprocessors and Symmetry</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Anders:Markus.html">Markus Anders</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12799">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Exploitation of symmetries is an indispensable approach to solve certain
classes of difficult SAT instances. Numerous techniques for the use of symmetry
in SAT have evolved over the past few decades. But no matter how symmetries are
used precisely, they have to be detected first. We investigate how to detect
more symmetry, faster. The initial idea is to reap the benefits of SAT
preprocessing for symmetry detection. As it turns out, applying an
off-the-shelf preprocessor before handling symmetry runs into problems: the
preprocessor can haphazardly remove symmetry from formulas, severely impeding
symmetry exploitation.
</p>
<p>Our main contribution is a theoretical framework that captures the
relationship of SAT preprocessing techniques and symmetry. Based on this, we
create a symmetry-aware preprocessor that can be applied safely before handling
symmetry. We then demonstrate that applying the preprocessor does not only
substantially decrease symmetry detection and breaking times, but also uncovers
hidden symmetry not detectable in the original instances. Overall, we depart
the conventional view of treating symmetry detection as a black-box, presenting
a new application-specific approach to symmetry detection in SAT.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:40:56Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12686</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12686" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Deterministic Massively Parallel Algorithms for Ruling Sets</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pai:Shreyas.html">Shreyas Pai</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pemmaraju:Sriram_V=.html">Sriram V. Pemmaraju</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12686">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper we present a deterministic $O(\log\log n)$-round algorithm for
the 2-ruling set problem in the Massively Parallel Computation model with
$\tilde{O}(n)$ memory; this algorithm also runs in $O(\log\log n)$ rounds in
the Congested Clique model. This is exponentially faster than the fastest known
deterministic 2-ruling set algorithm for these models, which is simply the
$O(\log \Delta)$-round deterministic Maximal Independent Set algorithm due to
Czumaj, Davies, and Parter (SPAA 2020). Our result is obtained by derandomizing
the 2-ruling set algorithm of Kothapalli and Pemmaraju (FSTTCS 2012).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:46:14Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12621</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12621" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Unbiased and Efficient Sampling of Dependency Trees</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Miloš Stanojević <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12621">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Distributions over spanning trees are the most common way of computational
modeling of dependency syntax. However, most treebanks require that every valid
dependency tree has a single edge coming out of the ROOT node, a constraint
that is not part of the definition of spanning trees. For this reason all
standard inference algorithms for spanning trees are sub-optimal for modeling
dependency trees.
</p>
<p>Zmigrod et al. (2021b) have recently proposed algorithms for sampling with
and without replacement from the single-root dependency tree distribution. In
this paper we show that their fastest algorithm for sampling with replacement,
Wilson-RC, is in fact producing biased samples and we provide two alternatives
that are unbiased. Additionally, we propose two algorithms (one incremental,
one parallel) that reduce the asymptotic runtime of their algorithm for
sampling $k$ trees without replacement to $\mathcal{O}(kn^3)$. These algorithms
are both asymptotically and practically more efficient.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:46:55Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12447</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12447" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Uniformly Bounded Regret in Dynamic Fair Allocation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Balseiro:Santiago_R=.html">Santiago R. Balseiro</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xia:Shangzhou.html">Shangzhou Xia</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12447">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study a dynamic allocation problem in which $T$ sequentially arriving
divisible resources need to be allocated to $n$ fixed agents with additive
utilities. Agents' utilities are drawn stochastically from a known
distribution, and decisions are made immediately and irrevocably. Most works on
dynamic resource allocation aim to maximize the utilitarian welfare of the
agents, which may result in unfair concentration of resources at select agents
while leaving others' demands under-fulfilled. In this paper, we consider the
egalitarian welfare objective instead, which aims at balancing the efficiency
and fairness of the allocation. To this end, we first study a fluid-based
policy derived from a deterministic approximation to the underlying problem and
show that it attains a regret of order $\Theta(\sqrt{T})$ against the hindsight
optimum, i.e., the optimal egalitarian allocation when all utilities are known
in advance. We then propose a new policy, called Backward Infrequent Re-solving
with Thresholding ($\mathsf{BIRT}$), which consists of re-solving the fluid
problem at most $O(\log\log T)$ times. We prove the $\mathsf{BIRT}$ policy
attains $O(1)$ regret against the hindsight optimum, independently of the time
horizon length $T$ and initial welfare. We also present numerical experiments
to illustrate the significant performance improvement against several benchmark
policies.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:46:55Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12442</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12442" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Lyapunov function approach for approximation algorithm design and analysis: with applications in submodular maximization</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Du:Donglei.html">Donglei Du</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12442">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We propose a two-phase systematical framework for approximation algorithm
design and analysis via Lyapunov function. The first phase consists of using
Lyapunov function as a guideline to design a continuous-time algorithm with
provable approximation ratio. The second phase then converts the
continuous-time algorithm to a discrete-time algorithm with the same
approximation ratio and a provable time complexity. Some immediate benefits of
the Lyapunov function approach include: (i) unifying many existing algorithms;
(ii) providing a guideline to design and analyze new algorithms; and (iii)
offer new perspectives to potentially improve existing algorithms. We use
various submodular maximization problems as running examples to illustrate our
framework.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:47:11Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12421</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12421" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Substring Complexities on Run-length Compressed Strings</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Akiyoshi Kawamoto, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/I:Tomohiro.html">Tomohiro I</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12421">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Let $S_{T}(k)$ denote the set of distinct substrings of length $k$ in a
string $T$, then the $k$-th substring complexity is defined by its cardinality
$|S_{T}(k)|$. Recently, $\delta = \max \{ |S_{T}(k)| / k : k \ge 1 \}$ is shown
to be a good compressibility measure of highly-repetitive strings. In this
paper, given $T$ of length $n$ in the run-length compressed form of size $r$,
we show that $\delta$ can be computed in $\mathit{C}_{\mathsf{sort}}(r, n)$
time and $O(r)$ space, where $\mathit{C}_{\mathsf{sort}}(r, n) = O(\min (r
\lg\lg r, r \lg_{r} n))$ is the time complexity for sorting $r$ $O(\lg n)$-bit
integers in $O(r)$ space in the Word-RAM model with word size $\Omega(\lg n)$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:44:19Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12377</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12377" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hardness of Maximum Likelihood Learning of DPPs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grigorescu:Elena.html">Elena Grigorescu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Juba:Brendan.html">Brendan Juba</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wimmer:Karl.html">Karl Wimmer</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xie:Ning.html">Ning Xie</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12377">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Determinantal Point Processes (DPPs) are a widely used probabilistic model
for negatively correlated sets. DPPs have been successfully employed in Machine
Learning applications to select a diverse, yet representative subset of data.
In seminal work on DPPs in Machine Learning, Kulesza conjectured in his PhD
Thesis (2011) that the problem is NP-complete. The lack of a formal proof
prompted Brunel, Moitra, Rigollet and Urschel (COLT 2017) to conjecture that,
in opposition to Kulesza's conjecture, there exists a polynomial-time algorithm
for computing a maximum-likelihood DPP. They also presented some preliminary
evidence supporting their conjecture.
</p>
<p>In this work we prove Kulesza's conjecture. In fact, we prove the following
stronger hardness of approximation result: even computing a
$\left(1-O(\frac{1}{\log^9{N}})\right)$-approximation to the maximum
log-likelihood of a DPP on a ground set of $N$ elements is NP-complete. At the
same time, we also obtain the first polynomial-time algorithm that achieves a
nontrivial worst-case approximation to the optimal log-likelihood: the
approximation factor is $\frac{1}{(1+o(1))\log{m}}$ unconditionally (for data
sets that consist of $m$ subsets), and can be improved to $1-\frac{1+o(1)}{\log
N}$ if all $N$ elements appear in a $O(1/N)$-fraction of the subsets.
</p>
<p>In terms of techniques, we reduce approximating the maximum log-likelihood of
DPPs on a data set to solving a gap instance of a "vector coloring" problem on
a hypergraph. Such a hypergraph is built on a bounded-degree graph construction
of Bogdanov, Obata and Trevisan (FOCS 2002), and is further enhanced by the
strong expanders of Alon and Capalbo (FOCS 2007) to serve our purposes.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12307</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.12307" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximate Euclidean lengths and distances beyond Johnson-Lindenstrauss</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1653523200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sobczyk:Aleksandros.html">Aleksandros Sobczyk</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Luisier:Mathieu.html">Mathieu Luisier</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2205.12307">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A classical result of Johnson and Lindenstrauss states that a set of $n$ high
dimensional data points can be projected down to $O(\log n/\epsilon^2)$
dimensions such that the square of their pairwise distances is preserved up to
a small distortion $\epsilon\in(0,1)$. It has been proved that the JL lemma is
optimal for the general case, therefore, improvements can only be explored for
special cases. This work aims to improve the $\epsilon^{-2}$ dependency based
on techniques inspired by the Hutch++ Algorithm , which reduces $\epsilon^{-2}$
to $\epsilon^{-1}$ for the related problem of implicit matrix trace estimation.
For $\epsilon=0.01$, for example, this translates to $100$ times less
matrix-vector products in the matrix-vector query model to achieve the same
accuracy as other previous estimators. We first present an algorithm to
estimate the Euclidean lengths of the rows of a matrix. We prove element-wise
probabilistic bounds that are at least as good as standard JL approximations in
the worst-case, but are asymptotically better for matrices with decaying
spectrum. Moreover, for any matrix, regardless of its spectrum, the algorithm
achieves $\epsilon$-accuracy for the total, Frobenius norm-wise relative error
using only $O(\epsilon^{-1})$ queries. This is a quadratic improvement over the
norm-wise error of standard JL approximations. We finally show how these
results can be extended to estimate the Euclidean distances between data points
and to approximate the statistical leverage scores of a tall-and-skinny data
matrix, which are ubiquitous for many applications. Proof-of-concept numerical
experiments are presented to validate the theoretical analysis.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-26T22:44:49Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=626</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2022/05/25/tcs-talk-wednesday-june-1-inbal-talgam-cohen-technion-israel-institute-of-technology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, June 1 — Inbal Talgam-Cohen, Technion – Israel Institute of Technology</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, June 1st at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). Inbal Talgam-Cohen from the Technion – Israel Institute of Technology will speak about “Algorithmic contract theory” (abstract below). You can reserve a spot as an individual or a […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p/>



<p/>


<p>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, June 1st at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). <a href="http://www.inbaltalgam.com/"><strong>Inbal Talgam-Cohen</strong></a> from the Technion – Israel Institute of Technology will speak about “<em>Algorithmic contract theory</em>” (abstract below).</p>
<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/next-tcs-talk">the online form</a>. Registration is <em>not</em> required to attend the interactive talk, and the link will be posted on the website the day prior to the talk; however, by registering in the form, you will receive a reminder, along with the link. (The recorded talk will also be posted <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/past-talks">on our website</a> afterwards) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/suggest-a-talk">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/">the website</a>.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>Abstract: Algorithms increasingly interact with strategic, self-interested players; their design must take player incentives into account or risk being “gamed” and failing miserably. The algorithmic game theory literature traditionally focused on “mechanisms” – algorithms that incentivize players to truthfully report the <strong>input</strong>. In this talk we shift focus from mechanisms to “contracts”, which are concerned with the algorithm’s <strong>output</strong> and players’ incentives to carry it out. The goal of this talk is to describe where we’re at in forming a new algorithmic theory of contract design.</p>
<p>I will demonstrate how algorithmic approaches – in particular the approach of <strong>beyond worst-case analysis</strong> – can shed light on a classic economic puzzle regarding simple contracts. Within the realm of <strong>incentives and learning</strong>, I will discuss how classifiers induce incentives and show a formal relation to contracts.</p>
<p>Based on joint works with Tal Alon, Magdalen Dobson, Paul Duetting, Ron Lavi, Ariel Procaccia, Tim Roughgarden, Elisheva Shamash and Jamie Tucker-Foltz.</p>
</blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-25T22:54:22Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-25T22:54:22Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:38:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/079</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/079" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-079 |  Lower Bound Methods for Sign-rank and their Limitations | 

	Hamed Hatami, 

	Pooya Hatami, 

	William Pires, 

	Ran Tao, 

	Rosie Zhao</title>
    <summary>The sign-rank of a matrix $A$ with $\pm 1$ entries is the smallest rank of a real matrix with the same sign pattern as $A$. To the best of our knowledge, there are only three known methods for proving lower bounds on the sign-rank of explicit matrices:  (i) Sign-rank is at least the VC-dimension; (ii) Forster's method, which states that sign-rank is at least the inverse of the largest possible average margin among the representations of the matrix by points and half-spaces; (iii) Sign-rank is at least a logarithmic function of the density of the largest monochromatic rectangle. 
 

We prove several results regarding the limitations of these methods. 


$\bullet$ We prove that, qualitatively,  the monochromatic rectangle density is the strongest of these three lower bounds. If it fails to provide a super-constant lower bound for the sign-rank of a  matrix, then the other two methods will fail as well.   
$\bullet$ We show that there exist $n \times n$ matrices with sign-rank $n^{\Omega(1)}$ for which none of these methods can provide a super-constant lower bound.   
$\bullet$ We show that sign-rank is at most an exponential function of the deterministic communication complexity with access to an equality oracle. We combine this result with Green and Sanders' quantitative version of  Cohen's idempotent theorem to show that for a large class of sign matrices (e.g., XOR-lifts), sign-rank is at most an exponential function of the $\gamma_2$ norm of the matrix. We conjecture that this holds for all sign matrices. 
$\bullet$ Towards answering a question of Linial,  Mendelson,   Schechtman, and  Shraibman regarding the relation between sign-rank and discrepancy, we conjecture that sign-ranks of the $\pm1$ adjacency matrices of hypercube graphs can be arbitrarily large. We prove that none of the three lower bound techniques can resolve this conjecture in the affirmative.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-25T20:42:28Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-25T20:42:28Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/078</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/078" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-078 |  Improved local testing for multiplicity codes | 

	Dan Karliner, 

	Amnon Ta-Shma</title>
    <summary>Multiplicity codes are a generalization of Reed-Muller codes which include derivatives as well as the values of low degree polynomials, evaluated in every point in $\mathbb{F}_p^m$. 
Similarly to Reed-Muller codes, multiplicity codes have a local nature that allows for local correction and local testing. 
Recently, the authors and Salama showed that the plane test, which tests the degree of the codeword on a random plane, is a good local tester for small enough degrees.
In this work we simplify and extend the analysis of local testing for multiplicity codes, giving a more general and tighter analysis. In particular, we show that multiplicity codes $\mathrm{MRM}_{p}(m, d, s)$ over prime fields with arbitrary $d$ are locally testable by an appropriate $k$-flat test, which tests the degree of the codeword on a random $k$-dimensional affine subspace. The relationship between the degree parameter $d$ and the required dimension $k$ is shown to be nearly optimal, and improves on the degree previously known in the case of planes.

Our analysis relies on a generalization of the technique of canonincal monomials introduced by Haramaty, Shpilka and Sudan (FOCS 2011). Generalizing canonical monomials to the multiplicity case requires substantially different proofs which exploit the algebraic structure of multiplicity codes.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-25T03:48:26Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-25T03:48:26Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/077</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/077" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-077 |  Explicit Lower Bounds Against $\Omega(n)$-Rounds of Sum-of-Squares | 

	Max Hopkins, 

	Ting-Chun Lin</title>
    <summary>We construct an explicit family of 3-XOR instances hard for $\Omega(n)$-levels of the Sum-of-Squares (SoS) semi-definite programming hierarchy. Not only is this the first explicit construction to beat brute force search (beyond low-order improvements (Tulsiani 2021, Pratt 2021)), combined with standard gap amplification techniques it also matches the (optimal) hardness of random instances up to imperfect completeness (Grigoriev TCS 2001, Schoenebeck FOCS 2008). 

Our result is based on a new form of small-set high dimensional expansion (SS-HDX) inspired by recent breakthroughs in locally testable and quantum LDPC codes. Adapting the recent framework of Dinur, Filmus, Harsha, and Tulsiani (ITCS 2021) for SoS lower bounds from the Ramanujan complex to this setting, we show any (bounded-degree) SS-HDX can be transformed into a highly unsatisfiable 3-XOR instance that cannot be refuted by $\Omega(n)$-levels of SoS. We then show Leverrier and Z\'emor's (Arxiv 2022) recent qLDPC construction gives the desired explicit family of bounded-degree SS-HDX. Incidentally, this gives the strongest known form of bi-directional high dimensional expansion to date.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-25T03:47:06Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-25T03:47:06Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://differentialprivacy.org/privacy-doona/</id>
    <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/privacy-doona/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Privacy Doona&amp;#58; Why We Should Hide Among The Clones</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In this blog post, we will discuss a recent(ish) result of Feldman, McMillan, and Talwar <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.12803" title="Vitaly Feldman, Audra McMillan, Kunal Talwar. Hiding Among the Clones: A Simple and Nearly Optimal Analysis of Privacy Amplification by Shuffling. FOCS 2021"><strong>[FMT21]</strong></a>, which provides an improved and simple analysis of the so-called “amplification by shuffling” formally connecting local privacy (LDP) and shuffle privacy.<sup id="fnref:1"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Now, I’ll assume the reader is familiar with both LDP and Shuffle DP: if not, a quick-and-dirty refresher (with less quick, and less dirty references) can be found <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/\trustmodels">here</a>, and of course there is also Albert Cheu’s excellent survey on Shuffle DP <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.11839" title="Albert Cheu. Differential Privacy in the Shuffle Model: A Survey of Separations. arXiv 2021"><strong>[Cheu21]</strong></a>.</p>

<p>I will also ignore most of the historical details, but it is worth mentioning that <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.12803" title="Vitaly Feldman, Audra McMillan, Kunal Talwar. Hiding Among the Clones: A Simple and Nearly Optimal Analysis of Privacy Amplification by Shuffling. FOCS 2021"><strong>[FMT21]</strong></a> is not the first paper on this “amplification by shuffling,” (which, for local reasons, I’ll just call a <em>privacy <a href="https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/doona">doona</a></em>) but rather is the culmination of a rather long line of work involving many cool ideas and papers, starting with <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.01394" title="Albert Cheu, Adam D. Smith, Jonathan Ullman, David Zeber, Maxim Zhilyaev. Distributed Differential Privacy via Shuffling. EUROCRYPT 2019"><strong>[CSUZZ19</strong></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1811.12469" title="&#xDA;lfar Erlingsson, Vitaly Feldman, Ilya Mironov, Ananth Raghunathan, Kunal Talwar, Abhradeep Thakurta. Amplification by Shuffling: From Local to Central Differential Privacy via Anonymity. SODA 2019"><strong>EFMRTT19]</strong></a>: I’d refer the reader to <strong>Table 1</strong> in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.12803" title="Vitaly Feldman, Audra McMillan, Kunal Talwar. Hiding Among the Clones: A Simple and Nearly Optimal Analysis of Privacy Amplification by Shuffling. FOCS 2021"><strong>[FMT21]</strong></a> for an overview.</p>

<p>Alright, now that the caveats are behind us, what <em>is</em> “amplification by shuffling”? In a nutshell, it is capturing the (false!) intuition that “anonymization provides privacy” (which, again, is false! Don’t do this!) and making it… less false. The idea is that while <em>anonymization does not provide in itself any meaningful privacy guarantee</em>, it can <em>amplify existing, rigorous privacy guarantee</em>. So if I start with a somewhat lousy LDP guarantee, but then all the messages sent by all users are completely anonymized, then my lousy LDP guarantee suddenly gets <em>much</em> stronger (roughly speaking, the \(\varepsilon\) parameter goes down with the square root of of the number of users involved). Which is wonderful! Let’s see what this means, quantitatively.</p>

<h3 id="the-result-of-feldman-mcmillan-and-talwar">The result of Feldman, McMillan, and Talwar.</h3>
<p>Here, we will focus on the simpler case of <em>noninteractive</em> protocols (one-shot messages from the users to the central server, no funny business with messages going back and forth); which is conceptually simpler to state and parse, still very rich and interesting, and, well, very relevant in practice (being the easiest and cheapest to deploy). If you want the results in their full glorious generality, though, they are in the paper.</p>

<p>What the main theorem of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.12803" title="Vitaly Feldman, Audra McMillan, Kunal Talwar. Hiding Among the Clones: A Simple and Nearly Optimal Analysis of Privacy Amplification by Shuffling. FOCS 2021"><strong>[FMT21]</strong></a> is saying for this noninteractive setting can then be stated as follows: if I have an <em>\(\varepsilon_L\)-locally private</em> (LDP) protocol for a task, where all \(n\) users pass their data through the same randomizer (algorithm) \(R\) and send the resulting message \(y_i \gets R(x_i)\), then just permuting the messages \(y_1\dots,y_n\) immediately gives an \((\varepsilon,\delta)\)-<em>shuffle</em> private protocol for the same task, for any pair \((\varepsilon,\delta)\) which satisfies
<a name="eq:eps:epsL"/>
\begin{equation}
		\varepsilon \leq \log\left( 1+ 16\frac{e^{\varepsilon_{L}}-1}{e^{\varepsilon_{L}}+1}\sqrt{\frac{e^{\varepsilon_{L}}\log\frac{4}{\delta}}{n}}\right) \tag{1}
\end{equation}
as long as \(n \gg e^{\varepsilon_{L}}\log(1/\delta)\). That is quite a lot to parse, though: what does this actually <em>mean</em>?</p>

<p><strong>First</strong>, the assumption that all users have the same randomizer (or at least cannot be distinguished by their randomizer) is quite natural: if they didn’t, then we wouldn’t be able to say anything in general, since the randomizer they use could just give away their identity completely. For instance, as an extreme case, the randomizer of user \(i\) could just append \(i\) to the message (it’s OK, still LDP!), and then shuffling achieves exactly nothing: we know who sent what. So OK, asking for all randomizers to be the same is not really a restriction.</p>

<p><strong>Second</strong>, each user only sends one message, and this preserves its length (we just shuffled the messages, didn’t modify them!). So if you start with an LDP protocol with amazing features XYZ (e.g., the messages are \(1\)-bit long, or users don’t share a random seed, or the randomizers run in time \(O(1)\)), then the shuffle protocol enjoys exactly the same properties. (It only enjoys naturally some <em>robustness</em>, in the sense that if \(10\%\) if the \(n\) users maliciously deviate from the protocol, they can’t really jeopardize the privacy of the remaining \(90\%\) of users.<sup id="fnref:2"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Which is… good.)</p>

<p><strong>Third</strong>, this is inherently approximate DP. Here we started with pure LDP (you can also extend that to approximate LDP) and ended up with approximate Shuffle DP: this is not a mistake, that’s how it is. I am not a purist (erm) myself, and that looks more than good enough to me; but if you seek pure Shuffle DP, then this result is not the droid you’re looking for.</p>

<p align="center">
  <img alt="This is not the pure DP guarantee you are looking for." src="https://differentialprivacy.org/../images/droids-looking.png" width="50%"/>
</p>
<p><br/></p>

<p>Alright, <em>what</em> is this guarantee stated in <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:eps:epsL">(1)</a> giving us? Let’s interpret the expression in <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:eps:epsL">(1)</a> in two parameter regimes, focusing on \(\varepsilon\) (fixing some small \(\delta&gt;0\)). If we start with \(\varepsilon_{L} \ll 1\) for our LDP randomizers \(R\), then a first-order Taylor expansion shows that we get
\[
		\varepsilon \approx \varepsilon_{L}\cdot 8\sqrt{\frac{\log\frac{4}{\delta}}{n}}
\]
so that <em>shuffling improved our privacy parameter by a factor \(\sqrt{n}\)</em>.<sup id="fnref:3"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> 😲 This is great! With more users, comes more privacy!</p>

<p>But that was starting with small \(\varepsilon_{L}\), that is, already pretty good privacy guarantees for our LDP “building block” \(R\). What happens if we start with “somewhat lousy” privacy guarantees, that is, \(\varepsilon_{L} \gg 1\)? Do we get anything interesting then?
Another Taylor expansion (everything is a Taylor expansion) shows us that, then,
<a name="eq:epsL:ll:one"/>
\[
\begin{equation}
		\varepsilon \approx \log\left( 1+ 8\sqrt{\frac{e^{\varepsilon_{L}}\log\frac{4}{\delta}}{n}}\right) \tag{2}
\end{equation}
\]
or, put differently,
<a name="eq:epsL:gg:one"/>
\[
\begin{equation}
		\varepsilon \approx 8e^{\varepsilon_{L}/2}\sqrt{\frac{\log\frac{4}{\delta}}{n}} \tag{3}
\end{equation}
\]
That’s a bit harder to interpret, but that seems… useful? It is: let us see how much, with a couple examples.</p>

<h4 id="learning">Learning.</h4>
<p>The first one is distribution learning, a.k.a. density estimation: you have \(n\) i.i.d. samples (one per user) from an unknown probability distribution \(\mathbf{p}\) over a discrete domain of size \(k\), and your goal is to output an estimate \(\widehat{\mathbf{p}}\) such that, with high (say, constant) probability, \(\mathbf{p}\) and \(\widehat{\mathbf{p}}\) are close in <em>total variation distance</em>:
\[
		\operatorname{TV}(\mathbf{p},\widehat{\mathbf{p}}) = \sup_{S\subseteq [k]} (\mathbf{p}(S) - \widehat{\mathbf{p}}(S) ) \leq \alpha
\]
(if total variation distance seems a bit mysterious, it’s exactly half the \(\ell_1\) distance between the probability mass functions). We know how to solve this problem in the non-private setting: \(n=\Theta\left( \frac{k}{\alpha^2} \right)\) samples are necessary and sufficient. We know how to solve this problem in the (central) DP setting: \(n=\Theta\left( \frac{k}{\alpha^2} + \frac{k}{\alpha\varepsilon} \right)\) samples are necessary and sufficient <a href="https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2015/hash/2b3bf3eee2475e03885a110e9acaab61-Abstract.html" title="Ilias Diakonikolas, Moritz Hardt, Ludwig Schmidt. Differentially Private Learning of Structured Discrete Distributions. NeurIPS 2015"><strong>[DHS15]</strong></a>. We know how to solve this problem in the LDP setting: 
<a name="eq:learning:ldp"/>
\begin{equation}
n=\Theta\left(\frac{k^2}{\alpha^2(e^\varepsilon-1)^2}+\frac{k^2}{\alpha^2e^\varepsilon}+\frac{k}{\alpha^2}\right) \tag{4}
\end{equation}
samples are necessary and sufficient <a href="http://proceedings.mlr.press/v89/acharya19a.html" title="Jayadev Acharya, Ziteng Sun, Huanyu Zhang. Hadamard Response: Estimating Distributions Privately, Efficiently, and with Little Communication. AISTATS 2019"><strong>[ASZ19]</strong></a> (note that the first term is just \(k/(\alpha^2\varepsilon^2)\) for small \(\varepsilon\)). Now, as they say in Mulan: <em>let’s make a shuffle DP algo out of you.</em></p>

<p>If we want to achieve \((\varepsilon,\delta)\)-shuffle DP, we need to select \(\varepsilon_L\). Based on <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:epsL:ll:one">(2)</a> and <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:epsL:gg:one">(3)</a>, and ignoring pesky constants we will choose it so that
<a name="eq:choice:epsL"/>
\begin{equation}
	 \varepsilon_{L} \approx \varepsilon \sqrt{\frac{n}{\log(1/\delta)}}  \quad\text{ or }\quad e^{\varepsilon_{L}} \approx \varepsilon^2 \cdot \frac{n}{\log(1/\delta)}\,. \tag{5}
\end{equation}
depending on whether \(\frac{\varepsilon^2 n}{\log(1/\delta)}\geq 1\). Plugging that back in <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:learning:ldp">(4)</a>, we see that the first case corresponds to the first term (small \(\varepsilon_{L}\)) and the second to the second term (\(\varepsilon_{L} \geq 1\)), and overall the condition on \(n\) for the original LDP algorithm to 
successful learn the distribution becomes
\[
	n \gtrsim 
	\frac{k^2}{\alpha^2(e^{\varepsilon_{L}}-1)^2}+\frac{k^2}{\alpha^2e^{\varepsilon_{L}}}+\frac{k}{\alpha^2}
	\approx \frac{k^2\log(1/\delta)}{\alpha^2\varepsilon^2 n}+\frac{k^2\log(1/\delta)}{\alpha^2\varepsilon^2 n}+\frac{k}{\alpha^2} 
	 \approx \frac{k^2\log(1/\delta)}{\alpha^2\varepsilon^2 n}+\frac{k}{\alpha^2}
\]
(where \(\gtrsim\) means “let’s ignore constants”). There is an \(n\) in the RHS as well, so reorganizing and handling the two terms separately the condition on \(n\) becomes
\[
	n \gtrsim \frac{k \sqrt{\log(1/\delta)}}{\alpha\varepsilon}+\frac{k}{\alpha^2}
\]
which… is great? We immediately get a sample complexity \(O\left(\frac{k}{\alpha^2}+\frac{k \sqrt{\log(1/\delta)}}{\alpha\varepsilon}\right)\) in the shuffle DP model, which (ignoring the \(\sqrt{\log(1/\delta)}\)) matches the one in the <em>central</em> DP setting!</p>

<p><strong>tl;dr:</strong> Taking an optimal LDP algorithm and just shuffling the messages <em>immediately</em> gives an optimal shuffle DP algorithm, no extra work needed.</p>

<h4 id="uniformity-testing">(Uniformity) Testing.</h4>
<p>Alright, maybe it was a fluke? Let’s look at another “basic” problem close to my heart: we don’t want to learn the probability distribution \(\mathbf{p}\), just test whether it is actually <em>the</em> uniform distribution<sup id="fnref:4"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> \(\mathbf{u}\) on the domain \([k]={1,2,\dots,k}\). So if \(\mathbf{p} =\mathbf{u}\), you’ve got to say “yes” with probability at least \(2/3\), and if \(\operatorname{TV}(\mathbf{p},\mathbf{u})&gt;\alpha\), then you need to say “no” with probability at least \(2/3\).</p>

<p>This is also well understood in the non-private setting (\(n=\Theta(\sqrt{k}/\alpha^2)\)) <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/4626074" title="Liam Paninski. A Coincidence-Based Test for Uniformity Given Very Sparsely Sampled Discrete Data. IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory 2008"><strong>[Paninski08]</strong></a> [see also <a href="https://ccanonne.github.io/survey-topics-dt.html}{my upcoming survey">my upcoming survey</a>], in the central DP setting (\(n=\Theta\left( \frac{\sqrt{k}}{\alpha^2} + \frac{\sqrt{k}}{\alpha\sqrt{\varepsilon}}+\frac{k^{1/3}}{\alpha^{4/3}\varepsilon^{2/3}} + \frac{1}{\alpha\varepsilon} \right)\)) <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1707.05128" title="Jayadev Acharya, Ziteng Sun, Huanyu Zhang. Differentially Private Testing of Identity and Closeness of Discrete Distributions. NeurIPS 2018"><strong>[ASZ18</strong></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1707.05497" title="Maryam Aliakbarpour, Ilias Diakonikolas, Ronitt Rubinfeld. Differentially Private Identity and Equivalence Testing of Discrete Distributions. ICML 2018"><strong>ADR18]</strong></a>, and in the LDP setting, where the result differs on whether the users can communicate or share a common random seed 
<a name="eq:testing:ldp:publiccoin"/>
\begin{equation}
	n=\Theta\left( \frac{k}{\alpha^2(e^\varepsilon-1)^2} + \frac{k}{\alpha^2e^{\varepsilon/2}} + \frac{\sqrt{k}}{\alpha^2}\right) \tag{6}
\end{equation} or not
<a name="eq:testing:ldp:privatecoin"/> 
\begin{equation}
	n=\Theta\left( \frac{k^{3/2}}{\alpha^2(e^\varepsilon-1)^2} + \frac{k^{3/2}}{\alpha^2e^{\varepsilon}} + \frac{\sqrt{k}}{\alpha^2}\right) \tag{7}
\end{equation}
as established in a sequence of papers <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1812.11476" title="Inference under Information Constraints: Lower Bounds from Chi-Square Contraction. COLT 2019"><strong>[ACT19</strong></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01452" title="Kareem Amin, Matthew Joseph, Jieming Mao. Pan-Private Uniformity Testing. COLT 2020"><strong>AJM20</strong></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.07981" title="Jayadev Acharya, Cl&#xE9;ment L. Canonne, Cody Freitag, Ziteng Sun, Himanshu Tyagi.  Inference Under Information Constraints III: Local Privacy Constraints. IEEE J. Sel. Areas Inf. Theory 2021"><strong>ACFST21</strong></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.10976" title="Jayadev Acharya, Cl&#xE9;ment L. Canonne, Yuhan Liu, Ziteng Sun, Himanshu Tyagi. Interactive Inference Under Information Constraints. IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory 2022"><strong>ACLST22</strong></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.08987" title="Cl&#xE9;ment L. Canonne, Hongyi Lyu. Uniformity Testing in the Shuffle Model: Simpler, Better, Faster. SOSA 2022"><strong>CL22]</strong></a>.</p>

<p>Now, say you want an (\(\varepsilon,\delta)\)-shuffle DP algorithm for uniformity testing, but don’t want to design one from scratch (though it <em>is</em> possible to do so, and some did <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.09481" title="Victor Balcer, Albert Cheu, Matthew Joseph, Jieming Mao. Connecting Robust Shuffle Privacy and Pan-Privacy. SODA 2021"><strong>[BCJM21</strong></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.08987" title="Cl&#xE9;ment L. Canonne, Hongyi Lyu. Uniformity Testing in the Shuffle Model: Simpler, Better, Faster. SOSA 2022"><strong>CL22</strong></a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.10032" title="Albert Cheu, Chao Yan. Pure Differential Privacy from Secure Intermediaries. arXiv 2021"><strong>CY21]</strong></a>). Let’s say you want to look at the “no-common-random-seed-shared-by-users” model (a.k.a. <em>private-coin</em> setting): so you stare at the corresponding LDP communication complexity, <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:testing:ldp:privatecoin">(7)</a>, and try to choose \(\varepsilon_L\) to start with before shuffling. This will be the same as in the learning example (i.e., <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:choice:epsL">(5)</a>): based on <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:epsL:ll:one">(2)</a> and <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:epsL:gg:one">(3)</a>, we will set
\begin{equation}
	 \varepsilon_{L} \approx \varepsilon \sqrt{\frac{n}{\log(1/\delta)}}  \quad\text{ or }\quad e^{\varepsilon_{L}} \approx \varepsilon^2 \cdot \frac{n}{\log(1/\delta)}\,.
\end{equation}
depending on whether \(\frac{\varepsilon^2 n}{\log(1/\delta)}\geq 1\). Plugging this back in <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:testing:ldp:privatecoin">(7)</a> and quickly checking which case corresponds to each term, we then easily get that for our algorithm to correctly solve the uniformity testing problem, it suffices that the sample complexity (number of users) \(n\) satisfies
\[
	n \gtrsim \frac{k^{3/2}}{\alpha^2(e^{\varepsilon_L}-1)^2} + \frac{k^{3/2}}{\alpha^2e^{\varepsilon_L}} + \frac{\sqrt{k}}{\alpha^2}
	 \approx \frac{k^{3/2}\log(1/\delta)}{\alpha^2\varepsilon^2 n } + \frac{\sqrt{k}}{\alpha^2}
\]
which, reorganizing and solving for \(n\), means that it suffices to have 
\[
	n \gtrsim \frac{k^{3/4}\sqrt{\log(1/\delta)}}{\alpha\varepsilon} + \frac{\sqrt{k}}{\alpha^2}\,.
\]
And, <em>voilà</em>! Even better, we also have strong evidence to suspect that this sample complexity \(O\Big(\frac{k^{3/4}\sqrt{\log(1/\delta)}}{\alpha\varepsilon}+ \frac{\sqrt{k}}{\alpha^2}\Big)\) is tight among all private-coin algorithms.<sup id="fnref:5"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup></p>

<p>Now, if you wanted to look at <em>public-coin</em> shuffle DP protocols (with a common random seed available), then you would start with an optimal public-coin LDP algorithm (and look at <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:testing:ldp:publiccoin">(6)</a>), and setting \(\varepsilon_L\) the same way you’d get a shuffle DP algorithm with sample complexity
\[
n=O\Big(\frac{k^{2/3}\log^{1/3}(1/\delta)}{\alpha^{4/3}\varepsilon^{2/3}} + \frac{\sqrt{k\log(1/\delta)}}{\alpha\varepsilon}+ \frac{\sqrt{k}}{\alpha^2}\Big)
\]
which, well, is <em>also</em> strongly believed to be optimal!</p>

<p><strong>tl;dr:</strong> Here again, taking an optimal off-the-shelf LDP algorithm and just shuffling the messages <em>immediately</em> gives an optimal shuffle DP algorithm, no extra work needed.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion.</h3>
<p>I hope the above convinced you of how useful this privacy amplification can be: from an optimal LDP algorithm, featuring any extra appealing characteristics you like, <em>just adding an extra shuffling step as postprocessing</em> yields an (often optimal? At least good) shuffle DP algorithm, <em>with the same characteristics</em> and built-in robustness against malicious users.</p>

<p>All you need is to make sure that your starting point, the LDP algorithm satisfies a couple things: (1) all users have the same randomizer,<sup id="fnref:6"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup> and (2) it works in all regimes of \(\varepsilon\) (both high-privacy, \(\varepsilon \leq 1\), <em>and</em> low-privacy, \(\varepsilon \gg 1\)). Once you’ve got this, Bob’s your uncle! You get shuffle DP algorithms for free.</p>

<p>It is not only appealing from a theoretical point of view, by the way! The authors of the paper worked hard to make their empirical analysis compelling as well, and their code is available <a href="https://github.com/apple/ml-shuffling-amplification">on GitHub</a> 📝. But more importantly, from a practitioner’s point of view, this means it is enough to design, implement, and test <em>one</em> algorithm (the LDP one we start with) to automatically get a trusted one in the shuffle DP model as well: this reduces the risks of bugs, security failures, the amount of work spending tuning, testing…</p>

<p>So yes, whenever possible, we <em>should</em> hide among the clones!</p>

<hr/>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>The title of this post is a reference to the title of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.12803" title="Vitaly Feldman, Audra McMillan, Kunal Talwar. Hiding Among the Clones: A Simple and Nearly Optimal Analysis of Privacy Amplification by Shuffling. FOCS 2021"><strong>[FMT21]</strong></a>, “Hiding Among The Clones,” and to the notion of <em>privacy blanket</em> introduced by Balle, Bell, Gascón, and Nissim <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-030-26951-7_22" title="Borja Balle, James Bell, Adri&#xE0; Gasc&#xF3;n, Kobbi Nissim. The Privacy Blanket of the Shuffle Model. CRYPTO 2019"><strong>[BBGN19]</strong></a>. Intuitively, the “amplification by shuffling” paradigm can be seen as anonymizing the messages from local randomizers, whose message distribution can be mathematically decomposed as a mixture of “noise distribution not depending on the user’s input” and “distribution actually depending on their input.” As a result, each user randomly sends a message from the first or second distribution of the mixture.  But the shuffling then hides the informative messages (drawn from the second part of the mixture) among the non-informative (noise) ones: so the noise messages end up providing a “privacy blanket” in which sensitive information is safely and soundly wrapped. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:1">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>More specifically, they can completely jeopardize the <em>utility</em> (accuracy) of the result, but in terms of privacy, all they can do is slightly reduce it: if \(10\%\) of users are malicious, the remaining \(90\%\) still get the privacy amplification of guarantee of <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#eq:eps:epsL">(1)</a>, but with \(0.9n\) instead of \(n\). <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:2">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Of course, we started with a local privacy guarantee, and ended up with a shuffle privacy guarantee: so the two are incomparable, and one has to interpret this “amplification” in that context. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:3">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>You can here replace uniform by any known distribution \(\mathbf{q}\) of your choosing, that doesn’t change the question (and result), but uniform is nice. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:4">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>As long as one is happy with approximate DP. One can achieve that in pure DP as well, but it’s a bit more complicated <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.10032" title="Albert Cheu, Chao Yan. Pure Differential Privacy from Secure Intermediaries. arXiv 2021"><strong>[CY21]</strong></a>. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:5">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>This is not such a big assumption usually, and there are somewhat-general ways to get to that using a logarithmic factor in the number of users. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:6">↩</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-24T15:45:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-24T15:45:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Clément Canonne</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://differentialprivacy.org</id>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Website for the differential privacy research community</subtitle>
      <title>Differential Privacy</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T22:49:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2022/05/23/ideal-workshop-on-high-dimensional-geometry-and-analysis/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2022/05/23/ideal-workshop-on-high-dimensional-geometry-and-analysis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>IDEAL Workshop on High-Dimensional Geometry and Analysis</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">May 27, 2022 Northwestern University Mudd 3514 https://www.ideal.northwestern.edu/events/high-dimensional-analysis/ Speakers Ainesh Bakshi (Carnegie Mellon University), Arnold Filtser (Bar Ilan University), Weiyun Ma (Stanford University), Assaf Naor (Princeton University), Erik Waingarten (Stanford University) Logistics Dates: Friday, May 27 Location: Northwestern University Rooms: Mudd 3514 Streaming: Zoom Registration Link on website- https://www.ideal.northwestern.edu/events/high-dimensional-analysis/ PRELIMINARY Schedule All times are in … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2022/05/23/ideal-workshop-on-high-dimensional-geometry-and-analysis/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">IDEAL Workshop on High-Dimensional Geometry and Analysis</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-05-23T22:38:18Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-23T22:38:18Z</published>
    <category term="workshop"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:38:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8334</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/23/why-i-am-not-a-longtermist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Why I am not a longtermist</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Apologies for yet another “philosophizing” blog post, hope to get back to posts with more equations soon… Should also mention that one response to this piece was that “anyone who writes a piece called “Why I am not a longtermist” is probably more of a longtermist than 90% of the population” 🙂 –Boaz] “Longtermism” is … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/23/why-i-am-not-a-longtermist/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Why I am not a longtermist</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>[Apologies for yet another <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/category/philosophizing/">“philosophizing” </a>blog post, hope to get back to posts with more equations soon… Should also mention that one response to this piece was that “anyone who writes a piece called “Why I am not a longtermist” is probably more of a longtermist than 90% of the population</em>” <img alt="&#x1F642;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f642.png" style="height: 1em;"/> <em>–Boaz]</em></p>



<p>“<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longtermism">Longtermism</a>” is a moral philosophy that places much more weight on the well-being of all future generations than on the current one. It <a href="https://www.effectivealtruism.org/articles/longtermism">holds</a> that “positively influencing the long-term future is a key moral priority of our time,” where “long term” can be <em>really</em> long term, e.g., “many thousands of years in the future, or much further still.”   At its core is the belief that each one of the potential quadrillion or more people that may exist in the future is as important as any single person today.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><img alt="" height="596" src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/JibhteUU2RwXMZCy3FU7bwjTqOYcNds8u29ny_iPP3aK5N-idd1vJtp4RKCi-Lv-7E7u3-nziFPYCNdD8C78f58X3CVM3HPbQoIsrPL3EvdLDNnzgeWuWpahl04cL9QMaG_lZVjcKL0G-r5s4w" width="439"/></figure></div>


<p>Longtermism has recently attracted attention, some of it in <a href="https://www.currentaffairs.org/2021/07/the-dangerous-ideas-of-longtermism-and-existential-risk">alarming tones</a>. The reasoning behind longtermism is natural: if we assume that human society will continue to exist for at least a few millennia, many more people will be born in the future than are alive today. However, since predictions are famously hard to make, especially about the future, longtermism invariably gets wrapped up with probabilities. Once you do these calculations, preventing an infinitely bad outcome, even if it would only happen with tiny probability, will have infinite utility. Hence longtermism tends to focus on so-called “existential risk”:  The risk that humanity will go through in an extinction event, like the one suffered by the Neanderthals or Dinosaurs, or another type of irreversible humanity-wise calamity.<br/></p>



<p>This post explains why I do not subscribe to this philosophy. Let me clarify that I am not saying that all longtermists are bad people. Many “longtermists” have given generously to improve people’s lives worldwide, particularly in developing countries. For example, none of the top charities of <a href="https://www.givewell.org/">Givewell</a> (an organization associated with the effective altruism movement, in which many prominent longtermists are members) focus on hypothetical future risks. Instead, they all deal with current pressing issues, including Malaria, childhood vaccinations, and extreme poverty. Overall the effective altruism movement has done much to benefit currently living people. Some of its members <a href="https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2018/10/15/17962134/future-perfect-podcast-kidney-donation">donated their kidneys to strangers</a>: These are good people- morally better than me. It is hardly fair to fault people that are already contributing more than most others for caring about issues that I think are less significant.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><img alt="" height="496" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/wGuGQ0ly7gKlSuGx80WXjdthvUrDt9ZSOgN5mma-p_dJ0_rQdjlSyAet9g5zLui8K6sw_uG8lzzd1VHb3l32QVEbNbj2wuzwLDi-VsH4Pn24RR-C3u2-9nB5-xWakbNP3tPlmgthzGBRQhsdfQ" width="506"/><a href="https://80000hours.org/2021/08/effective-altruism-allocation-resources-cause-areas/">Benjamin Todd’s</a> estimates of Effective Altruism resource allocations</figure></div>


<p/>



<p>This post critiques the philosophy of longtermism rather than the particular actions or beliefs of “longtermists.” In particular, the following are often highly correlated with one another:</p>



<ol><li>Belief in the philosophy of longtermism.</li><li>A belief that existential risk is not just a concern for the far-off future and a low-probability event, but there is a very significant chance of it happening in the near future (next few decades or at most a century).</li><li>A belief that the most significant existential risk could arise from artificial intelligence and that this is a real risk in the near future.</li></ol>



<p>Here I focus on (1) and explain why I disagree with this philosophy. While I might disagree on specific calculations of (2) and (3), I fully agree with the need to think and act regarding near-term risks.  Society tends to err on the side of being too myopic. We prepare too little even for risks that are not just predictable but are also predicted, including climate change, pandemics, nuclear conflict, and even software hacks. It is hard to motivate people to spend resources for safety when the outcome (bad event not happening) is invisible. It is also true that over the last decades, humanity’s technological capacities have grown so much that for the first time in history, we are capable of doing irreversible damage to our planet. </p>



<p>In addition to the above, I agree that we need to think carefully about the risks of any new technology, particularly one that, like artificial intelligence, can be very powerful but not fully understood.  Some AI risks are relevant to the shorter term: they are likely over the next decade or are already happening. There <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Weapons-Math-Destruction-Increases-Inequality/dp/0553418815">are</a> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Ethical-Algorithm-Science-Socially-Design/dp/0190948205">several</a> <a href="https://fairmlbook.org/">books</a> on these challenges. None of my critiques apply to such issues. At some point, I might write a separate blog post about artificial intelligence and its short and long-term risks. </p>



<p>My reasons for not personally being a “longtermist” are the following:</p>



<p><strong>The probabilities are too small to reason about.</strong></p>



<p>Physicists know that there is no point in writing a measurement up to 3 significant digits if your measurement device has only one-digit accuracy. Our ability to reason about events that are decades or more into the future is severely limited. At best, we could estimate probabilities up to an order of magnitude, and even that may be optimistic. Thus, claims such as <a href="https://www.existential-risk.org/concept.html">Nick Bostrom’s</a>, that <em>“the expected value of reducing existential risk by a mere one billionth of one billionth of one percentage point is worth a hundred billion times as much as a billion human lives”</em> make no sense to me.  This is especially the case since these “probabilities” are Bayesian, i.e., correspond to degrees of belief. If, for example, you evaluate the existential-risk probability by aggregating the responses of 1000 experts, then what one of these experts had for breakfast is likely to have an impact larger than 0.001 percent (which, according to Bostrom, would correspond to much more than 10²⁰ human lives). To the extent we can quantify existential risks in the far future, we can only say something like “extremely likely,” “possible,” or “can’t be ruled out.” Assigning numbers to such qualitative assessments is an exercise in futility. </p>



<p><strong>I cannot justify sacrificing current living humans for abstract probabilities.</strong></p>



<p>Related to the above, rather than focusing on specific, measurable risks (e.g., earthquakes, climate change), longtermism is often concerned with extremely hard to quantify risks. In truth, we cannot know what will happen 100 years into the future and what would be the impact of any particular technology. Even if our actions will have drastic consequences for future generations, the dependence of the impact on our choices is likely to be chaotic and unpredictable. To put things in perspective, many of the risks we are worried about today, including nuclear war, climate change, and AI safety, only emerged in the last century or decades. It is hard to underestimate our ability to predict even a decade into the future, let alone a century or more.</p>



<p>Given that there is so much suffering and need in the world right now, I cannot accept a philosophy that prioritizes abstract armchair calculations over actual living humans. (This concern is not entirely hypothetical: <a href="https://globalprioritiesinstitute.org/hilary-greaves-william-macaskill-the-case-for-strong-longtermism-2/">Greaves and MacAskill</a> estimate that $100 spent on AI safety would, in expectation, correspond to saving a <em>trillion lives</em> and hence would be “far more than the near-future benefits of bednet distribution [for preventing Malaria],” and recommend that it is better that individuals “fund AI safety rather than developing world poverty reduction.”)</p>



<p><a href="https://www.effectivealtruism.org/articles/longtermism">Moorhouse</a> compares future humans to ones living far away from us. He says that just like “something happening far away from us in space isn’t less intrinsically bad just because it’s far away,” we should care about humans in the far-off future as much as we care about present ones. But I think that we <em>should</em> care less about very far away events, especially if it’s so far away that we cannot observe them. E.g., as far as we know, there may well be trillions of sentient beings in the universe right now whose welfare can somehow be impacted by our actions. </p>



<p><strong>We cannot improve what we cannot measure.</strong></p>



<p>An inherent disadvantage of probabilities is that they are invisible until they occur. We have no direct way to measure whether a probability of an event X has increased or decreased. So, we cannot tell whether our efforts are working or not. The <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/03/philosophy-of-science-and-the-blockchain-a-book-review/">scientific revolution</a> involved moving from armchair philosophizing to making measurable predictions. I do not believe we can make meaningful progress without concrete goals. For some risks, we do have quantifiable goals (Carbon emissions, number of nuclear warheads). Still, there are significant challenges to finding a measurable proxy for very low-probability and far-off events. Hence, even if we accept that the risks are real and vital, I do not think we can directly do anything about them before finding such proxies. </p>



<p>Proxies do not have to be perfect: Theoretical computer science made much progress using the imperfect measure of worst-case asymptotic complexity. The same holds for machine learning and artificial benchmarks. It is enough that proxies encourage the generation of new ideas or technologies and achieve gradual improvement. One lesson from modern machine learning is that the objective (aka loss function) doesn’t have to perfectly match the task for it to be useful.</p>



<p><strong>Long-term risk mitigation can only succeed through short-term progress.</strong></p>



<p>Related to the above, I believe that addressing long-term risks can only be successful if it’s tied to shorter-term advances that have clear utility. For example, consider the following two extinction scenarios:</p>



<p>1. The actual Neanderthal extinction.<br/>2. A potential human extinction 50 years from now due to total nuclear war.</p>



<p>I argue that the only realistic scenario to avoid extinction in both cases is a sequence of actions that improve some measurable outcome. While sometimes extinction could theoretically be avoided by a society making a huge sacrifice to eliminate a hypothetical scenario, this could never actually happen.</p>



<p>While the reasons for the Neanderthal extinction are not fully known, most researchers believe that Neanderthals were out-competed by our ancestors – modern humans – who had better tools and ways to organize society. The crucial point is that the approaches to prevent extinction for Neanderthal were the same ones to improve their lives in their current environment. They may not have been capable of doing so, but it wasn’t because they were working on the wrong problems.</p>



<p>Contrast this with the scenario of human extinction through total nuclear war. In such a case, our conventional approaches for keeping nuclear arms in check, such as international treaties and sanctions, have failed. Perhaps in hindsight, humanity’s optimum course of action would have been a permanent extension of the middle ages, stopping the scientific revolution from happening through restricting education, religious oppression, and vigorous burning-at-stake of scientists.  Or perhaps humanity could even now make a collective decision to go back and delete all traces of post 17th-century science and technology.</p>



<p>I cannot rule out the possibility that, in hindsight, one of those outcomes would have had more aggregate utility than our current trajectory. But even if this is the case, such an outcome is simply not possible. Humanity can not and will not halt its progress, and solutions to significant long-term problems have to arise as a sequence of solutions to shorter-range measurable ones, each of which shows positive progress. Our only hope to avoid a total nuclear war is through piecemeal quantifiable progress.  We need to use diplomacy, international cooperation, and monitoring technologies to reduce the world’s nuclear arsenal one warhead at a time. This piecemeal, incremental approach may or may not work, but it’s the only one we have. </p>



<p><strong>Summary: think of the long term, but act and measure in the short term.</strong></p>



<p>It is appropriate for philosophers to speculate on hypothetical scenarios centuries into the future and wonder whether actions we take today could influence them. However, I do not believe such an approach will, in practice, lead to a positive impact on humanity and, if taken to the extreme, may even have negative repercussions. We should maintain epistemic humility. Statements about probabilities involving fractions of percentage points, or human lives in the trillions, should raise alarm bells. Such calculations can be particularly problematic since they can lead to a “the end justifies the means” attitude, which can accept any harm to currently living people in the name of the practically infinite multitudes of future hypothetical beings. </p>



<p>We need to maintain the invariant that, even if motivated by the far-off future, our actions “first do no harm” to living, breathing humans. Indeed, as I mentioned, even longtermists don’t wake up every morning thinking about how to reduce the chance that something terrible happens in the year 1,000,000 AD by 0.001%. Instead, many longtermists care about particular risks because they believe these risks are likely in the near-term future. If you manage to make a convincing case that humanity faces a real chance of near-term total destruction, then most people would agree that this is very very bad, and we should act to prevent it. It doesn’t matter whether humanity’s extinction is two times or a zillion times worse than the death of half the world’s population. Talking about trillions of hypothetical beings thousands of years into the future only turns people off. There is a reason that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pascal%27s_wager">Pascal’s Wager</a> is not such a winning argument, and I have yet to meet someone who converted to a particular religion because it had the grisliest version of hell.</p>



<p>This does not mean that thinking and preparing for longer-term risks is pointless. Maintaining seed banks, monitoring asteroids, researching pathogens, designing vaccine platforms, and working toward nuclear disarmament, are all essential activities that society should take. Whenever a new technology emerges, artificial intelligence included, it is crucial to consider how it can be misused or lead to unintended consequences. By no means do I argue that humanity should spend all of its resources only on actions that have a direct economic benefit. Indeed, the whole enterprise of basic science is built on pursuing directions that, in the short term, increase our knowledge but do not have practical utility. Progress is not measured only in dollars, but it should be measured somehow. Epistemic humility also means that we should be content with working on direct, measurable proxies, even if they are not perfect matches for the risk at hand. For example, the probability of extinction via total nuclear war might not be a direct function of the number of deployed nuclear warheads. However, the latter is still a pretty good proxy for it.</p>



<p>Similarly, even if you are genuinely worried about long-term risk, I suggest you spend most of your time in the present. Try to think of short-term problems whose solutions can be verified, which might advance the long-term goal. A “problem” does not have to be practical: it can be a mathematical question, a computational challenge, or an empirically verifiable prediction. The advantage is that even if the long-term risk stays hypothetical or the short-term problem turns out to be irrelevant to it, you have still made measurable progress. As <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/03/philosophy-of-science-and-the-blockchain-a-book-review/">has happened before</a>, to make actual progress on solving existential risk, the topic needs to move from philosophy books and blog discussions into empirical experiments and concrete measures.</p>



<p><strong>Acknowledgments:</strong> Thanks to Scott Aaronson and Ben Edelman for commenting on an earlier version of this post.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-23T14:37:36Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-23T14:37:36Z</published>
    <category term="Philosophizing"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20050</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/23/hilberts-lost-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hilbert’s Lost Problem</title>
    <summary>Mathematics consists in proving the most obvious thing in the least obvious way—Pólya. David Hilbert famously presented 23 important open mathematical problems at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Paris in 1900. He intended to include a 24th on the simplicity of proofs. Today we discuss this problem, which was “lost” until the historian Rüdiger […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<i>Mathematics consists in proving the most obvious thing in the least obvious way—Pólya.</i><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/23/hilberts-lost-problem/285px-david_hilbert_1886/" rel="attachment wp-att-20070"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-20070" height="170" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/285px-David_Hilbert_1886.jpg?resize=130%2C170&amp;ssl=1" width="130"/></a></p>
<p>
David Hilbert famously presented 23 important open mathematical problems at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Paris in 1900. He intended to include a 24th on the simplicity of proofs.</p>
<p>
Today we discuss this problem, which was “lost” until the historian Rüdiger Thiele discovered it in Hilbert’s papers in 2000 and brought it to light in a <a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download;jsessionid=C970003BC10AB452B346D45B8AAE14B6?doi=10.1.1.97.7633&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf">paper</a> for the American Mathematical Monthly.</p>
<p>
I (Ken) have long wondered why Hilbert targeted the number 23 for his list. That some of his <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilbert's_problems">problems</a> have broad, vague statements tells me he could have altered their number. To be sure, he discussed only 10 in his actual 1900 lecture; the rest appeared in his long <a href="http://www.ams.org/journals/bull/1902-08-10/S0002-9904-1902-00923-3/S0002-9904-1902-00923-3.pdf">article</a> that year. Until Dick drafted this post and I found Thiele’s article, I had not known about a No. 24—a nice factorial number. </p>
<p>
As <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/epdf/10.1098/rsta.2018.0040">discussed</a> by Inês Hipolito and Reinhard Kahle, in a <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/toc/rsta/2019/377/2140">special issue</a> of the UK Royal Society <em>Philosophical Transactions A</em> devoted to Hilbert’s 24th, there were only faint traces of it until Thiele’s discovery. They decline to guess Hilbert’s motives for leaving it out, but I venture this: Hilbert could not agree with himself on the terms by which to state it, even broadly. How to quantify simplicity was already the subject of Dick’s draft, into which we blend.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Pólya on Proofs </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
One simple question is whether a human notion of simpler proof would accord with, say, that of a Martian. George Pólya was one of a vanguard of Hungarian emigré scientists who came to be called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Martians_(scientists)">The Martians</a> after another of them, the physicist Leo Szilard, gave this answer to Enrico Fermi’s question of why aliens had not been detected when life in the universe should be plentiful:</p>
<blockquote><p>
“They are among us, but they call themselves Hungarians.”
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Kidding aside, this could set up a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linguistic_relativity">Sapir-Whorf</a> type hypothesis that humans from disparate linguistic groups and mathematical cultures could have different values for proofs. Even if so, the joke would be on non-Hungarians, because Paul Erdős, whose idea of “Proofs from The Book” set the internationally recognized standard of proof elegance, was also a “Martian.”</p>
<p>
Pólya’s quote above hits the nail on the head. For an example, consider the <a href="https://www.math.utah.edu/~alfeld/math/q1.html">theorem</a> that: </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 1</b> <em> The square root of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is irrational. </em></p></blockquote>
<p>
The well-known proof begins by supposing not: </p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/23/hilberts-lost-problem/proof-6/" rel="attachment wp-att-20055"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-20055" height="460" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/proof.png?resize=450%2C460&amp;ssl=1" width="450"/></a></p>
<p>
One might claim that this famous proof is not obvious—do you agree?</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> A Measure </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Now consider the general task of proving statements of this form:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 2</b> <em><a name="pos"/> For all <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, 	</em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  f(n) &gt; 0. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++f%28n%29+%3E+0.+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
</em><p><em> </em></p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Think this as an encoding of an interesting property: For example, for each <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> there is a prime <img alt="{p&gt;n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%3En%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. Or for each planar graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> there is some four coloring of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. Or <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>
To make this more concrete, let us base proofs on the Peano axioms for arithmetic, and suppose that <img alt="{f}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is well-defined in this system. Note that proving <img alt="{f}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> to be total computable is not the same as proving that all its values are <em>positive</em> as Theorem <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/#pos">2</a> asserts. In case Theorem <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/#pos">2</a> is provable, we have two key parameters:</p>
<li>D: The length of the definition of <img alt="{f(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.
</li><li>P: The length of the full proof of Theorem <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/#pos">2</a>.
<p/><p><br/>
Our proof simplicity measure is then 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  M=\frac{P}{D} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++M%3D%5Cfrac%7BP%7D%7BD%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p/><h2> Some Instances </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Here are some keys to understanding the value <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> intuitively:</p>
<ol>
<li> For known provable problems we might have that <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is not too large
</li><li> For classic problems like the Four-Color problem we might have that <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is huge. Think of the proof that arises in this case.
</li><li> For many chess positions where one side can win, say checkmate in 30 moves, the proof of that is likewise huge. Crafting chess problems where the proof is both crisp and hard to find is a centuries-old art.
</li><li> For open problems, <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is currently infinite.
</li><li> But for practical software we get something bounded. The trouble here is that <img alt="{D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BD%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is potentially huge and could be the size of <img alt="{P}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.
</li></ol>
<p>
Consider for the last case a program that calculates your tax payment based on the US tax code, for example. The code has wording like:  </p>
<blockquote><p>
An apparently insignificant discrepancy between the wording in the Statutes at Large and the wording in some editions of the U.S. Code with respect to a provision of the Internal Revenue Code (specifically, the words “any papers” in the first sentence of 6104(a)(1)(A) is described by the U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia in the case of Tax Analysts v. Internal Revenue Serv., 214 F.3d 179 (D.C. Cir. 2000), in footnote 1. According to the Court, some versions of the U.S. Code show the text as “any paper” while the Statutes at Large version shows the text as “any papers.”
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Thus the proof <img alt="{P}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> could be the same size of <img alt="{D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BD%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. Thus,</p>
<p>
Case: <img alt="{P &gt;&gt; D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP+%3E%3E+D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. This is the usual proof of a classic problem like the four-color problem. Huge proof. </p>
<p>
Case: <img alt="{P \approx D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP+%5Capprox+D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. This is like a simple problem or like a proof of a complex program with tons of bits in its description. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Proofs and Software </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
My famous—infamous?—<a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/social.pdf">paper</a> with Alan Perlis and Rich de Millo raised the related issue in the first sentence of our abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
It is argued that formal verifications of programs, no matter how obtained, will not play the same key role in the development of computer science and software engineering as proofs do in mathematics.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
This argument made over four decades ago has been argued by critics as being wrong. Take a look at <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/06/i-went-to-debate-about-program-verif.html">this</a> for comments about the recent <a href="https://scp.cc.gatech.edu/2021/05/26/debate-that-changed-programming-living-history/">debate</a> on the paper moderated by Harry Lewis.</p>
<p>
We claim that we were correct but for a different reason that we made in the original paper. We got it <b>right</b> but for the wrong reason. The real reason is alluded to in this <a href="http://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/publications/publication8316-abstract.html">statement</a> by Tony Hoare, whose programme of proofs for programs partly spurred our paper:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
Ten years ago, researchers into formal methods (and I was the most mistaken among them) predicted that the programming world would embrace with gratitude every assistance promised by formalisation to solve the problems of reliability that arise when programs get large and more safety-critical. Programs have now got very large and very critical—well beyond the scale which can be comfortably tackled by formal methods. … It has turned out that the world just does not suffer significantly from the kind of problem that our research was originally intended to solve.
</p></blockquote>
<p>
See also his 1996 <a href="http://176.9.41.242/docs/math/1996-hoare.pdf">position paper</a>, “How Did Software Get So Reliable Without Proof?”</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Does this measure <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> shed some light on the problems of program verification? Is it useful? Would it have satisfied Hilbert? Hilbert’s handwritten note discovered by Thiele showed him thinking in terms of proofs via polynomial invariants and equations—hence maybe not at a brute level of counting symbols.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
[some format fixes, young Hilbert picture]</p></li></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-23T11:20:42Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-23T11:20:42Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="David Hilbert"/>
    <category term="open problems"/>
    <category term="proof complexity"/>
    <category term="verification"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8785234285731310998</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/8785234285731310998/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/05/in-1960s-students-protested-vietnam.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8785234285731310998" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8785234285731310998" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/05/in-1960s-students-protested-vietnam.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>In the 1960's students protested the Vietnam war!/In 1830 students protested... Math?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> I was at SUNY Stonybrook for college 1976-1980. </p><p>I remember one student protest about a change to the calendar that (I think) would have us go home for winter break and then come back for finals.  I don't recall how that turned out. </p><p>However I had heard about the protests in the 1960's over the Vietnam war. Recall that there was a draft back then so college students were directly affected. </p><p>I was reading a book `<i>Everything you know is wrong'</i> which noted that some people thought the first time there were student protests was in the 1960's but this is not true. (Not quite as startling as finding out that a ships captain cannot perform weddings.) </p><p>It pointed to <i>The 1830 Conic Section Rebellion. </i>I quote Wikipedia (full entry is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conic_Sections_Rebellion">here</a>)</p><p><i>Prior to the introduction of blackboards, Yale students had been allowed to consult diagrams in their textbooks when solving geometry problems pertaining to conic sections – even on exams. When the students were no longer allowed to consult the text, but were instead required to draw their own diagrams on the blackboard, they refused to take the final exam. As a result forty-three of the ninety-six students – among them, Alfred Stille, and Andrew Calhoun, the son of John C. Calhoun (Vice Pres a the time) – were summarily expelled, and Yale authorities warned neighboring universities against admitting them.</i></p><p>Random Thoughts</p><p>1) From my 21st century prospective I am on the students side. It seems analogous to allowing students to use calculators-- which I do allow. </p><p>2) From my 21st century prospective the punishment seems unfair. </p><p>3) The notion of a school telling other schools to not admit student- I do not think this would happen now, and might even be illegal (anti-trust).</p><p>4) I am assuming  the students wanted to be able to consult their text out of some principle: we want to learn concepts not busy work.  And again, from my prospective I agree that it was busy work. </p><p>5) Since all of my thoughts are from a 21st century prospective, they may be incorrect, or at least not as transferable to the 1830 as I think. (Paradox: My ideas may not be as true as I think. But if I think that...) </p><p>6) I try to avoid giving busy work. When I teach Decidability and Undecidability I NEVER have the students actually write a Turing Machine that does something. In other cases I also try to make sure they never have to do drudge work.  And I might not even be right in the 21st century- some of my colleagues tell me its good for the students to get their hands dirty (perhaps just a little) with real TM to get a feel for the fact that they can do anything. </p><p>7) The only student protests I hear about nowadays are on political issues. Do you know of any student protests on issues of how they are tested or what the course requirements are, or something of that ilk? I can imagine my discrete math students marching with signs that say: </p><p>DOWN WITH INDUCTION!</p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-23T02:52:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-23T02:52:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T22:23:48Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/05/22/professor-in-computer-science-and-mathematics-at-warwick-at-university-of-warwick-apply-by-june-1-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/05/22/professor-in-computer-science-and-mathematics-at-warwick-at-university-of-warwick-apply-by-june-1-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Professor in Computer Science and Mathematics at Warwick at University of Warwick (apply by June 1, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at the University of Warwick and the Warwick Mathematics Institute invite applications for a full Professor post in the areas on the interface of Computer Science and Mathematics, including Algorithms and Complexity, Theoretical Computer Science, and Discrete Mathematics. Website: https://warwick.ac.uk/dimap/dimap_post_2022/ Email: A.Czumaj@warwick.ac.uk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at the University of Warwick and the Warwick Mathematics Institute invite applications for a full Professor post in the areas on the interface of Computer Science and Mathematics, including Algorithms and Complexity, Theoretical Computer Science, and Discrete Mathematics.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://warwick.ac.uk/dimap/dimap_post_2022/">https://warwick.ac.uk/dimap/dimap_post_2022/</a><br/>
Email: A.Czumaj@warwick.ac.uk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-22T22:55:06Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-22T22:55:06Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/076</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/076" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-076 |  Average-Case Hardness of Proving Tautologies and Theorems | 

	Hunter Monroe</title>
    <summary>We consolidate two widely believed conjectures about tautologies---no optimal proof system exists, and most require superpolynomial size proofs in any system---into a $p$-isomorphism-invariant condition satisfied by all paddable $\textbf{coNP}$-complete languages or none. The condition is: for any Turing machine (TM) $M$ accepting the language, $\textbf{P}$-uniform input families requiring superpolynomial time by $M$ exist (equivalent to the first conjecture) and appear with positive upper density in an enumeration of input families (implies the second). In that case, no such language is easy on average (in $\textbf{AvgP}$) for a distribution applying non-negligible weight to the hard families.

The hardness of proving tautologies and theorems is likely related. Motivated by the fact that arithmetic sentences encoding "string $x$ is Kolmogorov random" are true but unprovable with positive density in a finitely axiomatized theory $\mathcal{T}$ (Calude and Jürgensen), we conjecture that any propositional proof system requires superpolynomial size proofs for a dense set of $\textbf{P}$-uniform families of tautologies encoding "there is no $\mathcal{T}$ proof of size $\leq t$ showing that string $x$ is Kolmogorov random". This implies the above condition.

The conjecture suggests that there is no optimal proof system because undecidable theories help prove tautologies and do so more efficiently as axioms are added, and that constructing hard tautologies seems difficult because it is impossible to construct Kolmogorov random strings. Similar conjectures that computational blind spots are manifestations of noncomputability would resolve other open problems.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-22T05:41:55Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-22T05:41:55Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/075</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/075" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-075 |  Vanishing Spaces of Random Sets and Applications to Reed-Muller Codes | 

	Prahladh Harsha, 

	Siddharth Bhandari, 

	Srikanth Srinivasan, 

	Ramprasad Saptharishi</title>
    <summary>We study the following natural question on random sets of points in $\mathbb{F}_2^m$:
    

Given a random set of $k$ points $Z=\{z_1, z_2, \dots, z_k\} \subseteq \mathbb{F}_2^m$, what is the dimension of the space of degree at most $r$ multilinear polynomials that vanish on all points in $Z$?


We show that, for $r \leq \gamma m$ (where $\gamma &gt; 0$ is a small, absolute constant) and $k = (1-\epsilon) \cdot {m \choose {\leq r}}$ for any constant $\epsilon &gt; 0$, the space of degree at most $r$ multilinear polynomials vanishing on a random set $Z = \{z_1,\ldots, z_k\}$ has dimension exactly ${m \choose {\leq r}} - k$ with probability $1 - o(1)$. This bound shows that random sets have a much smaller space of degree at most $r$ multilinear polynomials vanishing on them, compared to the worst-case bound (due to Wei (IEEE Trans. Inform. Theory, 1991)) of ${m \choose{\leq r}} - {{\log_2 k}\choose {\leq r}} \gg {m\choose{\leq r}} - k$. 

    Using this bound, we show that high-degree Reed-Muller codes ($\text{RM}(m,d)$ with $d &gt; (1-\gamma) m$) ``achieve capacity'' under the Binary Erasure Channel in the sense that, for any $\epsilon &gt; 0$, we can recover from $(1 - \epsilon) \cdot {m\choose {\leq m-d-1}}$ random erasures with probability $1 - o(1)$. This also implies that $\text{RM}(m,d)$ is also efficiently decodable from $\approx {m\choose {\leq m-(d/2)}}$ random errors for the same range of parameters.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-21T19:53:52Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-21T19:53:52Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/05/21/congratulations-dr-osegueda</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/05/21/congratulations-dr-osegueda.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Congratulations, Dr. Osegueda!</title>
    <summary>Martha Osegueda, one of Mike Goodrich’s students at UC Irvine, successfully defended her doctoral dissertation yesterday. Martha is originally Salvadorean, and came to UCI from an undergraduate degree at the University of Texas El Paso. Her research at UCI has spanned a wide variety of topics in graph drawing, phylogeny, computational geometry, and parallel query complexity:</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Martha Osegueda, one of Mike Goodrich’s students at UC Irvine, successfully defended her doctoral dissertation yesterday. Martha is originally Salvadorean, and came to UCI from an undergraduate degree at the University of Texas El Paso. Her research at UCI has spanned a wide variety of topics in graph drawing, phylogeny, computational geometry, and parallel query complexity:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>“Minimum-width drawings of phylogenetic trees” from <em>COCOA</em> 2019 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-36412-0_4">doi:10.1007/978-3-030-36412-0_4</a>) is about drawing evolutionary trees compactly. For the version of tree drawing they study, it turns out to be NP-hard when the order of the leaves is unconstrained but linear-time solvable for fixed leaf orderings.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Reconstructing binary trees in parallel” from <em>SPAA</em> 2020 (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.15259">arXiv:2006.15259</a>) involved the reconstruction of evolutionary trees from queries asking which pair of a triple of species is closest.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Concatenation arguments and their applications to polyominoes and polycubes”, in <em>CGTA</em> 2021 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.comgeo.2021.101790">doi:10.1016/j.comgeo.2021.101790</a>) and “On the number of compositions of two polycubes” from <em>EuroComb</em> 2021 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-83823-2_12">doi:10.1007/978-3-030-83823-2_12</a>) strengthen the known lower bounds on the growth rates of polyominoes and polycubes, using arguments based on counting ways of gluing pairs of smaller polyforms into larger ones.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Angles of arc-polygons and Lombardi drawings of cacti”, from <em>CCCG</em> 2021 (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.03615">arXiv:2107.03615</a>) is my only collaboration with Martha and one <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/07/10/angles-arc-triangles.html">I have posted about here</a>. It characterizes the vertex angles that are possible in triangles with circular-arc sides, and uses that characterization to prove the existence of a Lombardi drawing for any cactus graph.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Parallel network mapping algorithms” from <em>SPAA</em> 2021 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3409964.3461822">doi:10.1145/3409964.3461822</a>) and “Mapping Networks via parallel \(k\)th-hop traceroute queries” from <em>STACS</em> 2022 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.4230/LIPIcs.STACS.2022.4">doi:10.4230/LIPIcs.STACS.2022.4</a>) are on traceroute-like problems: mapping the structure of a computer communication network using a small number of parallel rounds of pings to determine distances from nodes on the network.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Taming the knight’s tour: Minimizing turns and crossings” from <em>FUN</em> 2021 and <em>TCS</em> 2022 (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tcs.2021.12.002">doi:10.1016/j.tcs.2021.12.002</a>) shows how to move a chess knight around all of the squares of a chessboard, touching each square once, so that the number of times the knight’s path crosses itself or deviates from a straight path are both simultaneously approximately minimized.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>“Diamonds are forever in the blockchain: Geometric polyhedral point-set pattern matching” is her newest work, in submission. It studies problems of aligning a polyhedron to sample points from a similarly-shaped surface, motivated by an application in tracing the provenance of ethically sourced diamonds.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Despite all of these good publications, Mike tells me that it was difficult to persuade Martha that she had done enough for a doctorate. But she had, easily, and now she’s moving on to a position at Meta. Congratulations, Martha!</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108342653334960089">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-21T16:49:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-21T16:49:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T00:02:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=22620</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/05/20/oliver-janzer-and-benny-sudakov-settled-the-erdos-sauer-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Oliver Janzer and  Benny Sudakov Settled the Erdős-Sauer Problem</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Norbert Sauer The news in brief:  In the new paper Resolution of the Erdős-Sauer problem on regular subgraphs Oliver Janzer and Benny Sudakov proved that any graph G with vertices and more than edges contains a k-regular subgraph. This bound … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/05/20/oliver-janzer-and-benny-sudakov-settled-the-erdos-sauer-problem/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img alt="Norbert-Sauer" class="alignnone  wp-image-22703" height="243" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2022/05/norbert-sauer.jpg" width="162"/></p>
<p><a href="https://contacts.ucalgary.ca/info/math/profiles/101-152966">Norbert Sauer</a></p>
<p>The news in brief:  In the new paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12455">Resolution of the Erdős-Sauer problem on regular subgraphs</a> Oliver Janzer and Benny Sudakov proved <span class="abstract-full has-text-grey-dark mathjax" id="2204.12455v1-abstract-full"> that any graph G with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> vertices and more than <img alt="C_kn \log \log n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_kn+%5Clog+%5Clog+n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges contains a <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-12-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-52"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-53"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-54">k</span></span></span></span>-regular subgraph. This bound matches the lower bound of Pyber, Rödl and Szemerédi and thus completely resolved the well-known problem of Erdős and Sauer from 1975. The new bound </span><span class="abstract-full has-text-grey-dark mathjax" id="2204.12455v1-abstract-full">substantially improves an 1985 result of Pyber, who showed that <img alt="n \log n " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n+%5Clog+n+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-13-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-55"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-56"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-62"> edges</span></span></span></span> suffice.</span></p>
<h3>The history of the <span class="abstract-full has-text-grey-dark mathjax" id="2204.12455v1-abstract-full">Erdős -Sauer</span> problem 1975-2022</h3>
<p>Erdos and Sauer asked in 1975 how many edges (let’s denote the minimum number <img alt="f_k(n)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f_k%28n%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>) for an <em>n</em>-vertex graph guarantee a <em>k</em>-regular subgraph. In 1985 Laszlo Pyber proved that for some <img alt="C_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> every graph with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges and <img alt="C_kn \log n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_kn+%5Clog+n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges contains a <em>k</em>-regular graph. A few years later Pyber, Rodl and Szemeredi found a construction of a graph with<em> n</em> vertices and  <img alt="c n \log \log n " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=c+n+%5Clog+%5Clog+n+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges that contains no k-regular subgraph for every <img alt="k \ge 3" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k+%5Cge+3&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. (The paper appeared in 1995 but the result is from the late 80s.)</p>
<p>Paul <span class="abstract-full has-text-grey-dark mathjax" id="2204.12455v1-abstract-full">Erdős  mentioned the problem among his favorites in a famous paper in 1980 (Vol 1. Issue 1. of Combinatorica) and mentioned the results of Pyber and of Pyber, Rodl and Szemeredi in his 1989 paper.</span></p>
<p>Oliver and Benny proved an upper bound on the number of edges of k-regular free graphs that matches the Pyber, Rodl and Szemeredi lower bound. <span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>Congratulations!</strong></span></p>
<h3>AFK84 and the Berge-Sauer problem</h3>
<p><strong>Theorem: </strong>Every graph (or hypergraph) <em>G</em> with <em>n</em> vertices and <em>2n+1</em> edges contains a nontrivial subgraph <em>H</em> with all vertex-degrees divisible by 3.</p>
<p>This is a theorem of Noga Alon,  Shmuel Friedland, and me (AFK) from 1984.)</p>
<p><strong>Before the proof</strong>: If we want to get a subgraph with all vertex degrees even then we need<em> n</em> edges (or <em>n+1</em> edges for hypergraphs). This has a simple linear algebra proof which also gives an efficient algorithm.</p>
<p><strong>From-scratch proof scatch: </strong>Associate to every edge <em>e</em> of the graph a variable <img alt="x_e" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_e&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. Consider the two polynomial</p>
<p><em>P=</em> <img alt="\prod_{v \in V(G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cprod_%7Bv+%5Cin+V%28G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> <img alt="((\sum_{e: v \in e}x^2_e)^2-1)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28%28%5Csum_%7Be%3A+v+%5Cin+e%7Dx%5E2_e%29%5E2-1%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, and</p>
<p>Q=<img alt="\prod_{e\in E(G)}(x_e^2-1)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cprod_%7Be%5Cin+E%28G%29%7D%28x_e%5E2-1%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>If the theorem is false then <em>P-Q=0, </em>as polynomials over the field with three elements. This is impossible since P is a polynomial of degree <em>4n</em> while Q is a polynomial which has a monomial of degree <em>4n+2</em> with nonzero coefficient.</p>
<p>The theorem follows more directly from a theorem of Chevallay and even more directly from a theorem of Olson.</p>
<p>AFK84 was a necessary ingredients of Pyber 1985 upper bound as well as the Janzer-Sudakov new upper bound. It will be very nice to get rid of this ingredient. AFK84 came a little short of proving the Berge-Sauer conjecture that every 4-regular graph contains a 3-regular subgraph.  This conjecture was proved in a 1982 paper by Taskinov.</p>
<h3>Three problems</h3>
<p>A) Is it true that every graph with n vertices and 2n+1 edges with maximum degree 5 contains a 3-regular graph of type I? (Namely a 3-regular 3-edge colorable subgraph.)</p>
<p>B) How many edges for a 3-uniform hypergraph on n vertices guarantees a k-regular sub-hypergraph? (Here we refer to “3-regular hypergraph as a hypergraph so that every vertex belongs to three (or zero) edges. You can also demand that every pair of vertices belongs to three or zero edges.)</p>
<p>C) Is there a polynomial-time algorithm to find a<em> r</em>-regular subgraph for a graph with n vertices and <img alt="n^{1.01}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B1.01%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges.</p>
<h3>Climbing the Turan ladder</h3>
<p>Climbing the Turan ladder refers to unavoidable subgraphs of a graph of n vertices and m edges as m grows. (The Erdos-Renyi ladder is a similar notion for random graphs.)</p>
<p>Problem A) is related to the following:</p>
<p>When <img alt="m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is roughly <img alt="2n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p><strong>a)</strong> (for <img alt="m=2n-2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m%3D2n-2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>) you must have a subgraph with all degrees larger than 2</p>
<p><strong>b)</strong> (for <img alt="m= 2n+1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m%3D+2n%2B1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>) you must have a subgraph with all degrees divisible by 3 (AFK84), and</p>
<p><strong>c)</strong> (for <img alt="m=2n+1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m%3D2n%2B1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>) you also must have a subgraph <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> such that you can color its edges with three colors so that every (non-isolated) vertex have neighbors of the all color.</p>
<p>We don’t know what <img alt="m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> guarantees</p>
<p><strong>d)</strong> such an <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> so that for every vertex the number of edges of each color is the same modulo three.</p>
<p>Condition<strong> d)</strong> is stronger than both <strong>b)</strong> and <strong>c)</strong> and each of them is stronger than<strong> a)</strong>. Both<strong> a), b)</strong> and <strong>c)</strong> extend to hypergraphs.</p>
<h3>The relevance of Christos’s classes and the PME-conjecture.</h3>
<p>The <strong>Probabilistic Method is Efficient (PME)</strong> <strong>Conjecture</strong> asserts: Every mathematical proof based on the probabilistic method can be transformed into an efficient (randomized) algorithm.</p>
<p>This is a vague and controversial conjecture that I mentioned in the post <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2013/08/08/poznan-random-structures-and-algorithms-2013/" rel="bookmark">Poznań: Random Structures and Algorithms 2013</a>. (There I  referred to it as the Kalai-Spencer conjecture.) Now, if we can get rid of AFK84 and find a purely combinatorial/probabilistic  proof even just for the fact that every graph with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> vertices and <img alt="n^{1.01}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B1.01%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> edges contains a 3-regular subgraph, this would be nice on its own and may lead (especially for PME-believers) to an efficient algorithm. AFK84 is not supported by an efficient algorithm and, in fact it is related to one of Christos Papadimitriou’s classes describing the algorithmic difficulty for finding objects guarantees by mathematical proofs. See Papadimitriou’s  1994 paper: <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022000005800637" id="OT-8y8wGxeEJ"><span dir="ltr">On the complexity of the parity argument and other inefficient proofs of existence</span>‏.</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-20T13:00:53Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-20T13:00:53Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Benny Sudakov"/>
    <category term="Oliver Janzer"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/074</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/074" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-074 |  On Randomized Reductions to the Random Strings | 

	Michael Saks, 

	Rahul Santhanam</title>
    <summary>We study the power of randomized polynomial-time non-adaptive reductions to the problem of approximating Kolmogorov complexity and its polynomial-time bounded variants.

As our first main result, we give a sharp dichotomy for randomized non-adaptive reducibility to approximating Kolmogorov complexity. We show that any computable language $L$ that has a randomized polynomial-time non-adaptive reduction (satisfying a natural honesty condition) to $\omega(\log(n))$-approximating the Kolmogorov complexity is in AM $\cap$ coAM. On the other hand, using results of Hirahara [H20], it follows that every language in NEXP has a randomized polynomial-time non-adaptive reduction (satisfying the same honesty condition as before) to $O(\log(n))$-approximating the Kolmogorov complexity.

As our second main result, we give the first negative evidence against the NP-hardness of polynomial-time bounded Kolmogorov complexity with respect to randomized reductions. We show that for every polynomial t', there is a polynomial t such that if there is a randomized time t' non-adaptive reduction (satisfying a natural honesty condition) from SAT to $\omega(\log(n))$-approximating $K^t$ complexity, then either NE = coNE or E has sub-exponential size non-deterministic circuits infinitely often.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-20T10:27:57Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-20T10:27:57Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/073</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/073" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-073 |  Unbalanced Expanders from Multiplicity Codes | 

	Itay Kalev, 

	Amnon Ta-Shma</title>
    <summary>In 2007 Guruswami, Umans and Vadhan gave an explicit construction of a lossless condenser based on Parvaresh-Vardy codes. This lossless condenser is a basic building block in many constructions, and, in particular, is behind the state of the art extractor constructions.

We give an alternative construction that is based on Multiplicity codes. While the bottom-line result is similar to the GUV result, the analysis is very different. In GUV (and Parvaresh-Vardy codes) the polynomial ring is closed to a finite field, and every polynomial is associated with related elements in the finite field. In our construction a polynomial from the polynomial ring is associated with its iterated derivatives. Our analysis boils down to solving a differential equation over a finite field, and uses previous techniques, introduced by Kopparty for the list-decoding setting.
We also observe that these (and more general) questions were studied in differential algebra, and we use the terminology and result developed there.

We believe these techniques have the potential of getting better constructions and solving the current bottlenecks in the area.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-18T16:14:05Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-18T16:14:05Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=990</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2022/05/18/qa/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Q&amp;A</title>
    <summary>What led you to academia? Much to the shock of my fellow students, I have wanted to be a professor since my freshman year in Italy. The pursuit of knowledge and the lifestyle freedom really appealed to me. Naturally, I did not have a clue; but I would do it all over again, changing nothing… […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ol><li>What led you to academia?</li></ol>



<p>Much to the shock of my fellow students, I have wanted to be a professor since my freshman year in Italy. The pursuit of knowledge and the lifestyle freedom really appealed to me. Naturally, I did not have a clue; but I would do it all over again, changing nothing… alright, almost nothing.</p>



<ol start="2"><li>How did you become interested in theoretical computer science?</li></ol>



<p>I was totally hooked to computers since I was eight, and also worked on videogames in my early teens. In high school I didn’t mind math, but it was not my passion: It was mostly calculus which I thought was “only good for physics.” In college I had a first glimpse of theoretical computer science, and I was struck. The field was asking the right questions: What is a proof, what is knowledge, what is randomness, <em>when you are short on time?</em></p>



<ol start="3"><li>What are you currently working on?</li></ol>



<p>The most famous open problem in the field is the P vs. NP problem which can be phrased as asking to prove that <em>Super Mario</em> levels, properly constructed, are hard to beat. The general challenge is to exhibit problems that require a lot of time on computers. Much of my research concerns proving such limitations for restricted models of computers, for example computers with no memory. Even understanding such restricted models has proved enormously difficult, and a good reason for that is that they are extremely powerful, much more so than anyone anticipated.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-18T13:00:50Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-18T13:00:50Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="SpeakMemory"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1673</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2022/05/new-property-testing-book-by-arnab-bhattacharyya-and-yuichi-yoshida/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>New Property Testing book, by Arnab Bhattacharyya and Yuichi Yoshida</title>
    <summary>More great news: a new textbook on property testing, 📘 Property Testing: Problems and Techniques, by two experts in the field, Arnab Bhattacharyya and Yuichi Yoshida, is now available! As the overview below outlines (from the book’s website), the book covers a wide range of topics, and should give anyone interested a great overview of […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><strong>More great news:</strong> a new textbook on property testing, <img alt="&#x1F4D8;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f4d8.png" style="height: 1em;"/> <em><a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-981-16-8622-1">Property Testing: Problems and Techniques</a></em>, by two experts in the field,  <a href="https://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/~arnab/">Arnab Bhattacharyya</a> and <a href="http://research.nii.ac.jp/~yyoshida/">Yuichi Yoshida</a>, is now available!</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-full"><a href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/book.jpg"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1674" height="406" src="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/book.jpg" width="306"/></a><em>Property Testing: Problems and Techniques</em> (Springer, 2022)</figure></div>



<p>As the overview below outlines (from <a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-981-16-8622-1">the book’s website</a>), the book covers a wide range of topics, and should give anyone interested a great overview of scope, techniques, and results in testing.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote has-text-align-left"><p>This book introduces important results and techniques in property testing, where the goal is to design algorithms that decide whether their input satisfies a predetermined property in sublinear time, or even in constant time – that is, time is independent of the input size.</p><p>This book consists of three parts. The first part provides an introduction to the foundations of property testing. The second part studies the testing of specific properties on strings, graphs, functions, and constraint satisfaction problems. Vectors and matrices over real numbers are also covered. The third part is more advanced and explains general conditions, including full characterizations, under which properties are constant-query testable.</p><p>The first and second parts of the book are intended for first-year graduate students in computer science. They should also be accessible to undergraduate students with the adequate background. The third part can be used by researchers or ambitious graduate students who want to gain a deeper theoretical understanding of property testing.</p><p/></blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-18T03:54:06Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-18T03:54:06Z</published>
    <category term="Announcement"/>
    <category term="Surveys and books"/>
    <author>
      <name>Clement Canonne</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T22:49:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?p=154</id>
    <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/2022/05/17/virtual-dimacs-workshop-on-entropy-and-optimization-on-may-18-19-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>(Virtual) DIMACS Workshop on Entropy and Optimization on May 18, 19, 2022</title>
    <summary>Mohit Singh and I are organizing a two-day virtual DIMACS Workshop on Entropy and Optimization that starts tomorrow — May 18, 19, 2022. We have a stellar lineup of speakers: Nima Anari (Stanford University), Alexander Barvinok (Michigan), Mark Braverman (Princeton), Sebastien Bubeck (Microsoft Research), Péter Csikvári (Alfred Renyi Institute of Mathematics), Zongchen Chen (MIT), Ronen […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p/>



<p>Mohit Singh and I are organizing a two-day virtual DIMACS Workshop on <strong>Entropy and Optimization</strong> that starts tomorrow — May 18, 19, 2022. </p>



<p>We have a stellar lineup of speakers:  </p>



<p><em>Nima Anari (Stanford University), Alexander Barvinok (Michigan), Mark Braverman (Princeton), Sebastien Bubeck (Microsoft Research), Péter Csikvári (Alfred Renyi Institute of Mathematics), Zongchen Chen (MIT), Ronen Eldan (Weizmann), Tali Kaufman (Bar-Ilan University), Jon Lee (Michigan), Shayan Oveis-Gharan (U Washington)</em></p>



<p>The goal of this workshop is to explore various connections between entropy, optimization, and sampling. Entropy-maximizing probability distributions have been recently used in interesting ways in applications such as algorithms for counting problems, algorithms for NP-hard optimization problems, and interior-point methods for convex programming</p>



<p>Attendance to the workshop is free but <strong>registration is required</strong>. To see the program of the workshop and register, visit <a href="http://dimacs.rutgers.edu/events/details?eID=318">here</a>.</p>



<p>Looking forward to seeing many of you there!</p>



<p/>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-17T21:01:47Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-17T21:01:47Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>nisheethvishnoi</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Algorithms, Nature, and Society</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:38:14Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=20024</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/16/take-wing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Take Wing</title>
    <summary>It is a capital mistake to theorize before one has data—Sherlock Holmes Jeannette Wing is a Professor of Computer Science at Columbia University. She was recently appointed Executive VP for Research across all of Columbia’s campuses. She is also an adjunct Professor at Carnegie Mellon University. She stays busy. See this for her CV. Sixteen […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><i>It is a capital mistake to theorize before one has data—Sherlock Holmes</i></p>
<p>
Jeannette Wing is a Professor of Computer Science at Columbia University. She was recently <a href="https://president.columbia.edu/news/jeannette-wing-appointed-executive-vice-president-research">appointed</a> Executive VP for Research across all of Columbia’s campuses. She is also an adjunct Professor at Carnegie Mellon University. She stays busy. See <a href="https://www.cs.columbia.edu/~wing/">this</a> for her CV. </p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/05/16/take-wing/jw/" rel="attachment wp-att-20028"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-20028" height="225" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/jw.png?resize=225%2C225&amp;ssl=1" width="225"/></a></p>
<p>
Sixteen years ago she wrote a short <a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/afs/cs/usr/wing/www/publications/Wing06.pdf">position</a> paper for <em>Communications of the ACM</em> titled “Computational Thinking.” It begins:</p>
<p>
<em><br/>
 Computational thinking builds on the power and limits of computing processes, whether they are executed by a human or by a machine.<br/>
</em></p>
<p>
This is the first of sixteen sentences of the form “Computational thinking [verb]…,” plus one that follows a semicolon. The thirteenth prefaces six bulleted paragraphs giving characteristics of computational thinking. They fill page 3 of 3—the paper is shorter to read than this post. </p>
<p>
Her 2007 <a href="https://www.cs.cmu.edu/afs/cs/usr/wing/www/Computational_Thinking.pdf">talk</a> on “Computational Thinking” has oodles of things that aren’t in the paper: <em>pictures</em>. It also concludes by posing five questions that she put into another famous CACM paper.</p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Five Questions </b></p>
<p/><p>
This second <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2008/1/5481-five-deep-questions-in-computing/fulltext">paper</a> appeared in 2008 with the title “Five Deep Questions in Computing.” They are: </p>
<ol>
<li> P = NP?
</li><li> What is computable?
</li><li> What is intelligence?
</li><li> What is information?
</li><li> (How) can we build complex systems simply?
</li></ol>
<p>
The first is one of the basic questions of theory, of course. </p>
<p>
The next is about what are computations? This question complicates when one includes: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA_computing">DNA</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_computing">quantum</a> computers? Also what about man-machine joint computations? Given that humans and machines have different computing capability, now ask: What is computable? Pretty complex.</p>
<p>
Let’s skip what is intelligence for now.</p>
<p>
What is information? This is a perfect question: Information is not just <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>‘s and <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>‘s. DNA encodes information in a different way and with quantum computing, it’s not bits but qubits. Amazing. </p>
<p>
Finally we will also skip the last question. </p>
<p>
She ends with:<br/>
<em><br/>
I pose these questions to stimulate deep thinking and further discussion. What deep questions about computing would you want answered? In 50 years, how different will they and their answers be from what we ask and are able to answer today?<br/>
</em></p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Data Science </b></p>
<p/><p>
Wing is a leading expert of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_science">data science</a>. This field is traceable back to 1962 when <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Tukey">John Tukey</a> described an area he called “data analysis”. That is Tukey of Fast Fourier transform fame, who I knew when I was at Princeton. </p>
<p>
Data science combines the scientific method, math and statistics, specialized programming, advanced analytics, AI, and even storytelling to uncover and explain the business insights buried in data.</p>
<p>
Her current research interests are in trustworthy AI. Her areas of research expertise include security and privacy, formal methods, programming languages, and distributed and concurrent systems. She is widely recognized for her intellectual leadership in computer science, and more recently in data science. Wing’s seminal essay, titled “Computational Thinking,” was published more than a fifteen years ago and is credited with helping to establish the centrality of computer science to problem-solving in all other disciplines.</p>
<p>
Data can be precious for one of three reasons: the data set is expensive to collect; the data set contains a rare event (low signal-to-noise ratio); or the data set is artisanal—small, task-specific, and/or targets a limited audience. </p>
<ul>
<li> A good example of expensive data comes from large, one-off, expensive scientific instruments, for example, the Large Synoptic Survey Telescope, the Large Hadron Collider, and the IceCube Neutrino Detector at the South Pole.
</li><li> A good example of rare event data is data from sensors on physical infrastructure, such as bridges and tunnels; sensors produce a lot of raw data, but the disastrous event they are used to predict is (thankfully) rare. Rare data can also be expensive to collect.
</li><li> A good example of artisanal data is the tens of millions of court judgments that China has released online to the public since 2014.
</li></ul>
<p>
</p><p><b> Open Problems </b></p>
<p/><p>
Let’s take a cue from Wing: What other major aspects and objectives of computer science shall we put into crisp bullet points?</p>
<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-16T12:32:23Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-16T12:32:23Z</published>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6897620455238922302</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6897620455238922302/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/05/is-kamala-harris-our-first-female-prez.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6897620455238922302" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6897620455238922302" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/05/is-kamala-harris-our-first-female-prez.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Is Kamala Harris our first female PREZ? No. Do I have a theorem named after me. No. But in both cases...</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>On Nov 19, 2021 Joe Biden got a colonoscopy and hence the 25th amendment was used to make Kamala Harris the president temporarily (this source: <a href="https://nypost.com/2021/11/19/biden-returns-to-white-house-after-physical-colonoscopy/">here</a> says 85 minutes, though I thought I heard a few hours from other sources). </p><p>Does this make Kamala Harris our first female president?</p><p>I would say NO and I suspect you agree. A friend of mine suggested the phrasing <i>Kamala Harris is the</i> <i>first women to assume the powers of the president under the 25th amendment.  </i>True.  I don't think it means much. She tacked on the <i>under the 25th amendment </i>since Edith Wilson was essentially president when Woodrow Wilson had a stroke (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edith_Wilson#Increased_role_after_husband's_stroke">here</a>).</p><p><br/></p><p>A student asked me <i>Is there a theorem that is referred to as Gasarch's Theorem or something like that?</i></p><p>I will answer YES and NO, but really the answer is NO.</p><p>YES: In 1999 Gasarch and Kruskal had a paper in Mathematics Magazine: </p><p><a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/papers/dice.pdf">When can one load of Dice so that the sum is uniformly distributed</a>?<br/></p><p>In that paper we have a theorem that gives an exact condition on</p><p>(n_1,...,n_k) for when there is a loaded n_1-sided dice, n_2-sided dice,...,n_k-sided dice so that </p><p>the sums are all equally likely.</p><p>In 2018 Ian Morrison published a paper in the American Math Monthly:</p><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1411.2272">Sacks of dice with fair totals</a><br/></p><p>which used our work and referred to our main theorem as <b>The Gasarch-Kruskal Theorem.</b></p><p>Hence there is a theorem with my name on it!</p><p>NO: The Gasarch-Kruskal paper has only 8 citations (according to Google Scholar). This is more than I would have thought, but its not a lot. The fact that ONE person calls the main theorem THE GASARCH-KRUSKAL THEOREM hardly makes it a named theorem. </p><p>QUESTION: So what criteria can one use?</p><p>We could say that X has a theorem with their name on it if there is a Wikipedia entry about the theorem, using that name. That works to a point, but might fun afoul of Goodhart's law (if a measure becomes a target it stops being a measure) in that, for example, I could write a Wikipedia entry on The Gasarch-Kruskal Theorem. </p><p>We could say that 10 people need to refer to the theorem by the name of its authors. Why 10? Any number seems arbitrary. </p><p>CAVEAT: If someone asked Clyde Kruskal <i>is there a theorem that bears your name</i> that is trickier, since <i>The Kruskal Tree Theorem</i> bears his name.... but its not his theorem. Reminds me of the (fictional) scenario where a Alice steals  a Field's medal and tells Bob<i> I have a Field's Medal! </i>and Bob  thinks Alice is a world-class mathematician since she has a fields medal, rather than thinking Alice is a world class thief. See <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2018/08/how-valuable-is-fields-medal.html">here</a> for my post on that. </p><p>(I originally had Kruskal Three Theorem instead of Tree Theorem. I have corrected this but I hope it inspires Clyde to prove a theorem about the number Three so he can have a named theorem. And if he is lucky, over time, people will confuse it with the Kruskal Tree Theorem!) </p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><i><br/></i></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-16T04:41:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-16T04:41:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-05-26T22:23:48Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/072</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/072" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-072 |  Probabilistic Kolmogorov Complexity with Applications to Average-Case Complexity | 

	Zhenjian Lu, 

	Halley Goldberg, 

	Valentine Kabanets, 

	Igor Oliveira</title>
    <summary>Understanding the relationship between the worst-case and average-case complexities of $\mathrm{NP}$ and of other subclasses of $\mathrm{PH}$ is a long-standing problem in complexity theory. Over the last few years, much progress has been achieved in this front through the investigation of meta-complexity: the complexity of problems that refer to the complexity of the input string $x$ (e.g., given a string $x$, estimate its time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity). In particular, [Hir21] employed techniques from meta-complexity to show that if $\mathrm{DistNP} \subseteq \mathrm{AvgP}$ then $\mathrm{UP} \subseteq \mathrm{DTIME}[2^{O(n/\log n)}]$. While this and related results [HN21, CHV22] offer exciting progress after a long gap, they do not survive in the setting of ramdonmized computations: roughly speaking, "randomness" is the opposite of "structure", and upper bounding the amount of structure (time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity) of different objects is crucial in recent applications of meta-complexity. This limitation is significant, since randomized computations are ubiquitous in algorithm design and give rise to a more robust theory of average-case complexity [IL90].

In this work, we develop a probabilistic theory of meta-complexity, by incorporating randomness into the notion of complexity of a string $x$. This is achieved through a new probabilistic variant of time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity that we call $\mathrm{pK}^t$ complexity. Informally, $\mathrm{pK}^t(x)$ measures the complexity of $x$ when shared randomness is available to all parties involved in a computation. By porting key results from meta-complexity to the probabilistic domain of $\mathrm{pK}^t$ complexity and its variants, we are able to establish new connections between worst-case and average-case complexity in the important setting of probabilistic computations:

-  If $\mathrm{DistNP} \subseteq \mathrm{AvgBPP}$, then $\mathrm{UP}\subseteq\mathrm{RTIME}\!\left[2^{O(n/\log n)}\right]$. 

-  If $\mathrm{Dist\Sigma}^{\mathrm{P}}_{2} \subseteq \mathrm{AvgBPP}$, then $\mathrm{AM} \subseteq \mathrm{BPTIME}\!\left[2^{O(n/\log n)}\right]$. 

- In the fine-grained setting [CHV22], we get $\mathrm{UTIME}[2^{O(\sqrt{n\log n})}]\subseteq \mathrm{RTIME}[2^{O(\sqrt{n\log n})}]$ and $\mathrm{AMTIME}[2^{O(\sqrt{n\log n})}] \subseteq \mathrm{BPTIME}[2^{O(\sqrt{n\log n})}]$ from stronger average-case assumptions. 

- If $\mathrm{DistPH}\subseteq\mathrm{AvgBPP}$, then $\mathrm{PH}\subseteq\mathrm{BPTIME}\!\left[2^{O(n/\log n)}\right]$. Specifically, for any $\ell \geq 0$, if $\mathrm{Dist\Sigma}_{\ell+2}^{\mathrm{P}}\subseteq\mathrm{AvgBPP}$ then $\mathrm{\Sigma}_{\ell}^{\mathrm{P}}\subseteq\mathrm{BPTIME}\!\left[2^{O(n/\log n)}\right]$.

- Strengthening a result from [HN21], we show that if $\mathrm{DistNP}\subseteq\mathrm{AvgBPP}$ then polynomial size Boolean circuits can be agnostically PAC learned under any unknown $\mathrm{P}/\mathrm{poly}$-samplable distribution in polynomial time.

In some cases, our framework allows us to significantly simplify existing proofs, or to extend results to the more challenging probabilistic setting with little to no extra effort.</summary>
    <updated>2022-05-16T01:12:32Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-16T01:12:32Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8332</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/15/information-theoretic-cryptography-22-guest-post-by-benny-applebaum/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Information Theoretic Cryptography 22: Guest post by Benny Applebaum</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear friends, The third information-theoretic cryptography conference (ITC) 2022 will be held in-person at MIT this year from July 5-7. We have an exciting program with 17 cool papers and 6 plenary talks by Yuval Ishai, Rafael Pass, David Zuckerman, Omri Ben-Eliezer, Dakshita Khurana and Yevgeniy Dodis on topics that span the breadth of information-theoretic cryptography (and … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/15/information-theoretic-cryptography-22-guest-post-by-benny-applebaum/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Information Theoretic Cryptography 22: Guest post by Benny Applebaum</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear friends,</p>



<p>The third information-theoretic cryptography conference (ITC) 2022 will be held in-person at MIT this year from July 5-7. We have an exciting program with 17 cool papers and 6 plenary talks by Yuval Ishai, Rafael Pass, David Zuckerman, Omri Ben-Eliezer, Dakshita Khurana and Yevgeniy Dodis on topics that span the breadth of information-theoretic cryptography (and beyond). </p>



<p>More information here: <a href="https://t.co/VhueMjajyf" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">itcrypto.github.io/2022/index.html</a></p>



<p>We hope to see many of you at the conference.</p>



<p>The organizers</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-15T17:05:29Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-15T17:05:29Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/05/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/05/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>A tutorial on how to use Inkscape to make nice mathematical diagrams quickly enough for real-time note-taking in mathematical lectures (\(\mathbb{M}\), via). It’s from 2019, so doesn’t take advantage of newer features of Inkscape released since then. I use Illustrator, but without a site license it’s expensive; the other free program many of our students use is Ipe, more oriented to PDF than SVG but with good TeX integration.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://castel.dev/post/lecture-notes-2/">A tutorial on how to use Inkscape to make nice mathematical diagrams quickly enough for real-time note-taking in mathematical lectures</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108228874974700230">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=31227940">via</a>). It’s from 2019, so doesn’t take advantage of newer features of Inkscape released since then. I use Illustrator, but without a site license it’s expensive; the other free program many of our students use is <a href="https://ipe.otfried.org/">Ipe</a>, more oriented to PDF than SVG but with good TeX integration.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cop-win_graph">Cop-win graph</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108235112878367692">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> now a Wikipedia Good Article. It was the last of my current nominations, so it may be a while until the next. These are graphs on which a cop can catch a robber in a game where they alternate moving on edges or staying put, <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2016/08/18/game-of-cop.html">as I discussed in an earlier post</a>. The GA reviewer made me take out as unsourced a statement that a recognition algorithm of <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016%2FS0166-218X%2803%2900295-6">Spinrad 2004</a> uses time \(O(mn/\log n)\), faster than the bound of \(O(n^3/\log n)\) from Spinrad’s paper. But I still think it’s true.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://chaoxuprime.com/posts/2019-01-12-lights-out-game.html">Lights out game on a grid</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@chao/108228363268882685">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> This is the puzzle where you have to turn out all of a given set of lights on a grid graph using switches that flip the state of any grid cell and all of its neighbors. It’s just solving sparse systems of linear equations over \(\mathbb{F}_2\), but Gaussian elimination is slow and the usual form of nested dissection requires full-rank matrices. Instead Chao Xu describes an \(O(n^3)\)-time algorithm.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/publiccommentsonthecmf/">Stanford mathematics professor Brian Conrad takes a deeper look at the proposed revisions to the California Math Framework for high school mathematics</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108247956356449281">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/05/02/brian-conrad-takes-down-the-cmf/">via</a>), finding an “abundance of false or misleading citations”, “misrepresentations of facts and evidence”, “guidance lacking  details essential for implementation or seeming to be opinions rather than evidence-based”, and “bias toward data science … based on misinformation and hype”.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://twistypuzzles.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=37692">A twisty mechanical puzzle with exponential solution length</a> inspires <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@henryseg/108194775453014602">Henry Segerman to ask: are superexponential puzzles possible?</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Progress in polyhedral combinatorics <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108259553485852087">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/04/29/joshua-hinman-proved-baranys-conjecture-on-face-numbers-of-polytopes-and-lei-xue-proved-a-lower-bound-conjecture-by-grunbaum/">via</a>): <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02568">convex polytopes cannot have fewer intermediate-dimensional faces than the smaller of their numbers of facets or vertices</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/202205/noti2468/noti2468.html">Steven Clontz reviews <em>Games for Your Mind</em></a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@StevenXClontz/108261574819754988">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> by Jason Rosenhouse, in <em>Notices of the AMS</em>. It’s about logic puzzles in the style of Lewis Carroll and Raymond Smullyan, but the review has a broader focus on puzzles and metapuzzles more generally.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://amandaghassaei.com/projects/digital_marbling/">Digital marbling</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108270841049246147">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span>  A recent physics-based simulation project for paper marbling, by Amanda Ghassaei, who was also responsible for an <a href="https://origamisimulator.org/">origami simulator</a> that I <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2018/02/28/linkage.html">linked with a different url</a> a few years ago.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://eiko-fried.com/welcome-to-hotel-elsevier-you-can-check-out-any-time-you-like-not/">The information Elsevier tracks and resells about the scientists who access its journals</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108278540265067636">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=31326672">via</a>). An EU GDPR personal information request reveals not just dates and times from journal paper reading, writing, and reviewing data but also user names, phone numbers, and bank account information, whether you read the emails from them, and a huge list of the spam newsletters that they subscribe you to.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2022/05/10/partially-specified-mathematical-objects-ambient-parameters-and-asymptotic-notation/">Terry Tao tries to make mathematical sense of notations like \(\pm\) or \(O(\dots)\)</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108280853102871738">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>)</span>  that specify something partially rather than exactly. It’s a long post, but I think much less technical than most of Tao’s posts.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2022/05/11/how-scholarly-meeting-became-superspreader-event">Pandemic at the conference</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108284204495257458">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span> ACM CHI, the annual conference in computer–human interaction, was held in a hybrid format with 1900 physical attendees in New Orleans a week ago. It became a coronavirus superspreader event, despite its vaccine and mask mandates.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://retractionwatch.com/2022/05/12/a-college-that-doesnt-exist-an-email-address-that-goes-dark-who-wrote-this-paper/">The mystery of who wrote a mathematics paper in a special issue, heavily based on the work of the highly-cited special issue editor</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108289912652816183">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> It’s by someone who doesn’t seem to exist at a college that doesn’t exist. But the special issue editor can show emails from the author, so that’s something. Searching MathSciNet for similarly-titled works produces confidence-inspiring journals like <em>Chaos, Solitons, and Fractals</em> and <em>Fuzzy Sets and Systems</em>, but this one isn’t indexed.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://may12.womeninmaths.org/">May 12th was chosen as a day to globally celebrate women in mathematics</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@JordiGH/108289993565001699">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span>  It was the birthday of Maryam Mirzakhani (1977–2017), the first and so far only woman to win the Fields Medal. The link lists celebration events continuing for a month or so.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://medium.com/swlh/polyomino-loops-fc8f6fc92c2f">Polyomino loops</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/108304649157797618">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> Matthew Yuan wonders, if you play billiards in a polyomino and try shooting a ball diagonally from the midpoint of each of the polyomino edges, how to count the number of loops that these billiard paths will link up into. It’s somewhat related to the African lusona drawings that I <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/08/02/sona-enumeration.html">discussed in an earlier post</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://jeremykun.com/2022/05/14/practical-math-preview-collect-sensitive-survey-responses-privately/">Collecting sensitive survey responses privately</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@j2kun/108301309174075160">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> This excerpt by Jeremy Kun from his book-in-progress on practical programming techniques is about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randomized_response">randomized response</a>, a method for collecting accurate information from survey respondents on whether they may have participated in an illegal activity (like, say, abortion in the US in the 1960s) without revealing the identities of the participants to the data collectors. Similar ideas of preventing inferences about individuals in data sets also led to the development of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Differential_privacy">differential privacy</a>.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-15T16:11:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-15T16:11:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2022-05-22T00:02:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4630</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2022/05/14/the-first-xl-computer-scientist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The First XL Computer Scientist</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some time ago, I received a message to the effect that I was being considered for membership in the “Academy of the XL”, to which my reaction was, hey, we have all gone out of shape during the pandemic, and … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2022/05/14/the-first-xl-computer-scientist/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Some time ago, I received a message to the effect that I was being considered for membership in the “Academy of the XL”, to which my reaction was, hey, we have all gone out of shape during the pandemic, and body-shaming is never… then it was explained to me that, in this context, “XL” means “forty” and that the Academy of the Forty is Italy’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accademia_nazionale_delle_scienze">National Academy of Science</a>.</p>
<p>Italy has a wonderfully named, and well-known within the country, National Academy of Arts and Science, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accademia_dei_Lincei">Accademia dei Lincei</a>, which means something like academy of the “eagle-eyed” (literally, lynx-eyed), that is, people that can see far. The Accademia dei XL is much less well known, although it has a distinguished 240-year history, during which people like Guglielmo Marconi and Enrico Fermi were members. More recently, the much beloved Rita Levi-Montalcini, Holocaust survivor, Nobel Laureate, and Senator-for-life, was a member. Current members include Nobel Laureates Carlo Rubbia and Giorgio Parisi. Noted algebraist Corrado De Concini is the current president.</p>
<p>Be that as it may, the academicians did vote to make me a member, their first computer scientist ever. Next week, at the inauguration of their 240th academic year, I will speak to the other members about randomness and pseudorandomness in computation.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-05-14T15:07:57Z</updated>
    <published>2022-05-14T15:07:57Z</published>
    <category term="Italy"/>
    <category term="theory"/>
    <category term="Pseudorandomness"/>
    <category term="things that are excellent"/>
    <category term="XL"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2022-05-27T06:37:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
