<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-07-20T07:23:21Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09116</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09116" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Combinatorial Santa Claus Problem or: How to Find Good Matchings in Non-Uniform Hypergraphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Etienne Bamas, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Garg:Paritosh.html">Paritosh Garg</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rohwedder:Lars.html">Lars Rohwedder</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.09116">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider hypergraphs on vertices $P\cup R$ where each hyperedge contains
exactly one vertex in $P$. Our goal is to select a matching that covers all of
$P$, but we allow each selected hyperedge to drop all but an
$(1/\alpha)$-fraction of its intersection with $R$ (thus relaxing the matching
constraint). Here $\alpha$ is to be minimized. We dub this problem the
Combinatorial Santa Claus problem, since we show in this paper that this
problem and the Santa Claus problem are almost equivalent in terms of their
approximability.
</p>
<p>The non-trivial observation that any uniform regular hypergraph admits a
relaxed matching for $\alpha = O(1)$ was a major step in obtaining a constant
approximation rate for a special case of the Santa Claus problem, which
received great attention in literature. It is natural to ask if the uniformity
condition can be omitted. Our main result is that every (non-uniform) regular
hypergraph admits a relaxed matching for $\alpha = O(\log\log(|R|))$, when all
hyperedges are sufficiently large (a condition that is necessary). In
particular, this implies an $O(\log\log(|R|))$-approximation algorithm for the
Combinatorial Santa Claus problem with large hyperedges.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09099</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09099" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A dichotomy theorem for nonuniform CSPs simplified</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bulatov:Andrei_A=.html">Andrei A. Bulatov</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.09099">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In a non-uniform Constraint Satisfaction problem CSP(G), where G is a set of
relations on a finite set A, the goal is to find an assignment of values to
variables subject to constraints imposed on specified sets of variables using
the relations from G. The Dichotomy Conjecture for the non-uniform CSP states
that for every constraint language G the problem CSP(G) is either solvable in
polynomial time or is NP-complete. It was proposed by Feder and Vardi in their
seminal 1993 paper. In this paper we confirm the Dichotomy Conjecture.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09075</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09075" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Efficient Linear and Affine Codes for Correcting Insertions/Deletions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cheng:Kuan.html">Kuan Cheng</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Guruswami:Venkatesan.html">Venkatesan Guruswami</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Haeupler:Bernhard.html">Bernhard Haeupler</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Xin.html">Xin Li</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.09075">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper studies \emph{linear} and \emph{affine} error-correcting codes for
correcting synchronization errors such as insertions and deletions. We call
such codes linear/affine insdel codes.
</p>
<p>Linear codes that can correct even a single deletion are limited to have
information rate at most $1/2$ (achieved by the trivial 2-fold repetition
code). Previously, it was (erroneously) reported that more generally no
non-trivial linear codes correcting $k$ deletions exist, i.e., that the
$(k+1)$-fold repetition codes and its rate of $1/(k+1)$ are basically optimal
for any $k$. We disprove this and show the existence of binary linear codes of
length $n$ and rate just below $1/2$ capable of correcting $\Omega(n)$
insertions and deletions. This identifies rate $1/2$ as a sharp threshold for
recovery from deletions for linear codes, and reopens the quest for a better
understanding of the capabilities of linear codes for correcting
insertions/deletions.
</p>
<p>We prove novel outer bounds and existential inner bounds for the rate vs.
(edit) distance trade-off of linear insdel codes. We complement our existential
results with an efficient synchronization-string-based transformation that
converts any asymptotically-good linear code for Hamming errors into an
asymptotically-good linear code for insdel errors. Lastly, we show that the
$\frac{1}{2}$-rate limitation does not hold for affine codes by giving an
explicit affine code of rate $1-\epsilon$ which can efficiently correct a
constant fraction of insdel errors.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T01:29:40Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09065</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09065" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Improved Approximation Factor for Adaptive Influence Maximization via Simple Greedy Strategies</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Gianlorenzo D'Angelo, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Poddar:Debashmita.html">Debashmita Poddar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vinci:Cosimo.html">Cosimo Vinci</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.09065">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the adaptive influence maximization problem, we are given a social network
and a budget $k$, and we iteratively select $k$ nodes, called seeds, in order
to maximize the expected number of nodes that are reached by an influence
cascade that they generate according to a stochastic model for influence
diffusion. Differently from the non-adaptive influence maximization problem,
where all the seeds must be selected beforehand, here nodes are selected
sequentially one by one, and the decision on the $i$th seed is based on the
observed cascade produced by the first $i-1$ seeds. We focus on the myopic
feedback model, in which we can only observe which neighbors of previously
selected seeds have been influenced and on the independent cascade model, where
each edge is associated with an independent probability of diffusing influence.
Previous works showed that the adaptivity gap is at most $4$, which implies
that the non-adaptive greedy algorithm guarantees an approximation factor of
$\frac{1}{4}\left(1-\frac{1}{e}\right)$ for the adaptive problem. In this
paper, we improve the bounds on both the adaptivity gap and on the
approximation factor. We directly analyze the approximation factor of the
non-adaptive greedy algorithm, without passing through the adaptivity gap, and
show that it is at least $\frac{1}{2}\left(1-\frac{1}{e}\right)$. Therefore,
the adaptivity gap is at most $\frac{2e}{e-1}\approx 3.164$. To prove these
bounds, we introduce a new approach to relate the greedy non-adaptive algorithm
to the adaptive optimum. The new approach does not rely on multi-linear
extensions or random walks on optimal decision trees, which are commonly used
techniques in the field. We believe that it is of independent interest and may
be used to analyze other adaptive optimization problems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09045</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09045" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Integer factorization and Riemann's hypothesis: Why two-item joint replenishment is hard</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schulz:Andreas_S=.html">Andreas S. Schulz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Telha:Claudio.html">Claudio Telha</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.09045">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Distribution networks with periodically repeating events often hold great
promise to exploit economies of scale. Joint replenishment problems are a
fundamental model in inventory management, manufacturing, and logistics that
capture these effects. However, finding an efficient algorithm that optimally
solves these models, or showing that none may exist, has long been open,
regardless of whether empty joint orders are possible or not. In either case,
we show that finding optimal solutions to joint replenishment instances with
just two products is at least as difficult as integer factorization. To the
best of the authors' knowledge, this is the first time that integer
factorization is used to explain the computational hardness of any kind of
optimization problem. Under the assumption that Riemann's Hypothesis is
correct, we can actually prove that the two-item joint replenishment problem
with possibly empty joint ordering points is NP-complete under randomized
reductions, which implies that not even quantum computers may be able to solve
it efficiently. By relating the computational complexity of joint replenishment
to cryptography, prime decomposition, and other aspects of prime numbers, a
similar approach may help to establish (integer factorization) hardness of
additional open periodic problems in supply chain management and beyond, whose
solution has eluded standard methods.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T01:23:34Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09023</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09023" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Parameterized Complexity of Scheduling Chains of Jobs with Delays</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bodlaender:Hans_L=.html">Hans L. Bodlaender</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wegen:Marieke_van_der.html">Marieke van der Wegen</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.09023">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we consider the parameterized complexity of the following
scheduling problem. We must schedule a number of jobs on $m$ machines, where
each job has unit length, and the graph of precedence constraints consists of a
set of chains. Each precedence constraint is labelled with an integer that
denotes the exact (or minimum) delay between the jobs. We study different
cases; delays can be given in unary and in binary, and the case that we have a
single machine is discussed separately. We consider the complexity of this
problem parameterized by the number of chains, and by the thickness of the
instance, which is the maximum number of chains whose intervals between release
date and deadline overlap.
</p>
<p>We show that this scheduling problem with exact delays in unary is
$W[t]$-hard for all $t$, when parameterized by the thickness, even when we have
a single machine ($m = 1$). When parameterized by the number of chains, this
problem is $W[1]$-complete when we have a single or a constant number of
machines, and $W[2]$-complete when the number of machines is a variable. The
problem with minimum delays, given in unary, parameterized by the number of
chains (and as a simple corollary, also when parameterized by the thickness) is
$W[1]$-hard for a single or a constant number of machines, and $W[2]$-hard when
the number of machines is variable.
</p>
<p>With a dynamic programming algorithm, one can show membership in XP for exact
and minimum delays in unary, for any number of machines, when parameterized by
thickness or number of chains. For a single machine, with exact delays in
binary, parameterized by the number of chains, membership in XP can be shown
with branching and solving a system of difference constraints. For all other
cases for delays in binary, membership in XP is open.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T01:20:23Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09018</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.09018" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Solving hard cut problems via flow-augmentation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kim:Eun_Jung.html">Eun Jung Kim</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kratsch:Stefan.html">Stefan Kratsch</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pilipczuk:Marcin.html">Marcin Pilipczuk</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wahlstr=ouml=m:Magnus.html">Magnus Wahlström</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.09018">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a new technique for designing FPT algorithms for graph cut
problems in undirected graphs, which we call flow augmentation. Our technique
is applicable to problems that can be phrased as a search for an (edge)
$(s,t)$-cut of cardinality at most $k$ in an undirected graph $G$ with
designated terminals $s$ and $t$.
</p>
<p>More precisely, we consider problems where an (unknown) solution is a set $Z
\subseteq E(G)$ of size at most $k$ such that (1) in $G-Z$, $s$ and $t$ are in
distinct connected components, (2) every edge of $Z$ connects two distinct
connected components of $G-Z$, and (3) if we define the set $Z_{s,t} \subseteq
Z$ as these edges $e \in Z$ for which there exists an $(s,t)$-path $P_e$ with
$E(P_e) \cap Z = \{e\}$, then $Z_{s,t}$ separates $s$ from $t$. We prove that
in this scenario one can in randomized time $k^{O(1)} (|V(G)|+|E(G)|)$ add a
number of edges to the graph so that with $2^{-O(k \log k)}$ probability no
added edge connects two components of $G-Z$ and $Z_{s,t}$ becomes a minimum cut
between $s$ and $t$.
</p>
<p>We apply our method to obtain a randomized FPT algorithm for a notorious
"hard nut" graph cut problem we call Coupled Min-Cut. This problem emerges out
of the study of FPT algorithms for Min CSP problems, and was unamenable to
other techniques for parameterized algorithms in graph cut problems, such as
Randomized Contractions, Treewidth Reduction or Shadow Removal.
</p>
<p>To demonstrate the power of the approach, we consider more generally Min
SAT($\Gamma$), parameterized by the solution cost. We show that every problem
Min SAT($\Gamma$) is either (1) FPT, (2) W[1]-hard, or (3) able to express the
soft constraint $(u \to v)$, and thereby also the min-cut problem in directed
graphs. All the W[1]-hard cases were known or immediate, and the main new
result is an FPT algorithm for a generalization of Coupled Min-Cut.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08965</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08965" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Escaping a Polygon</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Abel:Zachary.html">Zachary Abel</a>, Hugo Akitaya, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Demaine:Erik_D=.html">Erik D. Demaine</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Demaine:Martin_L=.html">Martin L. Demaine</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hesterberg:Adam.html">Adam Hesterberg</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Ku:Jason_S=.html">Jason S. Ku</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lynch:Jayson.html">Jayson Lynch</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08965">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Suppose an "escaping" player moves continuously at maximum speed 1 in the
interior of a region, while a "pursuing" player moves continuously at maximum
speed $r$ outside the region. For what $r$ can the first player escape the
region, that is, reach the boundary a positive distance away from the pursuing
player, assuming optimal play by both players? We formalize a model for this
infinitesimally alternating 2-player game that we prove has a unique winner in
any region with locally rectifiable boundary, avoiding pathological behaviors
(where both players can have "winning strategies") previously identified for
pursuit-evasion games such as the Lion and Man problem in certain metric
spaces. For some regions, including both equilateral triangle and square, we
give exact results for the critical speed ratio, above which the pursuing
player can win and below which the escaping player can win (and at which the
pursuing player can win). For simple polygons, we give a simple formula and
polynomial-time algorithm that is guaranteed to give a 10.89898-approximation
to the critical speed ratio, and we give a pseudopolynomial-time approximation
scheme for arbitrarily approximating the critical speed ratio. On the negative
side, we prove NP-hardness of the problem for polyhedral domains in 3D, and
prove stronger results (PSPACE-hardness and NP-hardness even to approximate)
for generalizations to multiple escaping and pursuing players.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08914</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08914" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>All-Pairs LCA in DAGs: Breaking through the $O(n^{2.5})$ barrier</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grandoni:Fabrizio.html">Fabrizio Grandoni</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Italiano:Giuseppe_F=.html">Giuseppe F. Italiano</a>, Aleksander Łukasiewicz, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Parotsidis:Nikos.html">Nikos Parotsidis</a>, Przemysław Uznański <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08914">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Let $G=(V,E)$ be an $n$-vertex directed acyclic graph (DAG). A lowest common
ancestor (LCA) of two vertices $u$ and $v$ is a common ancestor $w$ of $u$ and
$v$ such that no descendant of $w$ has the same property. In this paper, we
consider the problem of computing an LCA, if any, for all pairs of vertices in
a DAG. The fastest known algorithms for this problem exploit fast matrix
multiplication subroutines and have running times ranging from $O(n^{2.687})$
[Bender et al.~SODA'01] down to $O(n^{2.615})$ [Kowaluk and Lingas~ICALP'05]
and $O(n^{2.569})$ [Czumaj et al.~TCS'07]. Somewhat surprisingly, all those
bounds would still be $\Omega(n^{2.5})$ even if matrix multiplication could be
solved optimally (i.e., $\omega=2$). This appears to be an inherent barrier for
all the currently known approaches, which raises the natural question on
whether one could break through the $O(n^{2.5})$ barrier for this problem.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we answer this question affirmatively: in particular, we
present an $\tilde O(n^{2.447})$ ($\tilde O(n^{7/3})$ for $\omega=2$) algorithm
for finding an LCA for all pairs of vertices in a DAG, which represents the
first improvement on the running times for this problem in the last 13 years. A
key tool in our approach is a fast algorithm to partition the vertex set of the
transitive closure of $G$ into a collection of $O(\ell)$ chains and $O(n/\ell)$
antichains, for a given parameter $\ell$. As usual, a chain is a path while an
antichain is an independent set. We then find, for all pairs of vertices, a
\emph{candidate} LCA among the chain and antichain vertices, separately. The
first set is obtained via a reduction to min-max matrix multiplication. The
computation of the second set can be reduced to Boolean matrix multiplication
similarly to previous results on this problem. We finally combine the two
solutions together in a careful (non-obvious) manner.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08900</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08900" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A fast approximate skeleton with guarantees for any cloud of points in a Euclidean space</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Yury Elkin, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Di.html">Di Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kurlin:Vitaliy.html">Vitaliy Kurlin</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08900">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The tree reconstruction problem is to find an embedded straight-line tree
that approximates a given cloud of unorganized points in $\mathbb{R}^m$ up to a
certain error. A practical solution to this problem will accelerate a discovery
of new colloidal products with desired physical properties such as viscosity.
We define the Approximate Skeleton of any finite point cloud $C$ in a Euclidean
space with theoretical guarantees. The Approximate Skeleton ASk$(C)$ always
belongs to a given offset of $C$, i.e. the maximum distance from $C$ to
ASk$(C)$ can be a given maximum error. The number of vertices in the
Approximate Skeleton is close to the minimum number in an optimal tree by
factor 2. The new Approximate Skeleton of any unorganized point cloud $C$ is
computed in a near linear time in the number of points in $C$. Finally, the
Approximate Skeleton outperforms past skeletonization algorithms on the size
and accuracy of reconstruction for a large dataset of real micelles and random
clouds.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08840</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08840" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Adaptive Gradient Methods for Constrained Convex Optimization</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Ene:Alina.html">Alina Ene</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nguyen:Huy_L=.html">Huy L. Nguyen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vladu:Adrian.html">Adrian Vladu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08840">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We provide new adaptive first-order methods for constrained convex
optimization. Our main algorithm AdaAGD+ is an accelerated method, which is
universal in the sense that it achieves nearly-optimal convergence rates for
both smooth and non-smooth functions, even when it only has access to
stochastic gradients. In addition, it does not require any prior knowledge on
how the objective function is parametrized, since it automatically adjusts its
per-coordinate learning rate. This can be seen as a truly accelerated AdaGrad
method for constrained optimization.
</p>
<p>We complement it with a simpler algorithm AdaGrad+ which enjoys the same
features, and achieves the standard non-accelerated convergence rate. We also
present a set of new results involving adaptive methods for unconstrained
optimization and monotone operators.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T01:28:08Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08836</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08836" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Efficient Exact Algorithms for Maximum Balanced Biclique Search in Bipartite Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Lu.html">Lu Chen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Chengfei.html">Chengfei Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhou:Rui.html">Rui Zhou</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xu:Jiajie.html">Jiajie Xu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Jianxin.html">Jianxin Li</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08836">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a bipartite graph, the maximum balanced biclique (\textsf{MBB})
problem, discovering a mutually connected while equal-sized disjoint sets with
the maximum cardinality, plays a significant role for mining the bipartite
graph and has numerous applications. Despite the NP-hardness of the
\textsf{MBB} problem, in this paper, we show that an exact \textsf{MBB} can be
discovered extremely fast in bipartite graphs for real applications. We propose
two exact algorithms dedicated for dense and sparse bipartite graphs
respectively. For dense bipartite graphs, an $\mathcal{O}^{*}( 1.3803^{n})$
algorithm is proposed. This algorithm in fact can find an \textsf{MBB} in near
polynomial time for dense bipartite graphs that are common for applications
such as VLSI design. This is because, using our proposed novel techniques, the
search can fast converge to sufficiently dense bipartite graphs which we prove
to be polynomially solvable. For large sparse bipartite graphs typical for
applications such as biological data analysis, an $\mathcal{O}^{*}(
1.3803^{\ddot{\delta}})$ algorithm is proposed, where $\ddot{\delta}$ is only a
few hundreds for large sparse bipartite graphs with millions of vertices. The
indispensible optimizations that lead to this time complexity are: we transform
a large sparse bipartite graph into a limited number of dense subgraphs with
size up to $\ddot{\delta}$ and then apply our proposed algorithm for dense
bipartite graphs on each of the subgraphs. To further speed up this algorithm,
tighter upper bounds, faster heuristics and effective reductions are proposed,
allowing an \textsf{MBB} to be discovered within a few seconds for bipartite
graphs with millions of vertices. Extensive experiments are conducted on
synthetic and real large bipartite graphs to demonstrate the efficiency and
effectiveness of our proposed algorithms and techniques.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08811</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08811" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Parameterized Complexity of Graph Burning</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kobayashi:Yasuaki.html">Yasuaki Kobayashi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Otachi:Yota.html">Yota Otachi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08811">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Graph Burning asks, given a graph $G = (V,E)$ and an integer $k$, whether
there exists $(b_{0},\dots,b_{k-1}) \in V^{k}$ such that every vertex in $G$
has distance at most $i$ from some $b_{i}$. This problem is known to be
NP-complete even on connected caterpillars of maximum degree $3$. We study the
parameterized complexity of this problem and answer all questions arose by Kare
and Reddy [IWOCA 2019] about parameterized complexity of the problem. We show
that the problem is W[2]-complete parameterized by $k$ and that it does no
admit a polynomial kernel parameterized by vertex cover number unless
$\mathrm{NP} \subseteq \mathrm{coNP/poly}$. We also show that the problem is
fixed-parameter tractable parameterized by clique-width plus the maximum
diameter among all connected components. This implies the fixed-parameter
tractability parameterized by modular-width, by treedepth, and by distance to
cographs. Although the parameterization by distance to split graphs cannot be
handled with the clique-width argument, we show that this is also tractable by
a reduction to a generalized problem with a smaller solution size.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08787</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08787" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Adaptive Exact Learning in a Mixed-Up World: Dealing with Periodicity, Errors, and Jumbled-Index Queries in String Reconstruction</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Afshar:Ramtin.html">Ramtin Afshar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Amir:Amihood.html">Amihood Amir</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Goodrich:Michael_T=.html">Michael T. Goodrich</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Matias:Pedro.html">Pedro Matias</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08787">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the query complexity of exactly reconstructing a string from
adaptive queries, such as substring, subsequence, and jumbled-index queries.
Such problems have applications, e.g., in computational biology. We provide a
number of new and improved bounds for exact string reconstruction for settings
where either the string or the queries are "mixed-up".
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08784</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08784" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal Algorithm for the Planar Two-Center Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Kyungjin Cho, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Oh:Eunjin.html">Eunjin Oh</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08784">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we consider the \emph{planar two-center problem}: Given a set
$S$ of $n$ points in the plane, the goal is to find two smallest congruent
disks whose union contains all points of $S$. We present an $O(n\log n)$-time
algorithm for the planar two-center problem. This matches the best known lower
bound of $\Omega(n\log n)$ as well as improving the previously best known
algorithms which takes $O(n\log^2 n)$ time.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08761</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08761" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dominated Minimal Separators are Tame (Nearly All Others are Feral)</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gartland:Peter.html">Peter Gartland</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lokshtanov:Daniel.html">Daniel Lokshtanov</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08761">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A class ${\cal F}$ of graphs is called {\em tame} if there exists a constant
$k$ so that every graph in ${\cal F}$ on $n$ vertices contains at most $O(n^k)$
minimal separators, {\em strongly-quasi-tame} if every graph in ${\cal F}$ on
$n$ vertices contains at most $O(n^{k \log n})$ minimal separators, and {\em
feral} if there exists a constant $c &gt; 1$ so that ${\cal F}$ contains
$n$-vertex graphs with at least $c^n$ minimal separators for arbitrarily large
$n$. The classification of graph classes into tame or feral has numerous
algorithmic consequences, and has recently received considerable attention.
</p>
<p>A key graph-theoretic object in the quest for such a classification is the
notion of a $k$-{\em creature}. In a recent manuscript [Abrishami et al., Arxiv
2020] conjecture that every hereditary class ${\cal F}$ that excludes
$k$-creatures for some fixed constant $k$ is tame. We give a counterexample to
this conjecture and prove the weaker result that a hereditary class ${\cal F}$
is strongly quasi-tame if it excludes $k$-creatures for some fixed constant $k$
and additionally every minimal separator can be dominated by another fixed
constant $k'$ number of vertices. The tools developed also lead to a number of
additional results of independent interest.
</p>
<p>{\bf (i) We obtain a complete classification of all hereditary graph classes
defined by a finite set of forbidden induced subgraphs into strongly quasi-tame
or feral. This generalizes Milani\v{c} and Piva\v{c} [WG'19]. {\bf (ii)} We
show that hereditary class that excludes $k$-creatures and additionally
excludes all cycles of length at least $c$, for some constant $c$, are tame.
This generalizes the result of [Chudnovsky et al., Arxiv 2019]. {\bf (iii)} We
show that every hereditary class that excludes $k$-creatures and additionally
excludes a complete graph on $c$ vertices for some fixed constant $c$ is tame.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08738</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08738" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Reliable Spanners for Metric Spaces</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Har=Peled:Sariel.html">Sariel Har-Peled</a>, Dániel Olah <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08738">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A spanner is reliable if it can withstand large, catastrophic failures in the
network. More precisely, any failure of some nodes can only cause a small
damage in the remaining graph in terms of the dilation, that is, the spanner
property is maintained for almost all nodes in the residual graph.
Constructions of reliable spanners of near linear size are known in the
low-dimensional Euclidean settings. Here, we present new constructions of
reliable spanners for planar graphs, trees and (general) metric spaces.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08717</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08717" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Improved Approximation Algorithms for Tverberg Partitions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Har=Peled:Sariel.html">Sariel Har-Peled</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhou:Timothy.html">Timothy Zhou</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08717">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>$\newcommand{\floor}[1]{\left\lfloor {#1} \right\rfloor}
\renewcommand{\Re}{\mathbb{R}}$
</p>
<p>Tverberg's theorem states that a set of $n$ points in $\Re^d$ can be
partitioned into $\floor{n/(d+1)}$ sets with a common intersection. A point in
this intersection (aka Tverberg point) is a centerpoint of the input point set,
and the Tverberg partition provides a compact proof of this, which is
algorithmically useful.
</p>
<p>Unfortunately, computing a Tverberg point exactly requires $n^{O(d^2)}$ time.
We provide several new approximation algorithms for this problem, which improve
either the running time or quality of approximation, or both. In particular, we
provide the first strongly polynomial (in both $n$ and $d$) approximation
algorithm for finding a Tverberg point.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08669</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08669" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Memoryless Algorithms for the Generalized $k$-server Problem on Uniform Metrics</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Christou:Dimitris.html">Dimitris Christou</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fotakis:Dimitris.html">Dimitris Fotakis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Koumoutsos:Grigorios.html">Grigorios Koumoutsos</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08669">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the generalized $k$-server problem on uniform metrics. We study
the power of memoryless algorithms and show tight bounds of $\Theta(k!)$ on
their competitive ratio. In particular we show that the \textit{Harmonic
Algorithm} achieves this competitive ratio and provide matching lower bounds.
This improves the $\approx 2^{2^k}$ doubly-exponential bound of Chiplunkar and
Vishwanathan for the more general setting of uniform metrics with different
weights.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08643</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08643" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dynamic Geometric Independent Set</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bhore:Sujoy.html">Sujoy Bhore</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cardinal:Jean.html">Jean Cardinal</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Iacono:John.html">John Iacono</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Koumoutsos:Grigorios.html">Grigorios Koumoutsos</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08643">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present fully dynamic approximation algorithms for the Maximum Independent
Set problem on several types of geometric objects: intervals on the real line,
arbitrary axis-aligned squares in the plane and axis-aligned $d$-dimensional
hypercubes.
</p>
<p>It is known that a maximum independent set of a collection of $n$ intervals
can be found in $O(n\log n)$ time, while it is already \textsf{NP}-hard for a
set of unit squares. Moreover, the problem is inapproximable on many important
graph families, but admits a \textsf{PTAS} for a set of arbitrary pseudo-disks.
Therefore, a fundamental question in computational geometry is whether it is
possible to maintain an approximate maximum independent set in a set of dynamic
geometric objects, in truly sublinear time per insertion or deletion. In this
work, we answer this question in the affirmative for intervals, squares and
hypercubes.
</p>
<p>First, we show that for intervals a $(1+\varepsilon)$-approximate maximum
independent set can be maintained with logarithmic worst-case update time. This
is achieved by maintaining a locally optimal solution using a constant number
of constant-size exchanges per update.
</p>
<p>We then show how our interval structure can be used to design a data
structure for maintaining an expected constant factor approximate maximum
independent set of axis-aligned squares in the plane, with polylogarithmic
amortized update time. Our approach generalizes to $d$-dimensional hypercubes,
providing a $O(4^d)$-approximation with polylogarithmic update time.
</p>
<p>Those are the first approximation algorithms for any set of dynamic arbitrary
size geometric objects; previous results required bounded size ratios to obtain
polylogarithmic update time. Furthermore, it is known that our results for
squares (and hypercubes) cannot be improved to a
$(1+\varepsilon)$-approximation with the same update time.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08585</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08585" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Planar Distance Oracles with Better Time-Space Tradeoffs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Long:Yaowei.html">Yaowei Long</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pettie:Seth.html">Seth Pettie</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08585">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In a recent breakthrough, Charalampopoulos, Gawrychowski, Mozes, and Weimann
(STOC 2019) showed that exact distance queries on planar graphs could be
answered in $n^{o(1)}$ time by a data structure occupying $n^{1+o(1)}$ space,
i.e., up to $o(1)$ terms, optimal exponents in time (0) and space (1) can be
achieved simultaneously. Their distance query algorithm is recursive: it makes
successive calls to a point-location algorithm for planar Voronoi diagrams,
which involves many recursive distance queries. The depth of this recursion is
non-constant and the branching factor logarithmic, leading to $(\log
n)^{\omega(1)} = n^{o(1)}$ query times.
</p>
<p>In this paper we present a new way to do point-location in planar Voronoi
diagrams, which leads to a new exact distance oracle. At the two extremes of
our space-time tradeoff curve we can achieve either
</p>
<p>$n^{1+o(1)}$ space and $\log^{2+o(1)}n$ query time, or
</p>
<p>$n\log^{2+o(1)}n$ space and $n^{o(1)}$ query time.
</p>
<p>All previous oracles with $\tilde{O}(1)$ query time occupy space
$n^{1+\Omega(1)}$, and all previous oracles with space $\tilde{O}(n)$ answer
queries in $n^{\Omega(1)}$ time.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T01:28:50Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08575</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08575" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Polyhedral value iteration for discounted games and energy games</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kozachinskiy:Alexander.html">Alexander Kozachinskiy</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08575">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a deterministic algorithm solving discounted games with $n$ nodes
in strongly $n^{O(1)}\cdot (2 + \sqrt{2})^n$-time. For a special case of
bipartite discounted games our algorithm runs in $n^{O(1)}\cdot 2^n$-time.
Prior to our work no deterministic algorithm running in time $2^{o(n\log n)}$
regardless of the discount factor was known.
</p>
<p>We call our approach polyhedral value iteration. We rely on a well-known fact
that the values of a discounted game can be found from the so-called optimality
equations. In the algorithm we consider a polyhedron obtained by relaxing
optimality equations. We iterate the points on the border of this polyhedron by
moving each time along a carefully chosen shift as far as possible. This
continues until the current point satisfies optimality equations.
</p>
<p>Our approach is heavily inspired by a recent algorithm of Dorfman et al.
(ICALP 2019) for energy games. For completeness, we present their algorithm in
terms of polyhedral value iteration. Our exposition, unlike the original
algorithm, does not require edge weights to be integers and works for arbitrary
real weights.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08368</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08368" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Shortest Watchman Tours in Simple Polygons under Rotated Monotone Visibility</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nilsson:Bengt_J=.html">Bengt J. Nilsson</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Orden:David.html">David Orden</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Palios:Leonidas.html">Leonidas Palios</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Seara:Carlos.html">Carlos Seara</a>, Paweł Żyliński <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08368">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present an $O(nrG)$ time algorithm for computing and maintaining a minimum
length shortest watchman tour that sees a simple polygon under monotone
visibility in direction $\theta$, while $\theta$ varies in $[0,180^{\circ})$,
obtaining the directions for the tour to be the shortest one over all tours,
where $n$ is the number of vertices, $r$ is the number of reflex vertices, and
$G\leq r$ is the maximum number of gates of the polygon used at any time in the
algorithm.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08123</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08123" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dynamic Products of Ranks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Eppstein:David.html">David Eppstein</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08123">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We describe a data structure that can maintain a dynamic set of points given
by their Cartesian coordinates, and maintain the point whose product of ranks
within the two coordinate orderings is minimum or maximum, in time
$O(\sqrt{n\log n})$ per update.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08110</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08110" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Private Approximations of a Convex Hull in Low Dimensions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Yuo Gao, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sheffet:Or.html">Or Sheffet</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08110">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We give the first differentially private algorithms that estimate a variety
of geometric features of points in the Euclidean space, such as diameter,
width, volume of convex hull, min-bounding box, min-enclosing ball etc. Our
work relies heavily on the notion of \emph{Tukey-depth}. Instead of
(non-privately) approximating the convex-hull of the given set of points $P$,
our algorithms approximate the geometric features of the $\kappa$-Tukey region
induced by $P$ (all points of Tukey-depth $\kappa$ or greater). Moreover, our
approximations are all bi-criteria: for any geometric feature $\mu$ our
$(\alpha,\Delta)$-approximation is a value "sandwiched" between
$(1-\alpha)\mu(D_P(\kappa))$ and $(1+\alpha)\mu(D_P(\kappa-\Delta))$.
</p>
<p>Our work is aimed at producing a \emph{$(\alpha,\Delta)$-kernel of
$D_P(\kappa)$}, namely a set $\calS$ such that (after a shift) it holds that
$(1-\alpha)D_P(\kappa)\subset \CH(\calS) \subset (1+\alpha)D_P(\kappa-\Delta)$.
We show that an analogous notion of a bi-critera approximation of a directional
kernel, as originally proposed by Agarwal et al~[2004], \emph{fails} to give a
kernel, and so we result to subtler notions of approximations of projections
that do yield a kernel. First, we give differentially private algorithms that
find $(\alpha,\Delta)$-kernels for a "fat" Tukey-region. Then, based on a
private approximation of the min-bounding box, we find a transformation that
does turn $D_P(\kappa)$ into a "fat" region \emph{but only if} its volume is
proportional to the volume of $D_P(\kappa-\Delta)$. Lastly, we give a novel
private algorithm that finds a depth parameter $\kappa$ for which the volume of
$D_P(\kappa)$ is comparable to $D_P(\kappa-\Delta)$. We hope this work leads to
the further study of the intersection of differential privacy and computational
geometry.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08069</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08069" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Maximizing coverage while ensuring fairness: a tale of conflicting objective</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Asudeh:Abolfazl.html">Abolfazl Asudeh</a>, Tanya Berger-Wolf, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/DasGupta:Bhaskar.html">Bhaskar DasGupta</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sidiropoulos:Anastasios.html">Anastasios Sidiropoulos</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08069">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Ensuring fairness in computational problems has emerged as a $key$ topic
during recent years, buoyed by considerations for equitable resource
distributions and social justice. It $is$ possible to incorporate fairness in
computational problems from several perspectives, such as using optimization,
game-theoretic or machine learning frameworks. In this paper we address the
problem of incorporation of fairness from a $combinatorial$ $optimization$
perspective. We formulate a combinatorial optimization framework, suitable for
analysis by researchers in approximation algorithms and related areas, that
incorporates fairness in maximum coverage problems as an interplay between
$two$ conflicting objectives. Fairness is imposed in coverage by using coloring
constraints that $minimizes$ the discrepancies between number of elements of
different colors covered by selected sets; this is in contrast to the usual
discrepancy minimization problems studied extensively in the literature where
(usually two) colors are $not$ given $a$ $priori$ but need to be selected to
minimize the maximum color discrepancy of $each$ individual set. Our main
results are a set of randomized and deterministic approximation algorithms that
attempts to $simultaneously$ approximate both fairness and coverage in this
framework.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08068</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08068" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Swendsen-Wang Dynamics on Trees</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Blanca:Antonio.html">Antonio Blanca</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Zongchen.html">Zongchen Chen</a>, Daniel Štefankovič, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vigoda:Eric.html">Eric Vigoda</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08068">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Swendsen-Wang algorithm is a sophisticated, widely-used Markov chain for
sampling from the Gibbs distribution for the ferromagnetic Ising and Potts
models with inverse temperature $\beta&gt;0$. Due to the global nature of the
updates of the Swendsen-Wang algorithm, the underlying Markov chain often mixes
rapidly in the low temperature region (large $\beta$) where long-range
correlations impair the convergence rate of local chains such as the Glauber
dynamics. With few exceptions, tight bounds on the convergence rate of the
Swendsen-Wang algorithm only hold for high temperature regions (small $\beta$)
corresponding to the uniqueness or the decay of correlations region.
</p>
<p>We present tight bounds on the convergence rate of the Swendsen-Wang
algorithm for the complete $d$-ary tree that extend to the non-uniqueness
region. Specifically, we show that a spatial mixing property known as the
Variance Mixing condition introduced by Martinelli et al. (2004) implies
constant spectral gap of the Swendsen-Wang dynamics. This implies that the
relaxation time (i.e., the inverse of the spectral gap) is $O(1)$ for all
boundary conditions in the uniqueness region or when $\beta&lt;\beta_1$ where
$\beta_1$ exceeds the uniqueness threshold for the Ising model and for the
$q$-state Potts model when $q$ is small with respect to $d$. In addition, we
prove $O(1)$ relaxation time for all $\beta$ for the monochromatic boundary
condition. Our proof introduces a novel spectral view of the Variance Mixing
condition inspired by several recent rapid mixing results on high-dimensional
expanders.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08031</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08031" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>New Nearly-Optimal Coreset for Kernel Density Estimation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tai:Wai_Ming.html">Wai Ming Tai</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08031">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a point set $P\subset \mathbb{R}^d$, kernel density estimation for
Gaussian kernel is defined as $\overline{\mathcal{G}}_P(x) =
\frac{1}{\left|P\right|}\sum_{p\in P}e^{-\left\lVert x-p \right\rVert^2}$ for
any $x\in\mathbb{R}^d$. We study how to construct a small subset $Q$ of $P$
such that the kernel density estimation of $P$ can be approximated by the
kernel density estimation of $Q$. This subset $Q$ is called \emph{coreset}. The
primary technique in this work is to construct $\pm 1$ coloring on the point
set $P$ by the discrepancy theory and apply this coloring algorithm
recursively. Our result leverages Banaszczyk's Theorem. When $d&gt;1$ is constant,
our construction gives a coreset of size
$O\left(\frac{1}{\varepsilon}\sqrt{\log\log\frac{1}{\varepsilon}}\right)$ as
opposed to the best-known result of
$O\left(\frac{1}{\varepsilon}\sqrt{\log\frac{1}{\varepsilon}}\right)$. It is
the first to give a breakthrough on the barrier of $\sqrt{\log}$ factor even
when $d=2$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.07994</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.07994" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximating the (continuous) Fr\'echet distance</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Connor Colombe, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fox:Kyle.html">Kyle Fox</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.07994">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We describe the first strongly subquadratic time algorithm with
subexponential approximation ratio for approximately computing the Fr\'echet
distance between two polygonal chains. Specifically, let $P$ and $Q$ be two
polygonal chains with $n$ vertices in $d$-dimensional Euclidean space, and let
$\alpha \in [\sqrt{n}, n]$. Our algorithm deterministically finds an
$O(\alpha)$-approximate Fr\'echet correspondence in time $O((n^3 / \alpha^2)
\log n)$. In particular, we get an $O(n)$-approximation in near-linear $O(n
\log n)$ time, a vast improvement over the previously best know result, a
linear time $2^{O(n)}$-approximation. As part of our algorithm, we also
describe how to turn any approximate decision procedure for the Fr\'echet
distance into an approximate optimization algorithm whose approximation ratio
is the same up to arbitrarily small constant factors. The transformation into
an approximate optimization algorithm increases the running time of the
decision procedure by only an $O(\log n)$ factor.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.07983</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.07983" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal angle bounds for quadrilateral meshes</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bishop:Christopher_J=.html">Christopher J. Bishop</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.07983">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We show that any simple planar n-gon can be meshed in linear time by $O(n)$
quadrilaterals with all new angles bounded between $60$ and $120$ degrees.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.07927</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.07927" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>How to Morph Graphs on the Torus</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chambers:Erin_Wolf.html">Erin Wolf Chambers</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Erickson:Jeff.html">Jeff Erickson</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lin:Patrick.html">Patrick Lin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Parsa:Salman.html">Salman Parsa</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.07927">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present the first algorithm to morph graphs on the torus. Given two
isotopic essentially 3-connected embeddings of the same graph on the Euclidean
flat torus, where the edges in both drawings are geodesics, our algorithm
computes a continuous deformation from one drawing to the other, such that all
edges are geodesics at all times. Previously even the existence of such a morph
was not known. Our algorithm runs in $O(n^{1+\omega/2})$ time, where $\omega$
is the matrix multiplication exponent, and the computed morph consists of
$O(n)$ parallel linear morphing steps. Existing techniques for morphing planar
straight-line graphs do not immediately generalize to graphs on the torus; in
particular, Cairns' original 1944 proof and its more recent improvements rely
on the fact that every planar graph contains a vertex of degree at most 5. Our
proof relies on a subtle geometric analysis of 6-regular triangulations of the
torus. We also make heavy use of a natural extension of Tutte's spring
embedding theorem to torus graphs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.07720</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.07720" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An $\tilde{O}(n^{5/4})$ Time $\varepsilon$-Approximation Algorithm for RMS Matching in a Plane</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595203200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lahn:Nathaniel.html">Nathaniel Lahn</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Raghvendra:Sharath.html">Sharath Raghvendra</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.07720">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The 2-Wasserstein distance (or RMS distance) is a useful measure of
similarity between probability distributions that has exciting applications in
machine learning. For discrete distributions, the problem of computing this
distance can be expressed in terms of finding a minimum-cost perfect matching
on a complete bipartite graph given by two multisets of points $A,B \subset
\mathbb{R}^2$, with $|A|=|B|=n$, where the ground distance between any two
points is the squared Euclidean distance between them. Although there is a
near-linear time relative $\varepsilon$-approximation algorithm for the case
where the ground distance is Euclidean (Sharathkumar and Agarwal, JACM 2020),
all existing relative $\varepsilon$-approximation algorithms for the RMS
distance take $\Omega(n^{3/2})$ time. This is primarily because, unlike
Euclidean distance, squared Euclidean distance is not a metric. In this paper,
for the RMS distance, we present a new $\varepsilon$-approximation algorithm
that runs in $O(n^{5/4}\mathrm{poly}\{\log n,1/\varepsilon\})$ time.
</p>
<p>Our algorithm is inspired by a recent approach for finding a minimum-cost
perfect matching in bipartite planar graphs (Asathulla et al., TALG 2020).
Their algorithm depends heavily on the existence of sub-linear sized vertex
separators as well as shortest path data structures that require planarity.
Surprisingly, we are able to design a similar algorithm for a complete
geometric graph that is far from planar and does not have any vertex
separators. Central components of our algorithm include a quadtree-based
distance that approximates the squared Euclidean distance and a data structure
that supports both Hungarian search and augmentation in sub-linear time.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-2418581440113974615</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/2418581440113974615/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/07/erdos-turan-for-k3-is-true.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2418581440113974615" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2418581440113974615" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/07/erdos-turan-for-k3-is-true.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Erdos-Turan for k=3 is True!</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(All of the math in this post is summarized (without proofs) in a writeup by Erik Metz and myself which you can find <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/users/gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/3apblog.pdf">here</a>. It is a pdf file so you can click on links in it to get to the papers it refers to. There have been posts on this topic by <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/07/08/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-7-bloom-and-sisask-just-broke-the-logarithm-barrier-for-roths-theorem/">Gil Kalai</a> and  <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/07/08/silver-linings/">Luca Trevisan</a>. If you know of others then let me know so I can add them to this post.)<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
This is a sequel to <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2010/12/breakthrough-result-on-density-and-3.html">A BREAKTHROUGH result on density and 3-AP's</a> and <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2017/06/big-news-on-w3r.html">Big news on W(3,r)!</a><br/>
<br/>
For this post N is large, and all inequalites have a big-O or a big-Omega.<br/>
<br/>
For this post [N] is {1,...,N}<br/>
<br/>
Let<br/>
<br/>
r(N) be the least N such that if A is a subset of [N] and |A|  &gt;  r(N), then A has a 3-AP.<br/>
<br/>
There has been a long sequence of results getting smaller and smaller upper bounds on r(N).<br/>
<br/>
The motivation for getting these results is that if r(N) is &lt; N/(log N)^{1+\delta} with delta&gt;0 then the following holds:<br/>
<br/>
If sum_{x\in A} 1/x diverges then A has a 3-AP.<br/>
<br/>
This is the k=3 case of one of the Erdos-Turan Conjectures.<br/>
<br/>
Bloom and Sisack HAVE gotten N/(log N)^{1+delta} so they HAVE gotten ET k=3. Wow!<br/>
<br/>
1) I am NOT surprised that its true.<br/>
<br/>
2) I am SHOCKED and DELIGHTED that it was proven.  Shocked because the results leading up to it (see the write up referenced at the beginning of this post) seemed Zeno-like, approaching the result needed got but not getting there. Delighted because... uh, as the kids say, just cause.<br/>
<br/>
I've heard that k=4 really is much harder (see my comments and Gil's response on his blog post, pointed to at the beginning of this post)  and it is true that there has been far less progress on that case (the write up I pointed to at the beginning of this post says what is known). Hence I will again be <i>shocked </i>if it is proven.  So, unlike The Who (see <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UDfAdHBtK_Q">here</a>) I CAN be fooled again. That's okay--- I will  be <i>delighted</i>.<br/>
<br/>
Erdos offered a prize of $3000 for a proof that A has, for all k, a k-AP.  The prize is now $5000. After Erdos passed away Ronald Graham became the Erdos-Bank and paid out the money when people solved a problem Erdos put a bounty on. What happens now? (If I have the facts wrong and/or if you know the answer, please leave a polite and enlightening comment.)<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-07-19T19:12:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-07-19T19:12:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-07-19T19:42:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/109</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/109" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-109 |  On Testing Hamiltonicity in the Bounded Degree Graph Model | 

	Oded Goldreich</title>
    <summary>We show that testing Hamiltonicity in the bounded-degree graph model requires a linear number of queries. This refers to both the path and the cycle versions of the problem, and similar results hold also for the directed analogues.
In addition, we present an alternative proof for the known fact that testing Independent Set Size (in this model) requires a linear number of queries.</summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T15:45:33Z</updated>
    <published>2020-07-19T15:45:33Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T07:21:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/108</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/108" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-108 |  Query Complexity of Global Minimum Cut | 

	Arijit Bishnu, 

	Arijit Ghosh, 

	Gopinath Mishra, 

	Manaswi Paraashar</title>
    <summary>In this work, we resolve the query complexity of global minimum cut problem for a graph by designing a randomized algorithm for approximating the size of minimum cut in a graph, where the graph can be accessed through local queries like \textsc{Degree}, \textsc{Neighbor}, and \textsc{Adjacency} queries.

Given $\epsilon \in (0,1)$, the algorithm with high probability outputs an estimate $\hat{t}$ satisfying the following $(1-\epsilon) t \leq \hat{t} \leq (1+\epsilon) t$, where $m$ is the number of edges in the graph and $t$ is the size of minimum cut in the graph. The expected number of local queries used by our algorithm is $\min\left\{m+n,\frac{m}{t}\right\}\mbox{poly}\left(\log n,\frac{1}{\epsilon}\right)$ where $n$ is the number of vertices in the graph. Eden and Rosenbaum showed that $\Omega(m/t)$ many local queries are required for approximating the size of minimum cut in graphs. These two results together resolve the query complexity of the problem of estimating the size of minimum cut in graphs using local queries.

Building on the lower bound of Eden and Rosenbaum, we show that, for all $t \in \mathbb{N}$, $\Omega(m)$ local queries are required to decide if the size of the minimum cut in the graph is $t$ or $t-2$. Also, we show that, for any $t \in \mathbb{N}$, $\Omega(m)$ local queries are required to find all the minimum cut edges even if it is promised that the input graph has a minimum cut of size $t$. Both of our lower bound results are randomized, and hold even if we can make \textsc{Random Edge} query apart from local queries.</summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T13:02:59Z</updated>
    <published>2020-07-19T13:02:59Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T07:21:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/107</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/107" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-107 |  Testing linear inequalities of subgraph statistics | 

	Lior Gishboliner, 

	Asaf Shapira, 

	Henrique Stagni</title>
    <summary>Property testers are fast randomized algorithms whose task is to distinguish between inputs satisfying some predetermined property ${\cal P}$ and those that are far from satisfying it. Since these algorithms operate by inspecting a small randomly selected portion of the input, the most natural property one would like to be able to test is whether the input does not contain certain forbidden small substructures. In the setting of graphs, such a result was obtained by Alon et al., who proved that for any finite family of graphs ${\cal F}$, the property of being induced ${\cal F}$-free (i.e. not containing an induced copy of any $F \in {\cal F}$) is testable.

It is natural to ask if one can go one step further and prove that more elaborate properties involving induced subgraphs are also testable. One such generalization of the result of Alon et al. was formulated by Goldreich and Shinkar who conjectured that for any finite family of graphs ${\cal F}$, and any linear inequality involving the densities of the graphs $F \in {\cal F}$ in the input graph,
the property of satisfying this inequality can be tested in a certain restricted model of graph property testing. Our main result in this paper disproves this conjecture in the following strong form: some properties of this type are not testable even in the classical (i.e. unrestricted) model of graph property testing.

The proof deviates significantly from prior non-testability results in this area. The main idea is to use a linear inequality relating induced subgraph densities in order to encode the property of being a quasirandom graph.</summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T13:01:55Z</updated>
    <published>2020-07-19T13:01:55Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-07-20T07:21:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08401</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08401" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal Vertex Fault-Tolerant Spanners in Polynomial Time</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595116800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bodwin:Greg.html">Greg Bodwin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dinitz:Michael.html">Michael Dinitz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Robelle:Caleb.html">Caleb Robelle</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08401">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Recent work has pinned down the existentially optimal size bounds for vertex
fault-tolerant spanners: for any positive integer $k$, every $n$-node graph has
a $(2k-1)$-spanner on $O(f^{1-1/k} n^{1+1/k})$ edges resilient to $f$ vertex
faults, and there are examples of input graphs on which this bound cannot be
improved. However, these proofs work by analyzing the output spanner of a
certain exponential-time greedy algorithm. In this work, we give the first
algorithm that produces vertex fault tolerant spanners of optimal size and
which runs in polynomial time. Specifically, we give a randomized algorithm
which takes $\widetilde{O}\left( f^{1-1/k} n^{2+1/k} + mf^2\right)$ time. We
also derandomize our algorithm to give a deterministic algorithm with similar
bounds. This reflects an exponential improvement in runtime over [Bodwin-Patel
PODC '19], the only previously known algorithm for constructing optimal vertex
fault-tolerant spanners.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08357</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08357" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Substring Complexity in Sublinear Space</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595116800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bernardini:Giulia.html">Giulia Bernardini</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fici:Gabriele.html">Gabriele Fici</a>, Paweł Gawrychowski, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pissis:Solon_P=.html">Solon P. Pissis</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08357">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Shannon's entropy is a definitive lower bound for statistical compression.
Unfortunately, no such clear measure exists for the compressibility of
repetitive strings. Thus, ad-hoc measures are employed to estimate the
repetitiveness of strings, e.g., the size $z$ of the Lempel-Ziv parse or the
number $r$ of equal-letter runs of the Burrows-Wheeler transform. A more recent
one is the size $\gamma$ of a smallest string attractor. Unfortunately, Kempa
and Prezza [STOC 2018] showed that computing $\gamma$ is NP-hard. Kociumaka et
al. [LATIN 2020] considered a new measure that is based on the function $S_T$
counting the cardinalities of the sets of substrings of each length of $T$,
also known as the substring complexity. This new measure is defined as $\delta=
\sup\{S_T(k)/k, k\geq 1\}$ and lower bounds all the measures previously
considered. In particular, $\delta\leq \gamma$ always holds and $\delta$ can be
computed in $\mathcal{O}(n)$ time using $\Omega(n)$ working space. Kociumaka et
al. showed that if $\delta$ is given, one can construct an $\mathcal{O}(\delta
\log \frac{n}{\delta})$-sized representation of $T$ supporting efficient direct
access and efficient pattern matching queries on $T$. Given that for highly
compressible strings, $\delta$ is significantly smaller than $n$, it is natural
to pose the following question: Can we compute $\delta$ efficiently using
sublinear working space?
</p>
<p>It is straightforward to show that any algorithm computing $\delta$ using
$\mathcal{O}(b)$ space requires $\Omega(n^{2-o(1)}/b)$ time through a reduction
from the element distinctness problem [Yao, SIAM J. Comput. 1994]. We present
the following results: an $\mathcal{O}(n^3/b^2)$-time and
$\mathcal{O}(b)$-space algorithm to compute $\delta$, for any $b\in[1,n]$; and
an $\tilde{\mathcal{O}}(n^2/b)$-time and $\mathcal{O}(b)$-space algorithm to
compute $\delta$, for any $b\in[n^{2/3},n]$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08285</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08285" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum algorithms for graph problems with cut queries</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595116800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lee:Troy.html">Troy Lee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Santha:Miklos.html">Miklos Santha</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Shengyu.html">Shengyu Zhang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08285">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Let $G$ be an $n$-vertex graph with $m$ edges. When asked a subset $S$ of
vertices, a cut query on $G$ returns the number of edges of $G$ that have
exactly one endpoint in $S$. We show that there is a bounded-error quantum
algorithm that determines all connected components of $G$ after making
$O(\log(n)^5)$ many cut queries. In contrast, it follows from results in
communication complexity that any randomized algorithm even just to decide
whether the graph is connected or not must make at least $\Omega(n/\log(n))$
many cut queries. We further show that with $O(\log(n)^7)$ many cut queries a
quantum algorithm can with high probability output a spanning forest for $G$.
</p>
<p>En route to proving these results, we design quantum algorithms for learning
a graph using cut queries. We show that a quantum algorithm can learn a graph
with maximum degree $d$ after $O(d \log(n)^2)$ many cut queries, and can learn
a general graph with $O(\sqrt{m} \log(n)^{3/2})$ many cut queries. These two
upper bounds are tight up to the poly-logarithmic factors, and compare to
$\Omega(dn)$ and $\Omega(m/\log(n))$ lower bounds on the number of cut queries
needed by a randomized algorithm for the same problems, respectively.
</p>
<p>The key ingredients in our results are the Bernstein-Vazirani algorithm,
approximate counting with "OR queries", and learning sparse vectors from inner
products as in compressed sensing.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T23:23:39Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08253</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.08253" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Improved Deterministic Network Decomposition</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1595116800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Ghaffari:Mohsen.html">Mohsen Ghaffari</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grunau:Christoph.html">Christoph Grunau</a>, Václav Rozhoň <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2007.08253">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Network decomposition is a central tool in distributed graph algorithms. We
present two improvements on the state of the art for network decomposition,
which thus lead to improvements in the (deterministic and randomized)
complexity of several well-studied graph problems.
</p>
<p>- We provide a deterministic distributed network decomposition algorithm with
$O(\log^5 n)$ round complexity, using $O(\log n)$-bit messages. This improves
on the $O(\log^7 n)$-round algorithm of Rozho\v{n} and Ghaffari [STOC'20],
which used large messages, and their $O(\log^8 n)$-round algorithm with $O(\log
n)$-bit messages. This directly leads to similar improvements for a wide range
of deterministic and randomized distributed algorithms, whose solution relies
on network decomposition, including the general distributed derandomization of
Ghaffari, Kuhn, and Harris [FOCS'18].
</p>
<p>- One drawback of the algorithm of Rozho\v{n} and Ghaffari, in the
$\mathsf{CONGEST}$ model, was its dependence on the length of the identifiers.
Because of this, for instance, the algorithm could not be used in the
shattering framework in the $\mathsf{CONGEST}$ model. Thus, the state of the
art randomized complexity of several problems in this model remained with an
additive $2^{O(\sqrt{\log\log n})}$ term, which was a clear leftover of the
older network decomposition complexity [Panconesi and Srinivasan STOC'92]. We
present a modified version that remedies this, constructing a decomposition
whose quality does not depend on the identifiers, and thus improves the
randomized round complexity for various problems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-07-19T23:26:33Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-07-17T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
