<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-08-07T16:22:51Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02215</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02215" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On cylindrical regression in three-dimensional Euclidean space</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565136000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Ageev:O=_V=.html">O. V. Ageev</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sharipov:R=_A=.html">R. A. Sharipov</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.02215">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The three-dimensional cylindrical regression problem is a problem of finding
a cylinder best fitting a group of points in three-dimensional Euclidean space.
The words best fitting are usually understood in the sense of the minimum root
mean square deflection of the given points from a cylinder to be found. In this
form the problem has no analytic solution. If one replaces the root mean square
averaging by a certain biquadratic averaging, the resulting problem has an
almost analytic solution. This solution is reproduced in the present paper in a
coordinate-free form.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-07T01:38:06Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02213</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02213" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Universality Theorem for Nested Polytopes</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565136000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Michael G. Dobbins, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Holmsen:Andreas.html">Andreas Holmsen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Miltzow:Tillmann.html">Tillmann Miltzow</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.02213">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In a nutshell, we show that polynomials and nested polytopes are topological,
algebraic and algorithmically equivalent. Given two polytops $A\subseteq B$ and
a number $k$, the Nested Polytope Problem (NPP) asks, if there exists a
polytope $X$ on $k$ vertices such that $A\subseteq X \subseteq B$. The polytope
$A$ is given by a set of vertices and the polytope $B$ is given by the defining
hyperplanes. We show a universality theorem for NPP. Given an instance $I$ of
the NPP, we define the solutions set of $I$ as $$ V'(I) = \{(x_1,\ldots,x_k)\in
\mathbb{R}^{k\cdot n} : A\subseteq \text{conv}(x_1,\ldots,x_k) \subseteq B\}.$$
As there are many symmetries, induced by permutations of the vertices, we will
consider the \emph{normalized} solution space $V(I)$. Let $F$ be a finite set
of polynomials, with bounded solution space. Then there is an instance $I$ of
the NPP, which has a rationally-equivalent normalized solution space $V(I)$.
Two sets $V$ and $W$ are rationally equivalent if there exists a homeomorphism
$f : V \rightarrow W$ such that both $f$ and $f^{-1}$ are given by rational
functions. A function $f:V\rightarrow W$ is a homeomorphism, if it is
continuous, invertible and its inverse is continuous as well. As a corollary,
we show that NPP is $\exists \mathbb{R}$-complete. This implies that unless
$\exists \mathbb{R} =$ NP, the NPP is not contained in the complexity class NP.
Note that those results already follow from a recent paper by Shitov. Our proof
is geometric and arguably easier.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02211</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02211" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Index for Sequencing Reads Based on The Colored de Bruijn Graph</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565136000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Diego Diaz-Domínguez <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.02211">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this article, we show how to transform a colored de Bruijn graph (dBG)
into a practical index for processing massive sets of sequencing reads. Similar
to previous works, we encode an instance of a colored dBG of the set using BOSS
and a color matrix C. To reduce the space requirements, we devise an algorithm
that produces a smaller and more sparse version of C. The novelties in this
algorithm are (i) an incomplete coloring of the graph and (ii) a greedy
coloring approach that tries to reuse the same colors for different strings
when possible. We also propose two algorithms that work on top of the index;
one is for reconstructing reads, and the other is for contig assembly.
Experimental results show that our data structure uses about half the space of
the plain representation of the set (1 Byte per DNA symbol) and that more than
99% of the reads can be reconstructed just from the index.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-07T01:21:24Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02174</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02174" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the maximum number of minimal connected dominating sets in convex bipartite graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565136000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sayadi:Mohamed_Yosri.html">Mohamed Yosri Sayadi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.02174">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The enumeration of minimal connected dominating sets is known to be
notoriously hard for general graphs. Currently, it is only known that the sets
can be enumerated slightly faster than $\mathcal{O}^{*}(2^n)$ and the algorithm
is highly nontrivial. Moreover, it seems that it is hard to use bipartiteness
as a structural aide when constructing enumeration algorithms. Hence, to the
best of our knowledge, there is no known input-sensitive algorithm for
enumerating minimal dominating sets, or one of their related sets, in bipartite
graphs better than that of general graphs. In this paper, we provide the first
input-sensitive enumeration algorithm for some non trivial subclass of
bipartite graphs, namely the convex graphs. We present an algorithm to
enumerate all minimal connected dominating sets of convex bipartite graphs in
time $\mathcal{O}(1.7254^{n})$ where $n$ is the number of vertices of the input
graph. Our algorithm implies a corresponding upper bound for the number of
minimal connected dominating sets for this graph class. We complement the
result by providing a convex bipartite graph, which have at least $3^{(n-2)/3}$
minimal connected dominating sets.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-07T01:27:34Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02129</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02129" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Engineering Negative Cycle Canceling for Wind Farm Cabling</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565136000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Sascha Gritzbach, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/u/Ueckerdt:Torsten.html">Torsten Ueckerdt</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wagner:Dorothea.html">Dorothea Wagner</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wegner:Franziska.html">Franziska Wegner</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wolf:Matthias.html">Matthias Wolf</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.02129">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In a wind farm turbines convert wind energy into electrical energy. The
generation of each turbine is transmitted, possibly via other turbines, to a
substation that is connected to the power grid. On every possible
interconnection there can be at most one of various different cable types. Each
type comes with a cost per unit length and with a capacity. Designing a
cost-minimal cable layout for a wind farm to feed all turbine production into
the power grid is called the Wind Farm Cabling Problem (WCP).
</p>
<p>We consider a formulation of WCP as a flow problem on a graph where the cost
of a flow on an edge is modeled by a step function originating from the cable
types. Recently, we presented a proof-of-concept for a negative cycle
canceling-based algorithm for WCP [14]. We extend key steps of that heuristic
and build a theoretical foundation that explains how this heuristic tackles the
problems arising from the special structure of WCP.
</p>
<p>A thorough experimental evaluation identifies the best setup of the algorithm
and compares it to existing methods from the literature such as Mixed-integer
Linear Programming (MILP) and Simulated Annealing (SA). The heuristic runs in a
range of half a millisecond to approximately one and a half minutes on
instances with up to 500 turbines. It provides solutions of similar quality
compared to both competitors with running times of one hour and one day. When
comparing the solution quality after a running time of two seconds, our
algorithm outperforms the MILP- and SA-approaches, which allows it to be
applied in interactive wind farm planning.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-07T01:21:27Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01956</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01956" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Parallel Batch-Dynamic Graphs: Algorithms and Lower Bounds</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565136000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Durfee:David.html">David Durfee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dhulipala:Laxman.html">Laxman Dhulipala</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kulkarni:Janardhan.html">Janardhan Kulkarni</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Peng:Richard.html">Richard Peng</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sawlani:Saurabh.html">Saurabh Sawlani</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sun:Xiaorui.html">Xiaorui Sun</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01956">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper we study the problem of dynamically maintaining graph
properties under batches of edge insertions and deletions in the massively
parallel model of computation. In this setting, the graph is stored on a number
of machines, each having space strongly sublinear with respect to the number of
vertices, that is, $n^\epsilon$ for some constant $0 &lt; \epsilon &lt; 1$. Our goal
is to handle batches of updates and queries where the data for each batch fits
onto one machine in constant rounds of parallel computation, as well as to
reduce the total communication between the machines. This objective corresponds
to the gradual buildup of databases over time, while the goal of obtaining
constant rounds of communication for problems in the static setting has been
elusive for problems as simple as undirected graph connectivity.
</p>
<p>We give an algorithm for dynamic graph connectivity in this setting with
constant communication rounds and communication cost almost linear in terms of
the batch size. Our techniques combine a new graph contraction technique, an
independent random sample extractor from correlated samples, as well as
distributed data structures supporting parallel updates and queries in batches.
</p>
<p>We also illustrate the power of dynamic algorithms in the MPC model by
showing that the batched version of the adaptive connectivity problem is
$\mathsf{P}$-complete in the centralized setting, but sub-linear sized batches
can be handled in a constant number of rounds. Due to the wide applicability of
our approaches, we believe it represents a practically-motivated workaround to
the current difficulties in designing more efficient massively parallel static
graph algorithms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-07T01:26:22Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01812</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01812" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal Joins using Compact Data Structures</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565136000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Navarro:Gonzalo.html">Gonzalo Navarro</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Reutter:Juan_L=.html">Juan L. Reutter</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rojas=Ledesma:Javiel.html">Javiel Rojas-Ledesma</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01812">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Worst-case optimal join algorithms have gained a lot of attention in the
database literature. We now count with several different algorithms that have
all been shown to be optimal in the worst case, and many of them have also been
implemented and tested in practice. However, the implementation of these
algorithms often requires an enhanced indexing structure: to achieve optimality
we either need to build completely new indexes or we must populate the database
with several different instantiations of common indexes such as B+-trees.
Either way, this means spending an extra amount of storage space that may be
non-negligible.
</p>
<p>In this paper we show that optimal algorithms can be obtained directly from a
representation that regards the relations as point sets in variable-dimensional
grids, without the need of extra storage. Our representation is a compact
quadtree for the static indexes and a dynamic quadtree sharing subtrees (which
we dub a Qdag) for intermediate results. We develop a compositional algorithm
to process full join queries when data is stored in said structures, and then
show that the running time of this algorithm is worst-case optimal in data
complexity.
</p>
<p>Remarkably, we can even extend our framework to compute more expressive
queries in relational algebra using both unions and a form of limited negation,
by introducing a lazy version of Qdags. Once again, we can show that the
running time of our algorithms is worst-case optimal.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01769</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01769" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Stress-Plus-X (SPX) Graph Layout</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565136000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Devkota:Sabin.html">Sabin Devkota</a>, Reyan Ahmed, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Luca:Felice_De.html">Felice De Luca</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Isaacs:Kate.html">Kate Isaacs</a>, Stephen Kobourov <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01769">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Stress, edge crossings, and crossing angles play an important role in the
quality and readability of graph drawings. Most standard graph drawing
algorithms optimize one of these criteria which may lead to layouts that are
deficient in other criteria. We introduce an optimization framework,
Stress-Plus-X (SPX), that simultaneously optimizes stress together with several
other criteria: edge crossings, minimum crossing angle, and upwardness (for
directed acyclic graphs). SPX achieves results that are close to the
state-of-the-art algorithms that optimize these metrics individually. SPX is
flexible and extensible and can optimize a subset or all of these criteria
simultaneously. Our experimental analysis shows that our joint optimization
approach is successful in drawing graphs with good performance across
readability criteria.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-07T01:38:15Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16143</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/08/06/code-it-up/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Code It Up</title>
    <summary>So you think you have a proof that P=NP Randi 2014 documentary source James Randi is a magician who has challenged paranormal claims of all kinds. Today Ken and I want to make a suggestion to those who claim they have proved P=NP. No the claim to have a proof that P=NP is not a […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>So you think you have a proof that P=NP</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://dickken.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/anhonestliarposter.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-18" height="192" src="https://dickken.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/anhonestliarposter.png?w=144&amp;h=192" width="144"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Randi 2014 documentary <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/An_Honest_Liar">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
James Randi is a magician who has challenged paranormal claims of all kinds.</p>
<p>
Today Ken and I want to make a suggestion to those who claim they have proved P=NP.</p>
<p>
No the claim to have a proof that P=NP is not a paranormal claim. But such claims are related to Randi—or the Amazing Randi as he is called. We talked about him before <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2012/02/23/an-amazing-result/">here</a>.</p>
<p>
Randi once helped run a contest to see who could find gold with their dowsing rod. He explained why he doubted one contestant: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> If they really could find gold, why were they dressed so poorly, and why were they so interested in winning the prize? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
I have the same question about those who claim that they have a proof that P=NP. Usually the proof is constructive and I agree with Randi:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> If they really could solve P=NP, why <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\dots}"/> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
You get the idea.</p>
<p>
Ken adds the obvious remark that if a foreign power or intelligence agency discovered P=NP, or factoring in P, they would still keep the lean-and-hungry look. But they are not the kind we are addressing here.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Coding Helps </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Let’s look at a claims that P=NP is resolved. Yes, such a result is unlikely—many would say impossible. But we do get claims like this:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> The following <img alt="{\cal H}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccal+H%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\cal H}"/> is known to be a NP-complete problem; the following <img alt="{\cal E}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccal+E%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\cal E}"/> is known to be a polynomial time problem. I can reduce <img alt="{\cal H}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccal+H%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\cal H}"/> to <img alt="{\cal E}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccal+E%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\cal E}"/> in polynomial time. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Usually the reduction is the reason their proof fails. Their claims about <img alt="{\cal H}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccal+H%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\cal H}"/> and <img alt="{\cal E}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccal+E%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\cal E}"/> are usually correct, since they are in the literature. </p>
<p>
The reduction is often complicated, often poorly defined, often defined by example. Giving a precise definition for the reduction is critical. This is the reason we suggest the following: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <i>Write the reduction down in code.</i> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Even better, write it as a program in a real language such as Python. </p>
<p>
There are two advantages in doing this. </p>
<ul>
<li>
Writing it as a program in a real language will likely force one to define it precisely. <p/>
</li><li>
Writing it down will also allow one to run the program on examples.
</li></ul>
<p>
The later point is the key point. Even trying your method on tiny examples is useful. Even better if you can say the following we might read the proof: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <i>I have tried my code on the following public set of difficult SAT problems. The code solved all in less than three minutes each.</i> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>This claim would greatly improve the likelihood that people might take your claims seriously. That your code worked correctly, forgetting the running time, would improve confidence. Greatly. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Animal Farm View<img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\dots}"/> </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Ken worries that some NP-complete problems are more equal than others. That is some problems, even though they are NP-complete may require reductions that blow up when encoding SAT. </p>
<p>
We wrote about this <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2012/04/22/the-travelling-salesmans-power/">before</a> regarding the “Power Index” idea of Richard Stearns and Harry Hunt III. In their <a href="http://www.cs.albany.edu/~res/powerindex.pdf">paper</a> they gave evidence that the reductions from SAT <em>to</em> many familiar NP-complete problems <em>must</em> expand the size of instances quadratically, insofar as those problems have <em>power index</em> <img alt="{0.5}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0.5%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0.5}"/>. This was based on their “SAT Hypothesis” which anticipated current forms of the Exponential Time Hypothesis, which we have <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2015/06/01/puzzling-evidence/">discussed</a>.</p>
<p>
Ken ponders a related issue. Even problems with power index <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/> run into the success of practical solvers. This means: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Anyone citing algorithmic success as evidence toward a claim of P=NP must compete with the real-world success of algorithms that do not represent claims of P=NP. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
We have <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2014/02/28/practically-pnp/">several</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2015/10/22/rankings-versus-ratings/">times</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2016/07/10/the-world-turned-upside-down/">discussed</a> the practical success of SAT-solvers on myriad real-world instances. </p>
<p>
This situation has become real in the argument over achieving quantum <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_supremacy">supremacy</a>. One who claims that quantum is superior to classic must worry that that classical algorithms can improve without making P=NP. A headline example from last year was when Ewin Tang—as a high-school senior—<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1807.04271">found</a> a classical way to remove a plausible quantum advantage in a matrix-completion problem that <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/teenager-finds-classical-alternative-to-quantum-recommendation-algorithm-20180731/">underlies</a> recommender systems.  There are many “industrial strength” examples in this argument—see this May 2019 <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/s/613507/the-new-benchmark-quantum-computers-must-beat-to-achieve-quantum-supremacy/">story</a> for a start.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> But… </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Ken’s insightful comments aside, the key point is still: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <i>Coding up your claimed algorithm for that NP-complete problem will still enhance belief.</i> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>This will happen even if the algorithm only succeeds on tiny examples. Indeed, if you cannot do this then I suggest that you will have an impossible time getting anyone to listen.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
How useful is this advice for the vast majority of us who are <em>not</em> claiming P=NP or the opposite?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-06T20:45:04Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-06T20:45:04Z</published>
    <category term="algorithms"/>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="claims"/>
    <category term="complexity"/>
    <category term="heuristic algorithms"/>
    <category term="James Randi"/>
    <category term="programming"/>
    <category term="quantum advantage"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:21:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/08/06/machine-learning-for-communication-systems-and-networks/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/08/06/machine-learning-for-communication-systems-and-networks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Machine Learning for Communication Systems and Networks</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">September 2-4, 2019 Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland https://connectcentre.ie/summer-school/ The Summer School will include a technical track with lectures and workshops on various aspects of Machine Learning, as well as associated training in areas such as research ethics, career development, communicating research, innovation, and public engagement. It will also include social and networking events. Speakers … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/08/06/machine-learning-for-communication-systems-and-networks/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Machine Learning for Communication Systems and Networks</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T18:49:21Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-06T18:49:21Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:22:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01664</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01664" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the cyclic regularities of strings</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Oluwole Ajala, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Alshammary:Miznah.html">Miznah Alshammary</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Alzamel:Mai.html">Mai Alzamel</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gao:Jia.html">Jia Gao</a>, Costas Iliopoulos, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Radoszewski:Jakub.html">Jakub Radoszewski</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rytter:Wojciech.html">Wojciech Rytter</a>, Bruce Watson <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01664">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Regularities in strings are often related to periods and covers, which have
extensively been studied, and algorithms for their efficient computation have
broad application. In this paper we concentrate on computing cyclic
regularities of strings, in particular, we propose several efficient algorithms
for computing: (i) cyclic periodicity; (ii) all cyclic periodicity; (iii)
maximal local cyclic periodicity; (iv) cyclic covers.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:31:07Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01662</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01662" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Proof of Correctness and Time Complexity Analysis of a Maximum Distance Transform Algorithm</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sahasrabudhe:Mihir.html">Mihir Sahasrabudhe</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chandra:Siddhartha.html">Siddhartha Chandra</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01662">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The distance transform algorithm is popular in computer vision and machine
learning domains. It is used to minimize quadratic functions over a grid of
points. Felzenszwalb and Huttenlocher (2004) describe an O(N) algorithm for
computing the minimum distance transform for quadratic functions. Their
algorithm works by computing the lower envelope of a set of parabolas defined
on the domain of the function. In this work, we describe an average time O(N)
algorithm for maximizing this function by computing the upper envelope of a set
of parabolas. We study the duality of the minimum and maximum distance
transforms, give a correctness proof of the algorithm and its runtime, and
discuss potential applications.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:38:17Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01624</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01624" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Learned Clause Minimization in Parallel SAT Solvers</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hartung:Marc.html">Marc Hartung</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schintke:Florian.html">Florian Schintke</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01624">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Learned clauses minimization (LCM) let to performance improvements of modern
SAT solvers especially in solving hard SAT instances. Despite the success of
LCM approaches in sequential solvers, they are not widely incorporated in
parallel SAT solvers. In this paper we explore the potential of LCM for
parallel SAT solvers by defining multiple LCM approaches based on clause
vivification, comparing their runtime in different SAT solvers and discussing
reasons for performance gains and losses. Results show that LCM only boosts
performance of parallel SAT solvers on a fraction of SAT instances. More
commonly applying LCM decreases performance. Only certain LCM approaches are
able to improve the overall performance of parallel SAT solvers.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:30:21Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01562</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01562" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Heuristic Algorithm for Generalized Function Matching</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mincu:Radu_Stefan.html">Radu Stefan Mincu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01562">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The problem of generalized function matching can be defined as follows: given
a pattern $p=p_1 \cdots p_m$ and a text $t=t_1 \cdots t_n$, find a mapping
$f:\Sigma_p\rightarrow\Sigma_t^{*}$ and all text locations $i$ such that
$f(p_1) f(p_2) \cdots f(p_m) = t_i \cdots t_j$, a substring of $t$.
</p>
<p>By modifying the restrictions of the matching function $f$, one can obtain
different matching problems, many of which have important applications. When
$f:\Sigma_p\rightarrow\Sigma_t$ we are faced with problems found in the
well-established field of combinatorial pattern matching. If the single
character constraint is lifted and $f:\Sigma_p\rightarrow\Sigma_t^{*}$, we
obtain generalized function matching as introduced by Amir and Nor (JDA 2007).
If we further constrain $f$ to be injective, then we arrive at generalized
parametrized matching as defined by Clifford et al. (SPIRE 2009).
</p>
<p>There are a number of important applications for pattern matching in
computational biology, text editors and data compression, to name a few.
Therefore, many efficient algorithms have been developed for a wide variety of
specific problems including finding tandem repeats in DNA sequences, optimizing
embedded systems by reusing code etc.
</p>
<p>In this work we present a heuristic algorithm illustrating a practical
approach to tackling a variant of generalized function matching where
$f:\Sigma_p\rightarrow\Sigma_t^{+}$ and demonstrate its performance on
human-produced text as well as random strings.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:36:06Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01426</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01426" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Geometry and Generation of a New Graph Planarity Game</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kraaijer:Rutger.html">Rutger Kraaijer</a>, Marc van Kreveld, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Meulemans:Wouter.html">Wouter Meulemans</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Renssen:Andr=eacute=_van.html">André van Renssen</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01426">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We introduce a new abstract graph game, Swap Planarity, where the goal is to
reach a state without edge intersections and a move consists of swapping the
locations of two vertices connected by an edge. We analyze this puzzle game
using concepts from graph theory and graph drawing, computational geometry, and
complexity. Furthermore, we specify quality criteria for puzzle instances, and
describe a method to generate high-quality instances. We also report on
experiments that show how well this generation process works.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:37:12Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01350</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01350" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Another Simple but Faster Method for 2D Line Clipping</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Dimitrios Matthes, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Drakopoulos:Vasileios.html">Vasileios Drakopoulos</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01350">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The majority of methods for line clipping make a rather large number of
comparisons and involve a lot of calculations compared to modern ones. Most of
the times, they are not so efficient as well as not so simple and applicable to
the majority of cases. Besides the most popular ones, namely, Cohen-Sutherland,
Liang-Barsky, Cyrus-Beck and Nicholl-Lee-Nicholl, other line-clipping methods
have been presented over the years, each one having its own advantages and
disadvantages. In this paper a new computation method for 2D line clipping
against a rectangular window is introduced. The proposed method has been
compared with the afore-mentioned ones as well as with two others; namely,
Skala and Kodituwakku-Wijeweera-Chamikara, with respect to the number of
operations performed and the computation time. The performance of the proposed
method has been found to be better than all of the above-mentioned methods and
it is found to be very fast, simple and can be implemented easily in any
programming language or integrated development environment.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:37:04Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01317</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01317" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Computing the inverse geodesic length in planar graphs and graphs of bounded treewidth</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cabello:Sergio.html">Sergio Cabello</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01317">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The inverse geodesic length of a graph $G$ is the sum of the inverse of the
distances between all pairs of distinct vertices of $G$. In some domains it is
known as the Harary index or the global efficiency of the graph. We show that,
if $G$ is planar and has $n$ vertices, then the inverse geodesic length of $G$
can be computed in roughly $O(n^{9/5})$ time. We also show that, if $G$ has $n$
vertices and treewidth at most $k$, then the inverse geodesic length of $G$ can
be computed in $O(n \log^{O(k)}n)$ time. In both cases we use techniques
developed for computing the sum of the distances, which does not have
``inverse'' component, together with batched evaluations of rational functions.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01263</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01263" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Matching reads to many genomes with the $r$-index</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mun:Taher.html">Taher Mun</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kuhnle:Alan.html">Alan Kuhnle</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Boucher:Christina.html">Christina Boucher</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gagie:Travis.html">Travis Gagie</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Langmead:Ben.html">Ben Langmead</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Manzini:Giovanni.html">Giovanni Manzini</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01263">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The $r$-index is a tool for compressed indexing of genomic databases for
exact pattern matching, which can be used to completely align reads that
perfectly match some part of a genome in the database or to find seeds for
reads that do not. This paper shows how to download and install the programs
ri-buildfasta and ri-align; how to call ri-buildfasta on a FASTA file to build
an $r$-index for that file; and how to query that index with ri-align.
</p>
<p>Availability: The source code for these programs is released under GPLv3 and
available at https://github.com/alshai/r-index .
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:23:18Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01241</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01241" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Iterative Collaborative Filtering for Sparse Noisy Tensor Estimation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Shah:Devavrat.html">Devavrat Shah</a>, Christina Lee Yu <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01241">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the task of tensor estimation, i.e. estimating a low-rank 3-order
$n \times n \times n$ tensor from noisy observations of randomly chosen entries
in the sparse regime. In the context of matrix (2-order tensor) estimation, a
variety of algorithms have been proposed and analyzed in the literature
including the popular collaborative filtering algorithm that is extremely well
utilized in practice. However, in the context of tensor estimation, there is
limited progress. No natural extensions of collaborative filtering are known
beyond ``flattening'' the tensor into a matrix and applying standard
collaborative filtering.
</p>
<p>As the main contribution of this work, we introduce a generalization of the
collaborative filtering algorithm for the setting of tensor estimation and
argue that it achieves sample complexity that (nearly) matches the conjectured
lower bound on the sample complexity. Interestingly, our generalization uses
the matrix obtained from the ``flattened'' tensor to compute similarity as in
the classical collaborative filtering but by defining a novel ``graph'' using
it. The algorithm recovers the tensor with mean-squared-error (MSE) decaying to
$0$ as long as each entry is observed independently with probability $p =
\Omega(n^{-3/2 + \epsilon})$ for any arbitrarily small $\epsilon &gt; 0$. It turns
out that $p = \Omega(n^{-3/2})$ is the conjectured lower bound as well as
``connectivity threshold'' of graph considered to compute similarity in our
algorithm.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:27:26Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01230</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01230" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fast Evolutionary Algorithms for Maximization of Cardinality-Constrained Weakly Submodular Functions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Crawford:Victoria_G=.html">Victoria G. Crawford</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kuhnle:Alan.html">Alan Kuhnle</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01230">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the monotone, weakly submodular maximization problem (WSM), which is
to find a subset of size $k$ from a universe of size $n$ that maximizes a
monotone, weakly submodular objective function $f$. For objectives with
submodularity ratio $\gamma$, we provide two novel evolutionary algorithms that
have an expected approximation guarantee of
$(1-n^{-1})(1-e^{-\gamma}-\epsilon)$ for WSM in linear time, improving upon the
cubic time complexity of previous evolutionary algorithms for this problem.
This improvement is a result of restricting mutations to local changes, a
biased random selection of which set to mutate, and an improved theoretical
analysis. In the context of several applications of WSM, we demonstrate the
ability of our algorithms to quickly exceed the solution of the greedy
algorithm and converge faster than existing evolutionary algorithms for WSM.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:30:54Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01223</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01223" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faster algorithm for Cograph Deletion</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tsur:Dekel.html">Dekel Tsur</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01223">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the Cograph Deletion problem the input is a graph $G$ and an integer $k$,
and the goal is to decide whether there is a set of at most $k$ edges whose
removal from $G$ results a graph that does not contain an induced path with
four vertices. In this paper we give an algorithm for Cograph Deletion whose
running time is $O^*(2.303^k)$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:29:58Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01181</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01181" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Power of the Weighted Sum Scalarization for Approximating Multiobjective Optimization Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bazgan:Cristina.html">Cristina Bazgan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ruzika:Stefan.html">Stefan Ruzika</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Thielen:Clemens.html">Clemens Thielen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vanderpooten:Daniel.html">Daniel Vanderpooten</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01181">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We determine the power of the weighted sum scalarization with respect to the
computation of approximations for general multiobjective minimization and
maximization problems. Additionally, we introduce a new multi-factor notion of
approximation that is specifically tailored to the multiobjective case and its
inherent trade-offs between different objectives.
</p>
<p>For minimization problems, we provide an efficient algorithm that computes an
approximation of a multiobjective problem by using an exact or approximate
algorithm for its weighted sum scalarization. In case that an exact algorithm
for the weighted sum scalarization is used, this algorithm comes arbitrarily
close to the best approximation quality that is obtainable by supported
solutions - both with respect to the common notion of approximation and with
respect to the new multi-factor notion. Moreover, the algorithm yields the
currently best approximation results for several well-known multiobjective
minimization problems. For maximization problems, however, we show that a
polynomial approximation guarantee can, in general, not be obtained in more
than one of the objective functions simultaneously by supported solutions.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:26:12Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01167</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01167" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Optimized Disk Scheduling Algorithm With Bad-Sector Management</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dash:Amar_Ranjan.html">Amar Ranjan Dash</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sahu:Sandipta_Kumar.html">Sandipta Kumar Sahu</a>, B Kewal <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01167">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In high performance computing, researchers try to optimize the CPU Scheduling
algorithms, for faster and efficient working of computers. But a process needs
both CPU bound and I/O bound for completion of its execution. With
modernization of computers the speed of processor, hard-disk, and I/O devices
increases gradually. Still the data access speed of hard-disk is much less than
the speed of the processor. So when processor receives a data from secondary
memory it executes immediately and again it have to wait for receiving another
data. So the slowness of the hard-disk becomes a bottleneck in the performance
of processor. Researchers try to develop and optimize the traditional disk
scheduling algorithms for faster data transfer to and from secondary data
storage devices. In this paper we try to evolve an optimized scheduling
algorithm by reducing the seek time, the rotational latency, and the data
transfer time in runtime. This algorithm has the feature to manage the
bad-sectors of the hard-disk. It also attempts to reduce power consumption and
heat reduction by minimizing bad sector reading time.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:22:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01087</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01087" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Network Shrinkage Estimation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Ahmed:Nesreen_K=.html">Nesreen K. Ahmed</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Duffield:Nick.html">Nick Duffield</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01087">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Networks are a natural representation of complex systems across the sciences,
and higher-order dependencies are central to the understanding and modeling of
these systems. However, in many practical applications such as online social
networks, networks are massive, dynamic, and naturally streaming, where
pairwise interactions become available one at a time in some arbitrary order.
The massive size and streaming nature of these networks allow only partial
observation, since it is infeasible to analyze the entire network. Under such
scenarios, it is challenging to study the higher-order structural and
connectivity patterns of streaming networks. In this work, we consider the
fundamental problem of estimating the higher-order dependencies using adaptive
sampling. We propose a novel adaptive, single-pass sampling framework and
unbiased estimators for higher-order network analysis of large streaming
networks. Our algorithms exploit adaptive techniques to identify edges that are
highly informative for efficiently estimating the higher-order structure of
streaming networks from small sample data. We also introduce a novel
James-Stein-type shrinkage estimator to minimize the estimation error. Our
approach is fully analytic with theoretical guarantees, computationally
efficient, and can be incrementally updated in a streaming setting. Numerical
experiments on large networks show that our approach is superior to baseline
methods.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:21:10Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01034</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01034" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Efficient Truncated Statistics with Unknown Truncation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kontonis:Vasilis.html">Vasilis Kontonis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tzamos:Christos.html">Christos Tzamos</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zampetakis:Manolis.html">Manolis Zampetakis</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01034">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the problem of estimating the parameters of a Gaussian distribution
when samples are only shown if they fall in some (unknown) subset $S \subseteq
\R^d$. This core problem in truncated statistics has long history going back to
Galton, Lee, Pearson and Fisher. Recent work by Daskalakis et al. (FOCS'18),
provides the first efficient algorithm that works for arbitrary sets in high
dimension when the set is known, but leaves as an open problem the more
challenging and relevant case of unknown truncation set.
</p>
<p>Our main result is a computationally and sample efficient algorithm for
estimating the parameters of the Gaussian under arbitrary unknown truncation
sets whose performance decays with a natural measure of complexity of the set,
namely its Gaussian surface area. Notably, this algorithm works for large
families of sets including intersections of halfspaces, polynomial threshold
functions and general convex sets. We show that our algorithm closely captures
the tradeoff between the complexity of the set and the number of samples needed
to learn the parameters by exhibiting a set with small Gaussian surface area
for which it is information theoretically impossible to learn the true Gaussian
with few samples.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:29:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01029</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01029" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Efficient Evolutionary Algorithm for Minimum Cost Submodular Cover</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Crawford:Victoria_G=.html">Victoria G. Crawford</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01029">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, the Minimum Cost Submodular Cover problem is studied, which is
to minimize a modular cost function such that the monotone submodular benefit
function is above a threshold. For this problem, an evolutionary algorithm EASC
is introduced that achieves a constant, bicriteria approximation in expected
polynomial time; this is the first polynomial-time evolutionary approximation
algorithm for Minimum Cost Submodular Cover. To achieve this running time,
ideas motivated by submodularity and monotonicity are incorporated into the
evolutionary process, which likely will extend to other submodular optimization
problems. In a practical application, EASC is demonstrated to outperform the
greedy algorithm and converge faster than competing evolutionary algorithms for
this problem.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:36:10Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01020</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.01020" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal Separation and Strong Direct Sum for Randomized Query Complexity</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1565049600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Blais:Eric.html">Eric Blais</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Brody:Joshua.html">Joshua Brody</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.01020">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We establish two results regarding the query complexity of bounded-error
randomized algorithms.
</p>
<p>* Bounded-error separation theorem. There exists a total function $f :
\{0,1\}^n \to \{0,1\}$ whose $\epsilon$-error randomized query complexity
satisfies $\overline{\mathrm{R}}_\epsilon(f) = \Omega( \mathrm{R}(f) \cdot
\log\frac1\epsilon)$.
</p>
<p>* Strong direct sum theorem. For every function $f$ and every $k \ge 2$, the
randomized query complexity of computing $k$ instances of $f$ simultaneously
satisfies $\overline{\mathrm{R}}_\epsilon(f^k) = \Theta(k \cdot
\overline{\mathrm{R}}_{\frac\epsilon k}(f))$.
</p>
<p>As a consequence of our two main results, we obtain an optimal superlinear
direct-sum-type theorem for randomized query complexity: there exists a
function $f$ for which $\mathrm{R}(f^k) = \Theta( k \log k \cdot
\mathrm{R}(f))$. This answers an open question of Drucker (2012). Combining
this result with the query-to-communication complexity lifting theorem of
G\"o\"os, Pitassi, and Watson (2017), this also shows that there is a total
function whose public-coin randomized communication complexity satisfies
$\mathrm{R}^{\mathrm{cc}} (f^k) = \Theta( k \log k \cdot
\mathrm{R}^{\mathrm{cc}}(f))$, answering a question of Feder, Kushilevitz,
Naor, and Nisan (1995).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-06T23:20:42Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/101</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/101" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-101 |  Streaming Verification of Graph Computations via Graph Structure | 

	Amit Chakrabarti, 

	Prantar Ghosh</title>
    <summary>We give new algorithms in the annotated data streaming setting---also known as verifiable data stream computation---for certain graph problems. This setting is meant to model outsourced computation, where a space-bounded verifier limited to sequential data access seeks to overcome its computational limitations by engaging a powerful prover, without needing to trust the prover. As is well established, several problems that admit no sublinear-space algorithms under traditional streaming do allow protocols using a sublinear amount of prover/verifier communication and sublinear-space verification.  We give algorithms for many well-studied graph problems including triangle counting, its generalization to subgraph counting, maximum matching, problems about the existence (or not) of short paths, finding the shortest path between two vertices, and testing for an independent set. While some of these problems have been studied before, our results achieve new tradeoffs between space and communication costs that were hitherto unknown. In particular, two of our results disprove explicit conjectures of Thaler (ICALP, 2016) by giving triangle counting and maximum matching algorithms for $n$-vertex graphs, using $o(n)$ space and $o(n^2)$ communication.</summary>
    <updated>2019-08-05T16:44:36Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-05T16:44:36Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:20:57Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/08/05/full-professor-on-the-interface-of-computer-science-and-mathematics-at-university-of-warwick-apply-by-september-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/08/05/full-professor-on-the-interface-of-computer-science-and-mathematics-at-university-of-warwick-apply-by-september-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Full Professor on the interface of Computer Science and Mathematics at University of Warwick (apply by September 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at the University of Warwick and the Warwick Mathematics Institute invite applications for a full Professor post in the areas on the interface of Computer Science and Mathematics, including Discrete Mathematics, Algorithms and Complexity, Theoretical Computer Science. Website: https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/dcs/jobs/?newsItem=8a1785d86c613bc7016c614a2c0f0046 Email: R.S.Lazic@warwick.ac.uk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at the University of Warwick and the Warwick Mathematics Institute invite applications for a full Professor post in the areas on the interface of Computer Science and Mathematics, including Discrete Mathematics, Algorithms and Complexity, Theoretical Computer Science.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/dcs/jobs/?newsItem=8a1785d86c613bc7016c614a2c0f0046">https://warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/dcs/jobs/?newsItem=8a1785d86c613bc7016c614a2c0f0046</a><br/>
Email: R.S.Lazic@warwick.ac.uk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-05T10:31:02Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-05T10:31:02Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:21:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/08/05/faculty-openings-in-computer-science-at-the-open-university-of-israel-apply-by-october-31-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/08/05/faculty-openings-in-computer-science-at-the-open-university-of-israel-apply-by-october-31-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty Openings in Computer Science at The Open University of Israel (apply by October 31, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Mathematics and Computer Science at the Open University of Israel invites applications in all areas of computer science for several senior faculty positions at all ranks (assistant professor, associate professor, professor) Website: https://www.openu.ac.il/about/departments/academic_secretary/messages/FacultyOpeningsCS.aspx Email: search@openu.ac.il</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Mathematics and Computer Science at the Open University of Israel invites applications in all areas of computer science for several senior faculty positions at all ranks (assistant professor, associate professor, professor)</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.openu.ac.il/about/departments/academic_secretary/messages/FacultyOpeningsCS.aspx">https://www.openu.ac.il/about/departments/academic_secretary/messages/FacultyOpeningsCS.aspx</a><br/>
Email: search@openu.ac.il</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-05T05:39:39Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-05T05:39:39Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:21:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=658</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2019/08/04/because-of-pollution-conferences-should-be-virtual/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Because of pollution, conferences should be virtual</title>
    <summary>Perhaps conferences made sense fifty years ago. We did not have internet, and the pollution was not as bad. Today, we can have effective virtual meetings, while the pollution has reached a level of crisis, see this moving talk by Greta_Thunberg. Moving to a system of virtual conferences is I believe a duty of every […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Perhaps conferences made sense fifty years ago. We did not have internet, and the pollution was not as bad. Today, we can have effective virtual meetings, while the pollution has reached a level of crisis, see this <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/greta_thunberg_school_strike_for_climate_save_the_world_by_changing_the_rules/transcript?language=en">moving talk by Greta_Thunberg</a>. Moving to a system of virtual conferences is I believe a duty of every scientist. Doing so will cut the significant air travel emissions that come from shipping scientists across the world. To attend a climate summit in the USofA, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/davidebanis/2019/07/29/gretha-thunberg-will-sail-across-the-atlantic-to-attend-un-climate-conferences/#27e93f87c3b2">Greta will sail across the Atlantic ocean on a zero emission boat</a><a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/greta_thunberg_school_strike_for_climate_save_the_world_by_changing_the_rules/transcript?language=en">.</a></p>
<p>We can keep everything the way it is, but simply give the talks online. This change doesn’t involve anybody higher up in the political ladder. It only involves us, the program chairs, the steering committees.</p>
<p>While we wait for that, we can begin by virtualizing the physical STOC/FOCS PC meetings,<a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2017/07/28/stocfocs-pc-meetings-does-nature-of-decisions-justify-cost/"> whose added value over a virtual meeting, if any, does not justify the cost</a>; and by holding conferences where the center of mass is, instead of exotic places where one can combine the trip with a vacation at the expense of tax payers’ money and everybody’s health. And that is also why I put a bid to hold the 2021 Conference on Computational Complexity in Boston.</p>
<p>NSF panels, making decisions worth millions, routinely have virtual panelists (I was the last few times). So why do we insist on shipping scientists across the globe multiple times a year to give 15-minute talks which to most people are less useful than spending 20 minutes reading the paper on the arxiv?</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-04T22:58:28Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-04T22:58:28Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="health"/>
    <category term="Utopia"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:21:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=17603</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/04/avi-wigdersons-integrating-computational-modeling-algorithms-and-complexity-into-theories-of-nature-marks-a-new-scientific-revolution-an-invitation-for-a-discussion/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Avi Wigderson’s: “Integrating computational modeling, algorithms, and complexity into theories of nature, marks a new scientific revolution!” (An invitation for a discussion.)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">  The cover of Avi Wigderson’s book “Mathematics and computation” as was first exposed to the public in Avi’s Knuth Prize videotaped lecture. (I had trouble with 3 of the words: What is EGDE L WONK 0?  what is GCAAG?GTAACTC … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/04/avi-wigdersons-integrating-computational-modeling-algorithms-and-complexity-into-theories-of-nature-marks-a-new-scientific-revolution-an-invitation-for-a-discussion/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/avi-book-cover.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17611" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/avi-book-cover.png?w=640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The cover of Avi Wigderson’s book “Mathematics and computation” as was first exposed to the public in <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1zxctNw-mA3hOT1tktE_dYjnmvOzZmC_A/view">Avi’s Knuth Prize videotaped lecture</a>. (I had trouble with 3 of the words: What is EGDE L WONK 0?  what is GCAAG?GTAACTC ?  TACGTTC ?  I only figured out the first.)</span></p>
<p>Avi Wigderson’s book  “<span style="color: #000000;"><a href="https://www.math.ias.edu/avi/book">Mathematics and computation, a theory revolutionizing technology and science</a>” is about to be published by Princeton University Press. The link is to a free copy of the book which will always be available on Avi’s homepage. (See also <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2017/10/27/must-read-book-by-avi-wigderson/">this re-blogged post here</a> of Boaz Barak.)</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">One main theme of the book is the rich connection between the theory of computing and other areas (in fact, most areas) of mathematics. See also this self contained survey (based on Chapter 13 of the book) by Avi <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.09780">Interactions of Computational Complexity Theory and Mathematics,</a> which in 27 pages overviews relations to number theory, Geometry, Operator Theory, Metric Geometry, Group Theory, Statistical Physics, Analysis and Probability, Lattice Theory and Invariant Theory. Of course, Avi himself is among the main heroes in finding many paths between mathematics and the theory of computing over the last four decades.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">Another theme of the book and of several talks by Avi is that the theory of computing has revolutionary connections with many fields of science and technology. Again, this theme is present in the entire book and is emphasized in Chapter 20, which also appeared as a self contained paper  “<a href="http://www.math.ias.edu/~avi/PUBLICATIONS/Wigderson2018.pdf">On the nature of the Theory of Computation (ToC).</a>”  Let me quote one sentence from Avi’s book that I propose for discussion. (For the complete quote see the end of the post.)</span></p>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<h3>The intrinsic study of computation transcends human-made artifacts, and its expanding connections and interactions with all sciences, integrating computational modeling, algorithms,  and complexity into theories of nature and society, marks a new scientific revolution!</h3>
</blockquote>
<p>Of course, <span style="color: #000000;">similar ideas were also expressed by several other prominent scientists, and let me mention Bernard Chazelle’s essay: <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~chazelle/pubs/algorithm.html">The Algorithm: Idiom of Modern Science</a>. (Feel free to give further examples and links in the comment section.)</span></p>
<h3>Let’s discuss:  Integrating computational modeling, algorithms,  and complexity into theories of nature, marks a new scientific revolution!</h3>
<p><span style="color: #000000;">I propose to discuss in the comment section the idea that the theory of computing offers a scientific revolution. Very nice cases to examine are the computational study of randomness and connections to statistics, connections with economy and connections with biology. Comments on the relations between the theory of computation and other areas of mathematics are also very welcome.</span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/avi-c-3.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17795" height="329" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/avi-c-3.png?w=640&amp;h=329" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Avi’s concluding slide compared these three great theories of human understanding.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"> (Previous attempts of open discussions were made in the following posts on this blog: </span><a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/03/26/10-milestones-in-the-history-of-mathematics-according-to-nati-and-me/" rel="bookmark">10 Milestones in the History of Mathematics according to Nati and Me</a>; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2013/05/23/why-is-mathematics-possible/" rel="bookmark">Why is mathematics possible?</a> (and a <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2013/06/19/why-is-mathematics-possible-tim-gowerss-take-on-the-matter/">follow up post</a>); <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2010/03/06/when-it-rains-it-pours/">When it rains it pours</a>;  <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/03/31/is-it-legitimate-ethical-for-google-to-close-google/" rel="bookmark">Is it Legitimate/Ethical for Google to close Google+?</a>; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2009/03/25/an-open-discussion-and-polls-around-roths-theorem/" rel="bookmark">An Open Discussion and Polls: Around Roth’s Theorem</a>; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/05/25/is-mathematics-a-science/" rel="bookmark">Is Mathematics a Science?</a>)</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/avi-c3.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17640" height="317" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/avi-c3.png?w=640&amp;h=317" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Avi promotes the idea of the central place of the theory of computing in his talks and writings</span><span id="more-17603"/></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/avi-c2.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17639" height="229" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/avi-c2.png?w=640&amp;h=229" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">And at the same time he is also humorously skeptical about it. (And mainly emphasizes that his far reaching claim requires careful discussion and ample evidence.)   </span></p>
<p> </p>
<h3>The full quote of Avi:</h3>
<blockquote><p><em>The Theory of Computation is as revolutionary, fundamental and beautiful as major theories of mathematics, physics, biology, economics… that are regularly hailed as such. Its impact has been similarly staggering. The mysteries still baffling ToC are as challenging as those left open in other fields. And quite uniquely, the theory of computation is central to most other sciences. In creating the theoretical foundations of computing systems ToC has already played, and continues to play a major part in one of the greatest scientific and technological revolutions in human history. But the intrinsic study of computation transcends man-made artifacts. ToC has already established itself as an important mathematical discipline, with growing connections to nearly all mathematical areas. And its expanding connections and interactions with all sciences, naturally integrating computational modeling, algorithms and complexity into theories of nature and society, marks the beginning of another scientific revolution!</em></p></blockquote>
<h3>More related material:</h3>
<ol>
<li>Avi’s talk <a href="https://youtu.be/Z4nhNbpx_u0">Scientific revolutions, ToC and PCP</a>  at the Tel Aviv PCP meeting and an <a href="https://youtu.be/-GQnK6ys6C0">interview of Avi by Alon Rosen</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://video.ias.edu/csdm/stepanov"> A talk by Avi on the Stepanov method</a></li>
<li>The recent works on polytopes arising from moment maps and related optimization problems and algorithmic aspects.  <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1zxctNw-mA3hOT1tktE_dYjnmvOzZmC_A/view">Avi’s Knuth prize videotaped lecture</a>; Avi’s lecture  <a href="http://www.fields.utoronto.ca/talks/Complexity-Optimization-and-Math-or-Can-we-prove-P-NP-gradient-descent">Complexity, Optimization and Math (or, Can we prove that P != NP by gradient descent?)</a> in the recent conference honoring Bill Cook. (I plan to come back to this fascinating topic.)</li>
<li><span style="color: #000000;">An essay by Oded Goldreich and Avi Wigderson (essentially from 1996) <a href="http://www.wisdom.weizmann.ac.il/~oded/PDF/toc-sp2.pdf">“The theory of computing –  a scientific perspective.”</a></span></li>
</ol>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/blog-comments.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-17771" height="300" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/blog-comments.png?w=300&amp;h=300" width="300"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The volume of comments in the first decade of this blog was modest. I recently read, however, wordpress’s advice on how to reply to blog comments like a pro. </span></p>
<p>And finally, EGDE L WONK 0 is 0-knowledge.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-04T20:14:01Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-04T20:14:01Z</published>
    <category term="Academics"/>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Open discussion"/>
    <category term="Philosophy"/>
    <category term="What is Mathematics"/>
    <category term="Avi Wigderson"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:21:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1144</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1144" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for July 2019</title>
    <summary>We saw quite an activity last month, with a total of 9 papers on property testing or related areas. Let’s start with a paper on PCPs:Revisiting Alphabet Reduction in Dinur’s PCP, by Venkatesan Guruswami, Jakub Opršal, and Sai Sandeep (ECCC). As mentioned in the title, this work provides an alternate proof of one of the […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We saw quite an activity last month, with a total of 9 papers on property testing or related areas.</p>



<p>Let’s start with a paper on PCPs:<br/><strong>Revisiting Alphabet Reduction in Dinur’s PCP</strong>, by Venkatesan Guruswami, Jakub Opršal, and Sai Sandeep  (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/092/">ECCC</a>). As mentioned in the title, this work provides an alternate proof of one of the two parts of the Dinur’s PCP theorem proof. In that proof, the argument goes by alternating two main steps: (i) amplifying the soundness gap, at the price of increasing the alphabet size (and the instance size); (ii) reducing the alphabet size, at the price of increasing the  instance size. From the observation that step (i) creates some structure in the instances that can be leveraged, the authors provide an alternative construction for (ii), leading to an arguably simpler analysis of the soundness of the underlying test. A nice throwback to some of the roots of property testing.</p>



<p>Then, four papers on distribution testing:<br/><strong>Testing Mixtures of Discrete Distributions</strong>, by Maryam Aliakbarpour, Ravi Kumar, Ronitt Rubinfeld (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.03190">arXiv</a>). One of the most studied problems in distribution testing is <em>identity testing</em> (a.k.a., goodness-of-fit): given a reference distribution \(q\) over a domain of size \(n\) and i.i.d. samples from an unknown \(p\), decide between \(p=q\) and \(d_\textrm{TV}(p,q) &gt; \varepsilon\). While this is now well-understood and can be done with a strongly sublinear number of samples (namely, \(\sqrt{n})\)), the case of <em>tolerant</em> testing is much sadder: Valiant and Valiant proved that \(\Theta(n/\log n)\) samples were required for distinguishing \(d_\textrm{TV}(p,q) &lt; \varepsilon/2\) from \(d_\textrm{TV}(p,q) &gt; \varepsilon\). So, noise-tolerance is almost as hard as it gets… <em>except</em>, as this works suggests and studies, if one has some guarantees on the noise! What if the noise in the completeness case was just that \(q\) is perturbed by some (known, or available via samples as well) noise coming from a second distribution \(\eta\)? I.e., the question is now to test whether \(p\) if of the form \(\alpha q + (1-\alpha) \eta\) for some \(\alpha\in [0,1]\), or if it is \(\varepsilon\)-far from all mixtures of \(q\) and \(\eta\). The authors have various results on this question and some extensions, but the upshot is: “with structured noise, strongly sublinear sample complexity is once again possible.”<br/><strong><br/>Can Distributed Uniformity Testing Be Local?</strong>, by Uri Meir, Dor Mintzer, and Rotem Oshman (<a href="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3331613">ACM PODC Proceedings</a>). More on identity testing, specifically uniformity testing. No noise here, but another constraint: the samples are distributed. There are \(k\) players, each holding \(q\) i.i.d. samples from a distribution \(p\) over \([n]\); each can send \(\ell=1\) bit to a central referee, in a non-interactive fashion. Is \(p\) the uniform distribution, or is it \(\varepsilon\)-far from it? The authors here consider the case where \(k,n,\varepsilon\) are fixed, and prove lower bounds on the number \(q=q(k,n,\varepsilon)\) of samples each player must hold in order to perform this uniformity testing task. (Note: their lower bounds hold even in the public-randomness setting.) Motivated by the LOCAL model, they focus on 3 cases of interest, for which they obtain tight or near-tight bounds on \(q\) (in view of upper bounds from previous work of a subset of the authors): (1)  when the referee’s decision has to be the \(\textsf{AND}\) of all \(n\) bits she receives; (2) when the referee can do something more involved, and use a threshold function; and (3) when the referee can use an arbitrary function of those \(n\) messages. Underlying those lower bounds is a neat application of Boolean Fourier analysis, recasting the analysis of the standard “Paninski” lower bound instance and the player’s decision functions as a question on Boolean functions.<br/><br/><strong>Domain Compression and its Application to Randomness-Optimal  Distributed Goodness-of-Fit</strong>, by Jayadev Acharya, Clément Canonne, Yanjun Han, Ziteng Sun, and Himanshu Tyagi (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.08743">arXiv</a>,<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/098/">ECCC</a>). Remember the paper just above? Now, focus on the case (3), where the referee can use any function of the message, allow each player to send \(\ell\) bits instead of one, but give only one sample (instead of \(q\)) to each player. This becomes a setting we have talked about before on this blog (specifically, with three papers on <a href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=990">these</a> <a href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1030">three</a> <a href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1075">months</a>). Those three papers established the optimal number of player \(k\), in terms of  the domain size \(n\), the distance parameter \(\varepsilon\), and the number of bits per player \(\ell\), in both the private-coin and public-coin settings. This new work interpolates between those two extremes, and gives the tight answer to the general question: if there are \( 0\leq s \leq \log n\) bits of public randomness available, what is the optimal number of players to perform identity testing? Behind the upper bounds is a new notion of (randomness-efficient) <em>domain compression</em> they introduce: how to reduce the domain size of the probability distributions while preserving the \(\ell_1\) distances between them as much as possible?<br/><br/><strong>Towards Testing Monotonicity of Distributions Over General Posets</strong>, by Maryam Aliakbarpour, Themis Gouleakis, John Peebles, Ronitt Rubinfeld, and Anak Yodpinyanee (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.03182">arXiv</a>). Away from identity testing, let’s now consider another central question, testing <em>monotonicity</em> of distributions. Specifically, a distribution \(p\) over a given poset \((\mathcal{X}, \prec)\) is said to be monotone if \(p(x) \leq p(y)\) whenever \(x\prec y\). While the question is fully understood for the familiar case of the line \(\mathcal{X} = \{1,2,\dots,n\}\), the case of general posets is much murkier, and more or less uncharted. This paper initiates a general study of the question, improving on previously known bounds for the matching poset and Boolean hypercube, and providing several new results and techniques for the general case, to establish both upper and lower bounds on the sample complexity.</p>



<p>And now… graphs!<br/><strong>Expansion Testing using Quantum Fast-Forwarding and Seed Sets</strong>, by Simon Apers (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.02369">arXiv</a>). This paper is concerned with (bicriteria) testing of vertex expansion of a given graph \(G=(V,E)\) in the bounded-degree graph model. Loosely speaking, given a value \(\Phi\) and query access <em>(i.e., sampling a node u.a.r., querying the degree of a node, and querying the \(i\)-th neighbor of a node) </em>to a graph \(G\) with maximum degree \(d=\Theta(1)\), the goal is to distinguish between (i) \(G\) has vertex expansion at most \(\Phi\) and (ii) \(G\) is \(\varepsilon\)-far from any \(G’\) with vertex expansion at most \(\Phi^2\) <em>(simplifying and dropping some technicalities)</em>. The previous state-of-the-art was a \(\tilde{O}_{\varepsilon}(n^{1/2}/\Phi^2)\) query complexity for classical algorithms, and a \(\tilde{O}_{\varepsilon}(\min(n^{1/3}/\Phi^2),n^{1/2}/\Phi^2))\) query complexity upper bound for quantum testers. The current work improves on this by providing a \(\tilde{O}_{\varepsilon}(n^{1/3}/\Phi)\) quantum tester. Graphs expand—and so does the gap between classical and quantum testing.<br/><br/><strong>Walking Randomly, Massively, and Efficiently</strong>, by Jakub Łącki, Slobodan Mitrović, Krzysztof Onak, and Piotr Sankowski  (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.05391">arXiv</a>). One very useful primitive, in many graph property testing results and of course well beyond property testing, is the ability to perform random walks on graphs. In the case of large, distributed (or merely impractically massive) graphs, however, it is not clear how to implement this primitive efficiently. This work addresses this question in the MPC (Massive Parallel Computation) model, and shows how to perform independently, from all of the \(n\) nodes of a graph (i.e., machine), an \(\ell\)-length random walk with only \(O(\log \ell)\) rounds of communication and \(O(n^\alpha)\) space per machine, for any constant \(\alpha \in(0,1)\). This round complexity matches a known (conditional) lower bound, and thus the result is as good as it gets — further, the authors obtain such MPC algorithms for both undirected and directed graph, somehow leveraging the latter case to handle the (significantly more complicated) directed case. As an application of this efficient random walk primitive, they provide MPC property testing algorithms for both bipartiteness and vertex expansion<em> (same definition as in the paper above: vertex expansion \(\Phi\) vs. \(\varepsilon\)-far from any \(G’\) with vertex expansion \(\Phi^2\))</em> in the general graph model. (Beyond property testing, another application—the main one in the paper— is computing PageRank in both graphs and directed graphs.)<br/><strong><br/>A Lower Bound on Cycle-Finding in Sparse Digraphs</strong>, by Xi Chen, Tim Randolph, Rocco Servedio, and Timothy Sun (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.12106">arXiv</a>). In this paper, the authors tackle the problem of one-sided testing of acyclicity of directed graphs, in the bounded-degree graph model (equivalently, on the task of finding a cycle in a digraph promised to be far from acyclic). Previously, an \(\Omega(\sqrt{n})\) lower bound for this task had been shown by Bender and Ron, based on a birthday-paradox-type argument; this work improves on this hardness result, showing that \(\tilde{\Omega}(n^{5/9})\) queries are necessary. Interestingly, whether achieving any \(o(n)\) query complexity is possible remains open.<br/><br/><strong>Constant-Time Dynamic \((\Delta+1)\)-Coloring and Weight Approximation for  Minimum Spanning Forest: Dynamic Algorithms Meet Property Testing</strong>, by Monika Henzinger and Pan Peng (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.04745">arXiv</a>). Finally, the last paper covered this month is concerned with <em>dynamic graph algorithms</em>: where updates to a graph (which can be both edge additions <em>and</em> deletions) come sequentially, and the objective is to maintain, e.g., a coloring, or an approximation of some function of the graph, at any time using as little time per update. This paper advocates the use of techniques from property testing <em>(loosely speaking, as their locality and query-efficiency translates to fast update times)</em> to design better dynamic graph algorithms. It illustrates this idea by obtaining several new results, in particular an (amortized) \(O(1)\)-update-time randomized algorithm to maintain a \((\Delta+1)\)-coloring in a graph with degree bound \(\Delta\). The algorithm relies on a random ranking of the nodes which, combined with a suitable randomized update rule for recoloring a vertex when needed, ensure that the recolorings will not (with high probability) “propagate” to much. This is the first time that this idea, previously used in several testing and sublinear-time papers, is used in the context of dynamic graph algorithms—adding an edge between the two areas, hopefully only the first of many.<br/></p>



<p><em>If we missed a paper this month, or represented some result above, please mention it in the comments.</em></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-04T00:56:33Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-04T00:56:33Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Clement Canonne</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2019-08-06T23:40:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16133</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/08/02/the-electoral-college-is-it-good/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Electoral College: Is It Good?</title>
    <summary>A old unpublished result, some new published results [ Playbill ] Alexander Hamilton was a framer of the U.S. Constitution. He wrote the bulk of the Federalist Papers (FP) defending the Constitution. Today he is best known for the playbill—the musical on his life—and the bill, the US ten dollar bill. Today I thought we […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>A old unpublished result, some new published results</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/08/02/the-electoral-college-is-it-good/96902-11/" rel="attachment wp-att-16136"><img alt="" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-16136" height="300" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/96902-11.jpg?w=194&amp;h=300" width="194"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">[ Playbill ]</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Alexander Hamilton was a framer of the U.S. Constitution. He wrote the bulk of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Federalist_Papers">Federalist Papers</a> (FP) defending the Constitution. Today he is best known for the playbill—the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamilton_(musical)">musical</a> on his life—and the bill, the US ten dollar bill.</p>
<p>
Today I thought we would discuss the U.S. electoral college (EC).<br/>
<span id="more-16133"/></p>
<p>
We are in the midst of the run-up to next year’s President election. An on-going discussion is the issue of the EC. Should it be modified? Should it be replaced? Is it a good idea? </p>
<p>
So let’s recall how the EC works. Then we will look at it from a theory viewpoint. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The College </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The electoral college is how every four years we elect the President of the United States. It is not a direct popular vote. The Constitution created it as a compromise between a direct popular vote and a vote by the members of Congress. Back then, the framers of the Constitution, including Hamilton, did not trust the electorate. Hence, the rationale for the EC.</p>
<p>
Today the EC consists of 538 electors. Voters in each state pick electors, who then vote in EC for the President. Thus by high math, 270 electors are required to win. A state gets one electoral vote for each member in the House of Representatives plus two. The latter rule ensures that no state gets too few votes. It is some times called the “two-plus rule”.</p>
<p>
The arguments for the EC are distilled in FP <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federalist_No._68">No. 68</a>. Although the collaboration/authorship status of numerous FP remains unclear, Hamilton’s claim in his last testament to sole authorship of FP 68 is not seriously disputed. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federalist_No._68">Quoting</a> Wikipedia:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Entitled “The Mode of Electing the President”, No. 68 describes a perspective on the process of selecting the Chief Executive of the United States. In writing this essay, the author sought to convince the people of New York of the merits of the proposed Constitution. Number 68 is the second in a series of 11 essays discussing the powers and limitations of the Executive branch and the only one to describe the method of selecting the president. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Opponents today argue against the EC. They point out that it allows one to win without getting the most votes. This has happened in two of the last five elections, in 2000 and 2016. The EC rewards uneven allocations of campaigning to the few “swing-states”. It also gives voters in less populated states more voting power. A vote from Wyoming has over three times the influence on the EC tally as a vote from California. The battle over FP 68 has even been <a href="https://securingdemocracy.gmfus.org/hamilton-68">internationalized</a>.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> My College </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Years ago. Decades ago. Eons ago. When I was in college, I almost flunked a required one-credit course in my senior year. The course was on issues of the election that year of the President. No it did not involve Hamilton. </p>
<p>
The grade of the course was based on a term paper. Mine, which got a <img alt="{\cal D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccal+D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\cal D}"/>, was based on an argument for the EC. Thankfully, the grade was just enough to get me a pass in the course, and allow me to graduate. I did not take the course seriously—my attendance was spotty, at best.</p>
<p>
My idea was that there was an argument for the EC based on a connection with the ability to manage elections. My central thesis was: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <i>The ability to accurately predict the outcome of a Presidential election is inherently undesirable</i>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Let’s agree that we will call this the <i>Prediction Assumption</i> (PA). Predicting the outcome of elections may not be a good idea. If predictions could be accurate, then one could argue that this would allow candidates to manipulate the election. I think you could make the case that this could be a problem. Candidates would be able to manage their opinions to optimize their chances of winning the election. </p>
<p>
In any event I then proved a result that showed that given PA, one could argue that the EC was better than a popular election. Note, the usual math arguments against the EC are based on the power of individual voters. See <a href="https://www.siam.org/Portals/0/Publications/SIURO/Vol12/S01616.pdf?ver=2019-02-12-215230-620">here</a> and <a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/the-funky-math-of-the-electoral-college/">here</a> for some of their insights.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> My College Paper </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The central point of my paper was informally this:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem:</b> <em> Prediction of an election using EC is more difficult than one using the popular vote. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
A simple example should help. Imagine an election with three states: Northeast, West, and South. Let them each have one electoral vote. Clearly <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/> are needed to win. Suppose the states are arranged like this:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Northeast: Almost all for A; <p/>
</li><li>
West: Almost all for B; <p/>
</li><li>
South: Close between A and B.
</li></ul>
<p>
Then prediction requires the polling to be able to tell the outcome of the South vote. The point is:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> The smaller the number of voters in the ensemble being predicted, the more uncertain the prediction. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Ken argues that simply having a multiplicity of component elections—one in each state plus DC—also increases the uncertainty. This may happen technically just because the result is a kind of average over unequal-sized averages. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Their Papers </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Modern results in Boolean function theory actually have studied the noise sensitivity of the EC. They have studied how errors in voting can flip an election. Look at Gil Kalai’s 2010 <a href="http://www.ma.huji.ac.il/~kalai/CHAOS.pdf">paper</a>, “Noise Sensitivity And Chaos In Social Choice Theory.” He shows that majority is more stable in the presence of noise than the EC. Look at Ryan O’Donnell’s <a href="https://www.cs.cmu.edu/~odonnell/papers/analysis-survey.pdf">paper</a>, “Some Topics in Analysis of Boolean Functions.” He shows a related point that errors in EC—in a simple model—can increase the chance that errors flip the election factor of about <img alt="{5.7}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B5.7%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{5.7}"/>.</p>
<p>
Neither paper strikes me as studying whether predictions are easier with the simple majority rule than with the EC.<br/>
I believe that their new results can be used to prove the same type of theorems on prediction. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Did I deserve a better grade than a <img alt="{\cal D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccal+D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\cal D}"/>? Or should I have flunked? Should I have published something?</p>
<p>
For comparison, the college term paper which eventually became the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twenty-seventh_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution">27th Amendment</a> to the Constitution received a better grade: <img alt="{\cal C}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccal+C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\cal C}"/>. Oh well.</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-02T14:32:54Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-02T14:32:54Z</published>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="Boolean functions"/>
    <category term="Boolean sensitivity conjecture"/>
    <category term="election"/>
    <category term="electoral college"/>
    <category term="old result"/>
    <category term="predictions"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:21:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/08/01/the-mathematics-of-quantum-computation-iiashuji-israel/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/08/01/the-mathematics-of-quantum-computation-iiashuji-israel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Mathematics of Quantum Computation (IIAS@HUJI, Israel)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">December 15-19, 2019 IIAS @ Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Israel http://ias.huji.ac.il/SchoolCSE4 Registration deadline: August 23, 2019 The school will introduce TCS and math students and faculty, who are interested in the theoretical aspects of quantum computation, to the beautiful and fascinating mathematical and computational open questions in the area, starting from scratch. No prior knowledge … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/08/01/the-mathematics-of-quantum-computation-iiashuji-israel/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">The Mathematics of Quantum Computation (IIAS@HUJI, Israel)</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-01T08:19:47Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-01T08:19:47Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:22:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/07/31/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/07/31/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>A little out of order because it made more sense that way:</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A little out of order because it made more sense that way:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@jeffgerickson/102453558801250536">A triangulated polygon, from <em>Les Amusemens Mathématiques</em> by André-Joseph Mancoucke, 1749</a>. Jeff Erickson delves once again into the history of mathematics, to find what might be the first statement of the theorem that every simple polygon has a triangulation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2019/06/13/dropbox-sucks">The new Dropbox sucks</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102459317265416759"/>). At least, it does if all you want is low-fuss synchronization of files between your computers. If you want cloud backup, a <a href="https://twitter.com/sandofsky/status/1138686582859239425">resource-intensive</a> desktop app, or easy collaboration between multiple users, it might still be ok for you.</p>

    <p>After getting annoyed with Dropbox’s mission creep and bloat, I’ve started trying <a href="https://syncthing.net/">syncthing</a> as a replacement (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102500777811510032"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20466469">via</a>). It seems like a pretty good replacement, without the bells and whistles that I don’t want or need.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/2019/07/manmade-patterns-and-uncanny-shadows-photographed-from-above-by-jp-and-mike-andrews/">Abstract aerial photography by JP and Mike Andrews</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102463616656875898"/>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://sympa.inria.fr/sympa/arc/compgeom-announce/2019-07/msg00006.html">Godfried Toussaint has died</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102469388912273069"/>). Godfried “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Godfried_Toussaint">is considered to be the father of computational geometry in Canada</a>”. This comes as a bit of a shock to me as he seemed healthy enough when I saw him last spring in Barbados. For more, see <a href="https://godfriedtoussaint.blogspot.com/">his memorial web site</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.chronicle.com/article/How-Should-Professors-Cite/246675">How should academics cite their transgender colleagues’ work produced under past identities?</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102478166860077268"/>).    This article has more questions than answers but the advice at the end (when in doubt, ask them what they prefer) seems like a good idea.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://archive.org/details/LesElementsDeLArtArabeBourgoin/page/n1">Les Éléments de l’Art Arabe</a></em> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102482369062908993"/>, <a href="https://www.metafilter.com/181967/geometry-and-ornament-in-Islamic-architecture">via</a>). Lots of plates of pretty geometric girih patterns, from an 1879 book by Jules Bourgoin.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.respol.2018.04.013">A walk on the wild side: Predatory journals and information asymmetries in scientific evaluations</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102489353679943016"/>, <a href="https://ideas.repec.org/a/eee/respol/v48y2019i2p462-477.html">non-paywalled version</a>, <a href="https://www.openaccessrepository.it/record/23448">talk slides</a>). A study of which Italian researchers use predatory journals, why, and how prevalent they are. One conclusion surprised me: 40% of Scopus-listed journals show symptoms of being predatory. See also <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Academic_Journals/Journals_cited_by_Wikipedia/Questionable1">a list of dubious journals aimed at helping Wikipedia editors identify bad sources</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/07/09/imre-barany-limit-shape/">Limit shapes and affine perimeters</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102495315622469118"/>), guest post on Gil Kalai’s blog by Imre Bárány. The affine perimeter of a convex curve is an affine-equivariant number in units of length, zero for polygons and larger for smooth curves. And the limit shape of a convex set is what you get by taking a uniformly random convex subset of a grid within the set, in the limit as the grid becomes very fine; it turns out to be the max-affine-perimeter curve contained in the set.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://blog.bonnieeisenman.com/projects/clojure-puzzles/">Voronoi diagrams + irregular line segment replacement curves + Clojure + SVG + laser cutter = jigsaw puzzles</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102506299092731515"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20531861">via</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.11808">Non-concentration of the chromatic number of a random graph</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102512091234238124"/>, <a href="ttps://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/06/28/another-sensation-annika-heckel-non-concentration-of-the-chromatic-number-of-a-random-graph/">via</a>).
<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02579208">Shamir &amp; Spencer ‘87</a> and <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/10.1007/BF01215914">Alon &amp; Krivelevich ‘97</a> proved that random graphs  with  have almost surely only two possible chromatic numbers. But now Annika Heckel has shown that dense random graphs have a significantly wider spread in colors.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://medium.com/open-glam/the-great-wave-what-hokusais-masterpiece-tells-us-about-museums-copyright-and-online-da0f25bd4ed2">The Great Wave: what Hokusai’s masterpiece tells us about museums, copyright and online collections today</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102516638326312168"/>, <a href="https://www.metafilter.com/182234/The-Great-Save">via</a>). An interesting comparison of different museum policies on re-use of images of their artworks, and availability of high-resolution images, when the art itself is old enough to be out of copyright but photos of the art might still be copyrighted depending on different national laws. The Library of Congress and Rijksmuseum get high marks.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.mathamaze.co.uk/artwork/">Helena Verrill’s mathematical/geometric art</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102534506175667851"/>), mostly involving arrangements of circles.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.13086">Atomic embeddability, clustered planarity, and thickenability</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102537368093048271"/>). Rado Fulek and Csaba Tóth announce a polynomial time algorithm for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clustered_planarity">clustered planarity</a> (given a graph and a hierarchical clustering of its vertices, draw the graph planarly with clusters as simple closed curves and no unnecessary cluster-edge crossings). If this holds up, it’s big: the problem has been open since 1995 and a lot of people have worked on it with only modest progress until now.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-31T23:16:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-31T23:16:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-08-01T06:42:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=17714</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/01/an-interview-with-noga-alon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An interview with Noga Alon</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Update: and here is a great interview of Noga in English and the interviewer is Narkis Alon, Noga’s youngest daughter and Amalya Duek. I was very happy to interview my academic doctoral  twin and long-time friend Noga Alon.  The interview … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/01/an-interview-with-noga-alon/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><strong>Update</strong>: and here is a <a href="http://www.careeryoga.life/440ebcdf?fbclid=IwAR2BWeyMdhTg2fbdHp5U-D9gCy2oqLZBk2ljRBMhjtyAEtSgqBCt7kMlSFk">great interview</a> of Noga in English and the interviewer is Narkis Alon, Noga’s youngest daughter and Amalya Duek.</p>
<p>I was very happy to interview my academic doctoral  twin and long-time friend Noga Alon.  <a href="https://youtu.be/9PhckP9eJhg">The interview</a> is an initiative of the Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities. (This is my second interview of this kind. See <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2018/06/15/an-interview-with-yisrael-robert-aumann/">here</a> for an interview with Yisrael Aumann.) The interview is in Hebrew. (Update: Automatically-produced  English subtitles are available.)</p>
<p/>
<p>For our English speaking readers here is a recent <a href="https://youtu.be/rwiEiGqgetU">Numberphile video</a> with Noga.</p>
<p>We agreed in advance that most of the interview would be about mathematics, and  most of the time  we courageously (and perhaps somewhat recklessly)  tried to explain to a large audience  (starting from scratch) some of Noga’s research directions and results. We hope that people will enjoy the beauty of it even with the missing details and background.</p>
<h3>Noga’s parents, family and childhood</h3>
<p>In the first part of the  interview  Noga talked about his family, his parents, Dror and Hemda, his great uncle <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yigal_Allon">Yigal Alon</a>, his early childhood, and his early interest in mathematics. Noga liked to solve mathematical riddles from a young age. One reason Noga was drawn to mathematics is that unlike other topics, in mathematics there are absolute truths, and a mathematical proof (when such exists)  is perhaps the only way you can settle a debate. Noga gave an amusing example from his youth regarding the Eurovision song context. Then he mentioned the <a href="https://www.reali.org.il/en/%d7%9e%d7%90%d7%94-%d7%a9%d7%a0%d7%95%d7%aa-%d7%a8%d7%99%d7%90%d7%9c%d7%99/">Hebrew Reali school in Haifa</a>, a mathematics teacher there, Yaakov Kaplan,  newly immigrated from the former Soviet Union, who greatly influenced Noga. Noga also talked about his participation in the Israeli Mathematical Olympiad where the two of us first met 45 years ago.  Next, the two of us met during our military service, and in parallel to his service, Noga finished his M. Sc. and Ph. D with Micha A. Perles, who was also my supervisor.</p>
<h3>An hour of mathematics</h3>
<p>The mathematical part of the video starts with Noga’s  overview of combinatorics. Then we moved to specific topics.</p>
<p>(22:40- 33:30) Noga’s negative solution to Shannon’s conjecture about the capacity of two graphs (and a little about Claude Shannon and information theory)</p>
<p>(33:30- 40:25) The combinatorial nullstellensatz and the polynomial method and a little about the game SET</p>
<p>(40:25 – 46:50) The probabilistic method and a little on the history of probability and about Paul Erdos.</p>
<p>(46:50-  54:50)  Streaming algorithms, a topic introduced by Noga Alon, Yossi Matias, and Mario Szegedy, and more generally, about positive and negative results in computer science, and their practical applications.</p>
<p>(54:50 – 59:25)    Expander graphs and “spectroscopy of graphs”</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga1.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-17717" height="326" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga1.png?w=640&amp;h=326" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>59:25  -1:05:40 Ramsey theory</p>
<p>1:05:40-1:12:20 Factoring integers with quantum computers and with classical methods</p>
<p>1:12:00-1:20:00 Combinatorics, economics and game theory:  Noga’s theorem that large committees require a large budget!</p>
<h3>Going back from mathematics to life itself</h3>
<p>After a full hour of mathematics, we returned to life itself. Memories from our years as postdocs at MIT, and our 1993 conference in Jerusalem. Noga talked a little about women in science and in society, about his three daughters, about  the possibility that science, like sport,  can bridge different groups and different peoples, and about politics and prospects for better relations with our Arab neighbors and Iran (Noga is somewhat optimistic and so am I),  prospects about getting old (we are hopeful about it), and advice to young researchers. Noga’s message at the end was that there are many paths to mathematical research and he encouraged young people that like mathematics to follow and enjoy them.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/alon-ramsey1.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-17740" height="266" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/alon-ramsey1.png?w=300&amp;h=266" width="300"/>  </a><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/alon-ramsey2.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-17737" height="275" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/alon-ramsey2.png?w=300&amp;h=275" width="300"/></a></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/alon-ramsey3.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-17738" height="204" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/alon-ramsey3.png?w=300&amp;h=204" width="300"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Ramsey theory and a conjecture by Erdos and Sos</span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/alon-prob-1.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-17743" height="272" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/alon-prob-1.png?w=640&amp;h=272" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Probability theory and the probabilistic method</span></p>
<p><span id="more-17714"/></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga3.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-17718" height="195" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga3.png?w=300&amp;h=195" width="300"/>  </a><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga2.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-17720" height="148" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga2.png?w=300&amp;h=148" width="300"/></a></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga4.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-17722" height="311" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga4.png?w=640&amp;h=311" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Pictures from our late twenties and a conversation about getting old.</span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga5.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-17723" height="186" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga5.png?w=300&amp;h=186" width="300"/>   </a><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga6.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-17725" height="154" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/07/noga6.png?w=300&amp;h=154" width="300"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Some advice to the young</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/alon-ramsey4.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-17780" height="370" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/alon-ramsey4.png?w=640&amp;h=370" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Added later: As it turns out You tube has automatic translation to English which is reasonable. It does translate “Noga” to “Venus”.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-31T21:09:15Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-31T21:09:15Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Noga Alon"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:21:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/100</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/100" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-100 |  Nonnegative rank measures and monotone algebraic branching programs | 

	Hervé Fournier, 

	Guillaume Malod, 

	Maud Szusterman, 

	Sébastien Tavenas</title>
    <summary>Inspired by Nisan's characterization of noncommutative complexity (Nisan 1991), we study different notions of nonnegative rank, associated complexity measures and their link with monotone computations. In particular we answer negatively an open question of Nisan asking whether nonnegative rank characterizes monotone noncommutative complexity for algebraic branching programs. We also prove a rather tight lower bound for the computation of elementary symmetric polynomials by algebraic branching programs in the monotone setting or, equivalently, in the homogeneous syntactically multilinear setting.</summary>
    <updated>2019-07-31T16:19:30Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-31T16:19:30Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:20:57Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/?p=5424</id>
    <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/2019/07/31/updates/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Updates</title>
    <summary>I did not post anything for almost five months – life has been very busy lately! I hope to get back to posting regularly relatively soon. In the meantime, I wanted to at least have a brief updates post. I just made a revision of my book about incidences and polynomial methods. Joshua Zahl and […]</summary>
    <updated>2019-07-31T02:25:50Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-31T02:25:50Z</published>
    <category term="Incidences"/>
    <category term="Math events"/>
    <author>
      <name>Adam Sheffer</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Discrete geometry and other typos</subtitle>
      <title>Some Plane Truths</title>
      <updated>2019-08-07T16:22:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4278</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4278" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4278#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4278" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Links, proofs, talks, jokes</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">For those who haven’t yet seen it, Erica Klarreich has a wonderful article in Quanta on Hao Huang’s proof of the Sensitivity Conjecture. This is how good popular writing about math can be. Klarreich quotes my line from this blog, “I find it hard to imagine that even God knows how to prove the Sensitivity […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>For those who haven’t yet seen it, Erica Klarreich has a <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematician-solves-computer-science-conjecture-in-two-pages-20190725/">wonderful article in </a><em><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematician-solves-computer-science-conjecture-in-two-pages-20190725/">Quanta</a></em> on Hao Huang’s proof of the Sensitivity Conjecture.  <em>This</em> is how good popular writing about math can be.</p>



<p>Klarreich quotes my line from this blog, “I find it hard to imagine that even God knows how to prove the Sensitivity Conjecture in any simpler way than this.”  However, even if God doesn’t know a simpler proof, that of course doesn’t rule out the possibility that <strong>Don Knuth</strong> does!  And indeed, a couple days ago Knuth posted <a href="https://www.cs.stanford.edu/~knuth/papers/huang.pdf">his own variant of Huang’s proof</a> on his homepage—in Knuth’s words, fleshing out the <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4229#comment-1813084">argument</a> that Shalev Ben-David previously posted on this blog—and then left a <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4229#comment-1815290">comment</a> about it here, the first comment by Knuth that I know about on this blog or any other blog.  I’m honored—although as for whether the variants that avoid the Cauchy Interlacing Theorem are actually “simpler,” I guess I’ll leave that between Huang, Ben-David, Knuth, and God.</p>



<p>In <em>Communications of the ACM</em>, Samuel Greengard has a <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2019/8/238339-the-algorithm-that-changed-quantum-machine-learning/fulltext?mobile=false">good, detailed article</a> on Ewin Tang and her dequantization of the quantum recommendation systems algorithm.  One warning (with thanks to commenter Ted): the sentence “The only known provable separation theorem between quantum and classical is sqrt(<em>n</em>) vs. <em>n</em>” is mistaken, though it gestures in the direction of a truth.  In the <em>black-box</em> setting, we can rigorously prove all sorts of separations: sqrt(<em>n</em>) vs. <em>n</em> (for Grover search), exponential (for period-finding), and more.  In the non-black-box setting, we can’t prove any such separations at all.</p>



<p>Last week I returned to the US from the <a href="https://fqxi.org/conference/home/2019">FQXi meeting</a> in the Tuscan countryside.  This year’s theme was “Mind Matters: Intelligence and Agency in the Physical World.”  I gave a talk entitled “The Search for Physical Correlates of Consciousness: Lessons from the Failure of Integrated Information Theory” (<a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/talks/iitfail.ppt">PowerPoint slides here</a>), which reprised my <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=1799">blog</a> <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=1823">posts</a> critical of IIT from five years ago.  There were thought-provoking talks by many others who might be known to readers of this blog, including Sean Carroll, David Chalmers, Max Tegmark, Seth Lloyd, Carlo Rovelli, Karl Friston … you can see the full schedule <a href="https://fqxi.org/conference/schedule/2019">here</a>.  Apparently video of the talks is not available yet but will be soon.</p>



<p>Let me close this post by sharing two important new insights about quantum mechanics that emerged from my conversations at the FQXi meeting:</p>



<p>(1) In Hilbert space, no one can hear you scream. Unless, that is, you scream the exact same way everywhere, or unless you split into separate copies, one for each different way of screaming.</p>



<p>(2) It’s true that, as a matter of logic, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schr%C3%B6dinger_equation">Schrödinger equation</a> does not imply the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Born_rule">Born Rule</a>.  Having said that, if the Schrödinger equation were leading a rally, and the crowd started a chant of “BORN RULE! BORN RULE! BORN RULE!”—the Schrödinger equation would just smile and wait 13 seconds for the chant to die down before continuing.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-07-30T14:15:03Z</updated>
    <published>2019-07-30T14:15:03Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-07-31T11:08:23Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
