<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-06-12T04:22:10Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06618</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06618" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>CoinPress: Practical Private Mean and Covariance Estimation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591920000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Sourav Biswas, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dong:Yihe.html">Yihe Dong</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kamath:Gautam.html">Gautam Kamath</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/u/Ullman:Jonathan.html">Jonathan Ullman</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.06618">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present simple differentially private estimators for the mean and
covariance of multivariate sub-Gaussian data that are accurate at small sample
sizes. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our algorithms both theoretically
and empirically using synthetic and real-world datasets---showing that their
asymptotic error rates match the state-of-the-art theoretical bounds, and that
they concretely outperform all previous methods. Specifically, previous
estimators either have weak empirical accuracy at small sample sizes, perform
poorly for multivariate data, or require the user to provide strong a priori
estimates for the parameters.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-12T01:29:19Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06566</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06566" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimally Deceiving a Learning Leader in Stackelberg Games</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591920000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Birmpas:Georgios.html">Georgios Birmpas</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gan:Jiarui.html">Jiarui Gan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hollender:Alexandros.html">Alexandros Hollender</a>, Francisco J. Marmolejo-Cossío, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rajgopal:Ninad.html">Ninad Rajgopal</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Voudouris:Alexandros_A=.html">Alexandros A. Voudouris</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.06566">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Recent results in the ML community have revealed that learning algorithms
used to compute the optimal strategy for the leader to commit to in a
Stackelberg game, are susceptible to manipulation by the follower. Such a
learning algorithm operates by querying the best responses or the payoffs of
the follower, who consequently can deceive the algorithm by responding as if
his payoffs were much different than what they actually are. For this strategic
behavior to be successful, the main challenge faced by the follower is to
pinpoint the payoffs that would make the learning algorithm compute a
commitment so that best responding to it maximizes the follower's utility,
according to his true payoffs. While this problem has been considered before,
the related literature only focused on the simplified scenario in which the
payoff space is finite, thus leaving the general version of the problem
unanswered. In this paper, we fill in this gap, by showing that it is always
possible for the follower to compute (near-)optimal payoffs for various
scenarios about the learning interaction between leader and follower.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-12T01:27:14Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06467</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06467" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Learning Halfspaces with Tsybakov Noise</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591920000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Diakonikolas:Ilias.html">Ilias Diakonikolas</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kontonis:Vasilis.html">Vasilis Kontonis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tzamos:Christos.html">Christos Tzamos</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zarifis:Nikos.html">Nikos Zarifis</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.06467">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the efficient PAC learnability of halfspaces in the presence of
Tsybakov noise. In the Tsybakov noise model, each label is independently
flipped with some probability which is controlled by an adversary. This noise
model significantly generalizes the Massart noise model, by allowing the
flipping probabilities to be arbitrarily close to $1/2$ for a fraction of the
samples. Our main result is the first non-trivial PAC learning algorithm for
this problem under a broad family of structured distributions -- satisfying
certain concentration and (anti-)anti-concentration properties -- including
log-concave distributions. Specifically, we given an algorithm that achieves
misclassification error $\epsilon$ with respect to the true halfspace, with
quasi-polynomial runtime dependence in $1/\epsilin$. The only previous upper
bound for this problem -- even for the special case of log-concave
distributions -- was doubly exponential in $1/\epsilon$ (and follows via the
naive reduction to agnostic learning). Our approach relies on a novel
computationally efficient procedure to certify whether a candidate solution is
near-optimal, based on semi-definite programming. We use this certificate
procedure as a black-box and turn it into an efficient learning algorithm by
searching over the space of halfspaces via online convex optimization.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-12T01:27:50Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06392</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06392" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Interpreting CNN for Low Complexity Learned Sub-pixel Motion Compensation in Video Coding</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591920000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Luka Murn, Saverio Blasi, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Smeaton:Alan_F=.html">Alan F. Smeaton</a>, Noel E. O'Connor, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mrak:Marta.html">Marta Mrak</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.06392">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Deep learning has shown great potential in image and video compression tasks.
However, it brings bit savings at the cost of significant increases in coding
complexity, which limits its potential for implementation within practical
applications. In this paper, a novel neural network-based tool is presented
which improves the interpolation of reference samples needed for fractional
precision motion compensation. Contrary to previous efforts, the proposed
approach focuses on complexity reduction achieved by interpreting the
interpolation filters learned by the networks. When the approach is implemented
in the Versatile Video Coding (VVC) test model, up to 4.5% BD-rate saving for
individual sequences is achieved compared with the baseline VVC, while the
complexity of learned interpolation is significantly reduced compared to the
application of full neural network.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-12T01:20:29Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06380</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06380" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Pointer Graph Networks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591920000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Petar Veličković, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Buesing:Lars.html">Lars Buesing</a>, Matthew C. Overlan, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pascanu:Razvan.html">Razvan Pascanu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vinyals:Oriol.html">Oriol Vinyals</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Blundell:Charles.html">Charles Blundell</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.06380">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Graph neural networks (GNNs) are typically applied to static graphs that are
assumed to be known upfront. This static input structure is often informed
purely by insight of the machine learning practitioner, and might not be
optimal for the actual task the GNN is solving. In absence of reliable domain
expertise, one might resort to inferring the latent graph structure, which is
often difficult due to the vast search space of possible graphs. Here we
introduce Pointer Graph Networks (PGNs) which augment sets or graphs with
additional inferred edges for improved model expressivity. PGNs allow each node
to dynamically point to another node, followed by message passing over these
pointers. The sparsity of this adaptable graph structure makes learning
tractable while still being sufficiently expressive to simulate complex
algorithms. Critically, the pointing mechanism is directly supervised to model
long-term sequences of operations on classical data structures, incorporating
useful structural inductive biases from theoretical computer science.
Qualitatively, we demonstrate that PGNs can learn parallelisable variants of
pointer-based data structures, namely disjoint set unions and link/cut trees.
PGNs generalise out-of-distribution to 5x larger test inputs on dynamic graph
connectivity tasks, outperforming unrestricted GNNs and Deep Sets.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-12T01:45:38Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06200</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06200" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Unsupervised Learning of 3D Point Set Registration</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591920000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wang:Lingjing.html">Lingjing Wang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Xiang.html">Xiang Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fang:Yi.html">Yi Fang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.06200">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Point cloud registration is the process of aligning a pair of point sets via
searching for a geometric transformation. Recent works leverage the power of
deep learning for registering a pair of point sets. However, unfortunately,
deep learning models often require a large number of ground truth labels for
training. Moreover, for a pair of source and target point sets, existing deep
learning mechanisms require explicitly designed encoders to extract both deep
spatial features from unstructured point clouds and their spatial correlation
representation, which is further fed to a decoder to regress the desired
geometric transformation for point set alignment. To further enhance deep
learning models for point set registration, this paper proposes Deep-3DAligner,
a novel unsupervised registration framework based on a newly introduced deep
Spatial Correlation Representation (SCR) feature. The SCR feature describes the
geometric essence of the spatial correlation between source and target point
sets in an encoding-free manner. More specifically, our method starts with
optimizing a randomly initialized latent SCR feature, which is then decoded to
a geometric transformation (i.e., rotation and translation) to align source and
target point sets. Our Deep-3DAligner jointly updates the SCR feature and
weights of the transformation decoder towards the minimization of an
unsupervised alignment loss. We conducted experiments on the ModelNet40
datasets to validate the performance of our unsupervised Deep-3DAligner for
point set registration. The results demonstrated that, even without ground
truth and any assumption of a direct correspondence between source and target
point sets for training, our proposed approach achieved comparative performance
compared to most recent supervised state-of-the-art approaches.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-12T01:47:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06171</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06171" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A General Framework for Analyzing Stochastic Dynamics in Learning Algorithms</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591920000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chou:Chi=Ning.html">Chi-Ning Chou</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wang:Mien_Brabeeba.html">Mien Brabeeba Wang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yu:Tiancheng.html">Tiancheng Yu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.06171">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a general framework for analyzing high-probability bounds for
stochastic dynamics in learning algorithms. Our framework composes standard
techniques such as a stopping time, a martingale concentration and a
closed-from solution to give a streamlined three-step recipe with a general and
flexible principle to implement it. To demonstrate the power and the
flexibility of our framework, we apply the framework on three very different
learning problems: stochastic gradient descent for strongly convex functions,
streaming principal component analysis and linear bandit with stochastic
gradient descent updates. We improve the state of the art bounds on all three
dynamics.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-12T01:45:22Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06067</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06067" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Treewidth versus clique number in graph classes with a forbidden structure</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591920000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dallard:Cl=eacute=ment.html">Clément Dallard</a>, Martin Milanič, Kenny Štorgel <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.06067">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Treewidth is an important graph invariant, relevant for both structural and
algorithmic reasons. A necessary condition for a graph class to have bounded
treewidth is the absence of large cliques. We study graph classes in which this
condition is also sufficient, which we call $(tw,\omega)$-bounded. Such graph
classes are known to have useful algorithmic applications related to variants
of the clique and $k$-coloring problems. We consider six well-known graph
containment relations: the minor, topological minor, subgraph, induced minor,
induced topological minor, and induced subgraph relations. For each of them, we
give a complete characterization of the graphs $H$ for which the class of
graphs excluding $H$ is $(tw,\omega)$-bounded. Our results imply that the class
of $1$-perfectly orientable graphs is $(tw,\omega)$-bounded, answering a
question of Bre\v{s}ar, Hartinger, Kos and Milani\v{c} from 2018. We also
reveal some further algorithmic implications of $(tw,\omega)$-boundedness
related to list $k$-coloring and clique problems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-12T01:45:14Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06052</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06052" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Accelerating linear solvers for large-scale Stokes problems with C++ metaprogramming</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591920000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Demidov:Denis.html">Denis Demidov</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mu:Lin.html">Lin Mu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wang:Bin.html">Bin Wang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.06052">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Ability to solve large sparse linear systems of equations is very important
in modern numerical methods. Creating a solver with a user-friendly interface
that can work in many specific scenarios is a challenging task. We describe the
C ++ programming techniques that can help in creating flexible and extensible
programming interfaces for linear solvers. The approach is based on
policy-based design and partial template specialization, and is implemented in
the open source AMGCL library. Convenience for the user and efficiency is
demonstrated on the example of accelerating a large-scale Stokes problem
solution with a Schur pressure correction preconditioner. The user may select
algorithmic components of the solver by adjusting template parameters without
any change to the codebase. It is also possible to switch to block values, or
use mixed precision solution, which results in up to 4 times speedup, and
reduces the memory footprint of the algorithm by about 50%.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:10Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06048</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06048" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Efficient Partial Snapshot Implementations</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591920000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kallimanis:Nikolaos_D=.html">Nikolaos D. Kallimanis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kanellou:Eleni.html">Eleni Kanellou</a>, Charidimos Kiosterakis <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.06048">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this work, we propose the $\lambda$-scanner snapshot, a variation of the
snapshot object, which supports any fixed amount of $0 &lt; \lambda \leq n$
different $SCAN$ operations being active at any given time. Whenever $\lambda$
is equal to the number of processes $n$ in the system, the $\lambda$-scanner
object implements a multi-scanner object, while in case that $\lambda$ is equal
to $1$, the $\lambda$-scanner object implements a single-scanner object. We
present the $\lambda-Snap$ snapshot object, a wait-free $\lambda$-scanner
snapshot implementation that has a step complexity of $O(\lambda)$ for $UPDATE$
operations and $O(\lambda m)$ for $SCAN$ operations. The space complexity of
$\lambda-Snap$ is $O(\lambda m)$. $\lambda-Snap$ provides a trade-off between
the step/space complexity and the maximum number of $SCAN$ operations that the
system can afford to be active on any given point in time. The low space
complexity that our implementations provide makes them more appealing in real
system applications. Moreover, we provide a slightly modified version of the
$\lambda-Snap$ implementation, which is called partial $\lambda-Snap$, that is
able to support dynamic partial scan operations. In such an object, processes
can execute modified $SCAN$ operations called $PARTIAL\_SCAN$ that could obtain
a part of the snapshot object avoiding to read the whole set of components.
</p>
<p>In this work, we first provide a simple single-scanner version of
$\lambda-Snap$, which is called $1-Snap$. We provide $1-Snap$ just for
presentation purposes, since it is simpler than $\lambda-Snap$. The $UPDATE$ in
$1-Snap$ has a step complexity of $O(1)$, while the $SCAN$ has a step
complexity of $O(m)$. This implementation uses $O(m)$ $CAS$ registers.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-12T01:29:56Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4845</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4845" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4845#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4845" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Book Review: “Will He Go?”</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Will He Go?, by legal scholar Lawrence Douglas, is, at 120 pages, a slim volume focused on a single question: what happens if the 2020 US election delivers a narrow or disputed result favoring Biden, and Trump refuses to concede? This question will, of course, either be answered or rendered irrelevant in half a year. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Will-He-Go-Election-Meltdown/dp/1538751887">Will He Go?</a>, by legal scholar Lawrence Douglas, is, at 120 pages, a slim volume focused on a single question: <em>what happens if the 2020 US election delivers a narrow or disputed result favoring Biden, and Trump refuses to concede?</em>  This question will, of course, either be answered or rendered irrelevant in half a year.  And yet, in my estimation, there’s at least a 15% probability that <em>Will He Go?</em> will enter the ranks of the most important and prescient books ever written.  You should read it right now (or at least read <a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2020/6/3/21257133/trump-2020-election-meltdown-lawrence-douglas">this Vox interview</a>), if you want to think through the contours of a civilizational Singularity that seems at least as plausible to me as the AI Singularity, but whose fixed date of November 3, 2020 we’re now hurtling toward.</p>



<p>In one of the defining memes of the past few years, a sign in a bookstore reads “Dear customers: post-apocalyptic fiction has been moved to the Current Affairs section.”  I was reminded of that as Douglas dryly lays out his horror scenario: imagine, hypothetically, that a President of the United States gets elected on a platform of racism and lies, with welcomed assistance from a foreign adversary.  Suppose that his every outrage only endears him further to his millions of followers.  Suppose that, as this president’s deepest (and perhaps only) principle, he never backs down, never apologizes, never acknowledges any inconvenient fact, and never accepts the legitimacy of any contest that he loses—and <em>this is perfectly rational for him, </em>as he’s been richly rewarded for this strategy his entire life.  Suppose that, during the final presidential debate, he pointedly refuses to promise to respect the election outcome if he loses—a first in American history.  And suppose that, after eking out a narrow win in the Electoral College, he then turns around and <em>disputes the election anyway</em> (!)—claiming, ludicrously, that he would’ve won the popular vote too, if not for millions of fraudulent voters.  Suppose that, for their own sordid reasons, Republican majorities in the Senate and Supreme Court enable this president’s chaotic rule, block his impeachment, and acquiesce to his daily cruelties and lies.</p>



<p>Then what happens in the <em>next</em> election?</p>



<p>Taking the existing catastrophe as given, Douglas asks: is America’s Constitutional machinery up to a challenge that it’s never yet faced, of a president who accepts democracy itself as legitimate only when he wins?  Douglas concludes that it isn’t—and this is the book’s terrifying and non-obvious part.  There are no checks or balances in the Constitution that will magically ensure a smooth transition of power.  On the contrary, the design flaws of our antiquated system make a meltdown <em>more</em> likely.</p>



<p>OK, but then why hasn’t America’s Reactor of Democracy exploded yet (or at least, not since the Civil War)?  Douglas spends a lot of time on historical parallels, including the Tilden-Hayes election of 1876 and the Bush-Gore election of 2000.  In each case, he finds, collapse was averted not because of mythical safeguards in our rickety, Rube-Goldberg system, but <em>only</em> because the relevant people (e.g., Samuel Tilden, Al Gore) stood down, having internalized the norm that the national good required them to.  But that’s precisely what Trump has telegraphed that he’ll never do.</p>



<p>The class of scenario that most worries Douglas runs as follows: just like last time, the election comes down to a few swing states, such as Pennsylvania, Wisconsin, and Michigan.  Crucially, right now all three of those states have Democratic governors and Republican-controlled legislatures … and <em>there’s no clear law about which of the two (the governor or the legislature) gets to certify election results and send them to Congress!</em>  So suppose Trump has a slight edge on election night, Fox News calls the race for him, but then an avalanche of absentee or provisional ballots shift things in Biden’s favor over the following week.  Can you imagine Trump or his supporters accepting the latter?</p>



<p>Or suppose that, on election day, Russian hackers cut off electricity or voter registration databases in Philadelphia or Detroit, via computer systems that <em>we know they already broke into and that remain exposed (!)</em>.  Hundreds of thousands are unable to vote; the Democratic governor orders a revote; the Republican legislature tries to preempt that by sending the original tally to Congress.</p>



<p>The final authority over election results rests with Congress.  The trouble is, the Senate is currently under Republican control and the House under Democratic control—and once again, <em>the Constitution and federal law provide no clear guidance on how to resolve a deadlock between the two on presidential succession (!!)</em>.  So what if Michigan or Pennsylvania or Wisconsin sends two separate sets of election results, and (predictably) the House accepts one and the Senate accepts the other?  And what if there’s no resolution by noon EST on January 20, 2021?  Then by law, the Speaker of the House, currently Nancy Pelosi, becomes acting president.  Can you imagine Trump willingly vacating the Oval Office if that comes to pass?</p>



<p>Douglas seems to have finished writing <em>Will He Go?</em> just as the coronavirus shut down the planet; he includes some comments about how that will massively exacerbate the above problems.  Election officials expect a historic number of absentee ballots, from people—disproportionately urban—who will (reasonably) consider it unsafe to wait in line for hours in a room packed with hundreds of strangers.  Alas, Trump has already told his followers that voting by mail is a scam to be fiercely opposed, never mind that he uses it himself.  Worse yet, the laws governing mail-in ballots—the signature, the postmark, the deadline for receipt—are byzantine, open to interpretation, and wildly different from county to county.  So again: imagine if mail-in ballots overturn what looked like a Trump win on election night.  The 2000 Florida recount battle was tea and cookies by comparison.</p>



<p>Douglas doesn’t mention, because it happened too recently, the nationwide Black Lives Matter protests (and in rarer cases, vandalism and looting) set off by the horrific murder of George Floyd, and the often shockingly militarized response.  But assuming the protests continue through the fall, they’ll of course give the Trumpists even more pretexts to meddle with the election, in the name of imposing “order.”</p>



<p>This is not a sound statistical methodology, but if I imagine a <em>gong</em> every time the US inches perceptibly closer to collapse—<em>gong</em> when Trump got elected, <em>gong</em> when covid made landfall and the states were abandoned to fight each other over medical supplies, <em>gong</em> when George Floyd was murdered and staid, conformist liberals suddenly became anarchists demanding the complete abolition of all police—well, the <em>gong</em>s seem to be getting more frequent!  Almost as if they were building toward a <em>gong</em>ularity that was, I dunno, sometime around November!</p>



<p>Douglas never mentions the prospect of a second Civil War until literally the book’s last sentence, but it’s the undercurrent of everything he writes—particularly given Trump’s frequent glorifications of violence, and his heavily armed base.  Having spent his career studying American jurisprudence, Douglas is willing to guide our imaginations all the way to the precipice but not over it.  Part of me still finds the possibility of going over unthinkable—although wasn’t the <em>first</em> Civil War similarly unthinkable until shortly before it happened?</p>



<p>If there <em>is</em> to be a Chernobyl-like meltdown of the Founding Fathers’ machine, at least it would retrospectively make sense of a lot that’s confused me in the past few years.  As I’m far from the only one to notice, “my” side, the left, has seemed less and less interested in debate and discussion, and more and more eager to denounce, ban, shame, and no-platform.  As just one example, out of hundreds that would serve, last week a 28-year-old analyst named David Shor was <a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2020/06/case-for-liberalism-tom-cotton-new-york-times-james-bennet.html">fired from his job</a> for <em>politely tweeting about an <a href="http://omarwasow.com/APSR_protests3_1.pdf">academic paper</a> offering evidence that peaceful protests are effective at winning public support for progressive, antiracist causes, while violence is ineffective</em>.  Hopefully <em>I</em> won’t now be fired for mentioning this!</p>



<p>Of course every cause has its extremists, but the puzzle is that I <em>know</em> plenty of people who will eagerly join whatever is the shaming or firing campaign du jour.  And many of those people strike me as friendly, insightful, honest, balanced, wise—at least when the topic is apolitical, as (alas) less and less seems to be these days.</p>



<p>Thought experiment: two protesters meet on a street, carrying huge signs that say “BLACK LIVES MATTER” and “ALL LIVES MATTER” respectively.  Can you imagine the following conversation ensuing: “Ah, my good fellow, it looks like you and I are allies, sharing deeply compatible moral messages with the world … one of us merely focused more on a special case, and the other on its generalization!  Shall we sit in the park to discuss our joint strategy?”</p>



<p>I guess it takes an Aspbergery STEM nerd even to <em>ask</em> why that never happens.  To spell it out: both sides are deploying English words, not for what they explicitly assert, but as markers of tribal affiliation, of <em>which side they’re on</em>.</p>



<p>It’s much the same with “Believe Women.”  “Believe <em>all</em> women, <em>always</em>?” asks our hapless STEM nerd.  “Women are goddesses who never lie?  Feminism is no longer the radical notion that women are people?”  “No, you sexist asshat,” replies the normie.  “It means listen to women, empathize with women, believe women, be on their side, be on <em>our</em> side.  What about that is so f-ing hard to understand?”</p>



<p>Or consider the slogans now conquering the world: “abolish the police” and “defund the police.”  “You mean <em>fundamentally reform</em> the police, right?” asks the STEM nerd.  “Eliminate qualified immunity, bust the unions that protect abusive cops, get rid of military gear, provide de-escalation training, stop treating homelessness and drug abuse as law enforcement problems, and all those other no-brainers?  But not, like, literally end all law enforcement, leave the 911 calls unanswered as machete-wielding rapists run free, and let gangsters and warlords fill the vacuum?”</p>



<p>“No, abolish the police means <em>abolish the police</em>,” reply the activists sternly.  “You refuse to listen.  You’re not our ally.”</p>



<p>Imagine a ragtag guerilla army encamped in the jungle, surrounded by a brutal occupying force and facing impossible odds, constantly on the alert for turncoats and spies and fair-weather friends in its midst.  Would it surprise you if these guerillas had a macabre initiation ritual for new recruits: say, slicing off the tips of recruits’ fingers?</p>



<p>Now suppose you reckoned that truth and justice were at least 3/4 on the guerillas’ side, and so decided to join them.  At your initiation, would you ask the guerillas if they’d analyzed whether finger-slicing <em>actually</em> leads to greater effectiveness in battle?  Or, as you swore the oath of eternal allegiance to the cause, with one hand on your heart and the other on your Kalashnikov, would you add: “… <em>assuming</em> that we continue to represent Enlightenment values like science, free speech, and intellectual charity”?</p>



<p>When the Nazis invaded the Soviet Union in 1941, it suddenly became reasonable to take the side of the bloodthirsty Stalin.  And it would’ve been <em>praiseworthy</em> for a Russian to say: “I now pledge my life to fighting for the Soviet government—even if, likely as not, that government will thank me afterward by sending me to the gulag for an invented crime.”</p>



<p>Five years ago, thousands of woke activists shamed me for writing about my teenage experiences on this blog, a few even calling for an end to my career.  Especially if those activists emerge victorious from a turbulent 2020—<em>as I hope they will</em>—I expect that they’ll come for me again.  (Well, if they get around to it.  I’m nowhere near the top of their list.)</p>



<p>And yet, if Lawrence Douglas’s scenario comes to pass—if, for example, the 2020 election leaves Trump barricaded in the White House with his loyalists, while a duly elected government waits in limbo—then I pledge to render whatever assistance I can, and even risk my life if needed, for the same side that the woke activists will be on.</p>



<p>I’d rather not, though.  As Douglas points out, the more overwhelming we can make Trump’s electoral defeat, the less chance that it ever comes to this.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-11T21:41:10Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-11T21:41:10Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T02:14:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05353</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05353" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>MeshWalker: Deep Mesh Understanding by Random Walks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Alon Lahav, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tal:Ayellet.html">Ayellet Tal</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.05353">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Most attempts to represent 3D shapes for deep learning have focused on
volumetric grids, multi-view images and point clouds. In this paper we look at
the most popular representation of 3D shapes in computer graphics - a
triangular mesh - and ask how it can be utilized within deep learning. The few
attempts to answer this question propose to adapt convolutions &amp; pooling to
suit Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs). This paper proposes a very different
approach, termed MeshWalker, to learn the shape directly from a given mesh. The
key idea is to represent the mesh by random walks along the surface, which
"explore" the mesh's geometry and topology. Each walk is organized as a list of
vertices, which in some manner imposes regularity on the mesh. The walk is fed
into a Recurrent Neural Network (RNN) that "remembers" the history of the walk.
We show that our approach achieves state-of-the-art results for two fundamental
shape analysis tasks: shape classification and semantic segmentation.
Furthermore, even a very small number of examples suffices for learning. This
is highly important, since large datasets of meshes are difficult to acquire.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:32:54Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05310</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05310" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Continuous Joint Replenishment Problem is Strongly NP-Hard</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tuisov:Alexander.html">Alexander Tuisov</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yedidsion:Liron.html">Liron Yedidsion</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.05310">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Continuous Periodic Joint Replenishment Problem (CPJRP) has been one of
the core and most studied problems in supply chain management for the last half
a century. Nonetheless, despite the vast effort put into studying the problem,
its complexity has eluded researchers for years. Although the CPJRP has one of
the tighter constant approximation ratio of 1.02, a polynomial optimal solution
to it was never found. Recently, the discrete version of this problem was
finally proved to be NP-hard. In this paper, we extend this result and finaly
prove that the CPJRP problem is also strongly NP-hard.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:20:31Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05104</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05104" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faster Queries on BWT-runs Compressed Indexes</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nishimoto:Takaaki.html">Takaaki Nishimoto</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tabei:Yasuo.html">Yasuo Tabei</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.05104">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Although a significant number of compressed indexes for highly repetitive
strings have been proposed thus far, developing compressed indexes that support
faster queries remains a challenge. Run-length Burrows-Wheeler transform
(RLBWT) is a lossless data compression by a reversible permutation of an input
string and run-length encoding, and it has become a popular research topic in
string processing. Recently, Gagie et al. presented r-index, an efficient
compressed index on RLBWT whose space usage does not depend on text length. In
this paper, we present a new compressed index on RLBWT, which we call
r-index-f, in which r-index is improved for faster locate queries. We introduce
a novel division of RLBWT into blocks, which we call balanced BWT-sequence as
follows: the RLBWT of a string is divided into several blocks, and a
parent-child relationship between each pair of blocks is defined. In addition,
we present a novel backward search algorithm on the balanced BWT-sequences,
resulting in faster locate queries of r-index-f. We also present new algorithms
for solving the queries of count query, extract query, decompression and prefix
search on r-index-f.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:31:17Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05084</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05084" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Reliable Detection for Spatial Modulation Systems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Al=Nahhal:Ibrahim.html">Ibrahim Al-Nahhal</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dobre:Octavia_A=.html">Octavia A. Dobre</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Ikki:Salama.html">Salama Ikki</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.05084">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Spatial modulation (SM) is a promising multiple-input multiple-output system
used to increase spectral efficiency. The maximum likelihood (ML) decoder
jointly detects the transmitted SM symbol, which is of high complexity. In this
paper, a novel reliable sphere decoder (RSD) algorithm based on tree-search is
proposed for the SM system. The basic idea of the proposed RSD algorithm is to
reduce the size of the tree-search, and then, a smart searching method inside
the reduced tree-search is performed to find the solution. The proposed RSD
algorithm provides a significant reduction in decoding complexity compared to
the ML decoder and existent decoders as well. Moreover, the RSD algorithm
provides a flexible trade-off between the bit error rate (BER) performance and
decoding complexity, so as to be reliable for a wide range of practical
hardware implementations. The BER performance and decoding complexity analysis
for the RSD algorithm are studied, and Monte Carlo simulations are then
provided to demonstrate the findings.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:22:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05051</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05051" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Constrained episodic reinforcement learning in concave-convex and knapsack settings</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Brantley:Kiant=eacute=.html">Kianté Brantley</a>, Miroslav Dudik, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lykouris:Thodoris.html">Thodoris Lykouris</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Miryoosefi:Sobhan.html">Sobhan Miryoosefi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Simchowitz:Max.html">Max Simchowitz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Slivkins:Aleksandrs.html">Aleksandrs Slivkins</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sun:Wen.html">Wen Sun</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.05051">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We propose an algorithm for tabular episodic reinforcement learning with
constraints. We provide a modular analysis with strong theoretical guarantees
for settings with concave rewards and convex constraints, and for settings with
hard constraints (knapsacks). Most of the previous work in constrained
reinforcement learning is limited to linear constraints, and the remaining work
focuses on either the feasibility question or settings with a single episode.
Our experiments demonstrate that the proposed algorithm significantly
outperforms these approaches in existing constrained episodic environments.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:31:35Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05028</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.05028" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Online Page Migration with ML Advice</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Indyk:Piotr.html">Piotr Indyk</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mallmann=Trenn:Frederik.html">Frederik Mallmann-Trenn</a>, Slobodan Mitrović, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rubinfeld:Ronitt.html">Ronitt Rubinfeld</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.05028">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider online algorithms for the {\em page migration problem} that use
predictions, potentially imperfect, to improve their performance. The best
known online algorithms for this problem, due to Westbrook'94 and Bienkowski et
al'17, have competitive ratios strictly bounded away from 1. In contrast, we
show that if the algorithm is given a prediction of the input sequence, then it
can achieve a competitive ratio that tends to $1$ as the prediction error rate
tends to $0$. Specifically, the competitive ratio is equal to $1+O(q)$, where
$q$ is the prediction error rate. We also design a ``fallback option'' that
ensures that the competitive ratio of the algorithm for {\em any} input
sequence is at most $O(1/q)$. Our result adds to the recent body of work that
uses machine learning to improve the performance of ``classic'' algorithms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:28:32Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04940</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04940" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Improved and Parallel Version of a Scalable Algorithm for Analyzing Time Series Data</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vitalis:Andreas.html">Andreas Vitalis</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.04940">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Today, very large amounts of data are produced and stored in all branches of
society including science. Mining these data meaningfully has become a
considerable challenge and is of the broadest possible interest. The size, both
in numbers of observations and dimensionality thereof, requires data mining
algorithms to possess time complexities with both variables that are linear or
nearly linear. One such algorithm, see Comput. Phys. Commun. 184, 2446-2453
(2013), arranges observations into a sequence called the progress index. The
progress index steps through distinct regions of high sampling density
sequentially. By means of suitable annotations, it allows a compact
representation of the behavior of complex systems, which is encoded in the
original data set. The only essential parameter is a notion of distance between
observations. Here, we present the shared memory parallelization of the key
step in constructing the progress index, which is the calculation of an
approximation of the minimum spanning tree of the complete graph of
observations. We demonstrate that excellent parallel efficiencies are obtained
for up to 72 logical (CPU) cores. In addition, we introduce three conceptual
advances to the algorithm that improve its controllability and the
interpretability of the progress index itself.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:31:12Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04933</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04933" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A New Integer Programming Formulation of the Graphical Traveling Salesman Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Carr:Robert_D=.html">Robert D. Carr</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Simonetti:Neil.html">Neil Simonetti</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.04933">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the Traveling Salesman Problem (TSP), a salesman wants to visit a set of
cities and return home. There is a cost $c_{ij}$ of traveling from city $i$ to
city $j$, which is the same in either direction for the Symmetric TSP. The
objective is to visit each city exactly once, minimizing total travel costs. In
the Graphical TSP, a city may be visited more than once, which may be necessary
on a sparse graph. We present a new integer programming formulation for the
Graphical TSP requiring only two classes of constraints that are either
polynomial in number or polynomially separable, while addressing an open
question proposed by Denis Naddef.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:28:21Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04880</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04880" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum Logspace Algorithm for Powering Matrices with Bounded Norm</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Girish:Uma.html">Uma Girish</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Raz:Ran.html">Ran Raz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhan:Wei.html">Wei Zhan</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.04880">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We give a quantum logspace algorithm for powering contraction matrices, that
is, matrices with spectral norm at most~1. The algorithm gets as an input an
arbitrary $n\times n$ contraction matrix $A$, and a parameter $T \leq
\mathrm{poly}(n)$ and outputs the entries of $A^T$, up to (arbitrary)
polynomially small additive error. The algorithm applies only unitary
operators, without intermediate measurements. We show various implications and
applications of this result:
</p>
<p>First, we use this algorithm to show that the class of quantum logspace
algorithms with only quantum memory and with intermediate measurements is
equivalent to the class of quantum logspace algorithms with only quantum memory
without intermediate measurements. This shows that the deferred-measurement
principle, a fundamental principle of quantum computing, applies also for
quantum logspace algorithms (without classical memory). More generally, we give
a quantum algorithm with space $O(S + \log T)$ that takes as an input the
description of a quantum algorithm with quantum space $S$ and time $T$, with
intermediate measurements (without classical memory), and simulates it
unitarily with polynomially small error, without intermediate measurements.
</p>
<p>Since unitary transformations are reversible (while measurements are
irreversible) an interesting aspect of this result is that it shows that any
quantum logspace algorithm (without classical memory) can be simulated by a
reversible quantum logspace algorithm. This proves a quantum analogue of the
result of Lange, McKenzie and Tapp that deterministic logspace is equal to
reversible logspace [LMT00].
</p>
<p>Finally, we use our results to show non-trivial classical simulations of
quantum logspace learning algorithms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:20:48Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04831</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04831" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Evaluation of Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm based on the approximation ratio of single samples</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Jason Larkin, Matías Jonsson, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Justice:Daniel.html">Daniel Justice</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Guerreschi:Gian_Giacomo.html">Gian Giacomo Guerreschi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.04831">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) is a hybrid
quantum-classical algorithm to solve binary-variable optimization problems. Due
to its expected robustness to systematic errors and the short circuit depth, it
is one of the promising candidates likely to run on near-term quantum devices.
We project the performance of QAOA applied to the Max-Cut problem and compare
it with some of the best classical alternatives, both for exact or approximate
solution. When comparing approximate solvers, their performance is
characterized by the computational time taken to achieve a given quality of
solution. Since QAOA is based on sampling, we introduce performance metrics
based on the probability of observing a sample above a certain quality. In
addition, we show that the QAOA performance varies significantly with the graph
type. By selecting a suitable optimizer for the variational parameters and
reducing the number of function evaluations, QAOA performance improves by up to
2 orders of magnitude compared to previous estimates. Especially for 3-regular
random graphs, this setting decreases the performance gap with classical
alternatives.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:27:48Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04823</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04823" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum Legendre-Fenchel Transform</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sutter:David.html">David Sutter</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nannicini:Giacomo.html">Giacomo Nannicini</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sutter:Tobias.html">Tobias Sutter</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Woerner:Stefan.html">Stefan Woerner</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.04823">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a quantum algorithm to compute the discrete Legendre-Fenchel
transform. Given access to a convex function evaluated at $N$ points, the
algorithm outputs a quantum-mechanical representation of its corresponding
discrete Legendre-Fenchel transform evaluated at $K$ points in the transformed
space. For a fixed regular discretizaton of the dual space the expected running
time scales as $O(\sqrt{\kappa}\,\mathrm{polylog}(N,K))$, where $\kappa$ is the
condition number of the function. If the discretization of the dual space is
chosen adaptively with $K$ equal to $N$, the running time reduces to
$O(\mathrm{polylog}(N))$. We explain how to extend the presented algorithm to
the multivariate setting and prove lower bounds for the query complexity,
showing that our quantum algorithm is optimal up to polylogarithmic factors.
For certain scenarios, such as computing an expectation value of an
efficiently-computable observable associated with a
Legendre-Fenchel-transformed convex function, the quantum algorithm provides an
exponential speedup compared to any classical algorithm.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:26:06Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04423</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.04423" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Condition Numbers for the Cube. I: Univariate Polynomials and Hypersurfaces</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1591833600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Josué Tonelli-Cueto), Elias Tsigaridas) <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2006.04423">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The condition-based complexity analysis framework is one of the gems of
modern numerical algebraic geometry and theoretical computer science. One of
the challenges that it poses is to expand the currently limited range of random
polynomials that we can handle. Despite important recent progress, the
available tools cannot handle random sparse polynomials and Gaussian
polynomials, that is polynomials whose coefficients are i.i.d. Gaussian random
variables. We initiate a condition-based complexity framework based on the norm
of the cube, that is a step in this direction. We present this framework for
real hypersurfaces. We demonstrate its capabilities by providing a new
probabilistic complexity analysis for the Plantinga-Vegter algorithm, which
covers both random sparse (alas a restricted sparseness structure) polynomials
and random Gaussian polynomials. We present explicit results with structured
random polynomials for problems with two or more dimensions. Additionally, we
provide some estimates of the separation bound of a univariate polynomial in
our current framework.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-06-11T23:32:48Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/06/10/postdoc-at-technion-apply-by-september-30-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/06/10/postdoc-at-technion-apply-by-september-30-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at Technion (apply by September 30, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Postdoctoral positions in distributed computing are available in the research group of Keren Censor-Hillel at the Technion. Candidates with a strong publication record in closely related areas are welcome to apply (deadline is flexible). To apply, send to Mrs. Hila Mizrahi: (1) a CV, (2) a 1-2 page research statement, (3) the contact details of […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Postdoctoral positions in distributed computing are available in the research group of Keren Censor-Hillel at the Technion. Candidates with a strong publication record in closely related areas are welcome to apply (deadline is flexible). To apply, send to Mrs. Hila Mizrahi: (1) a CV, (2) a 1-2 page research statement, (3) the contact details of 3 references, and (4) an expected graduation date.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://ckeren.net.technion.ac.il/">https://ckeren.net.technion.ac.il/</a><br/>
Email: hilamiz@cs.technion.ac.il</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-10T12:22:37Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-10T12:22:37Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:20:56Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/090</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/090" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-090 |  Tight Quantum Time-Space Tradeoffs for Function Inversion | 

	Kai-Min Chung, 

	Siyao  Guo, 

	Qipeng Liu, 

	Luowen Qian</title>
    <summary>In function inversion, we are given a function $f: [N] \mapsto [N]$, and want to prepare some advice of size $S$, such that we can efficiently invert any image in time $T$. This is a well studied problem with profound connections to cryptography, data structures, communication complexity, and circuit lower bounds. Investigation of this problem in the quantum setting was initiated by Nayebi, Aaronson, Belovs, and Trevisan (2015), who proved a lower bound of $ST^2 = \tilde\Omega(N)$ for random permutations against classical advice, leaving open an intriguing possibility that Grover's search can be sped up to time $\tilde O(\sqrt{N/S})$. Recent works by Hhan, Xagawa, and Yamakawa (2019), and Chung, Liao, and Qian (2019) extended the argument for random functions and quantum advice, but the lower bound remains $ST^2 = \tilde\Omega(N)$. 

In this work, we prove that even with quantum advice, $ST + T^2 = \tilde\Omega(N)$ is required for an algorithm to invert random functions. This demonstrates that Grover's search is optimal for $S = \tilde O(\sqrt{N})$, ruling out any substantial speed-up for Grover's search even with quantum advice. Further improvements to our bounds would imply a breakthrough in circuit lower bounds, as shown by Corrigan-Gibbs and Kogan (2019).

To prove this result, we develop a general framework for establishing quantum time-space lower bounds. We further demonstrate the power of our framework by proving the following results. 

* Yao's box problem: We prove a tight quantum time-space lower bound for classical advice. For quantum advice, we prove a first time-space lower bound using shadow tomography. These results resolve two open problems posted by Nayebi, Aaronson, Belovs, and Trevisan (2015). 

* Salted cryptography: We show that “salting generically provably defeats preprocessing,” a result shown by Coretti, Dodis, Guo, and Steinberger (2018), also holds in the quantum setting. In particular, we prove quantum time-space lower bounds for a wide class of salted cryptographic primitives in the quantum random oracle model. This yields a first quantum time-space lower bound for salted collision-finding, which in turn implies that ${PWPP}^{O} \not\subseteq {FBQP}^{O}{/qpoly}$ relative to a random oracle $O$.</summary>
    <updated>2020-06-10T06:43:41Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-10T06:43:41Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:20:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/089</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/089" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-089 |  Lower Bounds on  the Time/Memory Tradeoff of Function Inversion | 

	Dror Chawin, 

	Iftach Haitner, 

	Noam Mazor</title>
    <summary>We study time/memory tradeoffs of function inversion: an algorithm, i.e., an inverter, equipped with an $s$-bit advice for a randomly chosen function $f\colon [n] \mapsto [n]$ and using $q$ oracle queries to $f$, tries to invert a randomly chosen output $y$ of $f$ (i.e., to find $x$ such that $f(x)=y$). Much progress was done regarding adaptive function inversion - the inverter is allowed to make adaptive oracle queries. Hellman [IEEE transactions on Information Theory '80] presented an adaptive inverter that inverts with high probability a random $f$. Fiat and Naor [SICOMP '00] proved that for any $s,q$ with $s^2 q = n^2$ (ignoring low-order terms), an $s$-advice, $q$-query variant of Hellman's algorithm inverts a constant fraction of the image points of any function. Yao [STOC '90] proved a lower bound of $sq\ge n$ for  this problem. Closing the gap between the above lower and upper bounds is a long-standing open question.

Very little is known for the non-adaptive variant of the question - the inverter chooses its queries in advance. The only known upper bounds, i.e., inverters, are the trivial ones (with $s+q= n$), and the only lower bound is the above bound of Yao. In a recent work, Corrigan-Gibbs and Kogan [TCC '19] partially justified the difficulty of finding lower bounds on non-adaptive inverters, showing that a lower bound on the time/memory tradeoff of non-adaptive inverters implies a lower bound on low-depth Boolean circuits. Bounds that for a strong enough choice of parameters, are notoriously hard to prove.

We make progress on the above intriguing question, both for the adaptive and the non-adaptive case, proving the following lower bounds on restricted families of inverters:

	- Linear-advice (adaptive inverter): If the advice string is a linear function of $f$ (e.g., $A\times f$, viewing $f$ as  a vector in $[n]^n$), then $s+q \in \Omega(n)$.
	
	- Affine non-adaptive decoders: If the non-adaptive inverter has an affine decoder - it outputs a linear function, determined by the advice string and the element to invert, of the query answers - then $s \in \Omega(n)$ (regardless of $q$).
	
	- Affine non-adaptive decision trees: If the non-adaptive inversion algorithm is a $d$-depth affine decision tree - it outputs the evaluation of a decision tree whose nodes compute a linear function of the answers to the queries - and $q \le cn$ for some universal $c&gt;0$, then $s\in \Omega(n/d \log n)$.</summary>
    <updated>2020-06-09T13:19:02Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-09T13:19:02Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:20:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/088</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/088" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-088 |  Eliminating Intermediate Measurements in Space-Bounded Quantum Computation | 

	Bill Fefferman, 

	Zachary Remscrim</title>
    <summary>A foundational result in the theory of quantum computation known as the ``principle of safe storage'' shows that it is always possible to take a quantum circuit and produce an equivalent circuit that makes all measurements at the end of the computation.  While this procedure is time efficient, meaning that it does not introduce a large overhead in the number of gates, it uses extra ancillary qubits and so is not generally space efficient.  It is quite natural to ask whether it is possible to defer measurements to the end of a quantum computation without increasing the number of ancillary qubits.
		
		We give an affirmative answer to this question by exhibiting a procedure to eliminate all intermediate measurements that is simultaneously space-efficient and time-efficient. A key component of our approach, which may be of independent interest, involves showing that the well-conditioned versions of many standard linear-algebraic problems may be solved by a quantum computer in less space than seems possible by a classical computer.</summary>
    <updated>2020-06-08T21:24:06Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-08T21:24:06Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:20:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/087</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/087" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-087 |  Quantum Logspace Algorithm for Powering Matrices with Bounded Norm | 

	Uma Girish, 

	Ran Raz, 

	Wei Zhan</title>
    <summary>We give a quantum logspace algorithm for powering contraction matrices, that is, matrices with spectral norm at most 1. The algorithm gets as an input an arbitrary $n\times n$ contraction matrix $A$, and a parameter $T \leq poly(n)$ and outputs the entries of $A^T$, up to (arbitrary) polynomially small additive error. The algorithm applies only unitary operators, without intermediate measurements. We show various implications and applications of this result:

First, we use this algorithm to show that the class of quantum logspace algorithms with only quantum memory and with intermediate measurements is equivalent to the class of quantum logspace algorithms with only quantum memory without intermediate measurements. This shows that the deferred-measurement principle, a fundamental principle of quantum computing, applies also for quantum logspace algorithms (without classical memory). More generally, we give a quantum algorithm with space $O(S + \log T)$ that takes as an input the description of a quantum algorithm with quantum space $S$ and time $T$, with intermediate measurements (without classical memory), and simulates it unitarily with polynomially small error, without intermediate measurements.

Since unitary transformations are reversible (while measurements are irreversible) an interesting aspect of this result is that it shows that any quantum logspace algorithm (without classical memory) can be simulated by a reversible quantum logspace algorithm. This proves a quantum analogue of the result of Lange, McKenzie and Tapp that deterministic logspace is equal to reversible logspace.

Finally, we use our results to show non-trivial classical simulations of quantum logspace learning algorithms.</summary>
    <updated>2020-06-08T18:51:13Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-08T18:51:13Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:20:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-9046421052819875987</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/9046421052819875987/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/06/the-committee-for-adv-of-tcs-workshop.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/9046421052819875987" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/9046421052819875987" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/06/the-committee-for-adv-of-tcs-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Committee for the Adv. of TCS- workshop coming up SOON!</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><span id="docs-internal-guid-06a8f4c9-7fff-916b-0154-0d4b08969907"/><br/>
<div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span id="docs-internal-guid-06a8f4c9-7fff-916b-0154-0d4b08969907"><span>(Posted by request from Jelani Nelson.)</span></span></div>
<span id="docs-internal-guid-06a8f4c9-7fff-916b-0154-0d4b08969907"><br/><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>The Committee for the Advancement of Theoretical Computer Science (CATCS)</span></div>
<div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>is organizing a Visioning workshop.  The primary objective of the workshop</span></div>
<div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>is for TCS participants to brainstorm directions and talking points for TCS</span></div>
<div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>program managers at funding agencies to advocate for theory funding.</span></div>
<br/><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>There was some question of whether or not it would run this summer, but</span></div>
<div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>YES, it is going to run.</span></div>
<br/><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>If you are interested then reply (at the link below) by June 15.</span></div>
<div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>This is SOON so click that link SOON.</span></div>
<br/><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>The time commitment is 4-5 hours during the week of July 20-July 24 for</span></div>
<div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>most participants, or roughly 10 hours for those who are willing to</span></div>
<div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>volunteer to be group leaders.</span></div>
<br/><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span>The link to sign up is:</span></div>
<br/><div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<span><a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2020/06/05/tcs-visioning-workshop-call-for-participation/">https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2020/06/05/tcs-visioning-workshop-call-for-participation/</a></span></div>
<div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<br/></div>
<div dir="ltr" style="line-height: 1.38; margin-bottom: 0pt; margin-top: 0pt;">
<br/></div>
</span></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-08T15:03:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-08T15:03:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T08:14:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4392</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/06/08/visioning-workshop-call-for-participation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>“Visioning” workshop call for participation</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2008, the Committee for the Advancement of Theoretical Computer Science convened a workshop to brainstorm directions and talking points for TCS program managers at funding agencies to advocate for theory funding. The event was quite productive and successful. A … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/06/08/visioning-workshop-call-for-participation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In 2008, the <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/catcs/">Committee for the Advancement of Theoretical Computer Science</a> convened a workshop to brainstorm directions and talking points for TCS<br/>
program managers at funding agencies to advocate for theory funding. The event was quite productive and successful. </p>
<p>A second such workshop is going to be held, online, in the third week of July. Applications to participate are due on June 15, a week from today. Organizers expect that participants will have to devote about four hours of their time to the workshop, and those who volunteer to be team leads will have a time commitment of about ten hours.</p>
<p>More information <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2020/06/05/tcs-visioning-workshop-call-for-participation/">at this link</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-08T09:38:07Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-08T09:38:07Z</published>
    <category term="theory"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:20:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1343</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1343" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Welcome Akash Kumar!</title>
    <summary>Let’s welcome our latest editor, Akash Kumar. Akash will be taking the place of Gautam Kamath, who has decided to pass the torch on. Let’s also thank Gautam for all the help with PTReview.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Let’s welcome our latest editor, Akash Kumar. Akash will be taking the place of Gautam Kamath, who has decided to pass the torch on. Let’s also thank Gautam for all the help with PTReview.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-08T03:29:36Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-08T03:29:36Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Seshadhri</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T23:35:18Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1315</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1315" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for May 2020</title>
    <summary>Last month saw activity across a diverse collection of topics in sublinear algorithms. In particular, we had the following five six papers. (Sorry, I missed one) One-Sided Error Testing of Monomials and Affine Subspaces by Oded Goldreich and Dana Ron (ECCC). This work focuses on one-sided testing of two kinds of problems (and their variants): […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Last month saw activity across a diverse collection of topics in sublinear algorithms. In particular, we had the following <s>five</s> six papers. <em>(Sorry, I missed one)</em> </p>



<p><strong>One-Sided Error Testing of Monomials and Affine Subspaces</strong> by Oded Goldreich and Dana Ron (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/068/">ECCC</a>). This work focuses on one-sided testing of two kinds of problems (and their variants): <br/><span class="has-inline-color has-blue-color">1.</span> Testing Monomials: Suppose you are given a function \(f \colon \{0,1\}^n \to \{0,1\}\). Is \(f = \wedge_{i \in I} x_i\) (that is, is \(f\) a monotone monomial). <br/><span class="has-inline-color has-blue-color">2.</span> Testing Affine Subspaces: Consider the task of testing whether a \(f \colon \mathcal{F}^n \to \{0,1\}\) is the indicator of an \((n-k)\)-dimensional affine space for some \(k\) (where \(\mathcal{F}\) is a finite field).<br/></p>



<p>The paper shows that the general problem — the one in which the arity of the monomial (resp the co-dimension of the subspace) is not specified has one-sided query complexity \(\widetilde{O}(1/\varepsilon)\). The same holds for testing whether the arity of the monomial is at most \(k\) (resp the co-dimension of the subspace is at most \(k\)). Finally, the exact problem which seeks to test whether the arity of the monomial is exactly \(k\) (resp the co-dimension of the space is exactly \(k\)) has query complexity \(\Omega(\log n)\). For two sided testers however, size oblivious testers are known for this problem. Thus, like the authors remark, two-sided error is inherent in the case of the exact version of the problem.</p>



<p/>



<p><strong>Sampling Arbitrary Subgraphs Exactly Uniformly in Sublinear Time</strong> by Hendrik Fichtenberger, Mingze Gao, Pan Peng (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.01861v2">arXiv</a>). Readers of PT Review are no strangers to the problem of counting cliques in sublinear time (with a certain query model). Building on tools from [1], in [2], Eden-Ron-Seshadhri gave the first algorithms for counting number of copies \(K_r\) in a graph \(G\) to within a \((1 \pm \varepsilon)\) multiplicative factor. En route to this result, they also gave a procedure to sample cliques incident to some special set \(S \subseteq V(G)\). The query model in [2] allowed the following queries: a u.a.r vertex query, degree query, \(i^{th}\) neighbor query and a pair query which answers whether a pair \((u,v)\) forms an edge. The work under consideration shows a result which I personally find remarkable: given the additional ability to get a u.a.r edge sample, we can do the following. For any graph \(H\) we can obtain a uniformly random subgraph isomorphic to \(H\) in \(G\). Let that sink in: this work shows that you can sample \(H\) <em>exactly uniformly</em> from the graph \(G\).  </p>



<p><strong>Finding Planted Cliques in Sublinear Time</strong> by Jay Mardia, Hilal Asi, Kabir Aladin Chandrasekher (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.12002">arXiv</a>). Planted Clique is a time honored problem in average case complexity. This classic problem asks the following: You are given a \(G \sim \mathcal{G}(n, 1/2)\). Suppose I select a subset of \(k\) vertices in this graph and put a clique on the subgraph they induce. In principle it is possible to recover the clique I planted if \(k &gt; (2 + \varepsilon) \log n\). But it seems you get polynomial time algorithms only when \(k \geq \Omega(\sqrt n)\) even after you throw SDPs at the problem. Moreover, so far, the algorithms which recover the planted \(k\)-clique were known to take \(\widetilde{O}(n^2)\) time. This work shows that you actually get algorithms which take time \(\widetilde{O}(n^{3/2})\) if \(k \geq \Omega(\sqrt{n \log n})\). The key idea is to first obtain a “core” part of the clique of size \(O(\log n)\) in time \(\widetilde{O}(n^2/k)\). This is followed up with a clique completion routine where you mark all vertices connected to the entire core as being potentially in the clique. The paper also shows a conditional lower bound result which shows that given query access to adjacency matrix of the graph, a natural family of non-adaptive algorithms cannot recover a planted \(k\) clique in time \(o\left(\frac{n}{k}\right)^3\) (for \(k \geq \widetilde{\Omega}(\sqrt n))\).</p>



<p><strong>A robust multi-dimensional sparse Fourier transform in the continuous setting</strong> by Yaonan Jin, Daogao Liu and Zhao Song (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.06156">arXiv</a>).  Suppose you are given an unknown signal whose Fourier Spectrum is k-sparse (that is, there are at most k dominant Fourier Coefficients and all the others are zero or close to zero). Significant research effort has been devoted to learn these signals leading to works which study this problem for multi-dimensional discrete setting and in the one-dimensional continuous case. The \(d\)-dimensional continuous case \((d = \Theta(1))\) was largely unexplored. This work makes progress on this frontier by making some natural assumptions on the unknown signal. In particular, the paper assumes that the frequencies — which are vectors \(f_i’s \in R^d\) — are well separated and satisfy \(\|f_i – f_j\|_2 \leq \eta\) and that all \({f_i}_{i \in [k]} \subseteq [-F, F]^d\) sit inside a bounded box.<br/>The authors assume sample access to the signal in the sense that at any desired timestep \(\tau\), the algorithm can sample the signal’s value. With this setup, the authors show that all the dominant frequencies can be recovered with a \(O_d(k \cdot \log(F/\eta))\) samples by considering a relatively small time horizon.</p>



<p><strong>Extrapolating the profile of a finite population</strong> by Soham Jana, Yury Polyanskiy, Yihong Wu (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.10561">arXiv</a>). Consider the following setup. You are given a universe \(k\) balls. Ball come in up to \(k\) different colors. Say you \(\theta_j\) balls in color \(j\) for each \(j \in [k]\). One of the fundamental problems in statistics considers taking samples \(m\) balls from the universe and attempts estimating “population profile” (that is, the number of balls in each color). Historically, it is known that unless an overwhelming majority of the universe has been seen, one cannot estimate the empirical distribution of colors. This paper shows that in the sublinear regime, with \(m \geq \omega(k/\log k)\), it is possible to consistently estimate the population profile in total variation. And once you have a handle on the empirical distribution of the population, you can go ahead and learn lots of interesting label invariant properties of your universe (things like entropy, number of distinct elements etc). </p>



<p/>



<p><em>(Edit added later)</em></p>



<p><strong>Testing Positive Semi-Definiteness via Random Submatrices</strong> by Ainesh Bakshi, Nadiia Chepurko, Rajesh Jayaram (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.06441">arXiv</a>). Suppose I give you a PSD matrix \(A \in R^{n \times n}\). You know that all of its principle submatrices are also PSD. What if \(A\) was \(\varepsilon\)-far from the PSD cone (in a sense I will define soon)? What can you say about the eigenvalues of principle submatrices of \(A\) now? In this paper, the authors tackle precisely this question. The paper defines a matrix \(A\) to be \(\varepsilon\)-far in \(\ell_2^2\) distance from the PSD Cone if you have that \(\min_{B \geq 0: B \in R^{n \times n}}\|A – B\|_F^2 \geq \varepsilon n^2\). You are allowed to randomly sample a bunch of principle submatrices (of order roughly \(O(1/\varepsilon)\) by \(O(1/\varepsilon)\) and check if they are PSD. Armed with this setup, the paper gives a non-adaptive one sided tester for this problem which makes \(\widetilde{O}(1/\varepsilon^4)\) queries. The paper also supplements this result with a lower bound of \(\widetilde{\Omega}(1/\varepsilon^2)\) queries.</p>



<p>If I missed something, please let me know. This is my first post on PT Review and I might have botched up a few things.</p>



<p><strong>References</strong></p>



<p>[1] Talya Eden, Amit Levi, Dana Ron and C. Seshadhri. Approximately Counting Triangles in Sublinear Time. <em>56th Annual Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science, 2015</em></p>



<p>[2] Talya Eden, Dana Ron and C. Seshadhri. On approximating the number of k-cliques in sublinear time. Proceedings of the <em>50th Annual ACM SIGACT Symposium on Theory of Computing 2018</em>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-07T22:22:58Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-07T22:22:58Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>akumar</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2020-06-11T23:35:18Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17136</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/06/07/the-doomsday-argument-in-chess/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Doomsday Argument in Chess</title>
    <summary>Framing a controversial conversation piece as a conservation law Snip from Closer to Truth video on DA John Gott III is an emeritus professor of astrophysical sciences at Princeton. He was one of several independent inventors of the controversial Doomsday Argument (DA). He may have been the first to think of it but the last […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Framing a controversial conversation piece as a conservation law</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/06/07/the-doomsday-argument-in-chess/jrichardgottsnip/" rel="attachment wp-att-17138"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-17138" height="190" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/06/jrichardgottsnip.jpg?w=173&amp;h=190" width="173"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Snip from <em>Closer to Truth</em> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qlrj4iE7FA4">video</a> on DA</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
John Gott III is an emeritus professor of astrophysical sciences at Princeton. He was one of several independent inventors of the controversial <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doomsday_argument">Doomsday</a> <a href="http://www.anthropic-principle.com/?q=anthropic_principle/doomsday_argument">Argument</a> (DA). He may have been the first to think of it but the last to expound it in a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/363315a0.epdf">paper</a> or presentation.</p>
<p>
Today we expound DA as a defense against thought experiments that require unreasonable lengths of time.</p>
<p>
Gott thought of the argument when he saw the Berlin Wall as a 22-year-old touring Berlin in 1969. He reasoned that his visit was a uniformly random event in the lifetime <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> of the wall. That assumption gave him a 75% likelihood that he was not observing the wall in the first quarter of its lifetime. Since the wall was then 8 years old, that became a 75% likelihood that the wall would not last beyond 1993. It came down in late 1989.</p>
<p>
The “Doomsday” name comes when one’s birthdate <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> is regarded as a uniformly random sample from the sequence of all human births. If you are my age, <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> is probably <a href="https://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download;jsessionid=F7CF2C002ED22C17F221BE1788C43A6E?doi=10.1.1.49.5899&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf">closer</a> to ordinal 60 billion than 70 or 100 billion. We can then say we are 95% confident that we are not in the initial 5% of this sequence. That <em>entails</em> the sequence stopping before 1.2 trillion births. If our population levels off at 10 billion with 80 years’ life expectancy, that makes <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> extend no further than the year 12,000 AD. The upshot is that a longer <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> entails asserting that our random sample gave a point unusually <em>early</em> in the span. The purer form of DA also argues that <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> is not unusually <em>late</em>, giving this picture:</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/06/07/the-doomsday-argument-in-chess/doom/" rel="attachment wp-att-17140"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-17140" height="120" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/06/doom.png?w=290&amp;h=120" width="290"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Modified from Michael Stock <a href="https://michielstock.github.io/doomsday/">source</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>This doubles the span of <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> allowed with 95% confidence while giving reason—at the time <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> occurs—to believe that the end is not imminent: at least about 1.75 billion more births will come after <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/>. For <img alt="{x =}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx+%3D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x =}"/> my birth, however, this is already a given.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Debating DA </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The dependence on which observer is taken as the reference point <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> is one shiftable parameter of the DA. If you are a preteen reader, then your own birth may be closer to ordinal 70 billion in the sequence, which becomes <em>your</em> reference point. You can then tack on another 2,000 years to <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/>. The earliest human cave painters may have been among the first 3 billion <em>Homo sapiens</em>. With regard to their reference point, <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> has already gone past their 95% limit. </p>
<p>
A more fundamental rebuff to DA comes from the equal reasonableness of an alternate uniformity assumption: that you are a uniformly random element of the set <img alt="{H}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BH%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{H}"/> of all <em>possible</em> human beings. Only a subset <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> of <img alt="{H}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BH%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{H}"/> will ever be born. The longer <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> is, the higher was your prior probability of belonging to <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/>. Thus the fact of your birth can be construed as weighting the odds toward longer <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> in a way that cancels out the short-<img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/> reasoning of DA.</p>
<p>
Even when an instance of DA passes these objections, the inference remains controversial. We <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/22/predicting-when-pnp-is-resolved/">wrote</a> about DA last year in connection with estimating the lifespan of open problems remaining open. A clear <em>non</em>-instance is trying to apply DA to estimate the lifespan of the Covid-19 pandemic. We have all been going through the span together and <em>now</em> is not a uniformly random sample. </p>
<p>
The DA assumptions would however hold if an alien tourist with no prior knowledge of events dropped in on Earth today. The delicacy of the assumptions makes it significant to seek scenarios where DA firmly applies—and better, where the inference may be deemed <em>necessary</em> to preserve the validity of established modes of inference against extreme skeptical hypotheses. This is what we will try to argue in regard to inferences of cheating at chess. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The 1-in-100,000 Question </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We have <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2014/06/18/the-problem-of-catching-chess-cheaters/">posted</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2013/09/17/littlewoods-law/">numerous</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2013/01/13/the-crown-game-affair/">times</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2013/07/27/thirteen-sigma/">about</a> my statistical <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/10/18/london-calling/">chess</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/08/15/predicting-chess-and-horses/">model</a>, its giving judgments of odds against null hypotheses of fair play in the form of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_score"><em>z</em>-scores</a>, and my <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2011/10/12/empirical-humility/">means</a> of <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/08/20/our-trip-to-monte-carlo/">validating</a> them. We will suppose for this argument that the modeling is true in the sense that the distribution of <em>z</em>-scores from testing honest players conforms to the standard normal distribution. </p>
<p>
Now let us talk about chess in the years B.C.—before Covid—when the game was played over-the-board (OTB) in-person across a table. Suppose I obtained a <em>z</em>-score of 4.265 from a test of one player in one tournament. I have chosen this number for all of the following reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>
It corresponds to what I call “face-value odds” of 100,000-to-1 against the null hypothesis, as one can see from <a href="https://www.fourmilab.ch/rpkp/experiments/analysis/zCalc.html">this</a> or any similar calculator. <p/>
</li><li>
It is close to my number from an actual case in the year 1 B.C., that is, last year. <p/>
</li><li>
It is also typical of <em>z</em>-scores I have been obtaining these past three months since chess went online, at the point where certain online platforms have made their own decisions to impose sanctions. Here I must add that the platforms’ cheating detection systems avail much information about the manner of play that often furnishes much greater statistical evidence, whereas my minimalist model uses only the record of the moves played in the games.
</li></ul>
<p>
Suppose there were no other relevant information about the case. How would one assess the significance of the <em>z</em>-score of 4.265? Here are two different ways of reasoning that—in the case of OTB chess—arrive at similar answers:</p>
<ol>
<li>
The Bayesian prior probability of cheating in OTB chess has been estimated between 1-in-10,000 and 1-in-5,000. Suppose the former, and consider a thought experiment in which 100,000 players are tested. For simplicity, let’s suppose all true instances—that is, cheating players—give above 4.265. We expect there to be ten of them, plus one <em>natural</em> occurrence of 4.265 or more. Thus the odds that our score represents a true positive are only 10-in-11. This is well short of the odds range usually needed to meet the standard of <em>comfortable satisfaction</em> used for example by the Court of Arbitration for Sport. Thus the 4.265 datum alone should not be sufficient grounds for sanction. <p/>
</li><li>
Suppose there were a policy of sanction above a threshold of 4.25. The sum of playing fields in events held under auspices of the International Chess Federation (FIDE) each year exceeds 100,000. Thus we would expect to find at least one <em>z</em>-score over 4.265 per year by natural chance, whose sanctioning would be a serious human-rights error. FIDE cannot afford a rate of one such error per year. Thus it is insufficient for sanction.
</li></ol>
<p>
A 5.0 standard, however, gives a natural frequency of just over 1-in-3.5 million. The resulting error rate of once in 20-to-30 years might be acceptable in prospect. And the Bayesian argument based on a 0.0001 prior leaves about 350-to-1 odds against the null hypothesis, which is comfortably within the comfortable-satisfaction range as it has been applied. </p>
<p>
FIDE nevertheless has maintained a policy that statistical evidence must be accompanied by some other kind of evidence. If a player is caught looking at a chess position in a bathroom, or found to have a buzzing device or wires on his-or-her person, or signaling behavior is observed, then in fact much lower <em>z</em>-scores (to a threshold of 2.50, about 160-to-1 odds, in current FIDE regulations) are deemed to lend strong support to such evidence. </p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/06/07/the-doomsday-argument-in-chess/cheat/" rel="attachment wp-att-17142"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-17142" height="180" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/06/cheat.png?w=240&amp;h=180" width="240"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">2015 Peter Doggers/Chess.com <a href="https://www.chess.com/news/view/amateur-player-caught-cheating-at-tournament-in-new-delhi-7004?page=5">source</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
I posted a similar <a href="https://cse.buffalo.edu/~regan/chess/fidelity/Golfers.html">rationale</a> on my own website in early 2012, where causal evidence is likened to the “black spot” in the novel <em>Treasure Island</em>.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> One More Datum </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Now, however, suppose we have the 4.265 and one more piece of “evidence” that is pertinent but not as clearly causal. It could be:</p>
<ul>
<li>
The player wore a hat that covers the ears, or <p/>
</li><li>
An unusually bulky sweater (worn on a hot day), or <p/>
</li><li>
Unusual gestures or movements during the games.
</li></ul>
<p>
Say a search of the player turned up nothing, but this occurred after the sequence of games giving the 4.265, a day after the player had been put on notice of suspicion. So the extra information is not a black spot but instead a “grey spot.” What can we conclude now?</p>
<p>
The Bayesian argument seems to depend on judging how this information affects the prior probability of cheating. Does it make cheating a more likely hypothesis? We don’t actually know. Whereas the 1-in-10,000 global prior estimate was based on knowing dozens of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheating_in_chess#Incidents">cases</a> over the past decade, only a handful conformed to this level of indication—short of more obvious things like making frequent visits to the restroom or being seen with an ear adornment. The most we can say is that the datum is not irrelevant. An example of an irrelevant datum would be if the player were wearing neon green sneakers—not bulky, no wires, just a weird green.</p>
<p>
I would like, however, to argue that the player’s membership in a smaller sample <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> that is <em>pertinent</em> enhances the significance of the <em>z</em>-score. <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> must be defined by criteria that are not only independent of my statistical analysis of the games but also pertinent so as to avoid selection bias. What is needed to quantify this enhancement is:</p>
<blockquote><p>
(a) to collect all (other) kinds of items on a par with the above—say ostentatious bracelets that could camouflage electronic indicators—and</p>
<p>(b) to establish that the frequency of players having <em>any</em> such accoutrement over the global mass of tournaments is at most, say, 1-in-100.<br/>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Now there are several equivalent ways to continue the reasoning. One is to say that since <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> is “at worst” independent, the face-value odds are amplified by a factor of at least 100. The Bayesian mitigation then still leaves about 1,000-to-1 odds against the null hypothesis. Another is to say that in any given year, the natural chance of seeing the conjunction of <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> and the <em>z</em>-score is at most 1-in-100. Thus aside from the frequency of true positives, a policy of sanctioning in such cases would have a prospective error rate of once in 100 years. The conjoined error rate of that and sanctioning on 5.0 in isolation would be acceptable.</p>
<p>
A Bayesian defense attorney might still counter: Consider a thought experiment in which we test 100,000 such “bulky” players. We don’t have any new information on the prior rate of cheating by players in <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/>. For all we know, it is still 1-in-10,000. Thus the same terms as before will apply: our experiment will expect to have 10 cheaters in <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> plus the one natural false positive, leaving the odds only 10-to-1 as before. Put another way: without knowing the import of specializing to <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> on the likelihood of cheating, you can’t reach any further conclusion.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Doomsday to the Rescue </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The nub of rejecting this counter-argument is that:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Because there are only about 1,000 players in <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> per year, the thought experiment of testing 100,000 players in <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> now takes 100 years. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Moreover, the defense attorney is asserting that the mistaken false positive has occurred <em>unusually early</em> in this span. If this is the first year under consideration, then it is a uniformly random event in the first 1% of <img alt="{L}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L}"/>. By the same reasoning of DA, the odds of this are only 1-in-100. Compounded by the 10-1 odds against this particular score in the thought experiment being the false positive, we recover something near the 1,000-to-1 odds of the original reasoning.</p>
<p>
We might allow that we are not in the first year of “the cheating era” in chess. The thicket of high-profile cases with solid grounds for judgment goes back a little over 10 years. The factor from DA then goes down to 1-in-10. But this still leaves the overall odds about 100-to-1 against the null hypothesis, and that is commonly taken as an anchor point for the standard of comfortable satisfaction after all mitigating factors have been addressed. </p>
<p>
Thus I am casting the Doomsday interval argument as a defense against unreasonably long thought experiments. It restores a dimension of time that is ignored by the Bayesian objection. This dimension of time is correctly preserved in the analysis of the expected error rate from a policy of imposing sanctions under this <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/>–<em>z</em> combination of circumstances.</p>
<p>
Is my line of reasoning valid? You can be the judge. If so, then it is a class of instances where DA is applied merely to <em>conserve</em> an inference of unlikelihood that was originally made by other means. This supports the validity of DA-type inference in general.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Online Chess and the Time Warp </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We are now in the third month of “the online era” in chess. Even though online platforms can process many more kinds of information than I can avail from OTB play, my work has proved highly relevant for global early indications, second opinions, and transparent explanations. Alas, the sanction rate at the new featured tournaments has been well in excess of 1%. We hope this will come down as the playing pool—which has been greatly democratized in massive online events—wises up to the reality of getting caught.</p>
<p>
What I want to discuss here is how this brave new world flips the Bayesian reasoning in a way that may come on too strong <em>for the prosecution</em>, again by its indifference to the element of time. </p>
<p>
Take the 4.265 <em>z</em>-score with a <img alt="{1\%}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%5C%25%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1\%}"/> prior. The face-value odds from the <em>z</em>-score are now mitigated only to 1-in-1,000. This gives 99.9% confidence in imposing a sanction. However, the <em>rate of errors</em> would be <em>higher</em> than once-per-year because more players total have been involved per tournament. The tournaments are played at faster Rapid and Blitz paces allowing eight or more games per day, whereas classic OTB tournaments feature one game per day, sometimes two, over a span of a week to ten days. </p>
<p>
This is also set against a vastly higher global sample size. Whereas the entire historical record of OTB chess represented by the ChessBase <a href="https://shop.chessbase.com/en/products/mega_database_2020?ref=RF32-OET9DCF5AK&amp;gclid=EAIaIQobChMIu9P-4-_u6QIVGqSzCh0QQQsyEAAYASAAEgKcevD_BwE">Mega</a> database has yet to hit the 10 million games mark, the online platform <a href="https://lichess.org/">Lichess</a> has now hit 75 million games played <a href="https://database.lichess.org/">per month</a>. Adding in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Chess_Club">ICC</a> and <a href="https://www.chess.com/home">chess.com</a> and ChessBase’s and FIDE’s own servers yields an equation that recalls <a href="https://biblehub.com/psalms/90-4.htm">Ps 90:4</a> and <a href="https://biblehub.com/2_peter/3-8.htm">2 Peter 3:8</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> A thousand years of OTB are but a day that passes online. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
For online platforms in isolation, absent anything to distinguish one player’s set of games from any other’s (such as their belonging to a highest-profile tournament), this means that even a 5.0 standard is inadequate for sure judgment. At their volume, online sites can see deviations of by natural chance more than once per day. Thus they either tolerate a higher rate of errors or adopt a standard so high as to let many more guilty <a href="https://en.bab.la/dictionary/french-english/partie-d-echecs">parties</a> through the sieve. </p>
<p>
Such volume means all the more that one should hold a score of 4.265 as insufficient for judgment. This is despite the vastly higher Bayesian likelihood that a sanction based on that score is correct. The greater frequency of actual cheating does mean that the rate of error per positive reading declines, but the rate per absolute time, with regard to the fixed population of honest players, may matter more. This has accompanied deliberations of whether sanctions for online cheating must be given less permanent consequences in order to allow setting thresholds so that a high percentage of actual cheaters are flagged and the error rate can be tolerated.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Does this analysis square with you? Does it help in understanding controversies over the original Doomsday Argument’s paradigm?</p>
<p>
For another pass over the argument, suppose I get a <em>z</em>-score of 4.265 in a narrowly-defined event such as one country’s championship league. Does that limit the sample size, so that the score is more dispositive? The kind of reasoning in point (b) above, where we had to gather all possible indicators that would lead us to constrain the sample, would however mandate widening it at least to include other countries’ leagues. This is an aspect of the “look elsewhere” <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Look-elsewhere_effect">effect</a> where the space of potential tests is widened even before actual tests are considered. Possibly it should be widened to include all tournaments with similar levels of players, in which case we are back to the “square 1” of the 1-in-100,000 section of this post. The point of the analysis of the extra datum about the player is that the sample expansion has an effective pre-defined limit.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
[Added note about online cheating detection to third bullet in section 3.  Clarified: “… the conjunction of these two factors” –&gt; “… the conjunction of B and the z-score” and changed the succeeding sentence.]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-07T19:22:02Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-07T19:22:02Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="chess"/>
    <category term="detection"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Bayesian reasoning"/>
    <category term="cheating"/>
    <category term="Doomsday Argument"/>
    <category term="fraud-detection"/>
    <category term="John Richard Gott"/>
    <category term="online chess"/>
    <category term="statistics"/>
    <category term="time horizons"/>
    <author>
      <name>KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:20:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/086</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/086" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-086 |  A Survey on Approximation in Parameterized Complexity: Hardness and Algorithms | 

	Andreas Feldmann, 

	Karthik  C. S., 

	Euiwoong Lee, 

	Pasin Manurangsi</title>
    <summary>Parameterization and approximation are two popular ways of coping with NP-hard problems. More recently, the two have also been combined to derive many interesting results. We survey developments in the area both from the algorithmic and hardness perspectives, with emphasis on new techniques and potential future research directions.</summary>
    <updated>2020-06-07T13:52:52Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-07T13:52:52Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:20:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204.post-6421565733839282178</id>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/6421565733839282178/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=6421565733839282178" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/6421565733839282178" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/6421565733839282178" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2020/06/catcs-visioning-workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>CATCS Visioning Workshop</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div><span class="im">Reposting an important call -- these events have had big impact in the past!</span></div><div><span class="im">The <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/catcs/" style="color: #3f9291;">CATCS</a> will be hosting a virtual <strong>“Visioning Workshop”</strong> the <strong>week of </strong></span><strong>July 20</strong> in order to identify broad research themes within theoretical computer science (TCS) that have potential for a major impact in the future. The goals are similar to the <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/visioning-workshop/" style="color: #3f9291;">workshop of the same name</a> in 2008: to package these themes in a way that can be consumed <span class="im">by the general public, which we would deliver primarily to the Computing Community Consortium and others (e.g. funding agencies) to help them advocate for TCS.</span></div><div>While participation in the workshop is primarily through invitation, we have a few slots available for the broader community. If you are interested in participating, please see details of the application process below. The workshop will be organized according to area-wise breakout groups. Each breakout group will have 1-2 leads. Breakout groups will meet for 4-5 hours spread across several days and will be tasked with brainstorming ideas and preparing materials related to their topic. Leads are further expected to participate in plenary sessions held on Monday July 20 and Friday July 24 (4-5 hrs of additional time) where these materials will be discussed.</div><div>If you are interested in participating in the workshop, please fill out <a href="https://forms.gle/cdCTsLfUs56CDhKS9" style="color: #3f9291;">this Google form</a> by <strong>Monday June 15</strong>. On this form, applicants are asked to contribute one or two <span class="im">major results in the last 10 years whose significance can be explained in layperson terms, and one or two major challenges for theory whose significance can be explained in layperson terms. These descriptions </span>can be very brief. We will just use them to select participants and create breakout groups.</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-06T22:40:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-06T22:40:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/02161161032642563814</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204</id>
      <category term="conferences"/>
      <category term="research"/>
      <category term="society"/>
      <category term="algorithms"/>
      <category term="administration"/>
      <category term="teaching"/>
      <category term="Harvard"/>
      <category term="papers"/>
      <category term="graduate students"/>
      <category term="funding"/>
      <category term="talks"/>
      <category term="blogs"/>
      <category term="codes"/>
      <category term="jobs"/>
      <category term="reviews"/>
      <category term="personal"/>
      <category term="travel"/>
      <category term="undergraduate students"/>
      <category term="books"/>
      <category term="open problems"/>
      <category term="PCs"/>
      <category term="consulting"/>
      <category term="randomness"/>
      <category term="CCC"/>
      <category term="blog book project"/>
      <category term="research labs"/>
      <category term="ISIT"/>
      <category term="tenure"/>
      <category term="comments"/>
      <category term="recommendations"/>
      <category term="outreach"/>
      <category term="students"/>
      <author>
        <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06738274256402616703</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">My take on computer science -- <br/> 
algorithms, networking, information theory -- <br/> 
and related items.</div>
      </subtitle>
      <title>My Biased Coin</title>
      <updated>2020-06-09T07:46:52Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4839</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4839" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4839#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4839" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Jonathan Dowling (1955-2020)</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Today I woke up to the sad and shocking news that Jon Dowling (homepage / Twitter / Wikipedia)—physics professor at Louisiana State, guy who got the US government to invest in quantum computing back in the 90s, author of the popular book Schrödinger’s Killer App: Race to Build the World’s First Quantum Computer, investigator of […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><figure class="wp-block-image"><img alt="" src="http://phys.lsu.edu/~jdowling/index_files/Dowling.jpg"/></figure>



<p>Today I woke up to the sad and shocking news that Jon Dowling (<a href="http://phys.lsu.edu/~jdowling/">homepage</a> / <a href="https://twitter.com/jpdowling?lang=en">Twitter</a> / <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonathan_Dowling">Wikipedia</a>)—physics professor at Louisiana State, guy who got the US government to invest in quantum computing back in the 90s, author of the popular book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Schr%C3%B6dingers-Killer-App-Jonathan-Dowling/dp/1439896739">Schrödinger’s Killer App: Race to Build the World’s First Quantum Computer</a>, investigator of BosonSampling among many other topics, owner of a “QUBIT” license plate, and one of my main competitors in the field of quantum computing humor—has passed away at age 65, apparently due to an aortic aneurysm.</p>



<p>Three months ago, right before covid shut down the world, the <em>last</em> travel I did was a seven-hour road trip from Austin to Baton Rouge, together with my postdoc <a href="https://twitter.com/a_rocchetto?lang=en">Andrea Rocchetto</a>, to deliver something called the <a href="https://calendar.lsu.edu/event/the_hearne_eminent_lecture_with_scott_aaronson#.Xtv1HDpKg2w">Hearne Lecture</a> at the Louisiana State physics department.  My topic (unsurprisingly) was Google’s quantum supremacy experiment.</p>



<p>I’d debated whether to cancel the trip, as flying already seemed too dangerous.  Dowling was the one who said “why not just drive here with one of your postdocs?”—which turned into a memorable experience for me and Andrea, complete with a personal tour of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LIGO">LIGO</a> and a visit to an alligator hatchery.  I had no inkling that it was the last time I’d ever see Jon Dowling, but am now super-glad that we made the visit.</p>



<p>At the dinner after my talk, Dowling was exactly the same as every other time I’d seen him: loud, piss-drunk, obnoxious, and hilarious.  He dominated the conversation with stories and jokes, referring in every other sentence either to his Irishness or my Jewishness.  His efforts to banter with the waitress, to elicit her deepest opinions about each appetizer and bottle of wine, were so over-the-top that I, sitting next to him, blushed, as if to say, “hey, I’m just the visitor here!  I don’t necessarily <em>endorse</em> this routine!”</p>



<p>But Dowling got away with it because, no matter how many taboos he violated per sentence, there was never any hint of malice in it.  He was an equal-opportunity offender, with his favorite target being himself.  He loved to talk, for example, about my pathological obsession with airy-fairy abstractions, like some kind of “polynomial hierarchy” that hopefully wouldn’t “collapse”—with the punchline being that he, the hardheaded laser physicist, then needed to learn what that meant for his own research.</p>



<p>The quantum computing community of the southern US, not to mention of Twitter and Facebook, and indeed of the entire world, will be poorer without this inimitable, louder-than-life presence.</p>



<p>Feel free to share your own Dowling stories in the comments.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-06T20:37:22Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-06T20:37:22Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Adventures in Meatspace"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="CS/Physics Deathmatch"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T02:14:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=441</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2020/06/06/tcs-talk-wednesday-june-10-cliff-stein-columbia-university/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, June 10 — Cliff Stein, Columbia University</title>
    <summary>In solidarity with the current protests in the United States (https://www.shutdownstem.com/), our speaker asked that the talk this coming Wednesday be postponed. Cliff’s talk has been rescheduled to Thursday, June 18th; we will keep you updated in case of any further change. We would also take this opportunity to call the TCS community for feedback, […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>In solidarity with the current protests in the United States (<a href="https://www.shutdownstem.com/" rel="nofollow">https://www.shutdownstem.com/</a>), our speaker asked that the talk this coming Wednesday be postponed.</b></p>
<p><strong>Cliff’s talk has been rescheduled to <span style="color: #ff0000;">Thursday, June 18th</span>; we will keep you updated in case of any further change. We would also take this opportunity to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">call the TCS community for feedback, and for suggestions and comments</a>. As a small team organizing this virtual seminar, we are continuously trying to improve and welcome your input.</strong></p>
<p>The next TCS+ talk<em> (and the last of the season!)</em> will take place this coming Wednesday, June 10th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). <strong>Cliff Stein</strong> from Columbia University will speak about “<em>Parallel Approximate Undirected Shortest Paths Via Low Hop Emulators</em>” (abstract below).</p>
<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk/live-seat-reservation">the online form</a>. Due to security concerns, <em>registration is required</em> to attend the interactive talk. (The link to the YouTube livestream will also be posted <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk">on our<br/>
website</a> on the day of the talk, so people who did not sign up will still be able to watch the talk live.) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see &gt;the website.</p>
<blockquote><p>Abstract: Although sequential algorithms with (nearly) optimal running time for finding shortest paths in undirected graphs with non-negative edge weights have been known for several decades, near-optimal parallel algorithms have turned out to be a much tougher challenge. In this talk, we present a <img alt="(1+\varepsilon)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%281%2B%5Cvarepsilon%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0" title="(1+\varepsilon)"/>-approximate parallel algorithm for computing shortest paths in undirected graphs, achieving polylog depth and near-linear work. All prior <img alt="(1+\varepsilon)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%281%2B%5Cvarepsilon%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0" title="(1+\varepsilon)"/>-algorithms with polylog depth perform at least superlinear work. Improving this long-standing upper bound obtained by Cohen (STOC’94) has been open for 25 years.</p>
<p>Our algorithm uses several new tools. Prior work uses hopsets to introduce shortcuts in the graph. We introduce a new notion that we call low hop emulators. We also introduce compressible preconditioners, which we use in conjunction with Serman’s framework (SODA ’17) for the uncapacitated minimum cost flow problem.</p>
<p>Joint work with Alex Andoni and Peilin Zhong.</p></blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-06T18:16:14Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-06T18:16:14Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:21:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7750</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/06/06/tcs-visioning-workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS visioning workshop</title>
    <summary>[From Jelani Nelson and David Woodruff. This workshop can be very important to ensure TCS is represented in what is likely to be a difficult funding environment in coming years. –Boaz ] The CATCS will be hosting a virtual “Visioning Workshop” the week of July 20 in order to identify broad research themes within theoretical computer science (TCS) that have potential for […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>[From Jelani Nelson and David Woodruff. This workshop can be very important to ensure TCS is represented in what is likely to be a difficult funding environment in coming years. –Boaz ]</em> </p>



<p>The <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/catcs/">CATCS</a> will be hosting a virtual <strong>“Visioning Workshop”</strong> the <strong>week of </strong><strong>July 20</strong> in order to identify broad research themes within theoretical computer science (TCS) that have potential for a major impact in the future. The goals are similar to the <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/visioning-workshop/">workshop of the same name</a> in 2008: to package these themes in a way that can be consumed by the general public, which we would deliver primarily to the Computing Community Consortium and others (e.g. funding agencies) to help them advocate for TCS.</p>



<p>While participation in the workshop is primarily through invitation, we have a few slots available for the broader community. If you are interested in participating, please see details of the application process below. The workshop will be organized according to area-wise breakout groups. Each breakout group will have 1-2 leads. Breakout groups will meet for 4-5 hours spread across several days and will be tasked with brainstorming ideas and preparing materials related to their topic. Leads are further expected to participate in plenary sessions held on Monday July 20 and Friday July 24 (4-5 hrs of additional time) where these materials will be discussed.</p>



<p>If you are interested in participating in the workshop, please fill out <a href="https://forms.gle/cdCTsLfUs56CDhKS9">this Google form</a> by <strong>Monday June 15</strong> ( <a href="https://forms.gle/cdCTsLfUs56CDhKS9">https://forms.gle/cdCTsLfUs56CDhKS9</a> ). On this form, applicants are asked to contribute one or two major results in the last 10 years whose significance can be explained in layperson terms, and one or two major challenges for theory whose significance can be explained in layperson terms. <em>[The results need not and generally will not be your own. They just should be easy-to-explain major results in your research area–Boaz] </em>These descriptions can be very brief. We will just use them to select participants and create breakout groups.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-06T05:24:17Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-06T05:24:17Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:21:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-25562705.post-4113531432946112122</id>
    <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/feeds/4113531432946112122/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=25562705&amp;postID=4113531432946112122" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default/4113531432946112122" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default/4113531432946112122" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/2020/06/tcs-visioning-workshop-call-for.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS Visioning Workshop — Call for Participation</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reposting from here: <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2020/06/05/tcs-visioning-workshop-call-for-participation/">https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2020/06/05/tcs-visioning-workshop-call-for-participation/</a><br/><br/><div><div style="line-height: 22px; padding: 0px 0px 20px;"><span class="im">The <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/catcs/" style="color: #3f9291;">CATCS</a> will be hosting a virtual <strong>“Visioning Workshop”</strong> the <strong>week of </strong></span><strong>July 20</strong> in order to identify broad research themes within theoretical computer science (TCS) that have potential for a major impact in the future. The goals are similar to the <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/visioning-workshop/" style="color: #3f9291;">workshop of the same name</a> in 2008: to package these themes in a way that can be consumed <span class="im">by the general public, which we would deliver primarily to the Computing Community Consortium and others (e.g. funding agencies) to help them advocate for TCS.</span></div><div style="line-height: 22px; padding: 0px 0px 20px;">While participation in the workshop is primarily through invitation, we have a few slots available for the broader community. If you are interested in participating, please see details of the application process below. The workshop will be organized according to area-wise breakout groups. Each breakout group will have 1-2 leads. Breakout groups will meet for 4-5 hours spread across several days and will be tasked with brainstorming ideas and preparing materials related to their topic. Leads are further expected to participate in plenary sessions held on Monday July 20 and Friday July 24 (4-5 hrs of additional time) where these materials will be discussed.</div><div style="line-height: 22px; padding: 0px 0px 20px;">If you are interested in participating in the workshop, please fill out <a href="https://forms.gle/cdCTsLfUs56CDhKS9" style="color: #3f9291;">this Google form</a> by <strong>Monday June 15</strong>. On this form, applicants are asked to contribute one or two <span class="im">major results in the last 10 years whose significance can be explained in layperson terms, and one or two major challenges for theory whose significance can be explained in layperson terms. These descriptions </span>can be very brief. We will just use them to select participants and create breakout groups.</div></div><div/><div><br/></div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-05T22:59:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-05T22:59:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Aaron</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/09952936358739421126</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-25562705</id>
      <category term="game theory"/>
      <category term="news"/>
      <author>
        <name>Aaron</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/09952936358739421126</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Adventures in Computation</title>
      <updated>2020-06-06T09:46:52Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://thmatters.wordpress.com/?p=1312</id>
    <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2020/06/05/tcs-visioning-workshop-call-for-participation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS Visioning Workshop — Call for Participation</title>
    <summary>The CATCS will be hosting a virtual “Visioning Workshop” the week of July 20 in order to identify broad research themes within theoretical computer science (TCS) that have potential for a major impact in the future. The goals are similar to the workshop of the same name in 2008: to package these themes in a […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div>
<p><span class="im">The <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/catcs/">CATCS</a> will be hosting a virtual <strong>“Visioning Workshop”</strong> the <strong>week of </strong></span><strong>July 20</strong> in order to identify broad research themes within theoretical computer science (TCS) that have potential for a major impact in the future. The goals are similar to the <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/visioning-workshop/">workshop of the same name</a> in 2008: to package these themes in a way that can be consumed <span class="im">by the general public, which we would deliver primarily to the Computing Community Consortium and others (e.g. funding agencies) to help them advocate for TCS.</span></p>
<p>While participation in the workshop is primarily through invitation, we have a few slots available for the broader community. If you are interested in participating, please see details of the application process below. The workshop will be organized according to area-wise breakout groups. Each breakout group will have 1-2 leads. Breakout groups will meet for 4-5 hours spread across several days and will be tasked with brainstorming ideas and preparing materials related to their topic. Leads are further expected to participate in plenary sessions held on Monday July 20 and Friday July 24 (4-5 hrs of additional time) where these materials will be discussed.</p>
<p>If you are interested in participating in the workshop, please fill out <a href="https://forms.gle/cdCTsLfUs56CDhKS9">this Google form</a> by <strong>Monday June 15</strong>. On this form, applicants are asked to contribute one or two <span class="im">major results in the last 10 years whose significance can be explained in layperson terms, and one or two major challenges for theory whose significance can be explained in layperson terms. These descriptions </span>can be very brief. We will just use them to select participants and create breakout groups.</p>
</div>
<div/>
<div>(If the embedded link doesn’t work, paste this URL in your browser: <a href="https://forms.gle/cdCTsLfUs56CDhKS9" rel="nofollow">https://forms.gle/cdCTsLfUs56CDhKS9</a>.)</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-06-05T18:46:13Z</updated>
    <published>2020-06-05T18:46:13Z</published>
    <category term="workshops"/>
    <author>
      <name>shuchic</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://thmatters.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theory Matters</title>
      <updated>2020-06-12T04:21:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
