<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-01-09T02:24:34Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6812304357684621341</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6812304357684621341/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/01/silicon-valley-ethics.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6812304357684621341" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6812304357684621341" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/01/silicon-valley-ethics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Silicon Valley Ethics</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><b>Spoiler Alert: </b>This post has details from the final episodes of the HBO television series <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silicon_Valley_(TV_series)">Silicon Valley</a><br/>
<br/>
A few times I've gotten emails from people claiming they have shown P = NP and asking whether they should keep their algorithm a secret to protect the cryptography out there. My typical response is that they should use their algorithm to mine a few bitcoins and then get back to me.<br/>
<br/>
The fictional characters of Pied Piper faced this dilemma when they AI they created "developed a general solution to discrete log in polynomial time" with some nice complexity class diagrams in the background.<br/>
<br/>
<div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;">
<a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-0wC_yidITsY/Xg9oKlfZkrI/AAAAAAABu-g/OhzquwGwXbUqNDSDmGlpkU66wrjOcW62QCKgBGAsYHg/s1600/IMG_20200101_200809.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="240" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-0wC_yidITsY/Xg9oKlfZkrI/AAAAAAABu-g/OhzquwGwXbUqNDSDmGlpkU66wrjOcW62QCKgBGAsYHg/s320/IMG_20200101_200809.jpg" width="320"/></a></div>
<br/>
Pied Piper was about to roll out its new internet, a distributed network that communicated between cell phones based on a compression algorithm developed by Pied Piper's CEO. Rolling out the network would reveal even more advanced compression based on breaking discrete log. "If we cancel it or shut it down, then others will try to copy or reverse engineer everything that we've built ... Our launch has to fail, publicly and spectacularly."<br/>
<br/>
But here comes the P v NP dilemma: "And what about all the other stuff we're gonna do? I mean, give internet to underserved communities, students in the homework gap, refugees, genomic research. Pied Piper can help scientists cure cancer."<br/>
<br/>
I'd take broken encryption over cancer any day. You can still do encryption even if P = NP, one-time pads distributed via USB drives or quantum. And cancer sucks.<br/>
<br/>
They should have mined a few bitcoins.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-09T01:35:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-09T01:35:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T01:35:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02581</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02581" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Simplex Tree: an Efficient Data Structure for General Simplicial Complexes</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578528000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Boissonnat:Jean=Daniel.html">Jean-Daniel Boissonnat</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Maria:Cl=eacute=ment.html">Clément Maria</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.02581">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper introduces a data structure, called simplex tree, to represent
abstract simplicial complexes of any dimension. All faces of the simplicial
complex are explicitly stored in a trie whose nodes are in bijection with the
faces of the complex. This data structure allows to efficiently implement a
large range of basic operations on simplicial complexes. We provide theoretical
complexity analysis as well as detailed experimental results. We more
specifically study Rips and witness complexes.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02542</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02542" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Automatic surface mesh generation for discrete models: A complete and automatic pipeline based on reparameterization</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578528000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Beaufort:Pierre=Alexandre.html">Pierre-Alexandre Beaufort</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Geuzaine:Christophe.html">Christophe Geuzaine</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Remacle:Jean=Fran=ccedil=ois.html">Jean-François Remacle</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.02542">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Triangulations are an ubiquitous input for the finite element community.
However, most raw triangulations obtained by imaging techniques are unsuitable
as-is for finite element analysis. In this paper, we give a robust pipeline for
handling those triangulations, based on the computation of a one-to-one
parametrization for automatically selected patches of input triangles, which
makes each patch amenable to remeshing by standard finite element meshing
algorithms. Using only geometrical arguments, we prove that a discrete
parametrization of a patch is one-to-one if (and only if) its image in the
parameter space is such that all parametric triangles have a positive area. We
then derive a non-standard linear discretization scheme based on mean value
coordinates to compute such one-to-one parametrizations, and show that the
scheme does not discretize a Laplacian on a structured mesh. The proposed
pipeline is implemented in the open source mesh generator Gmsh, where the
creation of suitable patches is based on triangulation topology and
parametrization quality, combined with feature edge detection. Several examples
illustrate the robustness of the resulting implementation.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02481</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02481" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Nullstellensatz Size-Degree Trade-offs from Reversible Pebbling</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578528000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rezende:Susanna_F=_de.html">Susanna F. de Rezende</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Meir:Or.html">Or Meir</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nordstr=ouml=m:Jakob.html">Jakob Nordström</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Robere:Robert.html">Robert Robere</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.02481">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We establish an exactly tight relation between reversible pebblings of graphs
and Nullstellensatz refutations of pebbling formulas, showing that a graph $G$
can be reversibly pebbled in time $t$ and space $s$ if and only if there is a
Nullstellensatz refutation of the pebbling formula over $G$ in size $t+1$ and
degree $s$ (independently of the field in which the Nullstellensatz refutation
is made). We use this correspondence to prove a number of strong size-degree
trade-offs for Nullstellensatz, which to the best of our knowledge are the
first such results for this proof system.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-09T02:20:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02411</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02411" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Induced odd cycle packing number, independent sets, and chromatic number</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578528000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Zdeněk Dvořák, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pek=aacute=rek:Jakub.html">Jakub Pekárek</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.02411">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The \emph{induced odd cycle packing number} $\text{iocp}(G)$ of a graph $G$
is the maximum integer $k$ such that $G$ contains an induced subgraph
consisting of $k$ pairwise vertex-disjoint odd cycles. Motivated by
applications to geometric graphs, Bonamy et al. proved that graphs of bounded
induced odd cycle packing number, bounded VC dimension, and linear independence
number admit a randomized EPTAS for the independence number. We show that the
assumption of bounded VC dimension is not necessary, exhibiting a randomized
algorithm that for any integers $k\ge 0$ and $t\ge 1$ and any $n$-vertex graph
$G$ of induced odd cycle packing number returns in time $O_{k,t}(n^{k+4})$ an
independent set of $G$ whose size is at least $\alpha(G)-n/t$ with high
probability. In addition, we present $\chi$-boundedness results for graphs with
bounded odd cycle packing number, and use them to design a QPTAS for the
independence number only assuming bounded induced odd cycle packing number.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-09T02:21:02Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.01872</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.01872" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Spatial Applications of Topological Data Analysis: Cities, Snowflakes, Random Structures, and Spiders Spinning Under the Influence</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578528000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Feng:Michelle.html">Michelle Feng</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Porter:Mason_A=.html">Mason A. Porter</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.01872">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Spatial networks are ubiquitous in social, geographic, physical, and
biological applications. To understand their large-scale structure, it is
important to develop methods that allow one to directly probe the effects of
space on structure and dynamics. Historically, algebraic topology has provided
one framework for rigorously and quantitatively describing the global structure
of a space, and recent advances in topological data analysis (TDA) have given
scholars a new lens for analyzing network data. In this paper, we study a
variety of spatial networks --- including both synthetic and natural ones ---
using novel topological methods that we recently developed specifically for
analyzing spatial networks. We demonstrate that our methods are able to capture
meaningful quantities, with specifics that depend on context, in spatial
networks and thereby provide useful insights into the structure of those
networks, including a novel approach for characterizing them based on their
topological structures. We illustrate these ideas with examples of synthetic
networks and dynamics on them, street networks in cities, snowflakes, and webs
spun by spiders under the influence of various psychotropic substances.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4287</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/01/08/the-vaseline-of-the-people/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Vaseline of the People</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A couple of days ago, professor Walter Lapini of the University of Genova published a truly shameful op-ed in Corriere della Sera (Italy’s highest-circulation newspaper) confirming, and actually proudly affirming, all the worst stereotypes about Italian academia. At first I … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/01/08/the-vaseline-of-the-people/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>A couple of days ago, professor Walter Lapini of the University of Genova published a <a href="https://www.corriere.it/opinioni/20_gennaio_04/quei-superfinanziamentiche-sconvolgono-atenei-b9e91602-2f24-11ea-838c-ac55de770e3c.shtml">truly shameful op-ed</a> in Corriere della Sera (Italy’s highest-circulation newspaper) confirming, and actually proudly affirming, all the worst stereotypes about Italian academia. At first I wanted to comment on it, but there is already excellent commentary in various places, including <a href="https://www.ilpost.it/gianlucabriguglia/2020/01/06/il-ritorno-della-casta-dei-poverini/">here</a>.</em></p><em>
</em><p><em>Instead I think that the best way to shame professor Lapini is to simply repeat what he wrote. Here is an approximate translation of his op-ed. Sentences in square brackets are my annotations. I hasten to add that I have never heard anything like this from computer science folks, and I understand that these attitudes are mostly confined to medicine, humanities, and legal studies.</em></p>
<p>A dozen years ago, the Europe of merit, that is, the Europe of a renewed Darwinism, invented the now-famous Erc, pronounced Iarsi. These are grants for innovative research projects, accessible both to barons [Italian nickname for full professors who treat they area like a fiefdom] and to newcomers and unleashed dogs. They favor interdisciplinary themes, and overwhelm the winners with money (millions of Euro). The Erc, and similar funding schemes like the Marie Curie [fellowship], the quote premiali [an Italian funding scheme] and funding for so-called excellent departments are trendy because they represent the spirt of our times: to disparage a modest but safe return and to be excited by the gamble, the big deal, the all-or-nothing. Small potatoes (they say) are not enough any more, and so they, instead, dangle from above a big steak, and the stronger or the smarter will bite into it. It is an interesting social experiment, that could maybe be applied in the factory: instead of dividing something up between the workers, give half-a-something to just one, which is advantageous for the owner, who saves money, and which makes the others happy, because they lost but they “had a chance”.</p>
<p>Of course, the young man who wins an Erc cannot administer by himself one or two million Euro, but he has to find a university that will hire him, that be a base and a bank for him, getting a share of the dough. Now, for impoverished and hungry universities, the coming of an Erc winner is like the coming of grandma’s pension in [the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Down_and_Dirty_(film)">movie</a>] Down and Dirty: it means survival, a breath of fresh air. Everybody tries to get the goose that laid the golden egg, or maybe to breed one in-home. And so universities offer, with terrible terminology, “prestigious positions” to those who “bring” an Erc, or set up “instructional events” with the goal of “submitting a successful Erc”. These are courses, or series of lectures, that help you dress up your project by choosing the most intriguing of titles, the best acronym, the coolest formulation, to impress the reviewers who will mostly be from other areas, and who will have no idea about your area, or, even worse, will have the wrong idea. If you are a philosopher or an archeologist, you will have to convince people who see philosophy through De Crescenzo [an Italian comedian and writer, who has written humorous expository books on Greek philosophy] or see archeology through Indiana Jones. Everything, of course, will be in English, the vaseline of the people.</p>
<p>Hard sciences need a lot of money, we know. But when abnormal funding reaches a school of humanities the effect is like sudden heavy rain on dry soil: it washes away. Indeed, the goose who laid the golden egg does not lay for free: it “brings” the Erc but wants a safe job, maybe the highest one, a nice chair as full professor. He lands in a department and unhinges teaches plannings, jumps the line, cuts ahead of the many who were busily waiting their turn and now they have to step aside for the unstoppable march of the Million. And if the Erc winner does not have the qualifications to be a full professor it can be quickly fixed, because in this Italy that is cooptation-phile and competition-phobe there is a whole rainforest of agencies and authorities where it is not difficult to find a friendly institution that will give a tailor-made evaluation [sorry this sentence hardly makes any sense in Italian either]. Afterward, you do an exceptional hiring process and it is a fait-accompli that is, as is well known, impossible to reverse. And so the enterprising and appropriately trained young man, who has been able to express good intentions using trendy words like “sustainability” or “gender”, flies to a full professorship that has been, for all intents and purposes, purchased. And the human traffickers of the ope legis [“by virtue of the law”, meaning not through an open competition] and ope bursae [“by virtue of the grant”, this is meant as a joke / play on words] recruitment work with no opposition, knowing that the people they excluded, the people they damaged, will play along if they want some table scraps from grandma’s pension, and if they want to avoid a future of isolation and bullying. Pasolini said that there is no torturer’s plan that is not suggested by the look in the eyes of the victim. </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-08T20:39:27Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-08T20:39:27Z</published>
    <category term="Italy"/>
    <category term="things that are terrible"/>
    <category term="Walter Lapini"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:20:18Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=19104</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/01/08/the-brown-erdos-sos-1973-conjecture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Brown-Erdős-Sós 1973 Conjecture</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Greetings from Oberwolfach.  This week, there is a great meeting here on combinatorics. In this post I want to state the Brown-Erdős-Sós conjecture and one of its variants. The trigger was a beautiful talk I heard from Lior Gishboliner on … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/01/08/the-brown-erdos-sos-1973-conjecture/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: left;">Greetings from Oberwolfach.  This week, there is a great meeting here on combinatorics. In this post I want to state the Brown-Erdős-Sós conjecture and one of its variants. The trigger was a beautiful talk I heard from Lior Gishboliner on some impressive progress toward this very difficult problem.  Yet the solution of the problem seems far, and some people even doubt if the conjecture is true. Here is the paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08834">“A New Bound for the Brown-Erdős-Sós problem</a>” by David Conlon, Lior Gishboliner, Yevgeny Levanzov, and Asaf Shapira.</p>
<h2>The Brown-Erdős-Sós conjecture and strong versions</h2>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/01/pv.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-16790" height="169" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/01/pv.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>Lior’s talk reminded me that Peter Frankl and Voita Rodl told me in the late 80s about strong variants of the Brown-Erdős-Sós problem that implies the Szemeredi theorem. With the kind help of Voita Rodl  who is here I can tell you about two such variants. (But I am solely responsible for all mistakes.)</p>
<p>Let <em>f(n,v,e)</em> be the largest number of edges in an 3-uniform hypergraph with no v vertices spanning e edges or more.</p>
<p>Brown-Erdős-Sós Conjecture: <img alt="f(n,e+3,e)=o(n^2)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f%28n%2Ce%2B3%2Ce%29%3Do%28n%5E2%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="f(n,e+3,e)=o(n^2)"/>, for every <img alt="e\ge 3" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=e%5Cge+3&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="e\ge 3"/>.</p>
<p>For <img alt="e=3" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=e%3D3&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="e=3"/> the BES conjecture is the famous Ruzsa-Szemeredi theorem (that implies Roth’s theorem on 3-term arithmetic progressions). For <img alt="e=4" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=e%3D4&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="e=4"/> the conjecture is painfully open (and is stronger than Szemeredi theorem for 4-term APs).</p>
<p>Here is an even stronger conjectures that implies Szemeredi theorem arithmetic progressions of arbitrary length.</p>
<p>Consider the following 3-uniform hypergraph <em>H(v)</em> with<em> v+3</em> vertices and <em>v</em> edges: Start with a path with v+1 vertices (and v edges). Color the edges alternately with red and brown and add a red vertex and a brown vertex. Now form a 3-uniform hypergraph whose edges are the red edges of the path joined with the red vertex and the brown edges of the graph joined with the brown vertex.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/szem-voita1.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-19110" height="205" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/szem-voita1.png?w=300&amp;h=205" width="300"/></a></p>
<p><strong>Conjecture:</strong> Every <em>H(v)</em>-free 3-uniform hypergraph with <em>n</em> vertices has <img alt="o(n^2)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=o%28n%5E2%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="o(n^2)"/> vertices.</p>
<p>For another strengthening of the BES-conjecture that implies the Szemeredi theorem see the paper <a href="https://mathscinet.ams.org/mathscinet/search/publdoc.html?arg3=&amp;co4=AND&amp;co5=AND&amp;co6=AND&amp;co7=AND&amp;dr=all&amp;pg4=AUCN&amp;pg5=TI&amp;pg6=PC&amp;pg7=ALLF&amp;pg8=ET&amp;review_format=html&amp;s4=Rodl%20and%20Erdos&amp;s5=&amp;s6=&amp;s7=&amp;s8=All&amp;sort=Newest&amp;vfpref=html&amp;yearRangeFirst=&amp;yearRangeSecond=&amp;yrop=eq&amp;r=2&amp;mx-pid=1393704">A remark of Pisier-type theorems</a> of Erdos, Nesetril and Rodl. Famously, the celebrated hypergraph regularity lemma (and associated counting lemma) implies another Turan type theorem for hypergraphs that in turn implies Szemeredi’s theorem and its high dimensional extensions.</p>
<h2>The new bounds by Conlon, Gishboliner, Levanzov, and Shapira</h2>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/bes2.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19114" height="173" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/bes2.png?w=640&amp;h=173" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>Although the theorem is for 3-uniform hypergraph the proof relies on the hypergraph regularity lemma for higher dimensional hypergraphs.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/img_6303.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-19122" height="168" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/img_6303.jpg?w=300&amp;h=168" width="300"/></a><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/img_6302.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-19123" height="225" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/img_6302.jpg?w=300&amp;h=225" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>With Voita in 1985 (or 86) and today (2020)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-08T19:58:17Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-08T19:58:17Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Asaf Shapira"/>
    <category term="B. Nagle"/>
    <category term="David Conlon"/>
    <category term="Endre Szemeredi"/>
    <category term="Imre Z. Ruzsa"/>
    <category term="J. Skokan"/>
    <category term="Lior Gishboliner"/>
    <category term="M. Schacht"/>
    <category term="Paul Erdos"/>
    <category term="Peter Frankl"/>
    <category term="Tim Gowers"/>
    <category term="Vera T. S&#xF2;s"/>
    <category term="Voita Rodl"/>
    <category term="W. G. Brown"/>
    <category term="Yevgeny Levanzov"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16539</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/01/08/no-password-encryption/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>No Password Encryption</title>
    <summary>Who can remember passwords anyway? Real Bernie Sanders reaction source Larry David is an American comedian. He was the lead writer and producer of the Seinfeld TV series. During the previous and current election cycles he has played Presidential candidate Bernie Sanders in skits on Saturday Night Live. His “Bernie” rails about issues with passwords. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Who can remember passwords anyway?</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/larrydavidasbernie-1.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16542" height="140" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/larrydavidasbernie-1.jpg?w=200&amp;h=140" width="200"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Real Bernie Sanders reaction <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/ThisWeek/video/sen-bernie-sanders-reacts-larry-david-snl-impersonation-34555440">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Larry David is an American comedian. He was the lead writer and producer of the <em>Seinfeld</em> TV series. During the previous and current election cycles he has played Presidential candidate Bernie Sanders in skits on <em>Saturday Night Live</em>. His “Bernie” rails about issues with passwords.</p>
<p>
Today I want to talk about reducing our dependence on passwords.</p>
<p>
On SNL in October 2015, his “Bernie” branched off the topic of Hillary Clinton’s e-mails to famously <a href="https://www.geekwire.com/2015/this-snl-skit-starring-larry-david-as-bernie-sanders-claiming-to-be-bad-at-tech-is-a-big-youtube-hit/">rant</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> What’s the deal with e-mails anyway? I forgot my password the other day, so they say “We’ll email you a new one.” But I can’t get into my email to get the password. I mean, talk about a ball-buster. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
In the SNL <a href="https://deadline.com/2019/12/saturday-night-live-spoofs-democratic-debate-1202815760/">cold open</a> about the most recent debate three weeks ago, “Bernie” reprised the complaint:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Apple lies, Amazon lies, even my I-Phone lies. Every time it says it’s at 1 percent battery, it stays on for at least 20 minutes. The other times it’s at 7 percent—it shuts down immediately. Apple, what are you trying to hide? And what’s my password?!! </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Passwords are still needed. But, and this is the key, we wish to reduce our dependency on them and still be safe. Also the method fits nicely with today’s need for access to encrypted information by law enforcement. We have already discussed this recently <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/03/end-to-end-encryption-a-problem/">here</a>. The trick is to make information safe enough to please us, but not have as many passwords that we need to remember. “Bernie” would be happy. </p>
<p/><p>
Let’s next review why we use passwords at all.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Why We Have Passwords </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Passwords have been used forever. See our friends at Wikipedia for a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Password">story</a> by Polybius, an ancient historian, on how eons ago the Roman military used watchwords. Passwords have been used since the beginning of computing, forever in our world, to safeguard computer systems. The MIT computer system, CTSS, used them starting in 1961 to protect users. This is the reason Fernando Corbató is credited with the invention of computer passwords. </p>
<p>
The goal of passwords and watchwords, is simple: Control access. Both the real and fake Bernies use e-mail passwords to keep their communications private. We try to select good passwords, but the management of them can be challenging. It’s not just that people like “Bernie” forget theirs—it’s that our efforts to keep them in our heads often make them too easy to figure out. Jimmy Kimmel showed this in a 2017 <a href="https://www.cnet.com/news/jimmy-kimmel-gets-people-to-give-him-their-passwords/">segment</a> on his own show.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Passwords are Dead </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Managing passwords has lead to the theme, “passwords are dead.” If they are dead, then we must have alternative methods. Some are based on biometrics such as fingerprints and eye scans; others are based on additional hardware. Fingerprints are one of the most popular, but have major drawbacks: </p>
<ul>
<li>
They can be unreliable. <p/>
</li><li>
They can be attacked. <p/>
</li><li>
They cannot be changed.
</li></ul>
<p>I can attest that fingerprints are unreliable. I use a Global Pass to speed my re-entry into the US. After my flight arrives at the airport, I use a Global Pass machine that checks my fingerprints. The machine fails to recognize my fingerprints, every time. This forces me to talk to a custom agent and convince them am who I claim to be. Thus defeating the reason for using the Global Pass.</p>
<p>
A 2012 <a href="https://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/techreports/UCAM-CL-TR-817.html">study</a> by Joseph Bonneau, Cormac Herley, Paul Oorschot, and Frank Stajano tilted “The Quest to Replace Passwords” compared 35 alternatives to passwords on their security, usability, and deployability. They showed that most do better on security, many do better on usability. But all alternatives do worse on deployability. The authors conclude: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “Marginal gains are often not sufficient to reach the activation energy necessary to overcome significant transition costs, which may provide the best explanation of why we are likely to live considerably longer before seeing the funeral procession for passwords arrive at the cemetery.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Colorful language, but the point is that passwords are hard to beat.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> How to Remove Them </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I have a proposal on how to avoid reliance on just passwords. At least for many applications. The idea is: You would use a password and add a secret password that you do not remember. You do not even know this password. You do not write it down. Clearly, this is additional security if you do not even know the secret password. No one can steal it from you or guess it.</p>
<p>
So the issue is: How do you access your own stuff without accessing the secret password? The answer is simple: You run a program that tries all the possibilities. Let this take some time <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/>. This point is that for many situations you will not mind if <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> is large. For example, when the access that you are protecting occurs rarely. The security that this affords is based on this: An attacker can and will definitely be able to get access by expending <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> time, if they also know you standard password. But this protects against mass attacks. An attacker may be able to get your data, but will not be able to get millions of people’s data.</p>
<p>
Let’s examine a few applications: </p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>End-to-end Encryption:</i> The secret password could be protected by a <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> of order years or even decades of computer time. This would allow law enforcement to get information it needs, while stopping causal attackers.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>Recovery of your data:</i> The secret password could be protected by a <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> of order days of computer time. Your computer backup data is secured by such a password. Then it crashes. You need to run such a computation to recover the data. In many situations this would be fine.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>A banking site:</i> You would still use a good password. The extra secret one could have a <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> of an hour say. Then when you need to pay an on-line bill, you would have to wait a reasonable amount of time.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>Not need to place passwords in your will:</i> Omada King, in his 2013 <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Making-Identity-Passwords-Personal-Transformation/dp/1479781177">book</a> <em>The Making Identity</em>, wrote: </p>
<blockquote><p><em>[A]ccording to a recent survey from the University of London, one in ten people are now leaving their passwords in their wills to pass on this important information when they die. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This could be avoided by using a secret password with <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> of order <em>months</em>. When it is needed the heirs would run the recovery program and get the access they need.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Ken’s Words </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Ken points out that merely trying more than a few possibilities will usually generate a suspicious-activity message and usually a shutdown. So a system would have to be set up to permit “self-hacking.” Ken has a small rotation of “password extenders” not written down and often has to try two or three before gaining access to non-financial sites where he is registered.</p>
<p>
Ken is sometimes asked to monitor chess tournaments for possible cheating using the initial “screening” phase of his system. This phase requires minimal effort from Ken as it is supposed to be automated on a server that any chess tournament director would have quick access to, but for various reasons the International Chess Federation (FIDE) has not (yet) erected such a server. So Ken posts the auto-generated reports at a private location known only to him and the arbiter(s) of a particular tournament.</p>
<p>
Ken does not maintain a password scheme for the reports. This would become a headache precisely because of the difficulties people have with passwords. Ken does not want to assume the responsibility for managing them. Instead he includes a “quasi-password” as part of the URL he creates. These are often multi-lingual puns or references to quirky artists or factoids in the home country of the tournament. Being memorable and unusual enables the arbiter’s browser to learn the word and link without collision. </p>
<p>
This maximizes convenience: For Ken to e-mail reports or zipped folders as attachments would be cumbersome under daily updates. With Ken’s way, the arbiter can view updates even without having to pull up Ken’s previous e-mails with links, just by typing some letters of the weird word in the browser address bar. Hiding directory listings and a “no robots” directive completes minimal security for temporary use during the tournament.</p>
<p>
</p><h2> The First and Last Word? </h2><p/>
<p>We mentioned Fernando Corbató having originated passwords.  But before his passing last July 12, he came to regret them.  <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/despite-data-thefts-the-password-endures-1400725381">Here</a> he is quoted:</p>
<blockquote><p>
“It’s become a kind of nightmare.  I don’t think anybody can possibly remember all the passwords.”
</p></blockquote>
<p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
How practical do you find the “no-password” idea? At least the above suggestion may save us from having to place passwords in our wills. </p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-08T05:31:02Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-08T05:31:02Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="Bernie Sanders"/>
    <category term="crypto"/>
    <category term="Fernando Corbato"/>
    <category term="Larry David"/>
    <category term="passwords"/>
    <category term="security"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02191</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02191" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Equivalence Classes and Conditional Hardness in Massively Parallel Computations</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578441600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nanongkai:Danupon.html">Danupon Nanongkai</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Scquizzato:Michele.html">Michele Scquizzato</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.02191">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Massively Parallel Computation (MPC) model serves as a common abstraction
of many modern large-scale data processing frameworks, and has been receiving
increasingly more attention over the past few years, especially in the context
of classical graph problems. So far, the only way to argue lower bounds for
this model is to condition on conjectures about the hardness of some specific
problems, such as graph connectivity on promise graphs that are either one
cycle or two cycles, usually called the one cycle vs. two cycles problem. This
is unlike the traditional arguments based on conjectures about complexity
classes (e.g., $\textsf{P} \neq \textsf{NP}$), which are often more robust in
the sense that refuting them would lead to groundbreaking algorithms for a
whole bunch of problems.
</p>
<p>In this paper we present connections between problems and classes of problems
that allow the latter type of arguments. These connections concern the class of
problems solvable in a sublogarithmic amount of rounds in the MPC model,
denoted by $\textsf{MPC}(o(\log N))$, and some standard classes concerning
space complexity, namely $\textsf{L}$ and $\textsf{NL}$, and suggest
conjectures that are robust in the sense that refuting them would lead to many
surprisingly fast new algorithms in the MPC model. We also obtain new
conditional lower bounds, and prove new reductions and equivalences between
problems in the MPC model.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02172</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02172" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Data Structure Primitives on Persistent Memory: An Evaluation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578441600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/G=ouml=tze:Philipp.html">Philipp Götze</a>, Arun Kumar Tharanatha, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sattler:Kai=Uwe.html">Kai-Uwe Sattler</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.02172">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Persistent Memory (PM), as already available e.g. with Intel Optane DC
Persistent Memory, represents a very promising, next generation memory solution
with a significant impact on database architectures. Several data structures
for this new technology and its properties have already been proposed. However,
primarily merely complete structures were presented and evaluated hiding the
impact of the individual ideas and PM characteristics. Therefore, in this
paper, we disassemble the structures presented so far, identify their
underlying design primitives, and assign them to appropriate design goals
regarding PM. As a result of our comprehensive experiments on real PM hardware,
we were able to reveal the trade-offs of the primitives at the micro level.
From this, performance profiles could be derived for selected primitives. With
these it is possible to precisely identify their best use cases as well as
vulnerabilities. Beside our general insights regarding PM-based data structure
design, we also discovered new promising combinations not considered in the
literature so far.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02144</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02144" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Lifting with Simple Gadgets and Applications to Circuit and Proof Complexity</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578441600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rezende:Susanna_F=_de.html">Susanna F. de Rezende</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Meir:Or.html">Or Meir</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nordstr=ouml=m:Jakob.html">Jakob Nordström</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pitassi:Toniann.html">Toniann Pitassi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Robere:Robert.html">Robert Robere</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vinyals:Marc.html">Marc Vinyals</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.02144">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We significantly strengthen and generalize the theorem lifting
Nullstellensatz degree to monotone span program size by Pitassi and Robere
(2018) so that it works for any gadget with high enough rank, in particular,
for useful gadgets such as equality and greater-than. We apply our generalized
theorem to solve two open problems:
</p>
<p>* We present the first result that demonstrates a separation in proof power
for cutting planes with unbounded versus polynomially bounded coefficients.
Specifically, we exhibit CNF formulas that can be refuted in quadratic length
and constant line space in cutting planes with unbounded coefficients, but for
which there are no refutations in subexponential length and subpolynomial line
space if coefficients are restricted to be of polynomial magnitude.
</p>
<p>* We give the first explicit separation between monotone Boolean formulas and
monotone real formulas. Specifically, we give an explicit family of functions
that can be computed with monotone real formulas of nearly linear size but
require monotone Boolean formulas of exponential size. Previously only a
non-explicit separation was known.
</p>
<p>An important technical ingredient, which may be of independent interest, is
that we show that the Nullstellensatz degree of refuting the pebbling formula
over a DAG G over any field coincides exactly with the reversible pebbling
price of G. In particular, this implies that the standard decision tree
complexity and the parity decision tree complexity of the corresponding
falsified clause search problem are equal.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02139</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.02139" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Computing the rearrangement distance of natural genomes</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578441600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Leonard Bohnenkämper, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Braga:Mar=iacute=lia_D=_V=.html">Marília D. V. Braga</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Doerr:Daniel.html">Daniel Doerr</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Stoye:Jens.html">Jens Stoye</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.02139">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The computation of genomic distances has been a very active field of
computational comparative genomics over the last 25 years. Substantial results
include the polynomial-time computability of the inversion distance by
Hannenhalli and Pevzner in 1995 and the introduction of the double-cut and join
(DCJ) distance by Yancopoulos et al. in 2005. Both results, however, rely on
the assumption that the genomes under comparison contain the same set of unique
markers (syntenic genomic regions, sometimes also referred to as genes). In
2015, Shao, Lin and Moret relax this condition by allowing for duplicate
markers in the analysis. This generalized version of the genomic distance
problem is NP-hard, and they give an ILP solution that is efficient enough to
be applied to real-world datasets. A restriction of their approach is that it
can be applied only to balanced genomes, that have equal numbers of duplicates
of any marker. Therefore it still needs a delicate preprocessing of the input
data in which excessive copies of unbalanced markers have to be removed.
</p>
<p>In this paper we present an algorithm solving the genomic distance problem
for natural genomes, in which any marker may occur an arbitrary number of
times. Our method is based on a new graph data structure, the multi-relational
diagram, that allows an elegant extension of the ILP by Shao, Lin and Moret to
count runs of markers that are under- or over-represented in one genome with
respect to the other and need to be inserted or deleted, respectively. With
this extension, previous restrictions on the genome configurations are lifted,
for the first time enabling an uncompromising rearrangement analysis. Any
marker sequence can directly be used for the distance calculation.
</p>
<p>The evaluation of our approach shows that it can be used to analyze genomes
with up to a few ten thousand markers, which we demonstrate on simulated and
real data.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.01961</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.01961" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Complexity Issues of String to Graph Approximate Matching</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578441600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dondi:Riccardo.html">Riccardo Dondi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mauri:Giancarlo.html">Giancarlo Mauri</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zoppis:Italo.html">Italo Zoppis</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.01961">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The problem of matching a query string to a directed graph, whose vertices
are labeled by strings, has application in different fields, from data mining
to computational biology. Several variants of the problem have been considered,
depending on the fact that the match is exact or approximate and, in this
latter case, which edit operations are considered and where are allowed. In
this paper we present results on the complexity of the approximate matching
problem, where edit operations are symbol substitutions and are allowed only on
the graph labels or both on the graph labels and the query string. We introduce
a variant of the problem that asks whether there exists a path in a graph that
represents a query string with any number of edit operations and we show that
is is NP-complete, even when labels have length one and in the case the
alphabet is binary. Moreover, when it is parameterized by the length of the
input string and graph labels have length one, we show that the problem is
fixed-parameter tractable and it is unlikely to admit a polynomial kernel. The
NP-completeness of this problem leads to the inapproximability (within any
factor) of the approximate matching when edit operations are allowed only on
the graph labels. Moreover, we show that the variants of approximate string
matching to graph we consider are not fixed-parameter tractable, when the
parameter is the number of edit operations, even for graphs that have distance
one from a DAG. The reduction for this latter result allows us to prove the
inapproximability of the variant where edit operations can be applied both on
the query string and on graph labels.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.01914</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.01914" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum Algorithms for the Most Frequently String Search, Intersection of Two String Sequences and Sorting of Strings Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578441600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Khadiev:Kamil.html">Kamil Khadiev</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Ilikaev:Artem.html">Artem Ilikaev</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.01914">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study algorithms for solving three problems on strings. The first one is
the Most Frequently String Search Problem. The problem is the following. Assume
that we have a sequence of $n$ strings of length $k$. The problem is finding
the string that occurs in the sequence most often. We propose a quantum
algorithm that has a query complexity $\tilde{O}(n \sqrt{k})$. This algorithm
shows speed-up comparing with the deterministic algorithm that requires
$\Omega(nk)$ queries. The second one is searching intersection of two sequences
of strings. All strings have the same length $k$. The size of the first set is
$n$ and the size of the second set is $m$. We propose a quantum algorithm that
has a query complexity $\tilde{O}((n+m) \sqrt{k})$. This algorithm shows
speed-up comparing with the deterministic algorithm that requires
$\Omega((n+m)k)$ queries. The third problem is sorting of $n$ strings of length
$k$. On the one hand, it is known that quantum algorithms cannot sort objects
asymptotically faster than classical ones. On the other hand, we focus on
sorting strings that are not arbitrary objects. We propose a quantum algorithm
that has a query complexity $O(n (\log n)^2 \sqrt{k})$. This algorithm shows
speed-up comparing with the deterministic algorithm (radix sort) that requires
$\Omega((n+d)k)$ queries, where $d$ is a size of the alphabet.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.01803</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2001.01803" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A new approach on estimating the fluid temperature in a multiphase flow system using particle filter method</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1578441600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dang:Zhuoran.html">Zhuoran Dang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2001.01803">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Fluid temperature is important for the analysis of the heat transfers in
thermal hydraulics. An accurate measurement or estimation of the fluid
temperature in multiphase flows is challenging. This is due to that the
thermocouple signal that mixes with temperature signals for each phase and
non-negligible noises. This study provides a new approach to estimate the local
fluid temperature in multiphase flows using experimental time-series
temperature signal. The thermocouple signal is considered to be a sequence with
Markov property and the particle filter method is utilized in the new method to
extract the fluid temperature. A complete description of the new method is
presented in this article.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-01-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-01-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://thmatters.wordpress.com/?p=1291</id>
    <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2020/01/06/tcs-job-market-profiles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS job market profiles</title>
    <summary>Earlier this academic year, CATCS started a project to collect the profiles of TCS candidates on the job market this academic year. Those profiles can now be found at this webpage. The webpage offers a limited amount of search functionality, and we are continuing to improve the layout and add features. If you are at […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Earlier this academic year, CATCS <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2019/10/02/a-solicitation-for-tcs-job-market-profiles/">started a project</a> to collect the profiles of TCS candidates on the job market this academic year. Those profiles can now be found at <a href="http://tcsjobcandidates.web.unc.edu/job-candidates/">this webpage</a>. The webpage offers a limited amount of search functionality, and we are continuing to improve the layout and add features.</p>
<p>If you are at an institution that is hiring in theory, please feel free to use this database and share it with your colleagues as appropriate.</p>
<p>If you are going on the job market and would like to fill out a profile, please use <a href="http://tcsjobcandidates.web.unc.edu/application/">this form</a>. We will periodically update the webpage adding newer profiles.</p>
<p>Many thanks to Nicole Immorlica, Jack Snoeyink, and Chris Umans for putting together the website, and to all those who contributed their profiles. Questions and comments may be emailed to Shuchi Chawla.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-06T23:23:25Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-06T23:23:25Z</published>
    <category term="for PhD students"/>
    <category term="postdocs"/>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shuchic</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://thmatters.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theory Matters</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1096</id>
    <link href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1096" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>We are looking for YOU to join our award-winning scientific team!</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Have you just graduated your PhD and are considering a post-doc position in theory of informatics? Science is your passion and you would like to spend most of your post-doc researching on whatever interests you? You are in the right … <a href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1096">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Have you just graduated your PhD and are considering a post-doc position in theory of informatics? Science is your passion and you would like to spend most of your post-doc researching on whatever interests you? You are in the right place.</p>



<p>At MIM UW we offer you:</p>



<ol><li>Great FREEDOM OF CHOICE related to what to work on;</li><li>Just A FEW or NO teaching duties;</li><li>A lot of TIME FOR RESEARCH;</li><li>Chance to cooperate with VERY EXPERIENCED and TALENTED scientists;</li><li>FRIENDLY environment;</li><li>Excellent SUPPORT from our administrative staff;</li></ol>



<p>If you still hesitate, here are two interviews with former post-docs in ERC GRANT TUgbOAT.</p>



<p>Watch a video and find out more about benefits of working at MIM UW.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">

</div>Watch an interview with Krzysztof Fleszar, post-doc at the Faculty of Mathematics, Informatics and Mechanics, University of Warsaw and find out how the participation in the project has changed his life. <br/>For more information about ERC GRANT  TUgbOAT visit our blog <a href="https://duch.mimuw.edu.pl/~tugboat/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://duch.mimuw.edu.pl/~tugboat/</a>.</figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">

</div>Adam Karczmarz told us about his experience as a post-doc at the Faculty of Mathematics, Informatics and Mechanics, University of Warsaw in ERC GRANT „Towards Unification of Algorithmic Tools”. <br/>To find out more about TUgbOAT project visit our blog <a href="https://duch.mimuw.edu.pl/~tugboat/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://duch.mimuw.edu.pl/~tugboat/</a>.</figure></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-06T19:39:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-06T19:39:00Z</published>
    <category term="post"/>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Renata Czarniecka</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl</id>
      <link href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>University of Warsaw</subtitle>
      <title>Banach's Algorithmic Corner</title>
      <updated>2020-01-08T23:39:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2020/01/06/complexity-theory-with-a-human-face/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2020/01/06/complexity-theory-with-a-human-face/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Complexity Theory with a Human Face</title>
    <summary>September 1-4, 2020 Czech Republic http://users.math.cas.cz/talebanfard/workshop2020/ The workshop consists of excellent speakers giving enlightening tutorials on delectable aspects of complexity theory which will take place in Tábor, Czech Republic. The event is co-organized with Krajíček’s Fest celebrating the 60th birthday of Jan Krajíček.</summary>
    <updated>2020-01-06T13:42:39Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-06T13:42:39Z</published>
    <category term="workshop"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:24:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-32902056.post-8905653443034252450</id>
    <link href="http://paulwgoldberg.blogspot.com/feeds/8905653443034252450/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=32902056&amp;postID=8905653443034252450" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/32902056/posts/default/8905653443034252450" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/32902056/posts/default/8905653443034252450" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://paulwgoldberg.blogspot.com/2020/01/on-leaving-eu.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On leaving the EU</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div dir="ltr" style="text-align: left;">For someone based in the UK who works in any kind of international market, it looks reasonable to consider how his business strategy should be affected by leaving the EU. In the case of CS theory research, this perhaps runs counter to an idealised view in which all research is global, and should not be affected by squalid political considerations. The interest inherent in any specific problem or result ought to be independent of where it was studied. On a related note, it may be felt that it’s the research topic that chooses the researcher, not the researcher who chooses the topic. On the other hand, even in CS theory, ones political environment and associated social networks may have a stronger effect than we would like to acknowledge.<br/><br/>When I was a graduate student, Algorithms and Computational Complexity was relatively under-represented in the UK, compared with today. The UK theory community was dominated by so-called “Euro-theory”, which at the time did not seem to exhibit obvious points of contact with algorithms research. People like me had to look west for assurance that our research was of wider interest than what was apparent in our own backyard. To further justify that west-looking approach, it was clear that the USA was, in terms of research, the undisputed world leader. Then as now, it collected the lion’s share of Nobel prizes. It had industrial research labs producing leading CS theory research, such as IBM, AT&amp;T, and NEC, while Europe had nothing similar. For me, this sowed the seeds of a defiantly Atlanticist attitude to CS theory research — appropriate for Brexit Britain, perhaps? — that the best way to pursue high-quality research was via links with colleagues in the USA.<br/><br/>Fast-forward to about five years ago, and my attitude had softened. The UK’s algorithms-and-complexity community steadily grew, and is much larger than it was in the early 90’s. Travel within Europe is relatively quick and cheap, with no visa issues. The European research community became a bit of a comfort-zone, while the USA’s research ethic seemed comparatively intense and high-pressure. The perennial question of “Where’s my next STOC/FOCS paper going to come from?” has always seemed less urgent in Europe.<br/><br/>The EU has attempted to unify Europe’s academic research activity, which is supported by diverse governments, and gives rise to diverse complaints among European colleagues. I am reminded of the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_Karenina_principle">unhappy families</a>” quote from <i>Anna Karenina</i>. In an attempt to give it a bit of unity, there’s some EU funding for research, concerning which we have this criticism from <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/uploads/2018/06/geim_lecture.pdf">Andre Geim’s Nobel prize speech</a>:  “I can offer no nice words for the EU Framework programmes which, except for the  European Research Council, can be praised only by Europhobes for discrediting the whole idea of an effectively working Europe.” For my part, I recently tried to get a grant from the European Research Council but they turned me down. If I were a rational agent, I should at this point be one of Geim’s Europhobes; of course in reality things are not quite so simple. But at this point I reckon the US research funding system looks like the least worst. <a href="http://occamstypewriter.org/athenedonald/2019/12/16/post-election-christmas-reading-list/">A recent article</a> at Athene Donald’s blog discusses the post-EU era and the idea of a DARPA-like research agency for the UK.<br/><br/>So, leaving the EU looks like an opportune point to dust off the above-mentioned “Atlanticist attitude”. These days China is also becoming more important. But I hope that Europe will not give up on us, but will compete strenuously with them for our attention.</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-06T12:21:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-06T12:21:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="aggregator"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="politics"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="UK"/>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Goldberg</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/10952445127830395305</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-32902056</id>
      <category term="aggregator"/>
      <category term="UK academia"/>
      <category term="politics"/>
      <category term="meetings"/>
      <category term="research"/>
      <category term="research directions"/>
      <category term="conferences"/>
      <category term="funding"/>
      <category term="people"/>
      <category term="rant"/>
      <category term="economics"/>
      <category term="academia"/>
      <category term="forecasts"/>
      <category term="internet"/>
      <category term="advertisement"/>
      <category term="game theory"/>
      <category term="trips"/>
      <category term="University of Liverpool"/>
      <category term="editorial"/>
      <category term="technical"/>
      <category term="times higher"/>
      <category term="announcements"/>
      <category term="publications"/>
      <category term="teaching"/>
      <category term="work"/>
      <category term="postgraduate research"/>
      <category term="technology"/>
      <category term="books"/>
      <category term="social choice"/>
      <category term="talks"/>
      <category term="CACM"/>
      <category term="games"/>
      <category term="liverpool"/>
      <category term="open problems"/>
      <category term="problems"/>
      <category term="research assessment"/>
      <category term="tongue in cheek"/>
      <category term="administration"/>
      <category term="architecture"/>
      <category term="email"/>
      <category term="environment"/>
      <category term="mechanism design"/>
      <category term="puzzles"/>
      <category term="web sites"/>
      <category term="URLs"/>
      <category term="USS"/>
      <category term="education"/>
      <category term="higher education"/>
      <category term="oxford"/>
      <category term="schools"/>
      <category term="UCU"/>
      <category term="UK"/>
      <category term="go"/>
      <category term="intellectual property"/>
      <category term="jobs"/>
      <category term="league table"/>
      <category term="math education"/>
      <category term="money"/>
      <category term="products"/>
      <category term="science"/>
      <category term="students"/>
      <category term="Liberal democrats"/>
      <category term="XJTLU"/>
      <category term="behavioural economics"/>
      <category term="china"/>
      <category term="current affairs"/>
      <category term="diversity"/>
      <category term="epsrc"/>
      <category term="family"/>
      <category term="geography"/>
      <category term="holidays"/>
      <category term="joke"/>
      <category term="misc"/>
      <category term="nerd humour"/>
      <category term="pensions"/>
      <category term="predictions"/>
      <category term="proposals"/>
      <category term="psephology"/>
      <category term="region"/>
      <category term="student finance"/>
      <category term="visits"/>
      <category term="warwick"/>
      <category term="web"/>
      <category term="weekends"/>
      <category term="wikipedia"/>
      <category term="writing"/>
      <author>
        <name>Paul Goldberg</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/10952445127830395305</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://paulwgoldberg.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/32902056/posts/default/-/aggregator" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://paulwgoldberg.blogspot.com/search/label/aggregator" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/32902056/posts/default/-/aggregator/-/aggregator?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>theoretical computer science, economics, and academic life in general. Writing in personal capacity, not representing my employer or other colleagues</subtitle>
      <title>Paul Goldberg</title>
      <updated>2020-01-06T14:26:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8980814517027039027</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/8980814517027039027/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/01/the-wikipedia-entry-on-np-intermediary.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8980814517027039027" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8980814517027039027" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/01/the-wikipedia-entry-on-np-intermediary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Wikipedia Entry on NP-Intermediary Problems lists one of mine! I'm not bragging about it.</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I recently needed to look at what NP problems were possibly intermediary (neither in P nor NP-complete). So I went to Wikipedia and found <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NP-intermediate">this</a>.<br/>
<br/>
They had many problems, though some I had never heard of. Those that I had never heard of<br/>
<br/>
<i>should they be on the list?</i><br/>
<i><br/>
</i> That is, are they natural? That is hard to define rigorously, but I will take you through my train of thought as I read the first few:<br/>
<br/>
<b>Factoring Integers</b>. Yes, quite possibly intermediary: If  its NPC then PH collapses, and, at least so far, does not seem to be in P.  (the NPC--&gt; PH collapse result: We take<br/>
<br/>
FACT = { (n,x) : n has a nontrivial factor ≤ x }<br/>
<br/>
FACT is clearly in NP:<br/>
a complete factorization of n provides evidence that some nontrivial factor is \le x.<br/>
<br/>
FACT is clearly in coNP:<br/>
a complete factorization of n provides evidence that no nontrivial factor is \le x<br/>
<br/>
so if FACT is NP-complete then SAT is in coNP.<br/>
<br/>
Factoring is clearly an important and well studied problem. It even has its own Wikipedia entry!<br/>
<br/>
<b>Discrete Log</b>. Similar to Factoring. And it is also an important and well studied problem. It even has its own Wikipedia Entry!<br/>
<br/>
<b>Isomorphism Problems</b> They list Group and Ring isomorphism. They don't list Graph, which is odd. (ADDED LATER- my bad, they do mention Graph Isom in the section on Graph Algorithms) Anyway, if Graph Isom is NPC then PH collapses, and, at least so far, there is no algorithm for Graph Isom in P. (I do not think it is know if Group Isom NPC means PH collapses, or if Ring Isom NPC means PH collapses---if you know of such a proof leave a comment and a pointer to it.)<br/>
<br/>
Graph Isomorphism is a well studied problem and seems important and natural (I don't know if Graph Isomorphism has any real applications they way that factoring and DL do).  It even has its own Wikipedia entry! Group and Ring Isomorphism also seem important and natural. And they have their own Wikipedia entry!<br/>
<br/>
<b>Numbers in Boxes Problem </b>My first reaction-Gee, whats that? For the Factoring, DL, and Isomorphism they did not define the problem-- they gave pointers to the Wikipedia entries on them. For this one there was no Wikipedia entry. There was one reference. I went to it. <i>It was a blog entry of mine</i>! Here it is: <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2010/07/what-is-complexity-of-these-problems.html">her</a>e, and to save you time I'll say what it is:<br/>
<br/>
{ (1<sup>n</sup>,1<sup>k</sup>) : you can partition 1,...,n into k boxes so that no box has x,y,z with x + y = z }<br/>
<br/>
Is this problem important? Does it exist anywhere outside of my blog entry? Yes--- a special case of it was in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Doctor-Eccos-Cyberpuzzles-Dennis-Shasha/dp/0393325415/ref=sr_1_2?keywords=Dr.+Ecco&amp;qid=1577931523&amp;s=books&amp;sr=1-2">Dr. Ecco's Cyperpuzzles by Dennis Shasha</a> (note- Dennis was a classmate of mine in graduate school at Harvard). I think the case was to try to partition {1,...,100} as best you can. Actually I first saw the case of the problem in his book and then generalized it.<br/>
<br/>
The problem is sparse so if it was NP-complete then P = NP, very good evidence that its not NPC. And its been studied for thousands of years, with people looking for poly time algorithms (I think Pythagoras studied it) without success, so its almost surely not in P. OR that last sentence was complete nonsense. Indeed, I don't think anyone has studied the problem computationally, or, for that matter, at all. So the evidence that its not in P is... sparse.<br/>
<br/>
But its worse than that. One could devise MANY sparse problems that are, since spares, likely NOT NPC, and hardly studied, so as-of-now, not in P. Should those count? Only if (a) more people study them so there is an attempt to point to to get it into P, and (b) the problem is natural (which is hard to define).<br/>
<br/>
Note that I can vary the problem: x+2y=z (this relates to lower bounds on VDW numbers)<br/>
or any other combination of x,y,z or more that I like.<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
This raises a question:<br/>
<br/>
<b>When is a problem worthy of being put on lists of problems?</b><br/>
<b><br/>
</b> Here are some possibly criteria. One can take ANDS and ORS of them.<br/>
<br/>
1) The problem has a Wikipedia entry. This might fall victim to Goodhearts law: when a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a measure.  That is, I could make a Wikipedia entry on the Number-in-boxes problem and then say LOOK, its on Wikipedia!<br/>
<br/>
2) More than X people have worked on the problem for some value of X. But here is a reason this might not be a good criteria: look at the problem<br/>
<br/>
{ α : α is a reg expression that allows numbers (so a<sup>1000</sup> is fine, makes reg expressions  VERY succint) such that L(α)=Σ<sup>*</sup> }<br/>
<br/>
This problem looks natural, and was proven by Meyer and Stockmeyer to be EXPSPACE complete.<br/>
That is the only paper on this problem, yet the problem really does look natural, and the result is rightly celebrated as a natural problem that is provably not in P.<br/>
<br/>
3) When people in the field look at the problem they say YEAH, thats a good problem.<br/>
<br/>
4) The problem relates to other problems or other fields.<br/>
<br/>
I doubt the Number-in-boxes problem satisfies any of these criteria. The variant with x+2y=z relates to Ramsey Theory. Great.<br/>
<br/>
NOW, back to the list-- I won't go through any more on the list, but I note that for some of them the only reference seems to be a conversation on stack-exchange.  Some of those end up referring to real papers so are more likely natural, but some do not.<br/>
<br/>
Having said that, is there any harm in the list having on it some problems that are not ... worthy? Is that even the right word to use?<br/>
<br/>
Note that I don't have strong opinions on any of these matters, I am just wondering what criteria Wikipedia, and other sources, uses, when they have lists of problems.<br/>
<b><br/>
</b> <b><br/>
</b> <b><br/>
</b> <b><br/>
</b></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-06T04:54:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-06T04:54:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T01:35:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1250</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1250" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for December 2019</title>
    <summary>Happy new year! And now for the last post of 2019 papers. We have found a diverse collection of six papers, ranging from classic property testing topics to new perspectives on sublinear computation. Sublinear Optimal Policy Value Estimation in Contextual Bandits by Weihao Kong, Gregory Valiant, Emma Brunskill (arXiv). This isn’t our usual sublinear paper, but it […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Happy new year! And now for the last post of 2019 papers. We have found a diverse collection of six papers, ranging from classic property testing topics to new perspectives on sublinear computation. </p>



<p><strong>Sublinear Optimal Policy Value Estimation in Contextual Bandits</strong> by Weihao Kong, Gregory Valiant, Emma Brunskill (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.06111">arXiv</a>). This isn’t our usual sublinear paper, but it is definitely of interest to us sublinear folk. Let’s start with a stripped down definition of the problem (or rather, game). There are \(K\) “arms”, where the \(i\)th arm is represented by an unknown vector in \(\beta_i \in \mathbb{R}^d\). We are presented with a “context”, which is a vector \(x \in \mathbb{R}^d\). Our job is to choose an arm \(i \in [K]\). We get the reward \(x \cdot \beta_i\) (with some noise added). The contexts appears from a known distribution. To aid us, we observe the rewards of \(N\) iid contexts, so we observe a total of \(T = KN\) rewards. There has been much work on figuring out the minimum value of \(T\) required to learn the optimal policy. One requires at least \(d\) (the dimension) samples to estimate any of the arm vectors. This papers shows that one can actually estimate the expected reward of the optimal policy, without being able to describe it, with sublinear in \(d\) (technically, \(\widetilde{O}(\sqrt{d})\)) samples. We see this a lot in property testing, where producing the “optimal” solution for a problem requires linear-in-dimension samples, but estimating the optimal value is much cheaper (consider, for example, the situation of linearity testing, where we wish to find the closest linear function).</p>



<p><strong>Sublinear Time Numerical Linear Algebra for Structured Matrices </strong>by Xiaofei Shi and David P. Woodruff (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1912.06060.pdf">arXiv</a>). This follows the recent linear of advances in sublinear time linear algebra. Given a matrix \(A \in \mathbb{R}^{n \times d}\), the aim is to get algorithms that only look at \(o(nnz(A))\) entries (where \(nnz(A)\) is the number of non-zeroes, or the support). Consider the classic talk of low rank approximation. Unfortunately, suppose one entry is extremely large, and the others are extremely small. One has to find this large entry for any reasonable approximation, which (in the worst-case) requires \(nnz(A)\) queries into \(A\). Thus, previous papers make structural assumption (such as, \(A\) being a Vandermonde matrix) to get sublinear bounds. This paper gives a clean black box method to get a variety of such results. Basically, one can replace the usual \(nnz(A)\) term in many algorithms, by \(T(A)\), which is the time to compute the matrix-vector product \( Ay\), for \(y \in \mathbb{R}^d\). In many cases \(T(A) = \widetilde{O}(n)\), which can be significantly smaller than \(nnz(A)\). This paper gives such results for low-rank approximations and many regression problems.</p>



<p><strong>Robust and Sample Optimal Algorithms for PSD Low-Rank Approximation</strong> by Ainesh Bakshi, Nadiia Chepurko, and David P. Woodruff. Consider the low rank problem discussed above. As mentioned in the previous paragraph, we need structural assumptions on \(A\). Previous results gave sublinear time low-rank approximations assuming that \(A\) is positive semidefinite (PSD). The aim is to get a rank \(k\) matrix \(B\) such that \(\|A-B\|^2_2\) is at most \((1+\epsilon)\)-times the optimal such approximation. The previous algorithm of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1704.03371">Musco-Woodruff</a> makes \(\widetilde{O}(nk/\epsilon^{2.5})\) queries in to \(A\), while there is a lower bound of \(\Omega(nk/\epsilon)\). This gap between the complexities is resolved in this paper with an upper bound of \(\widetilde{O}(nk/\epsilon)\) queries.</p>



<p><strong>Constructive derandomization of query algorithms </strong>by Guy Blanc, Jane Lange, and Li-Yang Tan (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.03042">arXiv</a>). This paper discusses an intriguing angle to sublinear question: when can they be derandomized? Abstractly, consider a randomized algorithm \(R\) that makes \(q\) queries. Think of \(R\) as a function \(R(x,r)\), where \(x\) is the input, and \(r\) is the randomness. We would like to design a deterministic algorithm \(D\) making, ideally, close to \(q\) queries and approximates \(\mathop{E}_r[R(x,r)]\). For starters, consider some distribution over \(x\), and suppose we want \(\mathbb{E}_x[D(x) – \mathbb{E}_r[R(x,r)]] &lt; \epsilon\). By (the easy direction of) Yao’s minimax lemma, one can show the existence of such an algorithm \(D\) that makes \(O(q/\epsilon)\) queries. But how to explicitly construct it? Indeed, the first result of this paper gives a “meta-algorithm” that takes as input the description of \(R\) (which is of size \(N\)), has running time \(poly(N)2^{O(q/\epsilon)}\) and outputs a description of \(D\). When \(R\) satisfies the stronger property of “bounded error”, one can get a \(O(q^3)\)-query algorithm \(D\) that approximates \(\mathop{E}_r[R(x,r)]\) for all \(x\) (again, the existence is proven by a classic theorem of Nisan). Overall, this paper gives a method to derandomize sublinear time algorithms, and I wonder if there could be some applications of this method for proving lower bounds. After all, Yao’s minimax theorem is <em>the</em> tool for property testing lower bounds, and any perspective on Yao’s theorem is likely of relevance. </p>



<p><strong>Testing Membership for Timed Automata</strong> by Richard Lassaigne and Michel de Rougemont (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08277">arXiv</a>). Property testing for regular languages is a classic result in sublinear algorithms. This paper focuses on the more complex notion of timed automata. The technical definition is quite complicated, but here’s an overview. There is a finite automaton and a collection of “clocks”. Imagine a string being processed, where each alphabet symbol appears with a new timestamp. Thus, the input word is called a “timed word”. The transitions of the automaton involve the new symbol read, as well as constraints involving the clock times and the timestamp. Thus, we can enforce conditions like “only transition if another symbol is read within a single time unit”. In general, deciding whether a timed word is accepted by a timed automaton is NP-complete. This papers studies the property testing viewpoint. The paper gives a new definition of “timed edit distance” between timed words. The main result shows that one can distinguish time words accepted by a timed automaton from words that are far (according to timed edit distance), by querying a constant number of word positions.</p>



<p><strong>On the query complexity of estimating the distance to hereditary graph properties</strong> by Carlos Hoppen, Yoshiharu Kohayakawa, Richard Lang, Hanno Lefmann, and Henrique Stagni (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.01081">arXiv</a>). This paper concerns the classic setting of property testing of dense graphs. It is well-known that all hereditary graph properties are testable, and are moreover, one can estimate the distance to the property in time that only depends on \(\varepsilon\). Unfortunately, the queries complexities have large tower dependencies on \(\varepsilon\), arising from the use of the Szemeredi regularity lemma. The question of property testing in dense graphs can be reduced to finding “removal” lemmas (such as the classic triangle remove lemma). Such a lemma states that if at least \(\varepsilon n^2\) edges need to be removed from \(G\) to destroy all “forbidden subgraphs”, then there must be “many” forbidden subgraphs in \(G\). There is much recent research on finding families of forbidden subgraphs, where the “many” (in the above statement) is at least \(poly(\varepsilon)\) times  the trivial upper bound. This paper shows that one can also estimate the distance to any hereditary property, in a query complexity that depends directly on the corresponding removal lemma parameters. As a compelling example, one can estimate the distance to being chordal in \(\exp(1/\varepsilon)\) queries, a significant improvement over standard tower bounds.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-05T23:35:14Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-05T23:35:14Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Seshadhri</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2020-01-08T23:40:50Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16522</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/01/05/servant-the-tv-show/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Servant: The TV Show</title>
    <summary>Using logic to try and understand the show Servant [ M. Night ] M. Night Shyamalan is the creator of many wonderful horror movies, including The Village and The Sixth Sense. His films often have a twist ending. Today I thought I would try to apply math and logic to his latest creation, the TV […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Using logic to try and understand the show Servant</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/01/05/servant-the-tv-show/unknown-132/" rel="attachment wp-att-16525"><img alt="" class="alignright size-full wp-image-16525" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/unknown.jpeg?w=600"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">[ M. Night ]</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>M. Night Shyamalan is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M._Night_Shyamalan">creator</a> of many wonderful horror movies, including <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Village_(2004_film)">The Village</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sixth_Sense">The Sixth Sense</a>. His films often have a twist ending.</p>
<p>
Today I thought I would try to apply math and logic to his latest creation, the TV show called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Servant_(TV_series)">Servant</a>.</p>
<p><span id="more-16522"/></p>
<p>
I am not kidding. No number theory, no complexity theory, no strange theorems today. I thought I would try and apply some logic to attempt and understand M. Night’s story. The story was created by Tony Basgallop but M. Night’s direction modulates what we can see and how we feel it. <em>Servant</em> is on cable, on Apple TV, and is close to the end. It is a series of ten short episodes and the last two are due out in the next few days. </p>
<p>
The story is strange, scary, and unusual. M. Night likes to play with his viewers and make stories that are difficult to understand. Like many of our problems: Think P=NP or the Riemann Hypothesis, or the <img alt="{3x+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B3x%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{3x+1}"/> function problem. Our problems are strange, scary, and unusual too. Our difficulty is that we do not have a date when all will be explained. As we discussed <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/22/predicting-when-pnp-is-resolved/">here</a>, we might be waiting a long time before we get the “last” episode for P=NP, for example.</p>
<p>
Take a look at the rest even if you have not watched the series. I would like to think that working out the “solution” to the Servant is possible, but probably hard. I am not likely to have the answer here, but I think I may be on the right track, at least.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Story in Short </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Here is a brief <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Servant_(TV_series)">summary</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Six weeks after the death of their 13-week-old son, Philadelphia couple Dorothy and Sean Turner hire a young nanny, Leanne, to move in and take care of Baby Jericho, a reborn doll. The doll, which Dorothy believes is her real child, was the only thing that brought her out of her catatonic state following Jericho’s death. While Sean deals with the grief on his own, he becomes deeply suspicious of Leanne. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The players are: </p>
<ul>
<li>
The baby, Jericho. <p/>
</li><li>
The mom, Dorothy <p/>
</li><li>
The dad, Sean. <p/>
</li><li>
The brother, Julian. <p/>
</li><li>
The nanny, Leanne.
</li></ul>
<p>
I like this statement about <a href="https://netflixlife.com/2019/12/28/servant-s1e7-darkest-theory-jericho/">Servant</a>: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <em>Servant</em> continues to frighten viewers while at the same time not providing audiences with answers. But have they been telling us more than we know? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> On-line Comments </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Like P=NP there is much debate and discussion about <em>Servant</em>. Here is a typical comment: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Never mind the mystery of whether Jericho is truly alive again or not, there’s also the fact that we have no idea how he died in the first place. New theory is that Dorothy killed him, either on accident or due to a bad postpartum depression episode. This would mean Julian and Sean covered it up. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
There are lots of details in the story that may or may not be important. There are many theories about what could be going on. One thing seems clear is that what is happening is mystery. Is it one that we can shed any light on?</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Jericho is the Key </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The discussions on-line about what is happening seem to miss the key: Is the baby, Jericho, a plastic baby or a real baby? Most seem to accept that the baby was plastic and then was replaced by a real baby. This is where I can apply logical analysis. Let’s walk through the possible cases:</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Perhaps Jericho is a magical object. Than the whole story is a dream. Or the players are ghosts. Or some other magical possibility. This reflects the fact that we do not have precise rules or axioms. M. Night could do anything he wishes. But I like to think that he plays by some rules. So let’s agree that this case is out.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Perhaps Jericho was a plastic baby at first and then became a real baby. This is the consensus of almost all viewers. At least if we can rely on their comments. The issue here is how does this work? How can a living baby suddenly appear? How can the mom and the nanny not notice the baby has become real? </p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Perhaps Jericho was always a plastic baby. This seems to not be considered as a plausible case. It does require that the father and the brother are crazy. I like this idea. </p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Perhaps Jericho was always a real baby. This seems to be the most unusual idea. I think M. Night might like this direction. It would be the biggest twist. The baby was always real. Here M. Night is laughing at us: he would get the biggest shock if Jericho is always real. It would explain much. Then the mom and the nanny are just fine, we do not need to assume that they are crazy at all. Then the father and the brother are nuts. </p>
<p>
I think the last is my favorite. I wish I could “prove” that the last is the case. In a few days we should know what M. Night selected for the answer. I feel that our methods at least forced us to consider all the logical possibilities. Is this the right answer?</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I hope you did not mind this diversion from hard core math. I think that applying logic may be useful here. Too bad we do not have a reveal date for our problems like P=NP.</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-05T17:35:21Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-05T17:35:21Z</published>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Logic"/>
    <category term="M. Night"/>
    <category term="Servant"/>
    <category term="TV show"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=19093</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/01/02/tomorrow-boolean-functions-day-at-the-tau-theory-fest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tomorrow: Boolean functions day at the TAU theory fest</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As part of the 2019/2020 TAU theory fest, tomorrow, Friday, January 3, 2020,  is a Boolean function day at Tel Aviv University. The five speakers are Esty Kelman, Noam Lifschitz, Renan Gross, Ohad Klein, and Naomi Kirshner. For more (and … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/01/02/tomorrow-boolean-functions-day-at-the-tau-theory-fest/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/bfd.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19094" height="270" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/01/bfd.png?w=640&amp;h=270" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>As part of the 2019/2020 TAU theory fest, tomorrow, <strong>Friday, January 3, 2020</strong>,  is <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/boolean-functions/home">a Boolean function day</a> at Tel Aviv University. The five speakers are <strong>Esty Kelman, Noam Lifschitz, Renan Gross, Ohad Klein</strong>, and <strong>Naomi Kirshner</strong>.</p>
<p>For more (and probably not all) mathematical activities in Israel these days including <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/event/abel-jerusalem">Abel in Jerusalem</a> see <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/18/abel-in-jerusalem-sunday-january-12-2020-and-other-events/">this post</a>.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/event/abel-jerusalem">Abel in Jerusalem site</a> has now the titles and abstracts of all talks. The talks are aimed so that advanced undergraduate students can learn from them and enjoy them. (The conference celebrating <a href="https://math.biu.ac.il/en/node/2870">Boris Solomyak’s birthday</a> was just added to the <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/18/abel-in-jerusalem-sunday-january-12-2020-and-other-events/">post</a> on current math activities in Israel.)</p>
<p>Windows in theory <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/12/30/a-bet-for-the-new-decade/">reports from the theory</a> fest on an exciting scientific bet between Elchanan Mossel and Subhash Khot. (Raising again the question if scientific bets are good.) Also in Windows in theory a <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/12/28/quantum-school-lecture-notes-videos-and-more-guest-post-by-dorit-aharonov/">report by Dorit Aharonov</a> on the winter school on mathematics of quantum computing at HUJI.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-02T18:39:32Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-02T18:39:32Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Conferences"/>
    <category term="Convex polytopes"/>
    <category term="Boris Solomyak"/>
    <category term="Esty Kelman"/>
    <category term="Muli Safra"/>
    <category term="Naomi Kirshner"/>
    <category term="Noam Lifschitz"/>
    <category term="Ohad Klein"/>
    <category term="Renan Gross"/>
    <category term="Yuval Filmus"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:22:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/01/02/postdoc-at-kth-royal-insitute-of-technology-apply-by-january-23-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/01/02/postdoc-at-kth-royal-insitute-of-technology-apply-by-january-23-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at KTH – Royal Insitute of Technology (apply by January 23, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The postdoc position is in the area of computational complexity theory, focusing on questions at the intersection of approximation algorithms and subexponential algorithms. . This is includes both hardness results and algorithmic results. If so desired, up to 20% teaching can be included in the position. The position is for one year with a possible […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The postdoc position is in the area of computational complexity theory, focusing on questions at the intersection of approximation algorithms and subexponential algorithms. . This is includes both hardness results and algorithmic results. If so desired, up to 20% teaching can be included in the position. The position is for one year with a possible (and likely) extension to a second year.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.kth.se/en/om/work-at-kth/lediga-jobb/what:job/jobID:308077/where:4/">https://www.kth.se/en/om/work-at-kth/lediga-jobb/what:job/jobID:308077/where:4/</a><br/>
Email: johanh@kth.se</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-02T09:14:29Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-02T09:14:29Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=684</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2020/01/01/publish-and-perish/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Publish and perish</title>
    <summary>Moshe Vardi’s latest insight in the Communications of the ACM (whose title we adopt for this post) agrees with our previous post “Because of pollution, conferences should be virtual.” Vardi calls for “sweeping policy change […] requiring that authors of accepted papers that must fly to participate in a conference may opt out from in-person […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2020/1/241717-publish-and-perish/fulltext">Moshe Vardi’s latest insight in the Communications of the ACM </a>(whose title we adopt for this post) agrees with our previous post “<a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2019/08/04/because-of-pollution-conferences-should-be-virtual/">Because of pollution, conferences should be virtual.</a>” Vardi calls for “sweeping policy change […] requiring that authors of accepted papers that must fly to  participate in a conference may opt out from in-person involvement and  contribute instead by video.”  Vardi gives some indication of the environmental impact of the travel-based system, and further suspects that in-person conference participation is “much less valuable than we would like to believe.”</p>



<p>These issues are closely related to the decades-old discussion of journals vs. conferences. <a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/tag/utopia/">Several older posts on this blog </a>were devoted to that. Lance Fortnow, back in 2009, wrote that it’s <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2009/8/34492-viewpoint-time-for-computer-science-to-grow-up/abstract">Time for computer science to grow up</a>.  The full text of this article is premium content, but you can read a pre-publication version <a href="http://www.cs.uchicago.edu/~fortnow/papers/growup.pdf">here</a>. Basically, he argues in favor of a journal-based publication system.</p>



<p>Apparently in response, judging from the title, Boaz Barak wrote a piece titled <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2016/6/202644-computer-science-should-stay-young/abstract">Computer science should stay young.</a> I can’t quickly find a link to the whole thing, but his bottom line is online “I disagree with the conclusion that we should transition to a classical journal-based model similar to that of other fields. I believe conferences offer a number of unique advantages that have helped make computer science dynamic and successful, and can continue to do so in the future.”</p>



<p>I disagree that conferences are young. They belong to the BI (before internet) era, and so look rather anchored in the past to me.  Historically, I also suppose in-person discussion predates writing, though this is irrelevant.  What is young is the health impact of pollution (Fortnow and Barak’s pieces don’t touch on health issues). (By health impact I include climate change, but I prefer not to use that term for various reasons.)</p>



<p>And what is young and cool is arxiv overlay journals, TCS+ talks, videoconferences,  <a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/">ECCC</a>, etc.</p>



<p>Instead, we impose on our community most inconvenient transoceanic flights.  To end I’ll quote from <a href="http://www.wisdom.weizmann.ac.il/~oded/MC/269.html">Oded Goldreich’s my choices</a>:</p>



<p><b>Phoenix in June:</b> […] One must be out of their mind to hold a conference under such weather conditions. I guess humans can endure such weather conditions and even worse ones, but why choose to do so? Why call upon people from all over the world to travel to one of the least comfortable locations (per the timing)?</p>


<p><!--EndFragment--><br/><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-01-01T17:03:39Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-01T17:03:39Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="health"/>
    <category term="Utopia"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:50Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/001</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/001" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-001 |  Nullstellensatz Size-Degree Trade-offs from Reversible Pebbling | 

	Or Meir, 

	Susanna de Rezende, 

	Jakob Nordström, 

	Robert Robere</title>
    <summary>We establish an exactly tight relation between reversible pebblings of graphs and Nullstellensatz refutations of pebbling formulas, showing that a graph $G$ can be reversibly pebbled in time $t$ and space $s$ if and only if there is a Nullstellensatz refutation of the pebbling formula over $G$ in size $t+1$ and degree $s$ (independently of the field in which the Nullstellensatz refutation  is made). We use this correspondence to prove a number of strong size-degree trade-offs for Nullstellensatz, which to the best of our   knowledge are the first such results for this proof system.</summary>
    <updated>2020-01-01T07:53:22Z</updated>
    <published>2020-01-01T07:53:22Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:22:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16509</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/31/resolutions-for-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Resolutions For 2020</title>
    <summary>Some fun about resolutions. source Ben Orlin is a funny mathematician. His book title Change Is the Only Constant was selected by the blog Math-Frolic as the best mathematics book of 2019. Today Ken and I want to try to get you to at least smile, if not laugh. Orlin is a funny chap—okay I […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Some fun about resolutions.</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/benorlin.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16511" height="192" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/benorlin.jpg?w=122&amp;h=192" width="122"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2"><a href="https://mathwithbaddrawings.com/about-2/">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Ben Orlin is a funny mathematician. His <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Change-Only-Constant-Wisdom-Calculus/dp/0316509086/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=sl1&amp;tag=math0b2-20&amp;linkId=4b0342416ae54d5080032b8cc09bfc93&amp;language=en_US">book</a> title <i>Change Is the Only Constant</i> was <a href="https://math-frolic.blogspot.com/2019/12/books-closing-out-2019-with-some-faves.html">selected</a> by the blog <em>Math-Frolic</em> as the best mathematics book of 2019.</p>
<p>
Today Ken and I want to try to get you to at least smile, if not laugh.</p>
<p>
Orlin is a funny chap—okay I just got back from London—so forgive me for using “chap”. Check Orlin’s site out for <a href="https://mathwithbaddrawings.com/2015/12/30/a-mathematicians-new-years-resolutions/">proof</a> that he is funny. Here are some of his <a href="https://mathwithbaddrawings.com/2017/09/13/literatures-greatest-opening-lines-as-written-by-mathematicians/">examples</a> of math types rewriting famous opening lines from books. We will make this into a kind of quiz. You must guess the book title from the modified quote:</p>
<ol>
<li>
The times had high variance. <p/>
</li><li>
Up to isomorphism there is one happy family. <p/>
</li><li>
It was a bright cold day, and the clocks were not mod 12. <p/>
</li><li>
All this happened, but not with equality. <p/>
</li><li>
<img alt="{2^2 \cdot 31}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E2+%5Ccdot+31%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^2 \cdot 31}"/> was spiteful, full of a baby’s venom. <p/>
</li><li>
It was zero at the leading ordinal of viewing.
</li></ol>
<p>
The third is the first hard one—I did not get it. The last one (of three from Ken not Ben) is probably unfair. All six of them, however, are on the “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/First-Lines-Literature-Coffee-Slaughterhouse/dp/B01D6TGVHW">First Lines Literature Coffee Mug</a>” which Ken received a year ago as a Christmas present from his sister. I did not know this when I chose the first three.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Orlin’s Resolutions </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Many of us make resolutions for the new year. Here are some examples from Orlin:</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Be better at explaining what I do to family and friends. I, Dick, have trouble with this one.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Not to prove by contradiction what can be proved directly. Assume that <img alt="{1+1 \neq 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2B1+%5Cneq+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1+1 \neq 2}"/> and <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\dots}"/></p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Stop using the word “obviously.” Here at GLL we try to avoid this, at least when it is not obvious. We <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/02/28/phrases-that-drive-me-crazy/">posted</a> about phrases to avoid a year ago.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Our Resolutions </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Here are some of ours:</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Stop doubting quantum computer claims. Unless, adds Ken, you have a possible concrete way of challenging them…</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Start trying to apply AI methods to complexity theory. Could there be a new learning approach to 3-SAT? Note that PAC learning kind-of came from there. See for instance the end of <a href="https://elmos.scripts.mit.edu/mathofdeeplearning/2017/05/08/mathematics-of-deep-learning-lecture-4/">this</a>.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Stop trying to understand proofs that Peano arithmetic is inconsistent. I still do not understand what logic they use to prove that Peano is inconsistent. What if that logic is inconsistent? </p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> Start up some fundamental research ideas and attempts on hard problems again.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> And try to make GLL better, including making it appeal to a wider community. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The answers are:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<em>A Tale of Two Cities</em> by Charles Dickens: “It was the best of times, it was the worst of times.” <p/>
</li><li>
<em>Anna Karenina</em> by Leo Tolstoy: “Happy families are alike; every unhappy family is unlike in its own way.” <p/>
</li><li>
<em>1984</em> by George Orwell: “It was a bright cold day, and the clocks were striking thirteen.” <p/>
</li><li>
<em>Slaughterhouse-Five</em> by Kurt Vonnegut: “All this happened, more or less.” <p/>
</li><li>
<em>Beloved</em> by Toni Morrison, who died this year: “124 was spiteful, full of a baby’s venom.” This <a href="https://www.shmoop.com/quotes/124-was-spiteful.html">explanation</a> of the line continues: “We know all about numbers being spiteful. We took high school algebra. We’ve experienced the pain. But in this instance, the quote isn’t actually referring to a number. There’s not some mysterious mathematical entity that’s come to wreak havoc on the characters in our story. Here, ‘124’ refers to…” <p/>
</li><li>
<em>Lolita</em> by Vladimir Nabokov: “It was love at first sight…” But wait—this is not the first line of the novel. The first line is maybe not suitable for a coffee mug or family-friendly blog. Instead it is the first line of chapter 29 of part II. We did say it was unfair. <b>Update: Oops</b>—as noted <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/31/resolutions-for-2020/#comment-107459">here</a>, it is the first line of <em>Catch-22</em> by Joseph Heller.  Maybe Ken’s Google engine shares his tendency toward chess-playing authors…
</li></ol>
<p>
Have a happy new year, and make some fun resolutions. Please let us know some of them, or ideas for ours.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
[added Update fixing last first-line answer.]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-31T22:02:18Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-31T22:02:18Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Ben Orlin"/>
    <category term="humor"/>
    <category term="literature"/>
    <category term="New Year's"/>
    <category term="quiz"/>
    <category term="resolutions"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/12/31/year-end-linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/12/31/year-end-linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Year-end linkage</title>
    <summary>Reign in graphs (). Interesting collection of 3d models of graphs</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.shapeways.com/shops/jankrhaugland">Reign in graphs</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103321651787290257"/>). Interesting collection of 3d models of graphs</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://euro-math-soc.eu/news/19/12/17/zbmath-become-open-access">Zentralblatt going open access</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103324328632714865"/>). I mostly use a mix of Google Scholar (for searching), MathSciNet (for more targeted searches, reviews, and high-quality bibtex), and DBLP (for bibtex of CS papers not in MathSciNet) but maybe this will convince me to add ZB into the mix.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@christianp/103328394093228909">Christian Lawson-Perfect can’t explain why the Wikipedia article for “Author” was illustrated by a Ukrainian copyright certificate for a supposed proof of Fermat’s last theorem</a>. It seems to have been added in good faith there, but maybe as self-promotion to the “Copyright” article. Whatever, it’s now on “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudomathematics">Pseudomathematics</a>” where it belongs.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://lemire.me/blog/2019/12/19/xor-filters-faster-and-smaller-than-bloom-filters/">Xor filters</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103338548071725282"/>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.08258">preprint</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21840821">via</a>): A new alternative to Bloom filters and cuckoo filters for approximate set membership with a controlled rate of false positives and no false negatives. It’s fast and (for realistic error rates) uses fewer bits than Bloom or cuckoo. Cuckoo still wins if you need your sets dynamic, though: you can insert or delete elements easily, while Bloom can only insert and xor can’t handle any change.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.jamisbuck.org/mazes/">Visualizations of several maze-generation algorithms</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103349055666314448"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21828903">via</a>). They all appear to generate random tree-like mazes in a square grid, but with different probability distributions on the trees. E.g. Kruskal and Prim generate minimum spanning trees for random weights, different from the uniformly random trees of Aldous–Broder and Wilson, and many others appear quite different from both.
The alternative algorithm at the main link of the via link is probably not the best choice.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://twitter.com/johncarlosbaez/status/1208768265830354945">It’s easy for mathematical physics crackpottery to get published in a prestigious-sounding pay-to-publish journal from an actually-prestigious publisher, <em>Nature Scientific Reports</em></a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103355963066100289"/>).
In the ensuing discussion, Flavio Nogueira reports that <a href="https://twitter.com/F_S_Nogueira/status/1208787145911152640">editors rejected papers only to see them published anyway</a>. Should we start treating <em>Nature</em> as a predatory publisher?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convex_hull_of_a_simple_polygon">Convex hull of a simple polygon</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103360225573578914"/>). I’ve been working on cleaning up Wikipedia’s main convex hull article (not yet finished) and added this one to fill in some details. The problem has an interesting history: it’s been known to be solvable in linear time since 1979, and many different algorithms for the same problem have been published before and since, but most of them are wrong.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathoverflow.net/q/349228/440">Open convex hull of a closed set</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103365014241600450"/>). I can prove that (in Euclidean spaces) such sets are always Cartesian products of a line with a lower-dimensional set. But is there a reference in the literature for this, so I can add it to the Wikipedia article? If you know, please leave an answer on the MathOverflow link.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://youtu.be/fhBPhie1Tm0">David Bachman, Saul Schleimer and Henry Segerman finally explain what their cohomology fractals are</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@henryseg/103341309414601843"/>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/dec/26/turkish-court-wikipedia-block-lifted">Turkish supreme court rules that the country’s two-year block on Wikipedia is unconstitutional</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103378814260578782"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21888759">also</a>, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/europe/court-rules-turkey-violated-freedoms-by-banning-wikipedia/2019/12/26/880f263c-27de-11ea-9cc9-e19cfbc87e51_story.html">also</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/12/26/world/europe/wikipedia-ban-turkey.html">also</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematician-makes-euler-equations-blow-up-20191218/">Famous fluid equations spring a leak</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103384319532164607"/>). We still don’t know whether the differential equations governing fluid flow lead to consistent and unique solutions for all time. But if you simplify the equations to throw away viscosity and compressability, and you allow the initial state of the fluid to have discontinuous boundaries between volumes of fluid with very different motion, you can cause it to reach a point at which it spins infinitely quickly.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Relative_convex_hull">Relative convex hull</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103390220528024772"/>). Another new article related to my revision of the Wikipedia convex hull article. These are the shapes you get by stretching a rubber band around one set while fencing it inside a polygon. You don’t always get a simple polygon as a result, but it’s “weakly simple”.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/12/28/climate/trump-administration-war-on-science.html">Science under attack: How Trump is sidelining researchers and their work</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103393997740330853"/>). The fact that this link was <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21905957">flagged and censored from ycombinator hacker news</a> is also interesting, in its own way. Fortunately my RSS aggregator copied the link before it was taken down.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Wikipedia_Signpost/2019-12-27/Special_report">Are reputation management operatives scrubbing Wikipedia articles</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103399857216270322"/>). Answer: duh. The linked report has details of one such case, involving Theranos.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2019/12/30/compositionality-first-issue/">New open-access journal <em>Compositionality</em></a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103406379623694356"/>), on the mathematics of “how complex things can be assembled out of simpler parts”. It’s not a good fit for my own research, and the word “fuzzy” in the title of one of the initial papers is kind of a red flag for me, but I think it’s a good thing that the move towards diamond-model open access is continuing.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-31T21:23:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-31T21:23:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-01-01T05:48:15Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-5060142193352763387</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/5060142193352763387/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/complexity-year-in-review-2019.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/5060142193352763387" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/5060142193352763387" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/complexity-year-in-review-2019.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Complexity Year in Review 2019</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some great theorems this year including <a href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/2019/04/14/randomness-and-interaction-entanglement-ups-the-game/">non-deterministic double exponential time by quantumly entangled provers</a> and <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/">integer multiplication in O(n log n) time</a>. But the result of the year has to go to a paper that gave a <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/07/local-kid-makes-history.html">shockingly simple proof of a major longstanding conjecture</a>.<br/>
<br/>
<div style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.00847">Induced subgraphs of hypercubes and a proof of the Sensitivity Conjecture</a> by Hao Huang</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
Of course 2019 will be remembered in some circles for giving us Google's claims of quantum supremacy and all the quantum hype, deserved and otherwise, that goes with it.<br/>
<br/>
Personally Bill came out with his new book <a href="https://www.worldscientific.com/worldscibooks/10.1142/11261#t=toc">Problems with a Point; Exploring Math and Computer Science</a> co-authored with Clyde Kruskal (<a href="https://amzn.to/2s6IlPl">Amazon</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/02/problems-with-point-exploring-math-and.html">blog</a> <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/problems-with-point-not-plug-just-some.html">posts</a>). Lance <a href="https://www.iit.edu/news/lance-fortnow-designated-new-college-science-dean">became a dean</a>. </div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
We remember <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/11/obituaries/michael-atiyah-dead.html">Michael Atiyah</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/elwyn-berlekamp-died-april-9-2019.html">Elwyn Berlekamp</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/quiz-show-scandalsadmissions.html">Charles van Doren</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/06/ray-miller-one-of-our-founders-passes.html">Ray Miller</a>, <a href="https://www.lamsade.dauphine.fr/fr/actualites/detail-de-lactualite/article/deces-de-jerome-monnot-membre-du-laboratoire-lamsade.html">Jérôme Monnot</a> and <a href="https://news.stanford.edu/2019/04/24/nils-nilsson-pioneer-robotics-artificial-intelligence-dies-86/">Nils Nilsson</a>.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
Thanks to guest posters <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/10/quantum-supremacy-guest-post-by-abhinav.html">Abhinav Deshpande</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/01/the-paradigm-shift-in-fintech.html">Evangelos Georgiadis</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/07/guest-post-by-samir-khuller-on.html">Samir Khuller</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/06/ray-miller-one-of-our-founders-passes.html">Ming Lin</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/07/answer-to-both-infinite-hats-problems.html">David</a> <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/07/fortran-is-underated.html">Marcus</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/06/ray-miller-one-of-our-founders-passes.html">Ben Shneiderman</a> and <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/cuckoo-cycles.html">John Tromp</a>.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
As we move into the 2020s, we tend to look back and look forward. The 2010s will go down as the decade computing and data transformed society, for better and worse. Google turned 21 this year as its OG leadership stepped down. I turned 21 in 1984, but 1984 seems closer than ever.</div>
<div>
<br/></div>
<div>
Last year we ended the <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2018/12/complexity-year-in-review-2018.html">year in review</a> by </div>
<blockquote class="tr_bq">
We end the year with craziness, the stock market is going through wild gyrations, we have a partial government shutdown including all of NSF and an uncertain political landscape with different parties leading the two houses of congress. We're still in the midst of a technological revolution and governments around the world try to figure how to regulate it. I find it hard to predict 2019 but it will not be quiet.</blockquote>
2019 was not quiet and we're about to head into an impeachment trial, Brexit and a critical US presidential election. The real challenges of the twenties will come from massive transformation from automation, climate change and deepening divisions in our society. How will academia cope with changing demographics, financial challenges and educating to manage the technological revolution?<br/>
<br/>
Let's all take a deep breath, roll up our sleeves and get the decade going.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-31T18:02:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-31T18:02:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T01:35:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/186</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/186" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-186 |  Lifting with Simple Gadgets and Applications to Circuit and Proof Complexity | 

	Or Meir, 

	Susanna de Rezende, 

	Jakob Nordström, 

	Robert Robere, 

	Toniann Pitassi</title>
    <summary>We significantly strengthen and generalize the theorem lifting Nullstellensatz degree to monotone span program size by Pitassi and  Robere (2018) so that it works for any gadget with high enough rank, in particular, for useful gadgets such as  equality and greater-than. We apply our generalized theorem to solve two open problems:

* We present the first result that demonstrates a separation in proof power for cutting planes with unbounded versus polynomially bounded    coefficients.
Specifically, we exhibit CNF formulas that can be refuted in quadratic length and constant line space in cutting planes with unbounded coefficients, but for which there are no refutations in subexponential length and subpolynomial line space if coefficients are restricted to be of polynomial magnitude.

* We give the first explicit separation between monotone Boolean formulas and monotone real formulas. Specifically, we give an explicit family of functions that can be computed with monotone real formulas of nearly linear size but require monotone Boolean formulas of exponential size. Previously only a non-explicit separation was known.  
  
An important technical ingredient, which may be of independent interest, is that we show that the Nullstellensatz degree of refuting the pebbling formula over a DAG $G$ over any field coincides exactly with the reversible pebbling price of $G$. 
In particular, this implies that the standard decision tree complexity and the parity  decision tree complexity of the corresponding falsified clause search problem are equal.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-31T16:41:23Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-31T16:41:23Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:22:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7610</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/12/30/a-bet-for-the-new-decade/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A bet for the new decade</title>
    <summary>I am in Tel Aviv Theory Fest this week – a fantastic collection of talks and workshops organized by Yuval Filmus , Gil Kalai, Ronen Eldan, and Muli Safra. It was a good chance to catch up with many friends and colleagues. In particular I met Elchanan Mossel and Subhash Khot, who asked me to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I am in <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tau-theory-fest/home">Tel Aviv Theory Fest</a> this week – a fantastic collection of talks and workshops organized by Yuval Filmus , Gil Kalai, Ronen Eldan, and Muli Safra.</p>



<p>It was a good chance to catch up with many friends and colleagues. In particular I met Elchanan Mossel and Subhash Khot, who asked me to serve as a “witness” for their bet on the unique games conjecture. I am recording it here so we can remember it a decade from noe.</p>



<p>Specifically, Elchanan bets that the Unique Games conjecture will be proven in the next decade – sometime between January 1, 2020 and December 31, 2029 there will be a paper uploaded to the arxiv with a correct proof of the conjecture. Subhash bets that this won’t happen. They were not sure what to bet on, but eventually agreed to take my offer that the loser will have to collaborate on a problem chosen by the winner, so I think science will win in either case. (For what it’s worth, I think there is a good chance that Subhash will lose the bet because he himself will prove the UGC in this decade, though it’s always possible Subhash can both win the bet and prove the UGC if he manages to do it by tomorrow <img alt="&#x1F642;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f642.png" style="height: 1em;"/> )</p>



<p/>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-7612" src="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/img-1240.jpg?w=1024"/></figure>



<p>The conference itself is, as I mentioned, wonderful with an amazing collection of speakers.  Let me mention just a couple of talks from this morning. Shafi Goldwasser talked about “Law and Algorithms”. There is a recent area of research studying how to regulate algorithms, but Shafi’s talk focused mostly on the other direction: how algorithms and cryptography can help achieve legal objectives such as the “right to be forgotten” or the ability to monitor secret proceedings such as wiretap requests. </p>



<p>Christos Papadimitriou  talked about “Language, Brain, and Computation”.  Christos is obviously excited about understanding the language mechanisms in the brain. He said that studying the brain gives him the same feeling that you get when you sit in a coffee shop in Cambridge and hear intellectual discussions all around you: you don’t understand why everyone is not dropping everything they are doing and come here. (Well, his actual words were “sunsets over the Berkeley hills” but I think the Cambridge coffee shops are a better metaphor <img alt="&#x1F642;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f642.png" style="height: 1em;"/> )</p>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-30T21:50:04Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-30T21:50:04Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/30/assistant-professor-at-computer-science-dept-higher-school-of-economics-moscow-apply-by-january-12-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/30/assistant-professor-at-computer-science-dept-higher-school-of-economics-moscow-apply-by-january-12-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor at Computer Science Dept, Higher School of Economics, Moscow (apply by January 12, 2020)</title>
    <summary>National Research University Higher School of Economics (HSE University, Moscow, Russia), tenure track positions starting in 2020/2021 academic year. Knowledge of Russian is not required. The applicant should provide a CV, a statement and a recent research paper via online application form. At least two letters of recommendation should be sent directly to iri@hse.ru before […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>National Research University Higher School of Economics (HSE University, Moscow, Russia), tenure track positions starting in 2020/2021 academic year. Knowledge of Russian is not required. The applicant should provide a CV, a statement and a recent research paper via online application form. At least two letters of recommendation should be sent directly to iri@hse.ru before January 12, 2020.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://iri.hse.ru/announcements/304656320.html">https://iri.hse.ru/announcements/304656320.html</a><br/>
Email: sasha.shen@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-30T14:41:27Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-30T14:41:27Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/?p=1416</id>
    <link href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/12/30/a-decade-of-fun-and-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A decade of fun and learning</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I started out this decade with the project of writing a survey of the multi-armed bandit literature, which I had read thoroughly during the graduate studies that I was about to finish. At the time we resisted the temptation to … <a href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/12/30/a-decade-of-fun-and-learning/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I started out this decade with the project of writing a survey of the multi-armed bandit literature, which I had read thoroughly during the graduate studies that I was about to finish. At the time we resisted the temptation to name the survey “modern banditology”, which was indeed the right call given how much this “modern” picture has evolved over the decade! It is truly wonderful to now end the decade with two new iterations on the work we did in that survey: </p>
<ol>
<li><a class="lipdf" href="https://tor-lattimore.com/downloads/book/book.pdf">Bandit algorithms</a> by Tor Lattimore and Csaba Szepesvari</li>
<li><a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.07272">Introduction to bandits</a> by Alex Slivkins</li>
</ol>
<p>These new references very significantly expand the 2012 survey, and they are wonderful starting points for anyone who wants to enter the field.</p>
<p>Here are some of the discoveries in the world of bandits that stood out for me this decade:</p>
<ol>
<li>We now understand very precisely Thompson Sampling, the first bandit strategy that was proposed back in 1933. The most beautiful reference here is the one by Dan Russo and Ben Van Roy: <a class="lipdf" href="http://www.jmlr.org/papers/volume17/14-087/14-087.pdf">An Information-Theoretic Analysis of Thompson Sampling</a>, JMLR 2016. Another one that stands out is <a class="lipdf" href="http://www.jmlr.org/proceedings/papers/v23/agrawal12/agrawal12.pdf">Analysis of thompson sampling for the multi-armed bandit problem</a> by S. Agrawal and N. Goyal at COLT 2012.</li>
<li>T^{2/3} lower bound for  *non-stochastic* bandit with switching cost by Dekel, Ding, Koren and Peres at <u><font color="#000121"><a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1310.2997">STOC 201</a></font></u><a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1310.2997">4</a>. This is a striking result for several reasons. In particular the proof has to be based on a non-trivial stochastic process, since for the classical stochastic i.i.d. model one can obtain \sqrt{T} (very easily in fact). </li>
<li>We now know that bandit convex optimization is “easy”, in the sense that it is a \sqrt{T}-regret type problem. What’s more is that in our <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1607.03084">STOC 2017 paper</a> with Y.T. Lee and R. Eldan we introduced a new way to do function estimation based on bandit feedback, using kernels (I have written at length about this on <a class="liinternal" href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2016/08/06/kernel-based-methods-for-bandit-convex-optimization-part-1/">this blog</a>).</li>
<li>A very intriguing model of computation for contextual bandit was proposed, where one can access the policy space only through an offline optimization oracle. With such access, the classical Exp4 algorithm cannot be simulated, and thus one needs new strategies. We now have a reasonable understanding that \sqrt{T} is doable with mild assumptions (see e.g. this ICML 2014 paper on “<u><font color="#000117"><a class="liexternal" href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1402.0555">Taming the Monster</a></font>“</u> by Agarwal, Hsu, Kale, Langford, L. Li and Schapire) and that it is impossible with no assumptions (work of Hazan and Koren at <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1504.02089">STOC 2016</a>).</li>
<li>Honorable mentions also go to the work of Wei and Luo showing that very strong variation bounds are possible in bandits (see this <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1801.03265">COLT 2018 paper</a>), and Zimmert and Seldin who made striking progress on the best of both worlds phenomenon that we discovered with Slivkins at the beginning of the decade (I blogged about it <a class="liinternal" href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/06/10/amazing-progress-in-adversarially-robust-stochastic-multi-armed-bandits/">here</a> already).</li>
</ol>
<h2>Life beyond bandits</h2>
<p>In addition to starting the decade with the bandit survey, I also started it with being bored with the bandit topic altogether. I thought that many (if not most) of the fundamental results were now known, and it was a good idea to move on to something else. Obviously I was totally wrong, as you can see with all the works cited above (and many many more for stochastic bandits, including much deeper understanding of best arm identification, a topic very close to my heart, see e.g., <a class="lipdf" href="http://www.jmlr.org/papers/volume17/kaufman16a/kaufman16a.pdf">[Kaufmann, Cappe, Garivier, JMLR 16]</a>). In fact I am now optimistic that there is probably another decade-worth of exploration left for the bandit problem(s). Nevertheless I ventured outside, and explored the world of optimization (out of which first came <a class="lipdf" href="http://sbubeck.com/Bubeck15.pdf">a survey</a>, and more recently <a class="liinternal" href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLAPSKVSdi0oZPbS-UD_kwT4ePZQx_CiME">video lectures</a>) and briefly networks (another <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1609.03511">modest survey</a> came out of this too). </p>
<p>Here are some of the landmark optimization results of this decade in my view:</p>
<ol>
<li>Perhaps the most striking result of the decade in optimization is the observation that for finite sum problems, one can reduce the variance in stochastic gradient descent by somehow centering the estimates (e.g., using a slowly moving sequence on which we can afford to compute full gradients; but this is not the only way to perform such variance reduction). This idea, while very simple, has a lot of implications, both in practice and in theory! The origin of the idea are in the SAG algorithm of <a class="liexternal" href="http://papers.nips.cc/paper/4633-a-stochastic-gradient-method-with-an-exponential-convergence-_ra">[Schmidt, Le Roux, Bach, NIPS 2012]</a> and SDCA <a class="lipdf" href="http://www.jmlr.org/papers/volume14/shalev-shwartz13a/shalev-shwartz13a.pdf">[Shalev-Shwartz and Zhang, JMLR 2013]</a>. A simpler instantiation of the idea, called SVRG appeared shortly after in <a class="lipdf" href="http://papers.nips.cc/paper/4937-accelerating-stochastic-gradient-descent-using-predictive-variance-reduction.pdf">[Johnson and Zhang, NIPS 2013]</a> (and also independently at the same NeurIPS, in <a class="liinternal" href="https://papers.nips.cc/paper/4941-mixed-optimization-for-smooth-functions">[M. Madhavi, L. Zhang, R. Li, NIPS 2013]</a>).</li>
<li>An intriguing direction that I pursued fervently is the use of convex optimization for problems that have a priori nothing to do with convex optimization. A big inspiration for me was the COLT 2008 paper by Abernethy, Hazan and Rakhlin, who showed how mirror descent naturally solves bandit problems. In this decade, we (this we includes myself and co-authors, but also various other teams) explored how to use mirror descent for other online decision making problems, and made progress on some long-standing problems (k-server and MTS), see for example this set of <a class="liinternal" href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLAPSKVSdi0obG1b3w4k41JMLFbyBJS5AQ">video lectures</a> on the “Five miracles of mirror descent”.</li>
<li>Arnak Dalalyan showed how to use ideas inspired from convex optimization to <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1412.7392">analyze the Langevin Monte Carlo algorithm</a>. This was absolutely beautiful work, that led to many many follow-ups.</li>
<li>There has been a lot of rewriting of Nesterov’s acceleration, to try to demystify it. Overall the enterprise is not yet a resounding success in my opinion, but certainly a lot of progress has been made (again I have written a lot about it on this blog already). We now even have optimal acceleration for higher order of smoothness (see this 15 authors <u><font color="#000117"/><font><a class="lipdf" href="http://proceedings.mlr.press/v99/gasnikov19b/gasnikov19b.pdf">paper at COLT 2019</a></font></u>), but these techniques are clouded with the same shroud of mystery as was Nesterov’s original method.</li>
<li>Yin Tat Lee and Aaron Sidford obtained an <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.08033">efficient construction of a universal barrier</a>.</li>
<li>We now know that certain problems cannot be efficiently represented by SDPs (the so-called “extension complexity), see e.g. this work by <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1411.6317">Lee-Raghavendra-Steurer</a>.</li>
<li>We now know how to chase convex bodies, and we can even do so very elegantly with <a class="liinternal" href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/2019/11/05/convex-body-chasing-steiner-point-sellke-point-and-soda-2020-best-papers/">the Steiner/Sellke point</a>.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Some other things that captivated me</h2>
<p>The papers above are mostly topics on which I tried to work at some point. Here are some questions that I didn’t work on but followed closely and was fascinated by the progress:</p>
<ol>
<li>The stochastic block model was essentially solved during this decade, see for example <a class="lipdf" href="http://www.princeton.edu/~eabbe/publications/abbe_FNT_2.pdf">this survey</a> by Emmanuel Abbe.</li>
<li>The computational/statistical tradeoffs were extensively explored, yet they remain mysterious. A nice impulse to the field was given by this <a class="liinternal" href="https://projecteuclid.org/euclid.aos/1378386239">COLT 2013 paper</a> by Berthet and Rigollet relating sparse PCA and planted clique. In a similar spirit I also enjoyed the more recent work by Moitra, Jerry Li, and many co-authors on computationally efficient robust estimation (see e.g., <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.11366">this recent paper</a>)</li>
<li>Adaptive data analysis strikes me as both very important in practice, and quite deep theoretically, see e.g. <a class="lipdf" href="http://nematilab.info/bmijc/assets/091218_paper.pdf">the reusable holdout by Dwork et al</a>. A related paper that I liked a lot is this <a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1502.04585">ICML 2015 paper</a> by Blum and Hardt, which essentially explores the regularization effect of publishing only models that beat the state of the art significantly (more generally this is an extremely interesting question, of why we can keep using the same datasets to evaluate progress in machine learning, see this provokingly titled paper “<a class="liinternal" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.10811">Do ImageNet Classifiers Generalize to ImageNet?</a>“).</li>
<li>A general trend has been in finding very fast (nearly linear time) method for many classical problems. Sometimes these investigations even led to actually practical algorithm, as with this now classical paper by Marco Cuturi at NIPS 2013 titled “<a class="liexternal" href="http://papers.nips.cc/paper/4927-sinkhorn-distances-lightspeed-computation-of-optimal-transport">Sinkhorn Distances: Lightspeed Computation of Optimal Transport</a>“.</li>
</ol>
<h2>Oh, one last thing</h2>
<p>I also heard that, surprisingly, gradient descent can work to optimize highly non-convex functions such as training loss for neural networks. Not sure what this is about, it’s a pretty obscure topic, maybe it will catch up in the decade 2020-2029…</p>
<h2>Share some more in the comments!</h2>
<p>The above is only a tiny sample, there were many many more interesting directions being explored (tensor methods for latent variable models <a class="lipdf" href="http://www.jmlr.org/papers/volume15/anandkumar14b/anandkumar14b.pdf">[Anandkumar, Ge, Hsu, Kakade, Telgarsky, JMLR 14]</a>; phenomenon of “all local minima are good” for various non-convex learning problems, see e.g., <a class="liexternal" href="http://papers.nips.cc/paper/6048-matrix-completion-has-no-spurious-local-minimum">[Ge, Lee, Ma, NIPS 2016]</a>; etc etc). Feel free to share your favorite ML theory paper in the comments!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-30T07:22:52Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-30T07:22:52Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Sebastien Bubeck</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit</id>
      <link href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blogs.princeton.edu/imabandit" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Random topics in optimization, probability, and statistics. By Sébastien Bubeck</subtitle>
      <title>I’m a bandit</title>
      <updated>2020-01-08T23:40:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/185</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/185" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-185 |  Strategy-Stealing is Non-Constructive | 

	Greg Bodwin, 

	Ofer Grossman</title>
    <summary>In many combinatorial games, one can prove that the first player wins under best play using a simple but non-constructive argument called strategy-stealing.
This work is about the complexity behind these proofs: how hard is it to actually find a winning move in a game, when you know by strategy-stealing that one exists? 
We prove that this problem is PSPACE-Complete already for Minimum Poset Games and Symmetric Maker-Maker Games, which are simple classes of games that capture two of the main types of strategy-stealing arguments in the current literature.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-29T05:25:12Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-29T05:25:12Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:22:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7604</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/12/28/quantum-school-lecture-notes-videos-and-more-guest-post-by-dorit-aharonov/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A crash course on the math of quantum computing (guest post by Dorit Aharonov)</title>
    <summary>[The post below is by Dorit Aharonov who co-organized the wonderful school on quantum computing last week which I attended and greatly enjoyed. –Boaz] TL;DR: Last week we had a wonderful one-week intro course into the math of quantum computing at Hebrew U;  It included a one day crash course on the basics, and 7 mini-courses on math-oriented research […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>[The post below is by Dorit Aharonov who co-organized the wonderful school on quantum computing last week which I attended and greatly enjoyed. –Boaz] </em></p>



<p><strong>TL;DR: </strong> Last week we had a wonderful one-week intro course into the math of quantum computing at Hebrew U;  It included a one day crash course on the basics, and 7 mini-courses on math-oriented research topics (quantum delegation, Hamiltonian complexity, algorithms and more) by top-notch speakers. Most importantly – it is all online, and could be very useful if you want to take a week or two to enter the area and don’t know <a href="https://iias.huji.ac.il/SchoolCSE4" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">where to start</a>.   </p>



<p><br/><br/><br/></p>



<p>Hi Theory people!  </p>



<p>I want to tell you about a 5-days winter school called “<a href="https://iias.huji.ac.il/SchoolCSE4" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">The Mathematics of Quantum Computation</a>“, which we (me, Zvika Brakerski, Or Sattath and Amnon Ta-Shma) organized last week at the Institute for advanced studies (IIAS) at the Hebrew university in Jerusalem. </p>



<p>There were two reasons I happily agreed to Boaz’s suggestion to write a guest blogpost about this school. <br/><br/>a) The school was really great fun. We enjoyed it so much, that I think you might find it interesting to hear about it even if you were not there, or are not even into quantum computation. <br/><br/>And b), it might actually be useful for you or your quantum-curious friends. We put all material online, with the goal in mind that after the school, this collection of talks+written material will constitute all that is needed for an almost self-contained <strong>very-intensive-one-week-course of introduction into the mathematical side of quantum computation</strong>; I think this might be of real use for any theoretical computer scientist or mathematician interested in entering this fascinating but hard-to-penetrate area, and not knowing where to start.<br/>Before telling you a little more about what we actually learned in this school, let’s start with some names and numbers. We had:  </p>



<ul><li>160 participants (students and faculty) from all over the world. </li><li>7 terrific speakers: Adam Bouland (UC Berkeley), Sergey Bravyi (IBM), Matthias Christandl (Coppenhagen), András Gilyén (Caltech), Sandy Irani (UC Irvine), Avishay Tal (Berkeley), and Thomas Vidick (Caltech); </li><li>2 great TAs:  András Gilyén (Caltech) and Chinmay Nirkhe (UC Berkeley)</li><li>4 busy organizers: myself (Hebrew U), Zvika Brakerski (Weizmann), Or Sattath (Ben Gurion U), and Amnon Ta-Shma (Tel Aviv U)</li><li>1 exciting and very intensive <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1OcFzE1PHxBN4l87sOQB033FZLTgY934GHxnpVKi3NaM/edit" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">program</a></li><li>5 challenging and fascinating days of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLTn74Qx5mPsS2dqTpEq_2zxq8kWBmPUfb" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank"> talks</a>, <a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders/1n6W3Yjq2TYsyRwrocbN2bWK-xpyzkqSM" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">problem sessions</a> and really <a href="https://shvil.im/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">nice food</a>.   </li><li>1 great <a href="https://huji.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=599bc3e9-855e-42c1-ab1d-ab1f0062c481" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Rabin’s lecture</a> by Boaz Barak (Harvard)</li><li>1 beautiful <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DxrxXneg3lU&amp;list=PLTn74Qx5mPsS2dqTpEq_2zxq8kWBmPUfb&amp;index=21&amp;t=0s" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Quantum perspective lecture</a> by Sergey Bravyi (IBM)</li><li>8 panelists in the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H4t2G2gay7Q&amp;feature=youtu.be" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">supremacy panel</a> we had on the fifth day: Sandy Irani (UC Irvine), our wise moderator, and 7 panelists on stage and online: myself, Scott Aaronson (Austin, online), Boaz Barak, Adam Bouland, Sergio Boixo (Google, online), Gil Kalai (Hebrew U), and Umesh Vazirani (UC Berkeley, online) </li><li>8 brave speakers in the gong show, our very last session, each talking for 3 minutes;    </li><li>1 group-tour to 1 UNESCO site (<a href="https://everything-everywhere.com/caves-of-maresha-and-bet-guvrin-in-the-judean-lowlands-as-a-microcosm-of-the-land-of-the-caves/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Tel Maresha</a>) and <a href="https://www.srigim-beer.co.il/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">6 beers tasted</a> by ~80 tour participants</li><li>3 problem sets with 43 <a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders/1n6W3Yjq2TYsyRwrocbN2bWK-xpyzkqSM" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">problems</a> and (!) their <a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders/1n6W3Yjq2TYsyRwrocbN2bWK-xpyzkqSM" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">solution</a>s.   </li></ul>



<p>So why did we decide to organize this particular quantum school, given the many quantum schools around? Well, the area of quantum computation is just bursting now with excitement and new mathematical challenges; But there seems to be no easy way for theoreticians to learn about all these things unless you are already in the loop… The (admittedly) very ambitious goal of the school was to assume zero background in quantum computation, and quickly bring people up to speed on six or seven of the most interesting mathematical research forefronts in the area. </p>



<p>The first day of the school was intended to put everyone essentially on the same page: it included four talks about the very basics (qubits by Or Sattath, circuits, by myself, algorithms by Adam Bouland, and error correction by Sergey Bravyi). By the end of this first day everyone was at least supposed to be familiar with the basic concepts, and capable of listening to the mini-courses to follow. The rest of the school was devoted mainly to those mini-courses, whose topics included what I think are some of the most exciting topics on the more theoretical and mathematical side of quantum computation.</p>



<p>Yes, it was extremely challenging… the good thing was that we had two great TAs, András and Chinmay, who helped prepare problem sets, which people actually seriously tried to solve (!) during the daily one+ hour TA problem-solving sessions (with the help of the team strolling around ready to answer questions…). It seems that this indeed helped people follow, despite the fact that we did get into some hard stuff in those mini-courses… The many questions that were asked throughout the school proved that many people were following and interested till the bitter end. </p>



<p>So here is a summary of the mini-courses, by order of appearance. <br/>I added some buzz words of interesting related mathematical notions so that you know where these topics might lead you if you take the paths they suggest.   <br/></p>



<ul><li> Thomas Vidick gave a three-lecture wonderfully clear mini-course providing an intro to the recently very active and exciting area of <strong>quantum verification and delegation</strong>, connecting cryptography and quantum computational complexity. [Thomas didn’t have time to talk about it, but down the road this eventually connects to  approximate representation theory, as well as to Connes embedding conjecture, and more.]</li><li> Sandy Irani gave a beautiful exposition (again, in a a three lecture mini-course) on <strong>quantum Hamiltonian complexity</strong>. Sandy started with Kitaev’s quantum version of the Cook Levin theorem, showing that the local Hamiltonian problem is quantum NP complete; she then explained how this can be extended to more physically relevant questions such as translationally invariant 1D systems, questions about the thermodynamical limit, and more. [This topic is related to open questions such as quantum PCP, which was not mentioned in the school, as well as to beautiful recent results about undecidability of the spectral gap problem, and more.]    </li><li> Matthias Christandl gave an exciting two-lecture mini-course on the fascinating connection between <strong>tensor ranks and matrix product multiplication</strong>. Starting from what seemed to be childish games with small pictures in his first talk, he cleverly used those as his building blocks in his second talk, to enable him to talk about Strassen’s universal spectral points program for approaching the complexity of matrix multiplication, asymptotic ranks, border ranks and more. That included also very beautiful pictures of polytopes! Matthias explained the connection that underlines this entire direction, between entanglement properties of three body systems, with these old combinatorial problems.  </li><li> Avishay Tal gave a really nice two-lecture exposition on his recent breakthrough result with Ran Raz, proving that <strong>quantum polynomial time computation is not contained in the polynomial Hierarchy, in the oracle model</strong>. This included talking about AC0, a problem called forrelation, Fourier expansion, Gaussians and much more.</li><li>  András Gilyén gave a wonderful talk about a recent development: the evolution of the <strong>singular value approach to quantum algorithms</strong>. He left us all in awe showing that essentially almost any quantum algorithm you can think of falls into this beautiful framework… Among other things, he mentioned Chebychev’s polynomials, quantum walks, Hamiltonian simulations, and more. What else can be done with this framework remains to be seen.</li><li>Sergey Bravyi gave two talks (on top of his intro to quantum error correction). The first was as part of a monthly series at Hebrew university, called  “quantum perspectives”; in this talk, Sergey gave a really nice exposition of his breakthrough result (with Gosset and Konig) demonstrating an <strong><em>information theoretical</em> separation between quantum and classical constant depth circuits</strong>; this uses in a clever way the well known quantum magic square game enabling quantum correlations to win with probability one, while classical correlations are always bounded away from one;  somehow this result manages to cleverly turn this game into a computational advantage. In Sergey’s last talk, he gave the basics of the beautiful topic of <strong>stoqaustic Hamiltonians </strong>–  a model in between quantum Hamiltonians and classical constrained satisfaction problems, which poses many fundamental and interesting open questions (and is tightly related to classical Markov chains, and Markov chain Monte Carlo). </li><li>Finally, Adam Bouland gave two superb talks on <strong>quantum supremacy</strong>, explaining the beautiful challenges in this area – including his recent average case to worst case hardness results about sampling using quantum circuits, which is related to Google’s supremacy experiment.  </li><li>Ah, I also gave a talk – it was about three of the many different equivalent models of quantum computation – <strong>adiabatic computation</strong>, <strong>quantum walks</strong>, and the <strong>Jones polynomial </strong>(I also briefly mentioned a differential geometry model). The talk came out way too disordered in my mind (never give a talk when you are an organizer!), but hopefully it gave some picture about the immense variety of ways to think about quantum computation and quantum algorithms.</li></ul>



<p>In addition to the main lectures, we also had some special events intertwined: </p>



<ul><li>Boaz Barak gave the distinguished annual Rabin lecture, joint with the CS colloquium; His talk, which was given the intriguing title  <strong>“Quantum computing and classical algorithms: The best of frenemies”</strong>, focused on the fickle relationships between quantum and classical algorithms. The main players in this beautiful talk were SDPs and sums of squares, and it left us with many open questions.     </li><li>Last but not least, we had an <strong>international panel about the meaning of Google’s recent experiment claiming supremacy</strong>, joined by Sergio Boixo from Google explaining the experiment, as well as Scott Aaronson and Umesh Vazirani who woke up very early in the US to join us. I feared we would have some friction and fist fights, but this actually became a deep and interesting discussion! We went with quite some depth into the most important question in my mind about the supremacy experiment, which is the issue of noise; Unbelievably, it all went well even from the technological aspect! I really recommend watching this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H4t2G2gay7Q&amp;feature=youtu.be" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">discussion</a>. </li></ul>



<p>So, we had a great time…. and as I said, one of the best things is that it is all recorded and saved. You are welcome to follow the <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1OcFzE1PHxBN4l87sOQB033FZLTgY934GHxnpVKi3NaM/edit" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">program</a>, watch the recorded <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLTn74Qx5mPsS2dqTpEq_2zxq8kWBmPUfb" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">talks</a>, consult the <a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders/1M9F0zha6LY8DX58eKxjkiI1Dxq9uvptE" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">slides</a><a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders/1y_sHH1NsKzHeZwQ_xa2aVR_HKgOczytm" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">, lecture notes</a><a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders/1n6W3Yjq2TYsyRwrocbN2bWK-xpyzkqSM" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">, exercises and solutions</a> and also read the <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1s-DLl_M-Dpqh9RdSqn6f9l01e09AaLndMlbxDEmlPrw/edit?ts=5dc7c2b3" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">reading material</a> if you want to extend your knowledge beyond what is covered in the school. In case you know of any math or TCS-oriented person who wants to enter the field and start working on some problem at the forefront of research, just send him or her this post, or the link of the <a href="https://iias.huji.ac.il/SchoolCSE4" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">school’s website</a>;  It will take a very intensive week (well, maybe two) of following lectures and doing the exercises, but by the end of that time, one is guaranteed to be no longer a complete amateur to the area, as the set of topics covered gives a pretty good picture of what is going on in the field.   <br/>  </p>



<p>Last but not least, I would like to thank the Israeli quantum initiative, Vatat, and the IIAS, for their generous funding which enabled this school and the funding of students; the IIAS team for their immense help in organization;   and of course, thanks a lot to all participants who attended the school!<br/></p>



<p>Wishing everyone a very happy year of 2020,  </p>



<p>Dorit</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-28T22:11:53Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-28T22:11:53Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4447</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4447" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4447#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4447" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Quantum computing motte-and-baileys</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">In the wake of two culture-war posts—the first on the term “quantum supremacy,” the second on the acronym “NIPS”—it’s clear that we all need to cool off with something anodyne and uncontroversial. Fortunately, this holiday season, I know just the thing to bring everyone together: groaning about quantum computing hype! When I was at the […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In the wake of two culture-war posts—the <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450">first</a> on the term “quantum supremacy,” the <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4476">second</a> on the acronym “NIPS”—it’s clear that we all need to cool off with something anodyne and uncontroversial.  Fortunately, this holiday season, I know just the thing to bring everyone together: groaning about quantum computing hype!</p>



<p>When I was at the <a href="https://q2b.qcware.com/">Q2B conference</a> in San Jose, I learned about lots of cool stuff that’s happening in the wake of Google’s quantum supremacy announcement.  I heard about the 57-qubit superconducting chip that the Google group is now building, following up on its 53-qubit one; and also about their first small-scale experimental demonstration of my certified randomness protocol.  I learned about recent progress on costing out the numbers of qubits and gates needed to do fault-tolerant quantum simulations of useful chemical reactions (IIRC, maybe a hundred thousand qubits and a few hours’ worth of gates—scary, but not Shor’s algorithm scary).</p>



<p>I also learned about two claims about quantum algorithms that startups have made, and which are being wrongly interpreted.  The basic pattern is one that I’ve come to know well over the years, and which you could call a science version of the <a href="https://philpapers.org/archive/SHATVO-2.pdf">motte-and-bailey</a>.  (For those not up on nerd blogosphere terminology: in medieval times, the motte was a dank castle to which you’d retreat while under attack; the bailey was the desirable land that you’d farm once the attackers left.)</p>



<p>To wit:</p>



<ol><li>Startup makes claims that have both a true boring interpretation (e.g., you can do X with a quantum computer), as well as a false exciting interpretation (e.g., you can do X with a quantum computer, <em>and it would actually make sense to do this, because you’ll get an asymptotic speedup over the best known classical algorithm</em>).</li><li>Lots of business and government people get all excited, because they assume the false exciting interpretation must be true (or why else would everyone be talking about this?).  Some of those people ask me for comment.</li><li>I look into it, perhaps by asking the folks at the startup.  The startup folks clarify that they meant only the true boring interpretation.  To be sure, they’re actively <em>exploring</em> the false exciting interpretation—whether some parts of it might be true after all—but they’re certainly not making any claims about it that would merit, say, a harsh post on <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em>.</li><li>I’m satisfied to have gotten to the bottom of things, and I tell the startup folks to go their merry way.</li><li>Yet many people continue to seem as excited as if the false exciting interpretation had been shown to be true.  They continue asking me questions that presuppose its truth.</li></ol>



<p>Our first instance of this pattern is the <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/2227387-quantum-computer-sets-new-record-for-finding-prime-number-factors/">recent claim</a>, by <a href="https://www.zapatacomputing.com/">Zapata Computing</a>, to have set a world record for integer factoring (1,099,551,473,989 =  1,048,589 × 1,048,601) with a quantum computer, by running a QAOA/variational algorithm on IBM’s superconducting device.  Gosh!  That sure sounds a lot better than the 21 that’s been factored with Shor’s algorithm, doesn’t it?</p>



<p>I read the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.08927">Zapata paper</a> that this is based on, entitled “Variational Quantum Factoring,” and I don’t believe that a single word in it is false.  My issue is something the paper <em>omits</em>: namely, that once you’ve reduced factoring to a generic optimization problem, you’ve thrown away all the mathematical structure that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shor%27s_algorithm">Shor’s algorithm</a> cleverly exploits, and that makes factoring asymptotically easy for a quantum computer.  And hence there’s no reason to expect your quantum algorithm to scale any better than brute-force trial division (or in the most optimistic scenario, trial division enhanced with Grover search).  On large numbers, your algorithm will be roundly outperformed even by <em>classical</em> algorithms that do exploit structure, like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_number_field_sieve">Number Field Sieve</a>.  Indeed, the quantum computer’s success at factoring the number will have had little or nothing to do with its being <em>quantum</em> at all—a classical optimization algorithm would’ve served as well.  And thus, the only reasons to factor a number on a quantum device in this way, would seem to be stuff like calibrating the device.</p>



<p>Admittedly, to people who work in quantum algorithms, everything above is so obvious that it doesn’t need to be said.  But I learned at Q2B that there are interested people for whom this is <em>not</em> obvious, and even comes as a revelation.  So that’s why I’m saying it.</p>



<p>Again and again over the past twenty years, I’ve seen people reinvent the notion of a “simpler alternative” to Shor’s algorithm: one that cuts out all the difficulty of building a fault-tolerant quantum computer.  In every case, the trouble, typically left unstated, has been that these alternatives <em>also</em> cut out the exponential speedup that’s Shor’s algorithm’s raison d’être.</p>



<p>Our second example today of a quantum computing motte-and-bailey is the claim, by Toronto-based quantum computing startup <a href="https://www.xanadu.ai/">Xanadu</a>, that <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.01199">Gaussian BosonSampling</a> can be used to solve all sorts of graph problems, like graph isomorphism, graph similarity, and densest subgraph.  As the co-inventor of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boson_sampling">BosonSampling</a>, few things would warm my heart more than finding an actual application for that model (besides quantum supremacy experiments and, perhaps, certified random number generation).  But I still regard this as an open problem—if by “application,” we mean outperforming what you could’ve done classically.</p>



<p>In papers (see for example <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.10644">here</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.12646">here</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.10730">here</a>), members of the Xanadu team have given all sorts of ways to take a graph, and encode it into an instance of Gaussian BosonSampling, in such a way that the output distribution will then reveal features of the graph, like its isomorphism type or its dense subgraphs.  The trouble is that so far, I’ve seen no indications that this will actually lead to quantum algorithms that outperform the best classical algorithms, for any graph problems of practical interest.</p>



<p>In the case of Densest Subgraph, the Xanadu folks use the output of a Gaussian BosonSampler to seed (that is, provide an initial guess for) a classical local search algorithm.  They say they observe better results this way than if they seed that classical local search algorithm with completely random initial conditions.  But of course, the real question is: could we get equally good results by seeding with the output of some <em>classical</em> heuristic?  Or by solving Densest Subgraph with a different approach entirely?  Given how hard it’s turned out to be just to <em>verify</em> that the outputs of a BosonSampling device come from such a device at all, it would seem astonishing if the answer to these questions wasn’t “yes.”</p>



<p>In the case of Graph Isomorphism, the situation is even clearer.  There, the central claim made by the Xanadu folks is that given a graph G, they can use a Gaussian BosonSampling device to sample a probability distribution that encodes G’s isomorphism type.  So, isn’t this “promising” for solving GI with a quantum computer?  All you’d need to do now is invent some fast classical algorithm that could look at the samples coming from two graphs G and H, and tell you whether the probability distributions were the same.</p>



<p>Except, not really.  While the Xanadu paper never says so, if all you want is to sample a distribution that encodes a graph’s isomorphism type, that’s easy to do classically!  (I even put this on the final exam for my undergraduate Quantum Information Science course a couple weeks ago.)  Here’s how: given as input a graph G, just output G but with its vertices randomly permuted.  Indeed, this will even provide a further property, better than anything the BosonSampling approach has been shown to provide (or than it probably does provide): namely, if G and H are <em>not</em> isomorphic, then the two probability distributions will not only be different but will have disjoint supports.  Alas, this still leaves us with the problem of distinguishing which distribution a given sample came from, which is as hard as Graph Isomorphism itself.  None of these approaches, classical or quantum, seem to lead to any algorithm that’s subexponential time, let alone competitive with the <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=2521">“Babai approach”</a> of thinking really hard about graphs.</p>



<p>All of this stuff falls victim to what I regard as the Fundamental Error of Quantum Algorithms Research: namely, to treat it as “promising” that a quantum algorithm works at all, or works better than some brute-force classical algorithm, without asking yourself whether there are any indications that your approach will <em>ever</em> be able to exploit interference of amplitudes to outperform the <em>best</em> classical algorithm.</p>



<p>Incidentally, I’m not sure exactly why, but in practice, a major red flag that the Fundamental Error is about to be committed is when someone starts talking about “hybrid quantum/classical algorithms.”  By this they seem to mean: “outside the domain of traditional quantum algorithms, so don’t judge us by the standards of that domain.”  But I liked the way someone at Q2B put it to me: <em>every</em> quantum algorithm is a “hybrid quantum/classical algorithm,” with classical processors used wherever they can be, and qubits used only where they must be.</p>



<p>The other thing people do, when challenged, is to say “well, admittedly we have no <em>rigorous proof</em> of an asymptotic quantum speedup”—thereby brilliantly reframing the whole conversation, to make people like me look like churlish theoreticians insisting on an impossible and perhaps irrelevant standard of rigor, blind to some huge practical quantum speedup that’s about to change the world.  The real issue, of course, is not that they haven’t given a <em>proof</em> of a quantum speedup (in either the real world or the black-box world); rather, it’s that they’ve typically given no reasons whatsoever to think that there <em>might</em> be a quantum speedup, compared to the best classical algorithms available.</p>



<p>In the holiday spirit, let me end on a positive note.  When I did the Q&amp;A at Q2B—the same one where Sarah Kaiser asked me to comment on the term “quantum supremacy”—one of my answers touched on the most important theoretical open problems about sampling-based quantum supremacy experiments.  At the top of the list, I said, was whether there’s some interactive protocol by which a near-term quantum computer can not only exhibit quantum supremacy, but <em>prove</em> it to a polynomial-time-bounded classical skeptic.  I mentioned that there was <em>one</em> proposal for how to do this, in the IQP model, due to <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0809.0847">Bremner and Shepherd</a>, from way back in 2008.  I said that their proposal deserved much more attention than it had received, and that trying to break it would be one obvious thing to work on.  Little did I know that, <strong>literally while I was speaking</strong>, a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1912.05547">paper was being posted to the arXiv</a>, by Gregory Kahanamoku-Meyer, that claims to break Bremner and Shepherd’s protocol.  I haven’t yet studied the paper, but assuming it’s correct, it represents the first clear progress on this problem in years (even though of a negative kind).  Cool!!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-28T16:08:12Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-28T16:08:12Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-01-03T01:30:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16497</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/26/a-math-gift-for-all/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Math Gift For All</title>
    <summary>Happy holidays to all. Kathryn Farley is my dear wife. We just celebrated Christmas together and then went off to London for a holiday. Today I thought I would share a gift with you. Kathryn and I exchange books for the holiday. We do not wrap them—our tradition, which she started years ago. I like […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Happy holidays to all.</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/kathrynart.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-16499" height="300" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/kathrynart.jpg?w=158&amp;h=300" width="158"/></a></p>
<p>
Kathryn Farley is my dear wife. We just celebrated Christmas together and then went off to London for a holiday.</p>
<p>
Today I thought I would share a gift with you.<br/>
<span id="more-16497"/></p>
<p>
Kathryn and I exchange books for the holiday. We do not wrap them—our tradition, which she started years ago. I like doing this. Ken’s family re-uses wrapping paper year-to-year. I am pleased to see that there is a call to save wrapping on three <a href="https://frugalkite.com/zero-waste-christmas-three-genius-wrapping-methods/">gifts</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> If every American family wrapped just 3 presents in reused materials, it would save enough paper to cover 45,000 football fields. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Kathryn gave me a wonderful collection of books. One of them is not the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Computers-Rigidity-Moduli-Large-Scale-Riemannian/dp/B01FJ1E910">book</a>: <i>Computers, Rigidity, and Moduli: The Large-Scale Fractal Geometry of Riemannian Moduli Space</i>. The author is Shmuel Weinberger a mathematician from the University of Chicago. I already had his book but finally took a look at it while browsing my other gifts. So it is a delayed gift, from a Christmas past.</p>
<p>
The book is a combination of computer results, basic math results, and advanced math results. The last are a variety of topics that are well outside of my zone. I did like the book. Weinberger is a terrific writer, a terrific explainer, a gifted selector of topics. I was surprised to see that his book contained a puzzle that I had not thought about before. The puzzle is, like all good puzzles, easy to state—but hard to solve. At least for me. I did not see how to solve it. I hope you like it.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> A Puzzle </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Imagine that there are <img alt="{2n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2n}"/> distinct points in the plane. No three points are collinear. Half of them, <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> are labeled <font color="red"><b>red</b></font> and the other half are labelled <font color="green"><b>green</b></font>. Festive colors. Your job is to connect each red point with a unique green point by a straight line. That is easy, of course. But we hate when lines cross. So your job is more: Please select the lines so that the fewest ones cross.</p>
<p>
Thus the problem is. Find the fewest line crossings possible. As usual we wish to know the answer as a function of <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>. Is it <img alt="{\sqrt{n}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7Bn%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{n}}"/>? Or <img alt="{\log(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log(n)}"/>? What is the best possible in the worst case?</p>
<p>
The artwork on the wall behind Kathryn suggests a possible arrangement, likewise the floor. The art object directly behind her is in 3D space which is not allowed—but this is a photograph so its points are projected onto a plane anyway. Again, it’s important that no three points are collinear. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> There is a Best </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
For start we note that there is always a best. Each of <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> red points can match one of <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> green points. So there are only a finite number of possible matchings, namely 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  n! = n \times (n-1) \times \cdots \times 1. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++n%21+%3D+n+%5Ctimes+%28n-1%29+%5Ctimes+%5Ccdots+%5Ctimes+1.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  n! = n \times (n-1) \times \cdots \times 1. "/></p>
<p>This shows that there is always a best answer; moreover, it can be found. But <img alt="{n!}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%21%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n!}"/> can be huge, so another part of the question is: Can you find the best answer fast? How about finding the best answer in polynomial time?</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> A Solution </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The best answer is that the number of crossings is always at most 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  b(n) = c \log(n), " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++b%28n%29+%3D+c+%5Clog%28n%29%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  b(n) = c \log(n), "/></p>
<p>where <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/> is the constant 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  10^{2}+11^{2}+12^{2}- 13^{2} - 14^{2}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++10%5E%7B2%7D%2B11%5E%7B2%7D%2B12%5E%7B2%7D-+13%5E%7B2%7D+-+14%5E%7B2%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  10^{2}+11^{2}+12^{2}- 13^{2} - 14^{2}. "/></p>
<p>
Here is a proof that this bound is correct. Suppose that you have selected the fewest number of line crossings. We will argue that there are at most <img alt="{b(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b(n)}"/> line crossings. The plan is to show that we can descend—that is given a matching we can try and decrease the number of lines that cross. </p>
<p>
Given any two red nodes and any two green nodes, we can define the operation <em>swap</em> by having them exchange partners. If their lines cross before the swap, then after the swap the lines will <em>not</em> cross. The following figure shows this:</p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/points.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-16500" height="217" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/points.png?w=300&amp;h=217" width="300"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Oops. I thought the idea was to define an operation so that the number of line crossing could always be decreased. Wait the argument does not work. In the above figure the switch <em>increases</em> the number of crossings.</p>
<p>
There is a saving trick, however. Do not attempt to decrease the number of lines that cross. Instead decrease the total <i>length</i> of the lines selected. The above figure can be turned into a proof of a lemma that a <em>swap</em> of two crossing lines always decreases the sum of their lengths. The cool idea is that the swaps may actually increase the number of crossings, but they will always decrease the total length. </p>
<p>
In the end the length is minimal and there are <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0}"/> crossings. Thus 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  b(n) = 0. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++b%28n%29+%3D+0.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  b(n) = 0. "/></p>
<p>I cheated and used that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  10^{2}+11^{2}+12^{2} = 13^{2} + 14^{2}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++10%5E%7B2%7D%2B11%5E%7B2%7D%2B12%5E%7B2%7D+%3D+13%5E%7B2%7D+%2B+14%5E%7B2%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  10^{2}+11^{2}+12^{2} = 13^{2} + 14^{2}, "/></p>
<p>and so the constant <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/> is zero. Finally, no swap is ever undone—since the length always decreases—and so the process must finish within <img alt="{O(n^2)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E2%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n^2)}"/> swaps.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Hope that you liked this puzzle. I think it shows that are sometimes methods that while simple may be hard to find. Is <img alt="{O(n^2)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E2%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n^2)}"/> really the needed number of swaps? Are more than a linear number of swaps ever required?<br/>
 Happy holidays to all.</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-27T04:04:37Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-27T04:04:37Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="trick"/>
    <category term="Christmas"/>
    <category term="complexity"/>
    <category term="Kathryn Farley"/>
    <category term="puzzle"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=18835</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/27/the-google-quantum-supremacy-demo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Google Quantum Supremacy Demo and the Jerusalem HQCA debate.</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Below are 10 annotated slides from a spontaneous informal talk that I gave at the school on mathematics of quantum computing a weak ago. (Power point presentation.) Later in the afternoon we had  a panel/debate on quantum supremacy (click for … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/27/the-google-quantum-supremacy-demo/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Below are 10 annotated slides from a spontaneous informal talk that I gave at the <a href="http://ias.huji.ac.il/SchoolCSE4">school on mathematics of quantum computing</a> a weak ago. (<a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-demo-blog.pptx">Power point presentation</a>.) Later in the afternoon we had  <strong>a panel/debate on quantum supremacy </strong>(<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H4t2G2gay7Q&amp;feature=youtu.be">click for the video</a>) moderated by Sandy Irani and featuring Scott Aaronson, Dorit Aharonov, Boaz Barak, Sergio Boixo, Adam Bouland,  Umesh Vazirani, and me. It was a thoughtful and interesting discussion. (The presentation was initially prepared for the afternoon debate but at the end I gave it as a separate talk and presented just one slide at the panel itself. The plan was also to post it as a background material before the discussion, but not untypically, I was too slow, so here it is a week later.) I am thankful to Dorit for inviting me to the panel (and for organizing a great school!), to Sandy for her excellent moderation, and to all the panelists for their good spirit. (Update: <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/12/28/quantum-school-lecture-notes-videos-and-more-guest-post-by-dorit-aharonov/">A blog post by Dorit</a> at Windows on Theory)</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><strong>My assessment continues to be that both the Google supremacy claims and their other central claim about fidelity estimation are incorrect.</strong></span></p>
<p>(Dec 23, 2019: Following some <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450">renewed discussion</a> in the last days on the terminology I proposed to replace the term “quantum supremacy” with <strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">“HQCA – Huge Quantum Computational Advantage”</span></strong> and I myself may try to follow my new term in my own lectures/papers in the future and see how it goes. In fact, I already used HQCA in our Sunday’s Kazhdan seminar where I lectured about noise stability and sensitivity for Boolean functions, Boson Sampling, and quantum circuits (<a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/d7a1d7a8d799d7a7d7940006.pdf">lecture</a> <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/d7a1d7a8d799d7a7d7940007.pdf">notes</a>).)</p>
<h2>My Presentation on the Google Quantum Supremacy Demonstration</h2>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> you may click on a slide to see it in full screen.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide1.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18836" height="365" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide1.png?w=640&amp;h=365" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>My lecture is not about quantum computers and quantum supremacy in general but about the Google quantum supremacy claims. (If you want to know more about my general argument against quantum computers, quantum supremacy and quantum error correction go to the previous post <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/11/13/gils-collegial-quantum-supremacy-skepticism-faq/" rel="bookmark">Gil’s Collegial Quantum Supremacy Skepticism FAQ </a>and to <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/09/main-pr.pdf">several</a> of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02499">my</a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02499">papers</a> and <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/09/cern.pptx">presentations</a> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oR-ufBz13Eg">linked</a> there.)</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide12.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18875" height="362" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide12.png?w=640&amp;h=362" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>In this presentation I will concentrate on aspects of the Google experiment that are “too good to be true”. (Which is a bad sign, not a good sign.)</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide13.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18874" height="350" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide13.png?w=640&amp;h=350" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>There is an amazing agreement between the fidelity as estimated from the experimental data and a very simple high-school model based on the probability of individual qubits and gates to malfunction.  (An even simplified version, below in purple, requires just three parameters – the number n of qubits, the number g1 of 1-qubit gates and the number g2 of 2-qubit gates.)</p>
<p>Formula (77) itself is not surprising but the terrific success of Formula (77) may serve as a smoking gun for the claim that the Google’s experiment has serious methodological problems.</p>
<p>I was not the only one to be amazed. Here is what John Martinis, the scientific leader of the Google supremacy experiment told about it. (Nov 1., 2019) Read carefully!</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide6.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18849" height="400" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide6.png?w=640&amp;h=400" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>The accuracy of Formula (77) is the most amazing thing about the data, something that came as a big surprise, and that (jokingly) will let quantum scientists keep their jobs.</p>
<p>And here is what I think</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide7.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18851" height="367" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide7.png?w=640&amp;h=367" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>No no, you cannot estimate with precision of 10-20% the probability of failure of a physical system with 1000 interacting elements as the product of 1000 error-probabilities.</p>
<p><strong>This remarkable agreement is a major new discovery, and it is <em>not needed</em> for building quantum computers. It is only needed for the extrapolation argument leading the Google team to supremacy.</strong></p>
<p>Even if quantum computers will be built this is something that we are not going to witness. It is interesting to check if we see anything remotely like this for the IBM quantum computers.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide8.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18853" height="334" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide8.png?w=640&amp;h=334" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>Here on the left you see for various values of <em>n</em>, the number of qubits, two experiments with different circuits that leads to entirely different probability distributions. Since each pair have a similar number of gates, Formula (77) leads to very close fidelity estimates which are so accurate that the green and blue lines coincide! We do not expect to see such close agreements in experimental data.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide9.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18857" height="350" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide9.png?w=640&amp;h=350" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>Blue, orange and green analytic smooth curves representing three distributions. For all three you see also empirical samples from the distributions. For two of them the samples are perfect, for the other one you see a sample based on a complicated physical experiment.</p>
<p><strong>Test your intuition:</strong> can you tell the difference? Can you tell which is which?</p>
<p>(You can also test your intuition which was the single slide presented at the afternoon debate.)</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide10.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18860" height="360" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide10.png?w=640&amp;h=360" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><strong>Blind tests</strong> are standard in scientific experiments and are quite easy to implement here.</p>
<p>The meaning of the surprising statistical success of Formula (77) should be <strong>carefully examined</strong>.</p>
<h2>Two extra slides</h2>
<p>To put my view in context,  I devote one slide for my general argument against quantum computers, quantum supremacy and quantum error correction.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide2.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18839" height="363" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide2.png?w=640&amp;h=363" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>I mentioned that most experts do not agree with my argument or do not even understand it, and for some of them, this may give reasons for skepticism also about my critique on the Google experiment. I  personally think that my general argument is good, but  I don’t think it is ironclad and I am pleased to see this matter explored experimentally (properly). I also think that my critique on the Google demo stands well on its own.</p>
<p>And what may convince me to change my mind? poetry!</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/dslide16.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19013" height="362" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/dslide16.png?w=640&amp;h=362" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>Let me add that all my critique as described here and elsewhere was first presented to the Google team.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/fp12.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19089" height="178" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/fp12.png?w=640&amp;h=178" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">From right to left: Sandy Irani, me, Boaz Barak, Adam Bouland, Dorit Aharonov, and on the left Umesh Vazirani, Scott Aaronson, and Sergio Boixo. (Collage; More pictures – below.)</span></p>
<p><span id="more-18835"/></p>
<p><strong>Answer to Test your intuition:</strong> The orange graph is the one that comes from the experiments.</p>
<h2>Some recollections, reactions, and comments from the debate:</h2>
<h3>Uploading data for verification</h3>
<p>At the beginning of the debate, I nudged Sergio to upload some (additional; promised) data that is needed for verification and analysis of their results.</p>
<h3>Formula (77)</h3>
<p>Formula (77) was discussed in some details in Q/A of the the informal talk and also in the panel/debate. (I raised the question if the Google experiment is correct and specifically the issue with Formula (77) at <a href="https://youtu.be/H4t2G2gay7Q?t=2097">35:00</a> and Formula (77) was discussed for the next 25 minutes.) Of course, the surprising issue is the accurate predictions that Formula (77) gives.</p>
<p>Sergio briefly explained the statistical rationale for such a precision. The way I see it, the quality of the prediction for (77) requires two assumptions: (1) No systematic errors, (2) statistical independence. Both these assumptions seem utterly unrealistic. No systematic errors means that the average error estimation say for read-out errors or for gate errors are precise and fluctuations are symmetric. This is very unrealistic. The assumption of statistical independence also seems unrealistic. (Positive correlations will actually lead to better fidelity.)  Dorit, Boaz and several other people (and also Peter Shor earlier <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/11/13/gils-collegial-quantum-supremacy-skepticism-faq/#comment-61697">here on the blog</a>) proposed that the remarkable predictive power of (77) and, in particular, the required statistical independence may follow from having a random circuit. I don’t understand that.</p>
<p>Beside the concrete attempts to understand the predictive power of Formula (77) there were some general comments about it. Adam opined that <em>in physics</em> the data fits the models very well. Scott  joked that here I am arguing that the results fits the model too well and he could imagine me arguing in another universe that the results don’t fit the model well enough. At another point he said “First the data is not good enough, and now the data is too good, what will make you happy, Gil” and I answered that the data should be <em>reliable.</em></p>
<h3>The extended Church-Turing thesis (ECTT)</h3>
<p>Does “supremacy” (or HQCA), in general and in the context of Google’s experiment violates the extended Church-Turing thesis? Dorit claimed that the answer is negative since (roughly) the experiments cannot be scaled. Sergio sort of agreed and said they only claim to <em>challenge</em> the ECCT. (Indeed the fidelity goes exponentially to zero and even if producing such samples is beyond the power of a classical computer the sample sizes need to be exponential; it is an interesting question if every scalable supremacy demonstration requires quantum fault tolerance.)  A point that I made is that if we assume further certain “naturalness” principle, namely that, in practice,  constants in computational complexity asymptotic behavior are mild, then an astronomical speed-up as claimed by Google, can be considered as violating ECCT.</p>
<h3>Trillions</h3>
<p>Actually, in the early lecture I presented another slide about my initial feeling towards the Google (then licked) paper. I was surprised by the trillions-time speed up, and regarded the 300,000,000,000 speed-up as expressing some “supremacy fever:” why not start with a more modest speed-up but with convincing direct evidence?</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide3.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-18841" height="170" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide3.png?w=300&amp;h=170" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>Why the trillions speed up should not surprise us? Adam Bouland commented that this is to be expected when we think about exponential speed-up. BTW, Adam gave very nice lectures on quantum algorithms and quantum supremacy.</p>
<h3>Miscellaneous</h3>
<ol>
<li>I was slowly loosing my voice so in the earlier lecture Or Sattath read the quote from Martinis, and Adam read the poem by Renan. (I should try that also in talks where I am not loosing my voice.)</li>
<li> Sandy asked about other reasons for skepticism regarding the Google claims and Scott mentioned the possibility that much better classical algorithms will be found.</li>
<li>Both me and Scott (and perhaps others in the panel as well) emphasized the importance of replications.</li>
<li>Adam was Scott’s Ph. D student and Scott was Umesh’s Ph. D. student so we had on the panel three academic generations!</li>
<li>Toward the end Scott described briefly the decade-old history, theory+experiment, of quantum supremacy.</li>
<li>There were various other interesting issues that were raised.</li>
<li>For history: The video flipped left and right. In reality Sandy was right farthermost and I was second to the right.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Quantum error-correction</h3>
<p>Dorit asked about quantum error correction and I asked specifically about distance-3 surface code and Sergio said that the quality of gates is insufficient for that. If I understood correctly the error rate needs to be reduced by a factor of five. (The fact that good quality quantum error correction requires achieving lower error rate than what is required for quantum supremacy is an important ingredient of my general argument against quantum computers.)</p>
<h3>Noise models and the noisy data.</h3>
<p>Dorit and others raised the issue of the noise model and discussed some toy noise models.  There was some discussion on correlated errors. (This is unrelated to the statistical dependence of (77).) I pointed out that correlated errors are irrelevant to random circuits (but relevant to quantum error-correction). Later in the debate I mentioned the concern regarding not having large enough samples to determine the empirical noisy distribution.</p>
<p>At some point Umesh referred to another issue that I raised which is that the noisy model in the Google paper seems oversimplified. I came back to it briefly but we did not discuss this further. (At the Q/A part of my early lecture Boaz have made some interesting comments about identifying the effect of the errors in the last round of the computation.)</p>
<p>I also repeated my suggestion of “Beckner noise” (and correlated variants) as a good toy noise model for noisy quantum circuits.</p>
<h3>My argument against quantum computers</h3>
<p>At the panel I mentioned my general argument against quantum computers, quantum supremacy and quantum error correction only in a few sentences.</p>
<p>BTW, one way to think about the argument is as comparing four thresholds for the level of noise (on gates) <img alt="\rho_{\bf R}, \rho_{\bf S}, \rho_{\bf QEC}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+R%7D%2C+%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+S%7D%2C+%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+QEC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf R}, \rho_{\bf S}, \rho_{\bf QEC}"/> and <img alt="\rho_{\bf U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+U%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf U}"/>. <img alt="\rho_{\bf S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+S%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf S}"/> is what is required for <strong>HQCA</strong> (quantum supremacy); <img alt="\rho_{\bf QEC}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+QEC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf QEC}"/> is what is required for good quality quantum error correction (say, distance-5 surface code); <img alt="\rho_{\bf U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+U%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf U}"/> is what is required for universal quantum computing; <img alt="\rho_{\bf R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+R%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf R}"/> is the lower error rate that can realistically be achieved. I have a computational complexity argument (based on naturalness) that <img alt="\rho_{\bf R} &gt; \rho_{\bf S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+R%7D+%3E+%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+S%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf R} &gt; \rho_{\bf S}"/>. I also rely on <img alt="\rho_{\bf S} &gt; \rho_{\bf QEC}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+S%7D+%3E+%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+QEC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf S} &gt; \rho_{\bf QEC}"/>.</p>
<h3>Comparisons to Wright brothers’s first flight or to Fermi’s 1942 nuclear chain reaction</h3>
<p>Nobody in the afternoon panel discussion (to the best of my memory) repeated earlier enthusiastic comparisons between Google’s experiment and the first flight in 1903, the first landing on the moon in 1968 (well, I referred to that), Fermi’s 1942 nuclear chain reaction, the first vacuum tubes computers, the discovery of the Higgs boson, etc. etc.</p>
<h3>Silver lining (after-thought)</h3>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/silverlining.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-19048" height="192" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/silverlining.png?w=300&amp;h=192" width="300"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The beach of Tel Aviv</span></p>
<p>Major advances in human ability to simulate quantum physics and quantum chemistry are expected both if quantum supremacy can be demonstrated and quantum computers can be built and also if quantum supremacy cannot be demonstrated and quantum computers cannot be built.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Debate picture collage</span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/panel-gallery.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19042" height="371" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/panel-gallery.png?w=640&amp;h=371" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/panel-umesh.png"> </a></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/daud3.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-19070" height="163" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/daud3.png?w=300&amp;h=163" width="300"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The audience was happy</span></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-26T22:04:52Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-26T22:04:52Z</published>
    <category term="Controversies and debates"/>
    <category term="Quantum"/>
    <category term="Adam Bouland"/>
    <category term="Boaz Barak"/>
    <category term="Dorit Aharonov"/>
    <category term="Google"/>
    <category term="HQCA"/>
    <category term="Huge Quantum Computational Advantage"/>
    <category term="quantum supremacy"/>
    <category term="Sandy Irani"/>
    <category term="Scott Aaronson"/>
    <category term="Sergio Boixo"/>
    <category term="Umesh Vazirani"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/25/postdoctoral-research-associate-at-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-theory-of-distributed-systems-group-nancy-lynch-apply-by-february-28-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/25/postdoctoral-research-associate-at-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-theory-of-distributed-systems-group-nancy-lynch-apply-by-february-28-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral Research Associate at Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Theory of Distributed Systems Group, Nancy Lynch (apply by February 28, 2019)</title>
    <summary>Area: “Distributed Algorithms for Dynamic, Noisy Platforms: Wireless Networks, Robot Swarms, and Insect Colonies”. Candidates should have research experience with algorithms for at least one of these topics, preferably with noise and change. Strong background in probabilistic modeling/analysis is essential. Work will also involve simulation, and coordination with experimental researchers. Website: https://groups.csail.mit.edu/tds/reflist.html Email: lynch@csail.mit.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Area: “Distributed Algorithms for Dynamic, Noisy Platforms: Wireless Networks, Robot Swarms, and Insect Colonies”.</p>
<p>Candidates should have research experience with algorithms for at least one of these topics, preferably with noise and change. Strong background in probabilistic modeling/analysis is essential. Work will also involve simulation, and coordination with experimental researchers.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://groups.csail.mit.edu/tds/reflist.html">https://groups.csail.mit.edu/tds/reflist.html</a><br/>
Email: lynch@csail.mit.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-25T12:37:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-25T12:37:19Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-01-09T02:23:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
