<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2021-04-01T16:22:00Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-2369988409049011731</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/2369988409049011731/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/04/want-to-buy-theorem.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2369988409049011731" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2369988409049011731" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/04/want-to-buy-theorem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Want to Buy a Theorem?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This is embarrassing to admit but after a few badly timed trades on GameStop options I find myself a bit tight on money. To raise some cash, I reluctantly decided to sell one of my prized possessions, one of my theorems.</p><p><b>For Sale</b>: Boolean formula satisfiability cannot be solved in both logarithmic space and quasilinear time. For a more formal and slightly more general statement and a proof, see <a href="https://doi.org/10.1006/jcss.1999.1671">this paper</a>.</p><p><b>Bidding starts</b> at 12 BTC (about $705,000). </p><p><b>The winning bid, upon verified payment, will receive:</b></p><p/><ul style="text-align: left;"><li>The ability to give the theorem the name of your choice such as your own name, your best friend's mother's name or "Teddy McTheoremface".</li><li>A non-fungible token (NFT) attesting ownership of the theorem and the name you have chosen for it.</li><li>Anyone citing this result will be required to note that you own it and use the name you chose above. You cannot, however, limit the use of the theorem or receive compensation for its use. </li><li>By virtue of owning this theorem you will a Fortnow number of zero. This immediately gives you an Erdős number of 2. If you have previously written a paper with Paul Erdős then both of us will now have an Erdős number of 1.</li></ul><div><b>Frequently Asked Questions</b></div><div><b><br/></b></div><div><b>Q: </b>Why this theorem?</div><div><b><br/></b></div><div><b>A: </b>The theorem is in one of my few solely authored papers and I can't afford to share the proceeds of the sale. </div><div><br/></div><div><b>Q: </b>Doesn't Ryan Williams and others have <a href="http://pages.cs.wisc.edu/~dieter/Papers/sat-lb-survey-fttcs.pdf">stronger theorems</a>?</div><div><br/></div><div><b>A: </b>The results are incomparable. Ryan gives bounds on a single algorithm with low time and space. My theorem allows different machines for the time and space bounds.</div><div><br/></div><div>Also, to the best of my knowledge, Ryan's theorem is not for sale.</div><div><br/></div><div><b>Q: </b>Doesn't the proof of the theorem rely on other people's theorems such as Nepomnjascii? Shouldn't he get some of the value from this sale?</div><div><br/></div><div><b>A: </b>I'm not selling the proof of the theorem, just the theorem itself.</div><div><br/></div><div><b>Q: </b>If I purchase this theorem will I get to write next year's April Fools post?</div><div><br/></div><div><b>A: </b>No.</div><p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-04-01T13:22:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-04-01T13:22:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T13:22:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/049</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/049" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-049 |  Kolmogorov complexity and  nondeterminism versus determinism  for polynomial time computations | 

	Juraj Hromkovic</title>
    <summary>We call any consistent and sufficiently powerful formal theory that enables to algorithmically in polynomial time verify whether a text is a proof  \textbf{efficiently verifiable mathematics} (ev-mathematics). We study the question whether nondeterminism is more powerful than determinism for polynomial time computations in the framework of ev-mathematics. Our main results are as follows. \\
"$\P \subsetneq \NP$ or for any deterministic, polynomial time compression algorithm $A$ there exists a nondeterministic, polynomial time compression machine $M$ that reduces infinitely many binary strings logarithmically stronger than $A$." \\
"$\P \subsetneq \NP$ or f-time resource bounded Kolmogorov complexity of any binary string $x$ can be computed in deterministic polynomial time for each polynomial time constructible function $f$."</summary>
    <updated>2021-04-01T12:52:24Z</updated>
    <published>2021-04-01T12:52:24Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=18471</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/04/01/computer-science-gets-noted/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Computer Science Gets Noted</title>
    <summary>All non-metallic UK currency to feature Computing and Data Science pioneers Cropped from BBC source Charles Babbage and Ada Lovelace will be reunited. Their work on designing and programming a computing device, a century before any machine was built, is being honored by their appearance on the reverse of the 5-pound note in a new […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>All non-metallic UK currency to feature Computing and Data Science pioneers</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/04/01/computer-science-gets-noted/babbagelovelacenote/" rel="attachment wp-att-18474"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-18474" height="134" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/BabbageLovelaceNote.jpg?resize=250%2C134&amp;ssl=1" width="250"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Cropped from BBC <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-34710261?ocid=socialflow_facebook&amp;">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Charles Babbage and Ada Lovelace will be reunited. Their work on designing and programming a computing device, a century before any machine was built, is being honored by their appearance on the reverse of the 5-pound note in a new series authorized by the Bank of England. Royal Statistical Society Fellow Florence Nightingale will appear on the 10, EDSAC creator Maurice Wilkes on the 20, and Alan Turing on the 50. </p>
<p>
Today, April 1, we are delighted to convey this news and show previews of the banknotes. </p>
<p>
We have mentioned Babbage and Lovelace several times on this blog, the latter first <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2010/03/23/its-ada-lovelace-day/">here</a>. Our 2015 <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2015/02/17/ada-the-amplifier/">post</a> on her work on his project sought to engage a scholarly consensus that tends to minimize it. We argue that it should be judged on the plane of a doctoral or masters advisory relationship. Our point is that she greatly <em>amplified</em> the technical content of his work as shown to the scientific community. </p>
<p>
The design shown above makes a leap from their Victorian world to our online age. Being “online” back then probably meant being reached by the new railroad system centered on London. The one indelible connection between our world and theirs is shown by the obverse of the banknote: both worlds have a long-serving British queen.</p>
<p/><h2> Nightingale On The 10 </h2><p/>
<p>
Besides a long life (1820–1910), Nightingale has a long entry as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Founders_of_statistics">founder</a> of statistics. Her actions and influence extended for more than five decades after her iconic “Lady With the Lamp” ministry to soldiers of the Crimean War depicted on the 10-pound note:</p>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/04/01/computer-science-gets-noted/nightingalespecimen2021/" rel="attachment wp-att-18475"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-18475" height="252" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/NightingaleSpecimen2021.jpg?resize=450%2C252&amp;ssl=1" width="450"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Nightingale 200 Years <a href="https://www.florence-nightingale.co.uk/10-bank-note-featuring-florence-nightingale-1975-1992/">source</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
The picture at right is based on a <a href="https://www.amdigital.co.uk/about/blog/item/nightingale">photo</a> by William Kilburn, one of few series of photos she allowed to be taken. We have not found a definitive word on what she is holding—not even from this long <a href="https://theclassicphotomag.com/florence-nightingale-the-mysteries-behind-her-iconic-photographs/">article</a>—but we would like to believe it is a letter or paper regarding medical practice. Already in 1854, the <em>Oxford Chronicle and Reading Gazette</em> noted her bringing much more than a lamp:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> In a knowledge of the ancient languages and of the higher branches of mathematics, in general art, science, and literature, her attainments are extraordinary. There is scarcely a modern language which she does not understand; and she speaks French, German, and Italian as fluently as her native English. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Not only did she popularize the pie chart and invent other statistical visualization techniques, she was among the first people period to bring statistical inference into policy. This included demonstrating with data the higher exposure of nurses to multiple diseases among those they tended. She was inducted into the Royal Statistical Society in <b>1858</b>. </p>
<p>
Her medical conduct principles have been applied expressly during the pandemic, as <a href="https://nursing.vanderbilt.edu/news/lessons-from-florence-nightingale-are-primary-tools-in-covid-19-nursing/">recognized</a> by the time of the 200th anniversary of her birth last May 12, and field hospitals in the UK for Covid-19 treatment are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COVID-19_hospitals_in_the_United_Kingdom">named</a> for her. Her recognition on the currency was considered a way to honor first-line caregivers and was a unanimous vote of the Bank of England commission. It has the earliest release <a href="https://en.numista.com/catalogue/note203311.html">date</a> of all the banknotes.</p>
<p/><h2> Wilkes On The 20 </h2><p/>
<p>
Maurice Wilkes had an even longer life, 1913 to 2010. This marks a stark contrast to Turing. Wilkes was the second winner, in 1967, of the Turing Award. The Turing Award <a href="https://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/wilkes_1001395.cfm">citation</a> said he was</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “the builder and designer of the EDSAC, the first computer with an internally stored program.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
He was thus the first realizer of the full vision of Babbage and Lovelace, although many claim the stored-program distinction for the Manchester <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manchester_Baby">Baby</a> one year earlier, in 1948.</p>
<p>
There was controversy about the order of him and Turing. The banknotes were intended to go in chronological order. Turing’s famous paper conceiving the computer dates to 1936–37. Wilkes’s first brush with the project that became the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EDSAC">EDSAC</a> came in 1945, when he spent an iconic 24 hours with a loaned copy of John von Neumann’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Draft_of_a_Report_on_the_EDVAC">First EDVAC Report</a> that he was not able to mimeograph. However, Wilkes was involved with analog computing devices before 1937 and his EDSAC reached full operation in May 1949, whereas Turing’s own main project, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automatic_Computing_Engine">ACE</a>, launched its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pilot_ACE">pilot</a> version only in 1950. </p>
<p>
The ultimate determiner was that the 20-pound note was already recently revised to feature the artist Joseph Turner in February 2020. The Turner issue will have a five-year term, so Wilkes will appear in 2025. The banknote design has not yet been executed.</p>
<p/><h2> Turing On The 50 </h2><p/>
<p>
Of course, this is the highlight for us, and we are delighted to be able to show the Turing design in full glory. It was formally <a href="https://www.bankofengland.co.uk/news/2021/march/the-new-50-note-unveiled">unveiled</a> last week:</p>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/04/01/computer-science-gets-noted/turingbanknote/" rel="attachment wp-att-18476"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-18476" height="295" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/TuringBanknote.jpg?resize=550%2C295&amp;ssl=1" width="550"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Belfast Telegraph <a href="https://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/business/uk-world/birth-date-in-binary-code-among-features-of-new-alan-turing-banknote-40238025.html">source</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
The Pilot ACE machine is shown overlaid with Turing machine code from his 1936 paper. Turing tapes with binary code appear in three places. The big one represents his June 23, 1912 birth date—exactly how, we leave as a puzzle.  We’ll just hint that all our friends across the Pond write dates differently from how we do. The new banknotes are being released on Turing’s birthday this coming June.</p>
<p>
The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GCHQ">GCHQ</a>, which grew out of Turing’s employers at Bletchley Park, has just released its own puzzle <a href="https://www.gchq.gov.uk/information/turing-challenge">challenge</a>, which references Easter-egg features of the Turing banknote. The binary code puzzle is 11th of 12, but to our surprise, when you click it, it gives the answer to the birth date part right away.  Then it proceeds to something far more cryptic—well, it’s from GCHQ after all. </p>
<p/><h2> Other Notes </h2><p/>
<p>
The Turing release will also complete the conversion from paper to polymer of all Bank of England notes, which are also the only series issued for Wales. Scotland and Northern Ireland issue their own pound-denominated banknotes with different designs. They have yet to convert to polymer, and that will delay any consideration of adopting the new series.</p>
<p>
Turing’s family on his father’s side came from Scotland, so there is some sentiment for the Royal Bank of Scotland adopting the design. There is also discussion of recognizing Robin Milner and/or Donald Michie, though both were born in England. </p>
<p>
Over in Ireland, both sides of the Northern Ireland border are considering the statistician William Gosset, who as Head Brewer of Guinness over a century ago conceived the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Student's_t-test">Student t-test</a> among many innovations. However, Gosset was also born in England. The Bushmills distillery in Northern Ireland has already <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20150717073525/http://boini.bankofireland.com/about-boi-group/bank-notes/note/16">appeared</a> on their 5-pound note.</p>
<p>
In fact, Gosset and Milner and Michie were all originally <a href="https://www.bankofengland.co.uk/-/media/boe/files/banknotes/50-character-selection-names.pdf">nominated</a> alongside Turing for the 50-pound note. We spot Bertrand Russell and William Tutte and Karen Spärck-Jones on the list. In physics, we notice Paul Dirac and John Bell and Stephen Hawking, and also the astronomer Vera Rubin—who was only American, no? Bell was from Northern Ireland. </p>
<p>
Sir Michael Atiyah is not on the list because he was living at the time—no living person other than the monarch may appear on a banknote. This law does not apply to e-currency however, and this leads to what for us is the most exciting aspect of the Bank of England initiative.</p>
<p/><h2> Semi-Fungible Tokens </h2><p/>
<p>
The following is a GLL exclusive. It was conveyed to us by Dr. Lofa Polir, who since our <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2020/04/01/research-at-home/">story</a> a year ago has resided in England. It comes from a confluence of several facts:</p>
<ul>
<li>National banks regularly issue limited editions of currency apart from the main series.
</li><li>Government banks have largely refrained from direct involvement with digital currencies, but <a href="https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/speech/brainard20200813a.htm">observe</a> them closely.
</li><li>Large sections of the public have come to ascribe intrinsic value to <em>non-fungible tokens</em> (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-fungible_token">NFTs</a>), which come with a blockchain-verifiable certificate of unique ownership.
</li><li>A non-fungible token by-definition cannot be used as money but only bought and sold as a (unique) commodity.
</li><li>Playing cards in games such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic:_The_Gathering">Magic: the Gathering</a> are regularly traded online to the extent of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mt._Gox">melding</a> with cryptocurrencies or verging on being currency themselves.
</li></ul>
<p>
The Bank of England recently voted to create an active response to this situation: the <em>semi-fungible token</em> (SFT). Like Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies, SFTs limit their supply, but unlike them, SFTs are maintained by a central body and backed by its assets. As with NFTs, each SFT is associated to a piece of digital artwork. </p>
<p>
The new issues are based on the Royal Mail’s 2015 <a href="https://www.collectgbstamps.co.uk/explore/issues/?issue=22720">Inventive Britain</a> collection, whose honorees include Sir Tim Berners-Lee for the World Wide Web. The main stamps were abstract, but associated issues are not subject to the law against likenesses of living persons:</p>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/04/01/computer-science-gets-noted/bernersleewww/" rel="attachment wp-att-18477"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-18477" height="212" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/BernersLeeWWW.png?resize=534%2C212&amp;ssl=1" width="534"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Composite of <a href="https://gb-site.netlify.app/tim-berners-lee-biography/">src1</a>, <a href="https://www.bfdc.co.uk/2007/world_of_invention/sir_tim_berners_lee.html">src2</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
Berners-Lee will be the first honoree in the SFT series. We are not authorized to reveal the art design before its release. But Lofa sent us a list of nominees that includes Geoffrey Hinton, Tony Hoare, and Leslie Valiant on the CS side, plus David Spiegelhalter and Demis Hassabis in data science. Unlike with the banknotes, the Bank of England can “catch them all.” Imagine, then, you will soon be able to pay for groceries with cards of some of your favorite computer and data scientists—at least if they are British and you buy the groceries in Britain. </p>
<p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>
If you see a market for NFTs, do you see one for SFTs—or are they both April Fools?</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-04-01T08:36:16Z</updated>
    <published>2021-04-01T08:36:16Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Ada Lovelace"/>
    <category term="April Fool"/>
    <category term="Charles Babbage"/>
    <category term="Florence Nightingale"/>
    <category term="Lofa Polir"/>
    <category term="Maurice Wilkes"/>
    <category term="non-fungible tokens"/>
    <category term="Tim Berners-Lee"/>
    <category term="Turing"/>
    <author>
      <name>KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/03/31/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/03/31/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>As is often the case, not all of these are links; they’re copies of posts that I made over on my Mastodon account because they were too short to make full posts here.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>As is often the case, not all of these are links; they’re copies of posts that I made over on my Mastodon account because they were too short to make full posts here.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Borromean_rings">Borromean rings</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105898319690639869">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), now a Good Article on Wikipedia. You can’t make the Borromean rings with geometric circles: as Tverberg observed, an inversion would make one of them a line. But then each of the other two circles would span an angle less than \(\pi\) as viewed from the line, leaving an unspanned direction along which the line could escape to infinity, contradicting the inseparability of the rings.</p>

    <p>The same proof shows that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brunnian_link">Brunnian links</a> cannot be made from four geometric circles. But the original proof that Borromean rings are not circular, by <a href="https://doi.org/10.4310/jdg/1214440725">Freedman and Skora</a> using 4d hyperbolic geometry, applies more generally to any Brunnian link no matter how many components it has.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://twitter.com/mathpuzzle/status/1366756737882218500">Squares can be divided into \(45^\circ\)–\(60^\circ\)–\(75^\circ\) triangles</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105909672693909508">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), as Ed Pegg posts on twitter. This is an interesting variant on something I looked at a long time ago, <a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/junkyard/acute-square/">triangulating the square to minimize the maximum angle</a>. But Pegg’s subdivision is not edge-to-edge. And the triangles on my page are not all similar. Do squares have edge-to-edge triangulations by similar acute triangles?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://blogs.sciencemag.org/editors-blog/2021/02/18/a-new-name-change-policy/"><em>Science</em> joins other publishers in making it easy for authors to change their names on past publications</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105915141700667095">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://www.metafilter.com/190813/Making-it-easier-for-published-scientists-to-change-their-names">via</a>). Transgender scientists made this change necessary but I think it benefits all of us. I’ve seen plenty of name changes in the literature for other reasons (marriage, divorce, escaping prejudice, …) and making it easier to find your old papers is generally a good thing.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Cairo in Denmark? (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105920191343711124">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).  This is a screenshot from Google Maps of Havnepromenade in Copenhagen, where it meets the end of Cort Adelers Gade. I’m sad to have missed this spot when I was in Copenhagen a couple years ago; it’s a nice example of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cairo_pentagonal_tiling">Cairo pentagonal tiling</a>.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Pentagonal street pavers on Havnepromenade at Cort Adelers Gade in Copenhagen, taken as a screenshot from Google Maps" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2021/Cairo-in-Copenhagen.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="80%"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>My latest illustration trick: make complex non-Boolean combinations of shapes by overlaying simple shapes, exploding the overlay into simple regions, and unioning the regions into the shapes I want (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105929236692195138">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Exploding and unioning are single clicks in Illustrator’s pathfinder tool. I used two levels of this technique to make this diagram of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brunnian_link">Brunnian link</a>: once to make the shape of a single component, and again to make the over-under relation between components.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Six-rubberband link" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2021/six-rubberband-link.svg"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mattwthomas.com/blog/induction-on-reals/">Real induction</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@mwt/105862096547025004">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). An induction principle for proving statements about all real numbers in intervals.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/new-print-49071226">Recamán Sequence</a> (<a href="https://mastodon.social/@joshmillard/105935104495594723">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Linocut art by Josh Millard in a style drawn from a <em>Numberphile</em> video.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematicians-inch-closer-to-matrix-multiplication-goal-20210323/"><em>Quanta</em> surveys recent developments in fast matrix multiplication</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105943717367375547">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), including <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.05846">a paper from last SODA by Josh Alman and Virginia Williams</a> improving the exponent from 2.3728639 to 2.3728596. Known barriers to the widely-expressed hope that the exponent can be reduced to 2 (see the SODA paper’s introduction) are, I think too specific to be convincing. On the other hand at this rate there’s still a long way from here to 2…</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://fredrikj.net/blog/2021/03/printing-algebraic-numbers/">Printing algebraic numbers</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105946537048589616">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26566090">via</a>). So your code can handle symbolic representations of exact algebraic numbers rather than just approximating everything as complex/float. How do you get those representations out to human users in a readable way? From ‪Fredrik Johansson‬, long-time developer of open symbolic algebra and exact real arithmetic software including SymPy and Calcium.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermat%27s_right_triangle_theorem">Fermat’s right triangle theorem</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105951398938627194">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), now a Good Article on Wikipedia. As Fibonacci observed and Fermat proved (as his only surviving proof), integer right triangles cannot have an area that is a perfect square. One corollary of this is the exponent-4 case of Fermat’s Last Theorem.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mastodon.social/@tomharris/105956972687307734">Tom Harris asks: What’s your favorite OEIS sequence?</a> Mine for this week at least is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moser%E2%80%93De_Bruijn_sequence">Moser–De Bruijn sequence</a>, OEIS <a href="https://oeis.org/A000695">A000695</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The most recent image of me on my site was from 2009 and getting pretty out-of-date. So I took a screenshot of myself as I look these days on Zoom (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105964230654539136">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). This is far from the first time I’ve let my hair go at least this long, but I’m still looking forward to a time when I will feel more comfortable getting a haircut.
It occurs to me that there has been a reversal: now, instead of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Almost_Cut_My_Hair">showing off rebelliousness</a>, I am visibly conforming to safety rules.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="David Eppstein, self-portrait, Zoom screenshot" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2021/zoom.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="80%"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/03/free-climbing-rock-climbers-open-data-project-threatened-bogus-copyright-claims">Fight over open data in rock climbing</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105971892719302236">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26609945">via</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathoverflow.net/q/387543/440">Weird probability distributions on dyadic rationals from a simple averaging process</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105977625108931414">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Start with the two-element multiset \(\{0,1\}\), repeatedly draw two-element samples (without replacement) from the multiset and include the average into the multiset. The result tends to cluster around some value, not the same value every time but itself drawn from a bimodal distribution, with the clustering sort of looking Cauchy but not quite. Interesting new MathOverflow question.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/slicing-hypercube.html">How many hyperplanes does it take to slice all the edges of an -dimensional hypercube</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105982764812531388">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>)? Two if you can skim the ends of the edges or include entire edges in hyperplanes but more to really slice them. The obvious answer of axis-parallel cuts can be improved to \(5n/6\), and Lance Fortnow reports that the newest lower bound is \(\Omega(n^{0.57})\), by Gal Yehuda and Amir Yehudayoff, improving <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.05536">their own new preprint</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/30/all-the-news-that-fits-we-print/">A list of current blogs on computer theory and related math</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105986862218758838">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), from <em>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</em>.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-31T17:54:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-31T17:54:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T00:59:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16416</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16416" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Determining a Slater Winner is Complete for Parallel Access to NP</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1617148800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lampis:Michael.html">Michael Lampis</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16416">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the complexity of deciding the winner of an election under the
Slater rule. In this setting we are given a tournament $T = (V, A)$, where the
vertices of V represent candidates and the direction of each arc indicates
which of the two endpoints is preferable for the majority of voters. The Slater
score of a vertex $v\in V$ is defined as the minimum number of arcs that need
to be reversed so that $T$ becomes acyclic and $v$ becomes the winner. We say
that $v$ is a Slater winner in $T$ if $v$ has minimum Slater score in $T$.
</p>
<p>Deciding if a vertex is a Slater winner in a tournament has long been known
to be NP-hard. However, the best known complexity upper bound for this problem
is the class $\Theta_2^p$, which corresponds to polynomial-time Turing machines
with parallel access to an NP oracle. In this paper we close this gap by
showing that the problem is $\Theta_2^p$-complete, and that this hardness
applies to instances constructible by aggregating the preferences of 7 voters.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-03-31T22:40:19Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-03-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16390</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16390" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A note about claw function with a small range</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1617148800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Ambainis:Andris.html">Andris Ambainis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Balodis:Kaspars.html">Kaspars Balodis</a>, Jānis Iraids <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16390">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the claw detection problem we are given two functions $f:D\rightarrow R$
and $g:D\rightarrow R$ ($|D|=n$, $|R|=k$), and we have to determine if there is
exist $x,y\in D$ such that $f(x)=g(y)$. We show that the quantum query
complexity of this problem is between $\Omega\left(n^{1/2}k^{1/6}\right)$ and
$O\left(n^{1/2+\varepsilon}k^{1/4}\right)$ when $2\leq k&lt;n$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-03-31T22:37:34Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-03-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16340</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16340" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Scheduling in the Secretary Model</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1617148800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Albers:Susanne.html">Susanne Albers</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Janke:Maximilian.html">Maximilian Janke</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16340">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper studies Makespan Minimization in the secretary model. Formally,
jobs, specified by their processing times, are presented in a uniformly random
order. An online algorithm has to assign each job permanently and irrevocably
to one of m parallel and identical machines such that the expected time it
takes to process them all, the makespan, is minimized. We give two
deterministic algorithms. First, a straightforward adaptation of the
semi-online strategy LightLoad provides a very simple algorithm retaining its
competitive ratio of 1.75. A new and sophisticated algorithm is
1.535-competitive. These competitive ratios are not only obtained in
expectation but, in fact, for all but a very tiny fraction of job orders.
Classically, online makespan minimization only considers the worst-case order.
Here, no competitive ratio below 1.885 for deterministic algorithms and 1.581
using randomization is possible. The best randomized algorithm so far is
1.916-competitive. Our results show that classical worst-case orders are quite
rare and pessimistic for many applications. They also demonstrate the power of
randomization when compared to much stronger deterministic reordering models.
We complement our results by providing first lower bounds. A competitive ratio
obtained on nearly all possible job orders must be at least 1.257. This implies
a lower bound of 1.043 for both deterministic and randomized algorithms in the
general model.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-03-31T22:41:33Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-03-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16251</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16251" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The randomized local computation complexity of the Lov\'asz local lemma</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1617148800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Brandt:Sebastian.html">Sebastian Brandt</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grunau:Christoph.html">Christoph Grunau</a>, Václav Rozhoň <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16251">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Local Computation Algorithm (LCA) model is a popular model in the field
of sublinear-time algorithms that measures the complexity of an algorithm by
the number of probes the algorithm makes in the neighborhood of one node to
determine that node's output.
</p>
<p>In this paper we show that the randomized LCA complexity of the Lov\'asz
Local Lemma (LLL) on constant degree graphs is $\Theta(\log n)$. The lower
bound follows by proving an $\Omega(\log n)$ lower bound for the Sinkless
Orientation problem introduced in [Brandt et al. STOC 2016]. This answers a
question of [Rosenbaum, Suomela PODC 2020].
</p>
<p>Additionally, we show that every randomized LCA algorithm for a locally
checkable problem with a probe complexity of $o(\sqrt{\log{n}})$ can be turned
into a deterministic LCA algorithm with a probe complexity of $O(\log^* n)$.
This improves exponentially upon the currently best known speed-up result from
$o(\log \log n)$ to $O(\log^* n)$ implied by the result of [Chang, Pettie FOCS
2017] in the LOCAL model.
</p>
<p>Finally, we show that for every fixed constant $c \geq 2$, the deterministic
VOLUME complexity of $c$-coloring a bounded degree tree is $\Theta(n)$, where
the VOLUME model is a close relative of the LCA model that was recently
introduced by [Rosenbaum, Suomela PODC 2020].
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-03-31T22:41:20Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-03-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16245</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16245" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linear time DBSCAN for sorted 1D data and laser range scan segmentation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1617148800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Meglicki:Bartosz.html">Bartosz Meglicki</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16245">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper introduces new algorithm for line extraction from laser range data
including methodology for efficient computation. The task is cast to series of
one dimensional problems in various spaces. A fast and simple specialization of
DBSCAN algorithm is proposed to solve one dimensional subproblems. Experiments
suggest that the method is suitable for real-time applications, handles noise
well and may be useful in practice.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-03-31T22:41:04Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-03-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16185</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16185" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximation algorithm for finding short synchronizing words in weighted automata</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1617148800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ruszil:Jakub.html">Jakub Ruszil</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16185">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper we are dealing with the issue of finding possibly short
synchronizing words in automata with weight assigned to each letter in the
alphabet $\Sigma$. First we discuss some complexity problems, and then we
present new approximation algorithm in four variations.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-03-31T22:40:58Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-03-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16182</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16182" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Synch: A framework for concurrent data-structures and benchmarks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1617148800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kallimanis:Nikolaos_D=.html">Nikolaos D. Kallimanis</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16182">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The recent advancements in multicore machines highlight the need to simplify
concurrent programming in order to leverage their computational power. One way
to achieve this is by designing efficient concurrent data structures (e.g.
stacks, queues, hash-tables, etc.) and synchronization techniques (e.g. locks,
combining techniques, etc.) that perform well in machines with large amounts of
cores. In contrast to ordinary, sequential data-structures, the concurrent
data-structures allow multiple threads to simultaneously access and/or modify
them.
</p>
<p>Synch is an open-source framework that not only provides some common
high-performant concurrent data-structures, but it also provides researchers
with the tools for designing and benchmarking high performant concurrent
data-structures. The Synch framework contains a substantial set of concurrent
data-structures such as queues, stacks, combining-objects, hash-tables, locks,
etc. and it provides a user-friendly runtime for developing and benchmarking
concurrent data-structures. Among other features, the provided runtime provides
functionality for creating threads easily (both POSIX and user-level threads),
tools for measuring performance, etc. Moreover, the provided concurrent
data-structures and the runtime are highly optimized for contemporary NUMA
multiprocessors such as AMD Epyc and Intel Xeon.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-03-31T22:41:09Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-03-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16071</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2103.16071" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximate Nearest-Neighbor Search for Line Segments</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1617148800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Abdelkader:Ahmed.html">Ahmed Abdelkader</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mount:David_M=.html">David M. Mount</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16071">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Approximate nearest-neighbor search is a fundamental algorithmic problem that
continues to inspire study due its essential role in numerous contexts. In
contrast to most prior work, which has focused on point sets, we consider
nearest-neighbor queries against a set of line segments in $\mathbb{R}^d$, for
constant dimension $d$. Given a set $S$ of $n$ disjoint line segments in
$\mathbb{R}^d$ and an error parameter $\varepsilon &gt; 0$, the objective is to
build a data structure such that for any query point $q$, it is possible to
return a line segment whose Euclidean distance from $q$ is at most
$(1+\varepsilon)$ times the distance from $q$ to its nearest line segment. We
present a data structure for this problem with storage $O((n^2/\varepsilon^{d})
\log (\Delta/\varepsilon))$ and query time $O(\log
(\max(n,\Delta)/\varepsilon))$, where $\Delta$ is the spread of the set of
segments $S$. Our approach is based on a covering of space by anisotropic
elements, which align themselves according to the orientations of nearby
segments.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-03-31T22:42:39Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-03-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=18443</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/30/all-the-news-that-fits-we-print/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>All The News That Fits We Print</title>
    <summary>The New York Times is a great newspaper: it is also No Fun—Molly Ivins The Gray Lady, as the New York Times is usually called, believes in her real slogan: All the news that’s fit to print. This slogan started about 115 years ago, and is on the masthead of the paper. Today I thought, […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>The New York Times is a great newspaper: it is also No Fun—Molly Ivins</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/30/all-the-news-that-fits-we-print/nyt/" rel="attachment wp-att-18445"><img alt="" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-18445" height="164" src="https://i2.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/nyt.png?resize=300%2C164&amp;ssl=1" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>
The Gray Lady, as the New York Times is usually called, believes in her real slogan: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> All the news that’s fit to print. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/30/all-the-news-that-fits-we-print/gl/" rel="attachment wp-att-18446"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-18446" height="158" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/gl.jpg?resize=300%2C158&amp;ssl=1" width="300"/><br/>
</a></p>
<p>
This slogan started about 115 years ago, and is on the <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-16918787">masthead</a> of the paper. </p>
<p>
Today I thought, for something different, we would supply just news.<br/>
<span id="more-18443"/></p>
<p>
That is links to blogs on computer theory and related math. Links that are current, that are interesting, and that are fit to refer to. All the blogs that <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\dots}"/></p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Links </h2><p/>
<p>Our rule is we include a link provided it is current. It must have a recent post—say at least this year. See <a href="http://cstheory-feed.org">all</a> for a complete list. But we decided to emphasis those that are up to date. </p>
<p>
<i>What’s new</i> by Terence Tao<br/>
It is <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com">here</a>. A recent article is “Boosting the van der Corput inequality using the tensor power trick”.</p>
<p>
<i>Gower’s Weblog</i> by Timothy Gowers<br/>
It is <a href="https://gowers.wordpress.com">here</a>. A recent article is “Leicester mathematics under threat again”.</p>
<p>
<i>Not Even Wrong</i> by Peter Woit<br/>
It is <a href="http://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/">here</a>. A recent article is “The Future of Fundamental Physics”. </p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/30/all-the-news-that-fits-we-print/pure/" rel="attachment wp-att-18449"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-18449" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/pure.png?w=400&amp;ssl=1"/></a>





</p><p>
<i>Shtetl-Optimized</i> by  Scott Aaronson<br/>
It is <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/">here</a>. A recent article is “QC ethics and hype: the call is coming from inside the house”. </p>
<p>
<i>Some Plane Truths</i> by Adam Sheffer<br/>
It is <a href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com">here</a>. A recent article is “The 2021 Polymath Jr Program”.</p>
<p>
<i>Computational Complexity</i> by Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch<br/>
It is <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org">here</a>. A recent article is “The key to my Taylor series problem: Buddy can you spare a penny, nickel, dime, or quarter”. </p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/30/all-the-news-that-fits-we-print/book-4/" rel="attachment wp-att-18455"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-18455" height="300" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/book-1.png?resize=189%2C300&amp;ssl=1" width="189"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
<i>11011110</i> by David Eppstein<br/>
It is <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/">here</a>. A recent article is “More mathematics books by women”.</p>
<p>
<i>Decentralized Thoughts</i> by Ittai Abraham, Ittay Eyal, Kartik Nayak, Ling Ren, Alin Tomescu, Avishay Yanai<br/>
It is <a href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io">here</a>. A recent article is “Living with Asynchrony: the Gather protocol”.</p>
<p>
<i>Foundation of Data Science </i> by dstheory<br/>
It is <a href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com">here</a>. A recent <a href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2021/03/28/thursday-april-1st-ingrid-daubechies-from-duke-university/">article</a> previews a talk this Thu. Apr, 1 (at 1pm ET) by Ingrid Daubechies on “Discovering low-dimensional manifolds in high-dimensional data sets.”</p>
<p>
<i>Machine Learning Research Blog</i> by Francis Bach<br/>
It is <a href="https://francisbach.com">here</a>. A recent article “Going beyond least-squares – II : Self-concordant analysis for logistic regression”.</p>
<p>
<i>Combinatorics and more</i> by Gil Kalai<br/>
It is <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com">here</a>. A recent article “What is mathematics (or at least, how it feels)”. </p>
<p>
<i>Kamathematics</i> by Gautam Kamath<br/>
It is <a href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com">here</a>. A recent article “Learning Theory Alliance and Mentoring Workshop”.</p>
<p>
<i>Process Algebra Diary</i> by Luca Aceto<br/>
It is <a href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com">here</a>. A recent article “Article by Sergey Kitaev and Anthony Mendes in Jeff Remmel’s memory”.</p>
<p>
<i>in Theory</i> by Luca Trevisan<br/>
It is <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com">here</a>. A recent article is an announcement for accepted papers <a href="http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2021/accepted-papers.html">STOC 2021</a>. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “Marge, I agree with you — in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory.” — Homer Simpson. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
<i>Algorithms, Nature, and Society</i> by Nisheeth Vishnoi<br/>
It is <a href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com">here</a>. A recent article is an announcement for <a href="https://www.cs.yale.edu/homes/vishnoi/focs-2021-cfp.html">FOCS 2022</a>.</p>
<p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>Did we leave any out? Did we include any we should have <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\dots}"/></p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-30T18:00:47Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-30T18:00:47Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="blogs"/>
    <category term="links"/>
    <category term="list"/>
    <category term="times"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8037</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2021/03/29/new-summer-school-in-tcs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>New summer school in TCS</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Shuchi Chawla, Madhur Tulsiani, and I are organizing a new summer school aimed at exposing undergraduate students to research directions in theoretical computer science and its applications. The school will take place from May 31 till June 4, 2021. This first iteration will be online, but we hope it will become a recurring and lasting event.  … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2021/03/29/new-summer-school-in-tcs/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">New summer school in TCS</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Shuchi Chawla, Madhur Tulsiani, and I are organizing <a href="https://boazbk.github.io/tcs-summerschool/">a new summer school </a>aimed at exposing undergraduate students to research directions in theoretical computer science and its applications. The school will take place from <strong>May 31 till June 4, 2021</strong>. This first iteration will be online, but we hope it will become a recurring and lasting event.  See <a href="https://boazbk.github.io/tcs-summerschool/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://boazbk.github.io/tcs-summerschool/</a> for the webpage. We already have 5 exciting instructors signed up – <a href="http://www.cse.psu.edu/~azb1015/">Antonio Blanca</a>, <a href="https://www.ashiawilson.com/">Ashia Wlson</a>, <a href="https://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~minilek/">Jelani Nelson</a>, <a href="https://immorlica.com/">Nicole Immorlica</a>, and <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/yael/">Yael Kalai</a>. We plan to have both technical tutorials / mini-courses and networking/social events.<br/><br/>This course is aimed at undergraduate students, and in particular students from groups that are currently under-represented in our field. If you are a faculty member in a university, we would be grateful if you can spread the announcement below to both your colleagues, and any mailing lists for undergraduate students, and in particular chapters of affinity groups such as the National Society of Black Engineers, Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers, National Center for Women &amp; Information Technology, etc.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>The committee for advancement of theoretical computer science (<a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/catcs/">CATCS</a>) is organizing an online  summer course that will take place on May 31 till June 4, 2021. New horizons in theoretical computer science is a week-long online summer school which will expose undergraduates to exciting research areas in the area of theoretical computer science and its applications. The school will contain several mini-courses from top researchers in the field. The course is free of charge,and we welcome applications from undergraduates majoring in computer science or related fields. We particularly encourage applications from students that are members of groups that are currently under-represented in theoretical computer science. </p>



<p>The course is intended for currently enrolled undergraduate students that are majoring in computer science or related fields. Students will be expected to be familiar with the material typically taught in introductory algorithms and discrete mathematics / mathematics for computer science courses. If you are unsure if you are prepared for the course, please write to us at <a href="mailto:summer-school-admin@boazbarak.org" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">summer-school-admin@boazbarak.org</a><br/><br/>To apply for the course, please visit <a href="https://boazbk.github.io/tcs-summerschool/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://boazbk.github.io/tcs-summerschool/</a> and fill in the application form by <strong>April 15, 2021</strong>. <br/><br/><strong>Course organizers:</strong> Boaz Barak (Harvard), Shuchi Chawla (UT Austin), Madhur Tulsiani (TTI-Chicago)</p>



<p><strong>Current list of confirmed instructors:</strong>  Antonio Blanca (Penn State University), Ashia Wilson (MIT), Jelani Nelson (UC Berkeley), Nicole Immorlica (Microsoft Research), Yael Kalai (Microsoft research).</p>



<p>Please email  <a href="mailto:summer-school-admin@boazbarak.org" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">summer-school-admin@boazbarak.org</a> with any questions.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-29T14:57:41Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-29T14:57:41Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7850404914913698515</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7850404914913698515/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/slicing-hypercube.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7850404914913698515" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7850404914913698515" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/slicing-hypercube.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Slicing the Hypercube</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Here's a neat result I heard about at <a href="https://www.dagstuhl.de/en/program/calendar/semhp/?semnr=21121">virtual Dagstuhl</a> last week, a new lower bound on the number of hyperplanes that cuts all the edges of a hypercube.</p><p>A n-dimensional hypercube has 2<sup>n</sup> vertices corresponding to the binary strings of length n. Edges are between two vertices that differ in exactly one bit, for a total of (n/2) 2<sup>n</sup> edges. Hypercubes played a <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/07/degree-and-sensitivity.html">large role</a> in Hao Huang's recent proof of the sensitivity conjecture. </p><p>A hyperplane is just a linear inequality in x<sub>1</sub>,…,x<sub>n</sub> the bits of the string corresponding to a vertex. An edge is cut if the inequality is true for one vertex and false for the other.</p><p>With n hyperplanes you can cut all the edges in two very different ways. </p><p/><ul style="text-align: left;"><li>The hyperplanes x<sub>i</sub> &gt; 0 for each i. These are n orthogonal hyperplanes.</li><li>The hyperplanes x<sub>1</sub>+…+x<sub>n</sub> &gt; i for each i from 0 to n-1. These are n parallel hyperplanes.</li></ul><div>Do you need n hyperplanes to cut all the edges? Mike Paterson found 5 explicit hyperplanes that cuts all the edges of a 6-dimensional hypercube (see <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511662089.009">survey</a> by Mike Saks). Scaling that up means you need 5n/6 hyperplanes to cut an n-dimensional hypercube. That remains the best known upper bound.</div><div><br/></div><div>For the lower bound, in 1971 Patrick O'Neil <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0012-365X(71)90025-2">showed</a> that any hyperplane can cut at most O(n<sup>0.5</sup>) fraction of the edges (sharp by the hyperplane x<sub>1</sub>+…+x<sub>n</sub> &gt; n/2). Thus you need at least O(n<sup>0.5</sup>) hyperplanes which for 50 years was the best known bound.</div><div><br/></div><div>Gil Yehuda and Amir Yehudayoff have <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.05536">given a new lower bound</a> of O(n<sup>0.57</sup>). The paper gives a O(n<sup>0.51</sup>) bound but Yehudayoff said in a talk last week the bound has been improved.</div><div><br/></div><div>Yehudayoff didn't go into much details in his 20 minute talk but the proofs uses geometry, probability and antichains. </div><div><br/></div><div>The result has some applications to complexity, namely you need at least n<sup>1.57</sup> wires in a depth-two threshold circuit for parity. But the main fun is the question itself, that we finally made progress and there is still a long way to go.</div><p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-29T12:47:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-29T12:47:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T13:22:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://dstheory.wordpress.com/?p=91</id>
    <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2021/03/28/thursday-april-1st-ingrid-daubechies-from-duke-university/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Thursday April 1st — Ingrid Daubechies  from Duke University</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The next Foundations of Data Science virtual talk will take place on Thursday, April 1st at 10:00 AM Pacific Time (13:00 Eastern Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC).  Ingrid Daubechies from Duke Univeristy will speak about “Discovering low-dimensional manifolds in high-dimensional data sets.” Please register here to join the virtual talk. Abstract: This talk reviews<a class="more-link" href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2021/03/28/thursday-april-1st-ingrid-daubechies-from-duke-university/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">"Thursday April 1st — Ingrid Daubechies  from Duke University"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="has-text-align-justify">The next <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory/home" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Foundations of Data Science</a> virtual talk will take place on <strong>Thursday, April 1</strong>st at <strong>10:00 AM Pacific Time</strong> (13:00 Eastern Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC).  <strong><a href="https://ece.duke.edu/faculty/ingrid-daubechies" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Ingrid Daubechies</a></strong> from <strong>Duke Univeristy</strong> will speak about “Discovering low-dimensional manifolds in high-dimensional data sets.”</p>



<p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Please register here to join the virtual talk.</a></p>



<p class="has-text-align-justify"><strong>Abstract</strong>: This talk reviews diffusion methods to identify low-dimensional manifolds underlying high-dimensional datasets, and illustrates that by pinpointing additional mathematical structure, improved results can be obtained. Much of the talk draws on a case study from a collaboration with biological morphologists, who compare different phenotypical structures to study relationships of living or extinct animals with their surroundings and each other. This is typically done from carefully defined anatomical correspondence points (landmarks) on e.g. bones; such landmarking draws on highly specialized knowledge. To make possible more extensive use of large (and growing) databases, algorithms are required for automatic morphological correspondence maps, without any preliminary marking of special features or landmarks by the user.</p>



<p>The series is supported by the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1934846&amp;HistoricalAwards=false">NSF HDR TRIPODS Grant 1934846</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-28T03:16:12Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-28T03:16:12Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>dstheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://dstheory.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Foundation of Data Science – Virtual Talk Series</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:21:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/048</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/048" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-048 |  Better Pseudodistributions and Derandomization for Space-Bounded Computation | 

	William Hoza</title>
    <summary>Three decades ago, Nisan constructed an explicit pseudorandom generator (PRG) that fools width-$n$ length-$n$ read-once branching programs (ROBPs) with error $\varepsilon$ and seed length $O(\log^2 n + \log n \cdot \log(1/\varepsilon))$ (Combinatorica 1992). Nisan's generator remains the best explicit PRG known for this important model of computation. However, a recent line of work starting with Braverman, Cohen, and Garg (Braverman, Cohen, and Garg SICOMP 2020; Chattopadhyay and Liao CCC 2020; Cohen, Doron, Renard, Sberlo, and Ta-Shma ECCC 2021; Pyne and Vadhan ECCC 2021) has shown how to construct *weighted* pseudorandom generators (WPRGs, aka pseudorandom pseudodistribution generators) with better seed lengths than Nisan's generator when the error parameter $\varepsilon$ is small.
		
In this work, we present an explicit WPRG for width-$n$ length-$n$ ROBPs with seed length $O(\log^2 n + \log(1/\varepsilon))$. Our seed length eliminates $\log \log$ factors from prior constructions, and our generator completes this line of research in the sense that further improvements would require beating Nisan's generator in the standard constant-error regime. Our technique is a variation of a recently-discovered reduction that converts moderate-error PRGs into low-error WPRGs (Cohen et al. ECCC 2021; Pyne and Vadhan ECCC 2021). Our version of the reduction uses averaging samplers.
		
We also point out that as a consequence of the recent work on WPRGs, any randomized space-$S$ decision algorithm can be simulated deterministically in space $O(S^{3/2} / \sqrt{\log S})$. This is a slight improvement over Saks and Zhou's celebrated $O(S^{3/2})$ bound (JCSS 1999). For this application, our improved WPRG is not necessary.</summary>
    <updated>2021-03-27T08:27:49Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-27T08:27:49Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=18424</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/26/congrats-avi-and-laci-on-the-abel-prize/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Congrats Avi and Laci on the Abel Prize</title>
    <summary>The joy of knowing, understanding, and creating is common to all the sciences.—Vera Sós. Dorit Aharonov is a researcher in quantum computation. She was a Ph.D. student of Michael Ben-Or and Avi Wigderson. Her 1999 thesis, entitled “Noisy Quantum Computation,” included her role with Ben-Or as one of several superposed groups who discovered the quantum […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>The joy of knowing, understanding, and creating is common to all the sciences.—Vera Sós.</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/da.png?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-18426" height="155" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/da.png?resize=150%2C155&amp;ssl=1" width="150"/></a></p>
<p>
Dorit Aharonov is a researcher in quantum computation. She was a Ph.D. student of Michael Ben-Or and Avi Wigderson. Her 1999 <a href="https://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~doria/thesis.ps">thesis</a>, entitled “Noisy Quantum Computation,” included her role with Ben-Or as one of several superposed groups who discovered the quantum fault tolerance threshold <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_threshold_theorem">theorem</a>.</p>
<p>
Today Ken and I wish to send our congratulations to Avi and Laci—László Lovász—on winning the 2021 <a href="https://www.abelprize.no">Abel Prize</a>.</p>
<p>
The prize citation is: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> For their foundational contributions to theoretical computer science and discrete mathematics, and their leading role in shaping them into central fields of modern mathematics. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><h2> Genealogy </h2><p/>
<p>
You might wonder why we are talking about Aharonov? She was a student of Avi and he was a student of mine—see <a href="https://www.mathgenealogy.org/id.php?id=82100">this</a> for more details. I am proud of Avi for his terrific results and also for his great students. I guess Aharonov is a grand-student of mine. </p>
<p>
Lovász and Ken’s advisor, Dominic Welsh of Oxford, partnered with Dominic’s student Magnus Bordewich and Michael Freedman of Microsoft on a 2005 <a href="http://community.dur.ac.uk/m.j.r.bordewich/papers/Bordewich2005-c.pdf">paper</a> titled, “Approximate counting and quantum computation.” The paper translates criteria for approximating the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jones_polynomial">Jones polynomial</a> into simulations of quantum circuits. It references how topological quantum field theory (TQFT) implicitly embodies a quantum algorithm that meets the criteria, hence showing that the Jones approximation problem is complete for <img alt="{\mathsf{BQP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BBQP%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\mathsf{BQP}}"/> in a suitable promise-problem sense. </p>
<p>
The genealogy of the Jones polynomial is that it was discovered by Vaughan Jones. Aharonov, with Jones and his student Zeph Landau, wrote a 2009 <a href="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007/s00453-008-9168-0.pdf">paper</a> that makes the quantum algorithm for approximating the Jones polynomial explicit. To quote the converse of a statement in their abstract, removing the dependence on TQFT makes the algorithm “accessible to computer scientists.”</p>
<p>
Aharonov’s work thus represents the mixing of elements of classical mathematics and computing theory (including quantum, i.e. non-classical, computing) that this year’s Abel Prize recognizes. <em>Mixing</em> is indeed the word, since results on the mixing rates of Markov chains by Lovász and many others undergird some of this work. This is true even more directly of a notable <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/quant-ph/0012090.pdf">paper</a> by her with Andris Ambainis, Julia Kempe, and Umesh Vazirani on quantum walks. </p>
<p/><h2> More Quantum </h2><p/>
<p>
When we hosted the 2012 <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2012/01/30/perpetual-motion-of-the-21st-century/">debate</a> between Gil Kalai and Aram Harrow on the feasibility of large-scale quantum computing, Gil led off with the following photo of the physicist Robert Alicki, Ben-Or, Aharonov, and himself, which was taken in Jerusalem in 2005.</p>
<p/><p>
<a href="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/BAAK.png?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-18428" height="415" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/BAAK.png?resize=557%2C415&amp;ssl=1" width="557"/></a></p>
<p/><p>
Aharonov wrote an influential long <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/quant-ph/9812037.pdf">survey</a> in 1998 titled “Quantum Computation,” which grew out of her thesis and is sometimes <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/2864868_Noisy_Quantum_Computation">confused</a> with it. Ken and I owe a small debt to diagrams she used in the survey, for which she in turn alluded to Richard Feynman’s path integrals and their visualizations: </p>
<p/><p>
<a href="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/AharonovSnip.png?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-18429" height="231" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/AharonovSnip.png?resize=487%2C231&amp;ssl=1" width="487"/></a></p>
<p/><p>
We expanded on this kind of diagram in our textbook on quantum computing with MIT Press, whose <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/introduction-quantum-algorithms-linear-algebra-second-edition">second edition</a> is scheduled to appear next month. </p>
<p/><h2> Abel Prize and Lower Bounds </h2><p/>
<p>
Whereas the Fields Medals are awarded only every four years, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abel_Prize">Abel Prize</a> is annual. It commemorates the Norwegian mathematician Niels Abel. Although it has been awarded only since 2003, it was originally proposed in 1899 expressly as a counterpart to the Nobel Prizes—and fell through only because of the 1905 separation of Sweden and Norway. We most recently <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/03/21/the-shortest-path-to-the-abel-prize/">covered</a> the 2019 prize going to Karen Uhlenbeck.</p>
<p>
Abel of course is the mathematician who gave his name to abelian groups and much <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_things_named_after_Niels_Henrik_Abel">else</a>. About his short life of twenty-seven years, Charles Hermite said: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Abel has left mathematicians enough to keep them busy for five hundred years. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
What we note is that Abel’s most famous result is a lower bound type result. He showed the impossibility of solving the general quintic equation in radicals. Finding clever identities, clever inequities, clever algorithms is hard. But not as hard as showing that something cannot be done. </p>
<p>
Abel’s result is perhaps like proving today, in the 21st century, a lower bound on the complexity of some concrete problem. Some of Avi’s and also Laci’s best work has been directed toward this quest: Prove some non-trivial lower bound. Avi has worked on numerous approaches, including the <a href="https://www.math.ias.edu/avi/node/817">fusion method</a> in 1993. Although its lack of breakthroughs has caused jibes about “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold_fusion">cold fusion</a>,” Avi noted the following in a recent <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/talks/tbd-9">talk</a> at the Simons Institute: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> I will review (and hope to revive) a collection of old works, which suggest obtaining circuit lower bounds by “fusing” many correct computations (of a circuit too small) into an incorrect computation.</em></p><em>
</em><p><em>
In a couple of models, this viewpoint led to (slight) superlinear lower bounds, which nonetheless have not been improved upon for 25 years. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
We hope that the Abel Prize award will promote efforts to achieve not-so-slightly super-linear lower bounds on circuit size, running time, algebraic size, quantum effort, anything like that…</p>
<p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>
We also tip our hat to others who have reported on the Abel Prize, including some of our fellow bloggers: Gil Kalai <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/03/17/cheerful-news-in-difficult-times-the-abel-prize-is-awarded-to-laszlo-lovasz-and-avi-wigderson/">here</a>, Scott Aaronson <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5388">here</a>, Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/i-read-news-today-oh-boy.html">here</a>, plus Kevin Hartnett for <i>Quanta</i> <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/avi-wigderson-and-laszlo-lovasz-win-abel-prize-20210317/">here</a>.</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-26T16:22:55Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-26T16:22:55Z</published>
    <category term="algorithms"/>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Teaching"/>
    <category term="Abel Prize"/>
    <category term="approximation"/>
    <category term="Avi Wigderson"/>
    <category term="Dorit Aharonov"/>
    <category term="Laszlo Lovasz"/>
    <category term="Michael Ben-Or"/>
    <category term="Niels Abel"/>
    <category term="Prize"/>
    <category term="quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2021-03-26-living-with-asynchrony-the-gather-protocol/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2021-03-26-living-with-asynchrony-the-gather-protocol/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Living with Asynchrony: the Gather protocol</title>
    <summary>A very useful tool in Asynchronus distributed computing is Reliable Broadcast, or simply called Broadcast. It allows a leader to send a message, knowing that all parties will eventually receive the same message, even if a malicious adversary control $f$ parties and $f&lt;n/3$. Broadcast is deterministic and takes just a...</summary>
    <updated>2021-03-26T10:54:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-26T10:54:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2021-03-31T22:46:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/047</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/047" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-047 |  Random restrictions and PRGs for PTFs in Gaussian Space | 

	Zander Kelley, 

	Raghu Meka</title>
    <summary>A polynomial threshold function (PTF) $f:\mathbb{R}^n \rightarrow \mathbb{R}$ is a function of the form $f(x) = sign(p(x))$ where $p$ is a polynomial of degree at most $d$. PTFs are a classical and well-studied complexity class with applications across complexity theory, learning theory, approximation theory, quantum complexity and more. We address the question of designing pseudorandom generators (PRG) for polynomial threshold functions (PTFs) in the gaussian space: design a PRG that takes a seed of few bits of randomness and outputs a $n$-dimensional vector whose distribution is indistinguishable from a standard multivariate gaussian by a degree $d$ PTF. 
     
     Our main result is a PRG that takes a seed of $d^{O(1)}\log ( n / \varepsilon)\log(1/\varepsilon)/\varepsilon^2$ random bits with output that cannot be distinguished from $n$-dimensional gaussian distribution with advantage better than $\varepsilon$ by degree $d$ PTFs. The best previous generator due to O'Donnell, Servedio, and Tan (STOC'20) had a quasi-polynomial dependence (i.e.,  seedlength of $d^{O(\log d)}$) in the degree $d$. Along the way we prove a few nearly-tight  structural properties of restrictions of PTFs that may be of independent interest.</summary>
    <updated>2021-03-26T10:15:24Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-26T10:15:24Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6040846843118046934</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6040846843118046934/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/the-key-to-my-taylor-series-problem.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6040846843118046934" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6040846843118046934" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/the-key-to-my-taylor-series-problem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The key to my Taylor series problem: Buddy can you spare a penny, nickel, dime, or quarter</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> In my last blog post I posed a question about finding the coeff of x^100 in a particular Taylor Series. The question and answer are given  <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/users/gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/taylorcoins.pdf">here</a>:</p><p><br/></p><p>The key to the problem was to recognize that it was asking how many ways you can make change of a dollar using pennies, nickels, dimes, and quarters. This can be done by hand (its 242). </p><p>1) Someone who I gave the problem to solved it by available software, but when he saw the answer was 242 he realized how to do it via making change.</p><p><br/></p><p>2) How hard would this problem me to do completely by hand- say as a Putnam Problem? Its hard for me to say since I started with the trick and then found the problem. </p><p><br/></p><p>3) Is this a well known trick? </p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-26T02:58:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-26T02:58:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T13:22:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://toc4fairness.org/?p=1551</id>
    <link href="https://toc4fairness.org/videos-up/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Videos Up</title>
    <summary>With a bit of a delay, we are starting to upload the videos of our seminar’s talks. The Inaugural Meeting of our seminar was devoted to a wonderful talk by ...</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>With a bit of a delay, we are starting to upload the videos of our seminar’s talks. The <a href="https://toc4fairness.org/inaugural-meeting-toc4fairness-seminar-annette-zimmermann/">Inaugural Meeting</a> of our seminar was devoted to a wonderful talk by Dr. <a href="https://www.annette-zimmermann.com/">Annette Zimmermann</a>.  I highly recommend watching <a href="https://toc4fairness.org/inaugural-meeting-toc4fairness-seminar-annette-zimmermann-2/">the video</a>, and following up with some additional reading (some pointers below).</p>



<p>I won’t try to summarize the talk because I doubt that I can do it justice, but one of the themes (which I fully support) is that it is not enough to consider “fair” implementations of specific tasks. Instead, we (also) want to explore the right task to implement and if it is appropriate to implement any algorithmic task in any specific context. </p>



<p>As a side note, I loved Annette’s statement on ethics,  “if we can choose, we’re on the hook.” For me, it beautifully complements the paradigm that “ought implies can.” In other words, ethical imperatives only exist when the expected action is possible but every choice has ethical implications.   </p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>Some resources for additional reading.</p>



<p><strong>Resources on exploitation</strong></p>



<p><strong>Introductory / very accessible for an interdisciplinary audience</strong></p>



<p>Nicholas Vrousalis, “Exploitation: A Primer,” <em>Philosophy Compass</em> 13, no. 2 (2018).</p>



<p><strong>Background</strong></p>



<p>G.A. Cohen, “The Labor Theory of Value and the Concept of Exploitation,” <em>Philosophy and Public Affairs</em> 8, no. 4 (1979): 338–360.</p>



<p>Joel Feinberg, <em>Harmless Wrongdoing</em>, Oxford: Oxford University Press (1988).`</p>



<p>Robert E. Goodin, “Exploiting a Situation and Exploiting a Person,” in Andrew Reeve (ed.), <em>Modern Theories of Exploitation</em>, London: Sage (1987), 166–200.</p>



<p>Ruth Sample, <em>Exploitation, What It Is and Why it is Wrong</em>, Lanham, MD: Rowman and Littlefield (2003).</p>



<p>Nicholas Vrousalis, “Exploitation, Vulnerability, and Social Domination,” <em>Philosophy and Public Affairs</em>, 41, no. 2 (2013): 131–157.</p>



<p>Alan Wertheimer, <em>Exploitation</em>, Princeton: Princeton University Press (1996).</p>



<p>Iris Marion Young, “Five Faces of Oppression,” in Thomas Wartenberg (ed.), <em>Rethinking Power</em>, Albany, NY: SUNY Press (1992).</p>



<p><strong>Resource on the political philosophy of AI (for a general audience)</strong></p>



<p>Annette Zimmermann, Elena Di Rosa, Hochan Kim, “<a href="http://bostonreview.net/science-nature-politics/annette-zimmermann-elena-di-rosa-hochan-kim-technology-cant-fix-algorithmic">Technology Can’t Fix Algorithmic Injustice</a>, <em>Boston Review</em> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-25T22:50:07Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-25T22:50:07Z</published>
    <category term="Blog"/>
    <author>
      <name>Omer Reingold</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://toc4fairness.org</id>
      <logo>https://i1.wp.com/toc4fairness.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/cropped-favicon.png?fit=32%2C32&amp;ssl=1</logo>
      <link href="https://toc4fairness.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://toc4fairness.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a simons collaboration project</subtitle>
      <title>TOC for Fairness</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:22:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>http://offconvex.github.io/2021/03/25/beyondNTK/</id>
    <link href="http://offconvex.github.io/2021/03/25/beyondNTK/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>When are Neural Networks more powerful than Neural Tangent Kernels?</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The empirical success of deep learning has posed significant challenges to machine learning theory: Why can we efficiently train neural networks with gradient descent despite its highly non-convex optimization landscape? Why do over-parametrized networks generalize well? The recently proposed Neural Tangent Kernel (NTK) theory offers a powerful framework for understanding these, but yet still comes with its limitations.</p>

<p>In this blog post, we explore how to analyze wide neural networks beyond the NTK theory, based on our recent <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01619">Beyond Linearization paper</a> and follow-up <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.13436">paper on understanding hierarchical learning</a>. (This blog post is also cross-posted at the <a href="https://blog.einstein.ai/beyond-ntk/">Salesforce Research blog</a>.)</p>

<h3 id="neural-tangent-kernels">Neural Tangent Kernels</h3>
<p>The Neural Tangent Kernel (NTK) is a recently proposed theoretical framework for establishing provable convergence and generalization guarantees for wide (over-parametrized) neural networks <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1806.07572">(Jacot et al. 2018)</a>. Roughly speaking, the NTK theory shows that</p>

<ul>
  <li>A sufficiently wide neural network trains like a linearized model governed by the derivative of the network with respect to its parameters.</li>
  <li>At the infinite-width limit, this linearized model becomes a kernel predictor with the Neural Tangent Kernel (the NTK).</li>
</ul>

<p>Consequently, a wide neural network trained with small learning rate converges to 0 training loss and generalize as well as the infinite-width kernel predictor. For a detailed introduction to the NTK, please refer to the earlier <a href="http://www.offconvex.org/2019/10/03/NTK/">blog post</a> by Wei and Simon.</p>

<h3 id="does-ntk-fully-explain-the-success-of-neural-networks">Does NTK fully explain the success of neural networks?</h3>
<p>Although the NTK yields powerful theoretical results, it turns out that real-world deep learning <em>do not operate in the NTK regime</em>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Empirically, infinite-width NTK kernel predictors perform slightly worse (though competitive) than fully trained neural networks on benchmark tasks such as CIFAR-10 <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.11955">(Arora et al. 2019b)</a>. For finite width networks in practice, this gap is even more profound, as we see in Figure 1: The linearized network is a rather poor approximation of the fully trained network at practical optimization setups such as large initial learning rate <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.04010">(Bai et al. 2020)</a>.</li>
  <li>Theoretically, the NTK has poor <em>sample complexity for learning certain simple functions</em>. Though the NTK is a universal kernel that can interpolate any finite, non-degenerate training dataset <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.02054">(Du et al. 2018</a><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1811.03804">, 2019)</a>, the test error of this kernel predictor scales with the RKHS norm of the ground truth function. For certain non-smooth but simple functions such as a single ReLU, this norm can be exponentially large in the feature dimension <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.00687">(Yehudai &amp; Shamir 2019)</a>. Consequently, NTK analyses yield poor sample complexity upper bounds for learning such functions, whereas empirically neural nets only require a mild sample size <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1410.1141">(Livni et al. 2014)</a>.</li>
</ul>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<img src="http://www.offconvex.org/assets/taylor-plot.png" style="width: 700px;"/>
<br/>
<i><b>Figure 1.</b>
Linearized model does not closely approximate the training trajectory of neural networks with practical optimization setups, whereas higher order Taylor models offer a substantially better approximation.
</i>
<br/>
<br/>
</div>

<p>These gaps urge us to ask the following</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Question</strong>: How can we theoretically study neural networks beyond the NTK regime? Can we prove that neural networks outperform the NTK on certain learning tasks?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The key technical question here is to mathematically understand neural networks operating <em>outside of the NTK regime</em>.</p>

<h2 id="higher-order-taylor-expansion">Higher-order Taylor expansion</h2>
<p>Our main tool for going beyond the NTK is the <em>Taylor expansion</em>. Consider a two-layer neural network with $m$ neurons, where we only train the “bottom” nonlinear layer $W$:</p>

\[f_{W_0 + W}(x) = \frac{1}{\sqrt{m}} \sum_{r=1}^m a_r \sigma( (w_{0,r} + w_r)^\top x).\]

<p>(Here, $W_0+W$ is an $m\times d$ weight matrix, where $W_0$ denotes the random initialization and $W$ denotes the trainable “movement” matrix initialized at zero). For small enough $W$, we can perform a Taylor expansion of the network around $W_0$ and get</p>

\[f_{W_0+W}(x) = \frac{1}{\sqrt{m}} \sum_{r=1}^m a_r \sigma(w_{0,r}^\top x) + \sum_{k=1}^\infty \frac{1}{\sqrt{m}} \sum_{r=1}^m a_r \frac{\sigma^{(k)} (w_{0,r}^\top x)}{k!} (w_r^\top x)^k\]

<p>Let us denote the $k$-th order term as $ f^{(k)}_{W_0, W}$, and rewrite this as</p>

\[f_{W_0+W}(x) = f^{(0)}_{W_0}(x) + \sum_{k=1}^\infty f^{(k)}_{W_0, W}(x).\]

<p>Above, term $f^{(k)}$ is a $k$-th order polynomial of the trainable parameter $W$. For the moment assume that $f^{(0)}(x)=0$ (this can be achieved via techniques such as the symmetric initialization).</p>

<p>The key insight of the NTK theory can be described as the following <strong>linearized approximation</strong> property</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>For small enough $W$, the neural network $f_{W_0,W}$ is closely approximated by the linear model $f^{(1)}$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Towards moving beyond the linearized approximation, in our <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01619">Beyond Linearization paper</a>, we start by asking</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Why just $f^{(1)}$? Can we also utilize the higher-order term in the Taylor series such as $f^{(2)}$?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>At first sight, this seems rather unlikely, as in Taylor expansions we always expect the linear term $f^{(1)}$ to dominate the whole expansion and have a larger magnitude than $f^{(2)}$ (and subsequent terms).</p>

<h3 id="killing-the-ntk-term-by-randomized-coupling">“Killing” the NTK term by randomized coupling</h3>
<p>We bring forward the idea of <em>randomization</em>, which helps us escape the “domination” of $f^{(1)}$ and couple neural networks with their quadratic Taylor expansion term $f^{(2)}$. This idea appeared first in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1811.04918">Allen-Zhu et al. (2018)</a> for analyzing three-layer networks, and as we will show also applies to two-layer networks in a perhaps more intuitive fashion.</p>

<p>Let us now assign each weight movement $w_r$ with a <em>random sign</em> $s_r\in\{\pm 1\}$, and consider the randomized weights $\{s_rw_r\}$. The random signs satisfy the following basic properties:</p>

\[E[s_r]=0 \quad {\rm and} \quad s_r^2 \equiv 1.\]

<p>Therefore, let $SW\in\mathbb{R}^{m\times d}$ denote the randomized weight matrix, we can compare the first and second order terms in the Taylor expansion at $SW$:</p>

\[E_{S} \left[f^{(1)}_{W_0, SW}(x)\right] = E_{S} \left[ \frac{1}{\sqrt{m}}\sum_{r\le m} a_r \sigma'(w_{0,r}^\top x) (s_rw_r^\top x) \right] = 0,\]

<p>whereas</p>

\[f^{(2)}_{W_0, SW}(x) = \frac{1}{\sqrt{m}}\sum_{r\le m} a_r \frac{\sigma^{(2)}(w_{0,r}^\top x)}{2} (s_rw_r^\top x)^2 = \frac{1}{\sqrt{m}}\sum_{r\le m} a_r \frac{\sigma^{(2)}(w_{0,r}^\top x)}{2} (w_r^\top x)^2 = f^{(2)}_{W_0, W}(x).\]

<p>Observe that the sign randomization keeps the quadratic term $f^{(2)}$ unchanged, but “kills” the linear term $f^{(1)}$ in expectation!</p>

<p>If we train such a randomized network with freshly sampled signs $S$ at each iteration, the linear term $f^{(1)}$ will keep oscillating around zero and does not have any power in fitting the data, whereas the quadratic term is not affected at all and thus becomes the leading force for fitting the data. (The keen reader may notice that this randomization is similar to Dropout, with the key difference being that we randomize the weight <em>movement</em> matrix, whereas vanilla Dropout randomizes the weight matrix itself.)</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<img src="http://www.offconvex.org/assets/beyond-ntk.png" style="width: 700px;"/>
<br/>
<i><b>Figure 2.</b>
The NTK regime operates in the "NTK ball" where the network is approximately equal to the linear term. The quadratic regime operates in a larger ball where the network is approximately equal to the sum of first two terms, but the linear term dominates and can blow up at large width. Our randomized coupling technique resolves this by introducing the random sign matrix that in expectation "kills" the linear term but always preserves the quadratic term.
</i>
<br/>
<br/>
</div>

<p>Our first result shows that networks with sign randomization can still be efficiently optimized, despite its now non-convex optimization landscape:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem</strong>: Any escaping-saddle algorithm (e.g. noisy SGD) on the regularized loss function $E_S[L(W_0+SW)]+R(W)$, with freshly sampled sign $S=S_t$ per iteration, can find the global minimum in polynomial time.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The proof builds on the quadratic approximation $E_S[f]\approx f^{(2)}$ and recent understandings on neural networks with quadratic activation, e.g. <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1707.04926">Soltanolkotabi et al. (2017)</a> &amp; <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.01206">Du and Lee (2018)</a>.</p>

<h3 id="generalization-and-sample-complexity-case-study-on-learning-low-rank-polynomials">Generalization and sample complexity: Case study on learning low-rank polynomials</h3>
<p>We next study the generalization of these networks in the context of learning <em>low-rank degree-$p$ polynomials</em>:</p>

\[f_\star(x) = \sum_{s=1}^{r_\star} \alpha_s (\beta_s^\top x)^{p_s}, \quad |\alpha_s|\le 1,\|(\beta_s^\top x)^{p_s}\|_{L_2} \le 1, p_s\le p \quad \textrm{for all } s.\]

<p>We are specifically interested in the case where $r_\star$ is small (e.g. $O(1)$), so that $y$ only depends on the projection of $x$ on a few directions. This for example captures teacher networks with polynomial activation of bounded degree and analytic activation (approximately), as well as constant depth teacher networks with polynomial activations.</p>

<p>For the NTK, the sample complexity of learning polynomials have been studied extensively in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.08584">(Arora et al. 2019a)</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.12191">(Ghorbani et al. 2019)</a>, and many concurrent work. Combined, they showed that the sample complexity for learning degree-$p$ polynomials is $\Theta(d^p)$, with matching lower and upper bounds:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem (NTK)</strong> : Suppose $x$ is uniformly distributed on the sphere, then the NTK requires $O(d^p)$ samples in order to achieve a small test error for learning any degree-$p$ polynomial, and there is a matching lower bound of $\Omega(d^p)$ for any inner-product kernel method.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In our <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.0161">Beyond Linearization paper</a>, we show that the quadratic Taylor model achieves an improved sample complexity of  $\tilde{O}(d^{p-1})$ with isotropic inputs:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem (Quadratic Model)</strong>: For mildly isotropic input distributions, the two-layer quadratic Taylor model (or two-layer NN with sign randomization) only requires $\tilde{O}({\rm poly}(r_\star, p)d^{p-1})$ samples in order to achieve a small test error for learning a low-rank degree-$p$ polynomial.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In our <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.13436">follow-up paper on understanding hierarchical learning</a>, we further design a “hierarchical learner” using a specific three-layer network, and show the following</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem (Three-layer hierarchical model)</strong>: Under mild input distribution assumptions, a three-layer network with a fixed representation layer of width $D=d^{p/2}$ and a trainable quadratic Taylor layer can achieve a small test error using only $\tilde{O}({\rm poly}(r_\star, p)d^{p/2})$ samples.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When $r_\star,p=O(1)$, the quadratic Taylor model can improve over the NTK by a multiplicative factor of $d$, and we can further get a substantially larger improvement of $d^{p/2}$ by using the three-layer hierarchical learner. Here we briefly discuss the proof intuitions, and refer the reader to our papers for more details.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Generalization bounds</strong>: We show that, while the NTK and quadratic Taylor model expresses functions using similar random feature constructions, their generalization depends differently on the norm of the input. In the NTK, the generalization depends on the L2 norm of the features (as well as the weights), whereas generalization of the quadratic Taylor model depends on the operator norm of the input matrix features $\frac{1}{n}\sum x_ix_i^\top$ times the nuclear norm of $\sum w_rw_r^\top$. It turns out that this decomposition can match the one given by the NTK (it is never worse), and in addition be better by a factor of $O(\sqrt{d})$ if the input distribution is mildly isotropic so that $\|\frac{1}{n}\sum x_ix_i^\top\|_{\rm op} \le 1/\sqrt{d} \cdot \max \|x_i\|_2^2$, leading to the $O(d)$ improvement in the sample complexity.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Hierarchical learning</strong>: The key intuition behind the hierarchical learner is that we can utilize the $O(d)$ sample complexity gain to its fullest, by applying quadratic Taylor model to not the input $x$, but a feature representation $h(x)\in \mathbb{R}^D$ where $D\gg d$. This yields a gain as long as $h$ is rich enough to express $f_\star$ and also isotropic enough to let the operator norm $\|\frac{1}{n}\sum h(x_i)h(x_i)^\top\|_{\rm op}$ be nice. In particular, for learning degree-$p$ polynomials, the best we can do is to choose $D=d^{p/2}$, leading to a sample complexity saving of $\tilde{O}(D)=\tilde{O}(d^{p/2})$.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="concluding-thoughts">Concluding thoughts</h3>
<p>In this post, we explored higher-order Taylor expansions (in particular the quadratic expansion) as an approach to deep learning theory beyond the NTK regime. The Taylorization approach has several advantages:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Non-convex but benign optimization landscape;</li>
  <li>Provable generalization benefits over NTKs;</li>
  <li>Ability of modeling hierarchical learning;</li>
  <li>Convenient API for expeirmentation (cf. the <a href="https://github.com/google/neural-tangents">Neural Tangents</a> package and the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.04010">Taylorized training</a> paper).</li>
</ul>

<p>We believe these advantages make the Taylor expansion a powerful tool for deep learning theory, and our results are just a beginning. We also remark that there are other theoretical frameworks such as the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.08156">Neural Tangent Hierarchy</a> or the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.06561">Mean-Field Theory</a> that go beyond the NTK with their own advantages in various angles, but without computational efficiency guarantees. See the <a href="https://jasondlee88.github.io/slides/beyond_ntk.pdf">slides</a> for more on going beyond NTK. Making progress on any of these directions (or coming up with new ones) would be an exciting direction for future work.</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-03-25T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-25T14:00:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>http://offconvex.github.io/</id>
      <author>
        <name>Off the Convex Path</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://offconvex.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://offconvex.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Algorithms off the convex path.</subtitle>
      <title>Off the convex path</title>
      <updated>2021-03-31T22:45:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/046</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/046" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-046 |  Fourier Growth of Parity Decision Trees | 

	Uma Girish, 

	Avishay Tal, 

	Kewen Wu</title>
    <summary>We prove that for every parity decision tree of depth $d$ on $n$ variables, the sum of absolute values of Fourier coefficients at level $\ell$ is at most $d^{\ell/2} \cdot O(\ell \cdot \log(n))^\ell$. 
Our result is nearly tight for small values of $\ell$ and extends a previous Fourier bound for standard decision trees by Sherstov, Storozhenko, and Wu (STOC, 2021). 

As an application of our Fourier bounds, using the results of Bansal and Sinha (STOC, 2021), we show that the $k$-fold Forrelation problem has (randomized) parity decision tree complexity  $\tilde{\Omega}\left(n^{1-1/k}\right)$, while having quantum query complexity $\lceil k/2\rceil$. 

Our proof follows a random-walk approach, analyzing the contribution of a random path in the decision tree to the level-$\ell$ Fourier expression. 
To carry the argument, we apply a careful cleanup procedure to the parity decision tree, ensuring that the value of the random walk is bounded with high probability. We observe that step sizes for the level-$\ell$ walks can be computed by the intermediate values of level $\le \ell-1$ walks, which calls for an inductive argument.
Our approach differs from previous proofs of Tal (FOCS, 2020) and Sherstov, Storozhenko, and Wu (STOC, 2021) that relied on decompositions of the tree. In particular, for the special case of standard decision trees we view our proof as slightly simpler and more intuitive.

In addition, we prove a similar bound for noisy decision trees of cost at most $d$ -- a model that was recently introduced by Ben-David and Blais (FOCS, 2020).</summary>
    <updated>2021-03-25T03:37:04Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-25T03:37:04Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=539</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2021/03/23/tcs-talk-wednesday-march-31-jasper-lee-brown-university/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, March 31 — Jasper Lee, Brown University</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, March 31th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). Jasper Lee from Brown University will speak about “Optimal Sub-Gaussian Mean Estimation in ” (abstract below). You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, March 31th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). <a href="http://cs.brown.edu/~clee10/"><strong>Jasper Lee</strong></a> from Brown University will speak about “<em>Optimal Sub-Gaussian Mean Estimation in <img alt="\mathbb{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></em>” (abstract below).</p>
<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/next-tcs-talk">the online form</a>. Due to security concerns, <em>registration is required</em> to attend the interactive talk. (The recorded talk will also be posted <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/past-talks">on our website</a> afterwards, so people who did not sign up will still be able to watch the talk)</p>
<p>As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/suggest-a-talk">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/">the website</a>.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Abstract: We revisit and settle a fundamental problem in statistics: given access to independent samples from a 1D random variable (with finite but unknown mean and variance), what is the best way to estimate the mean in the high probability regime, in terms of error convergence with respect to sample size? The conventional wisdom is to use the empirical mean as our estimate. However, it is known that the empirical mean can in fact have exponentially sub-optimal convergence for certain heavy-tailed distributions. On the other hand, the median-of-means estimator (invented and reinvented in various literature) does have sub-Gaussian convergence for all finite-variance distributions, albeit only in the big-O sense with a sub-optimal multiplicative constant. The natural remaining question then, is whether it is possible to bridge the gap, and have an estimator that has optimal convergence with the right constant for all finite-variance distributions.</p>
<p>In this talk, we answer the question affirmatively by giving an estimator that converges with the optimal constant inside the big-O, up to a 1+o(1) multiplicative factor. The estimator is also easy to compute. The convergence analysis involves deriving tail bounds using linear and convex-concave programming dualities, which may be of independent interest.</p>
<p>Based on joint work with Paul Valiant.</p></blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-24T03:37:07Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-24T03:37:07Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:21:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=18389</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/23/moby-dick-meet-theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Moby Dick Meet Theory</title>
    <summary>People seem to be afraid of mathematics. And I think that’s such a shame, because I don’t think it’s as hard as people seem to think it is. —Heidi Hammel Sarah Hart holds a chair that dates back to 1597—Gresham Professor of Geometry at Birkbeck, University of London. She is a British mathematician specialising in […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>People seem to be afraid of mathematics. And I think that’s such a shame, because I don’t think it’s as hard as people seem to think it is. —Heidi Hammel</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?attachment_id=18328" rel="attachment wp-att-18328"><img alt="" class="alignright  wp-image-18328" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/sh2.jpg?w=250&amp;ssl=1"/></a></p>
<p>
Sarah Hart holds a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gresham_Professor_of_Geometry">chair</a> that dates back to 1597—Gresham Professor of Geometry at Birkbeck, University of London.  She is a British mathematician specialising in group theory. The British <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_and_British_English_spelling_differences">modifier</a> is redundant since I spelled specialising with a “s” not a “z”: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Today’s British English spellings mostly follow Samuel Johnson’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Dictionary_of_the_English_Language">A Dictionary of the English Language</a> (1755), while many American English spellings follow Webster’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Webster%27s_Dictionary">An American Dictionary of the English Language</a> (1828). </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Today we will discuss history, making history, and more.<br/>
<span id="more-18389"/></p>
<p>
Hart is an excellent writer about math with a special interest in history and in non-standard applications of math to things like Moby-Dick. See the recent <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/06/science/math-gresham-sarah-hart.html">article</a> in the science section of the New York Times about Hart: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> For the mathematician Sarah Hart, a close reading of “Moby-Dick” reveals not merely “one of the strangest and most wonderful books in the world” and “the greatest book of the sea ever written,” but also a work awash in mathematical metaphors. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?attachment_id=18329" rel="attachment wp-att-18329"><img alt="" class="alignright size-full wp-image-18329" height="194" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/wt.png?resize=259%2C194&amp;ssl=1" width="259"/></a></p>
<p>
Hart’s paper on Moby-Dick is titled <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12102.pdf">Ahab’s Arithmetic</a>. I bet few articles on the arxiv website are on fictional works like Moby-Dick: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Herman Melville’s novel Moby-Dick contains a surprising number of mathematical allusions. In this article we explore some of these, as well as discussing the questions that naturally follow: why did Melville choose to use so much mathematical imagery? How did Melville come to acquire the level of mathematical knowledge shown in the novel? And is it commensurate with the general level of mathematical literacy at that time? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Hart also has given many talks on math from a unique point of <a href="https://www.gresham.ac.uk/professorships/geometry-professorship/">view</a>.</p>
<p/><h2> Group Theory History </h2><p/>
<p>
Hart is the current <a href="https://www.bshm.ac.uk/where-our-members-are">president</a> of the British Society for the History of Mathematics: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Mathematics has been part of human culture since the beginnings of civilization. Its study and practice has gone hand in hand with the evolution and development of commerce, architecture, legal theory, cosmology, astrology, and countless other activities. The history of mathematics today addresses a rich cultural heritage across continents, peoples, and ages, taking in the practical traditions of merchants’ accounts and surveying just as it does the elevated traditions of learned scholars at court or the modern day university professor. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Hart adds: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> In this <a href="https://eprints.bbk.ac.uk/id/eprint/26953/">article</a> we explore mathematical allusions in Herman Melville’s novel Moby-Dick. We argue that both the quantity and sophistication of these allusions are evidence for Melville’s high level of mathematical knowledge and ability. We discuss some of the most compelling mathematical imagery, as well as giving background on the several mathematicians and mathematics books mentioned in the novel. We also include some biographical details supporting the assertion that Melville had an unusually good mathematical education. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Another view of history is given by Alma <a href="https://history.columbia.edu/person/alma-steingart/">Steingart</a> of the history department of Columbia. Steingart has written, for example, an <a href="https://sites.tufts.edu/histmath/files/2015/11/steingart-group-theory.pdf">article</a> on the history of the classification of all simple groups: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Over a period of more than 30 years, more than 100 mathematicians worked on a project to classify mathematical objects known as finite simple groups. The Classification, when officially declared completed in 1981, ranged between 300 and 500 articles and ran somewhere between 5,000 and 10,000 journal pages. Mathematicians have hailed the project as one of the greatest mathematical achievements of the 20th century, and it surpasses, both in scale and scope, any other mathematical proof of the 20th century. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Decades ago as soon as we started to think about the <a href="https://www.uni-ulm.de/fileadmin/website_uni_ulm/iui.inst.190/Mitarbeiter/wagner/GroupIso_040712.pdf">group isomorphism</a> problem we realized there is an application of the classification theorem: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> We can use it to prove that isomorphism for finite simple groups is in polynomial time. The proof is simple—bad pun: Just use the fact that all simple groups are generated by at most <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{2}"/> elements. So just try all possible pairs. See <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2013/05/11/advances-on-group-isomorphism/">GLL</a> for some more comments. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><h2> Making Group Theory History </h2><p/>
<p>
Hart may be interested in the history of math, but proving new theorems is perhaps the best way to affect history. The <a href="https://www.combinatorics.org/ojs/index.php/eljc/article/view/v16i1r59/pdf">paper</a> titled Small maximal sum-free sets by Michael Giudici and Hart solves a previously open problem. The site <i>Theorem of day</i> highlights this paper <a href="https://www.theoremoftheday.org/GroupTheory/SumFree/TotDSumFree.pdf">here</a>. Also Tim <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/0710.3877.pdf">Gowers</a> proved some related results.</p>
<p>
Hart’s main theorem is: </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 1</b> <em> Let <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> be a finite group and let <img alt="{&lt;S&gt;}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3CS%3E%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{&lt;S&gt;}"/> be the subgroup generated by a subset <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> of the elements of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/>. Then unless <img alt="{|S | \le 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CS+%7C+%5Cle+2%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{|S | \le 2}"/>, <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> cannot be both maximally sum-free and minimal with respect to generating <img alt="{&lt;S&gt;}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3CS%3E%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{&lt;S&gt;}"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Consider a set <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> of elements in a finite group <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/>. There are two properties that <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> can have, and these properties act in opposite directions.</p>
<ul>
<li>Force <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> to be smaller: The set <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> is sum-free. This means that for <img alt="{a, b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%2C+b%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{a, b}"/> in <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/>,
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  ab \not\in S. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++ab+%5Cnot%5Cin+S.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  ab \not\in S. "/></p>
</li><li>Force <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> to be larger: The set is minimal generator for <img alt="{&lt;S&gt;}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3CS%3E%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{&lt;S&gt;}"/>. This means that it is not possible to generate <img alt="{&lt;S&gt;}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3CS%3E%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{&lt;S&gt;}"/> with less elements than <img alt="{|S|}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CS%7C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{|S|}"/>.  Intuitively these properties work against each other. Adding an element to <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> could violate sum-free; deleting an element from <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{S}"/> could violate generation.
</li></ul>
<p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>
Here is an <a href="https://www.newton.ac.uk/science/outreach/women/six-questions/hart-sarah">interview</a> with Hart—take a look.</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-23T14:31:05Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-23T14:31:05Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="group theory"/>
    <category term="Moby dick"/>
    <category term="Sarah Hart"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=21227</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/03/23/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-22-some-mathematical-news-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>To cheer you up in difficult times 22: some mathematical news! (Part 1)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To cheer you up, in these difficult times, here are (in two parts) some mathematical news that I heard in personal communications or on social media. (Maybe I will write later, in more details,  about few of them that are … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/03/23/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-22-some-mathematical-news-part-1/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>To cheer you up, in these difficult times, here are (in two parts) some mathematical news that I heard in personal communications or on social media. (Maybe I will write later, in more details,  about few of them that are closer to combinatorics.)</p>
<h2>Mathematics and the real world</h2>
<h3>Zvi Artstein  <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/c30.pdf">The pendulum under vibrations revisited</a></h3>
<p>Zvi (Zvika) was one of the first people that I met in 1971 at the university as a high school student and he gave me a lot of good advice and help. Here he shed light on an old mystery!</p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>Abstract: A simple intuitive physical explanation is offered, of the stability of the inverted pendulum under fast violent vibrations. The direct description allows to analyze, both intuitively and rigorously, the effect of vibrations in similar, and in more general, situations. The rigorous derivations in the paper follow a singular perturbations model of mixed slow and fast dynamics. The approach allows applications beyond the classical inverted pendulum model.</em></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I first heard about the stability of the inverted pendulum under fast violent vibrations from Sylvia Serfaty in connection with <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2009/04/20/the-intermediate-value-theorem-applied-to-football/">my study of “forehead-football.” See this post</a>. Let me mention with pride that Endre Szemeredi, who is a fan of football in general (and a capable player), is also a fan of my forehead-football idea.</p>
<h3>Imre Bárány, William Steiger, and Sivan Toledo <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.06838">the cocked hat</a></h3>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>Abstract (arXive): We revisit the cocked hat — an old problem from navigation — and examine under what conditions its old solution is valid.</em></span></p>
</blockquote>
<h2><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/cokedhat.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-21402" height="296" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/cokedhat.png" width="426"/></a></h2>
<p>This is a great story, read it in <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-navigation/article/abs/cocked-hat-formal-statements-and-proofs-of-the-theorems/5264C1491A61116CAF7B890161CFD091">The Journal of Navigation</a>, or <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.06838">on the arXive.</a></p>
<h2>Rigidity</h2>
<h3>Katie Clinch, Bill Jackson, Shin-ichi Tanigawa: Maximal Matroid Problem on Graphs</h3>
<div>In mid January, we had a <strong>great lecture</strong> by <b/>Shin-ichi Tanigawa (University of Tokyo). I certainly plan to blog about it. Here is the abstract.</div>
<div> </div>
<blockquote>
<div><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>The problem of characterizing the 3-dimensional generic rigidity of graphs is one of the major open problems in graph rigidity theory. Walter <span class="il">Whiteley</span> conjectured that the 3-dimensional generic matroid coincides with a matroid studied in the context of bivariate splines.  In this talk I will show a solution to the characterization problem for the latter matroid. </em></span></div>
<div> </div>
<div><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>I will explain the idea of our characterization from the view point of constructing maximal matroids on complete graphs. Specifically, for a graph H, a matroid on the edge set of a complete graph is called an H-matroid if every edge set of each subgraph isomorphic to H is a circuit. A main theme of my talk will be about identifying and constructing a maximal H-matroid with respect to the weak order. This talk is based on a joint work with Bill Jackson and Katie Clinch.</em></span>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://huji.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=a588e411-26c9-4f35-9e1b-acb400bcf8de">Here is the video</a></p>
</div>
</blockquote>
<div>The papers on the arxive</div>
<div>Katie Clinch, Bill Jackson, Shin-ichi Tanigawa, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.00205">Abstract 3-Rigidity and Bivariate <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-19-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-52"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-53"><span class="msubsup" id="MathJax-Span-54"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-55">C</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-56">1</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-57">2</span></span></span></span></span>-Splines I: Whiteley’s Maximality Conjecture </a></div>
<div>Katie Clinch, Bill Jackson, Shin-ichi Tanigawa <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.00207">Abstract 3-Rigidity and Bivariate <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-15-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-34"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-35"><span class="msubsup" id="MathJax-Span-36"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-37">C</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-38">1</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-39">2</span></span></span></span></span>-Splines II: Combinatorial Characterization</a></div>
<div> </div>
<h2>Polytopes</h2>
<h3>Ardila and Escobar:  The harmonic polytope</h3>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em><strong><span class="has-text-black-bis has-text-weight-semibold">Abstract</span>:</strong> <span class="abstract-full has-text-grey-dark mathjax" id="2006.03078v1-abstract-full">We study the harmonic polytope, which arose in Ardila, Denham, and Huh’s work on the Lagrangian geometry of matroids. We show that it is a <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-5-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-40"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-41"><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-42">(</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-43">2</span><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-44">n</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-45">−</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-46">2</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-47">)</span></span></span></span>-dimensional polytope with $latex <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-6-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-48"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-49"><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-50">(</span><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-51">n</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-52">!</span><span class="msubsup" id="MathJax-Span-53"><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-54">)^</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-55">2 </span></span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-56">(</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-57">1</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-58">+</span><span class="mfrac" id="MathJax-Span-59"><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-60">1/</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-61">2</span></span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-62">+</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-63">⋯</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-64">+</span><span class="mfrac" id="MathJax-Span-65"><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-66">1/</span><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-67">n</span></span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-68">)$</span></span></span></span> vertices and $latex <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-7-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-69"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-70"><span class="msubsup" id="MathJax-Span-71"><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-72">3^</span><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-73">n</span></span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-74">−</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-75">3$</span></span></span></span> facets. We give a formula for its volume: it is a weighted sum of the degrees of the projective varieties of all the toric ideals of connected bipartite graphs with <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-8-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-76"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-77"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-78">n</span></span></span></span> edges; or equivalently, a weighted sum of the lattice point counts of all the corresponding trimmed generalized permutahedra.</span></em></span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>These polytopes look truly great!</p>
<p>Federico Ardila, Laura Escobar, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.03078">The <span class="search-hit mathjax">harmonic</span> <span class="search-hit mathjax">polytope</span></a></p>
<h2>Percolation</h2>
<p> I am thankful to Itai Benjamini who told me about these results.</p>
<h3>At last: Rotation invariance theorem for planar percolation for the square grid.</h3>
<p class="title is-5 mathjax"><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.11672"><span class="search-hit mathjax">Rotational</span> invariance in critical planar lattice models</a></p>
<p>This is very big news: twenty years after Smirnov’s result for the triangular grid, finally rotational invariance is proved for critical percolation on the square grid.</p>
<p class="authors"><span class="has-text-black-bis has-text-weight-semibold">Authors:</span> Hugo Duminil-Copin, Karol Kajetan Kozlowski, Dmitry Krachun, Ioan Manolescu, Mendes Oulamara</p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em><strong>Abstract: </strong> In this paper, we prove that the large scale properties of a number of two-dimensional lattice models are rotationally invariant. More precisely, we prove that the random-cluster model on the square lattice with cluster-weight <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-1-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-1"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-2"><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-3">1</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-4">≤</span><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-5">q</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-6">≤</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-7">4</span></span></span></span> exhibits rotational invariance at large scales. This covers the case of Bernoulli percolation on the square lattice as an important example. We deduce from this result that the correlations of the Potts models with <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-2-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-8"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-9"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-10">q</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-11">∈</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-12">{</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-13">2</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-14">,</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-15">3</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-16">,</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-17">4</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-18">}</span></span></span></span> colors and of the six-vertex height function with <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-3-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-19"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-20"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-21">Δ</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-22">∈</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-23">[</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-24">−</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-25">1</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-26">,</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-27">−</span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-28">1</span><span class="texatom" id="MathJax-Span-29"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-30"><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-31">/</span></span></span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-32">2</span><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-33">]</span></span></span></span> are rotationally invariant at large scales.</em></span></p>
</blockquote>
<h3>Noise sensitivity for planar percolation without Fourier</h3>
<p>Endre Szemeredi sometimes say that we should try to avoid the use of his regularity lemma “at all costs”. Similarly, we should try to avoid Fourier tools if we can. Vincent and Hugo could!</p>
<p class="title mathjax"><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.04572">Noise sensitivity of percolation via differential inequalities</a>, Vincent Tassion and Hugo Vanneuville</p>
<blockquote>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em><strong>Abstract:</strong> Consider critical Bernoulli percolation in the plane. We give a new proof of the sharp noise sensitivity theorem shown by Garban, Pete and Schramm. Contrary to the previous approaches, we do not use any spectral tool. We rather study differential inequalities satisfied by a dynamical four-arm event, in the spirit of Kesten’s proof of scaling relations. We also obtain new results in dynamical percolation. In particular, we prove that the Hausdorff dimension of the set of times with both primal and dual percolation equals <span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-1-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-1"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-2"><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-3">2</span><span class="texatom" id="MathJax-Span-4"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-5"><span class="mo" id="MathJax-Span-6">/</span></span></span><span class="mn" id="MathJax-Span-7">3</span></span></span></span> a.s.</em></span></p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="title mathjax"><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.11903">Plaquette Percolation on the Torus</a> by  Paul Duncan, Matthew Kahle, and Benjamin Schweinhart</h3>
<p>Harry Kesten famously proved that the critical probability for planar percolation is 1/2. Planar duality is crucial.  Many people expected or speculated that a similar statement for <img alt="2d" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2d&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-dimensions holds if we replace “connectivity” by some statement about <img alt="d" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> dimensional homology. This is what the new paper does.</p>
<p>(Next part: Topology, graph theory, algebra, Boolean functions, and Mathematics over the media.)</p>
<p> </p>


<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-23T08:53:33Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-23T08:53:33Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Convex polytopes"/>
    <category term="Convexity"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7448114190319986834</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7448114190319986834/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/a-taylor-series-problem.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7448114190319986834" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7448114190319986834" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/a-taylor-series-problem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Taylor Series Problem</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> I post a problem today and its solution on Thursday.</p><p>Comments are fine, though if you don't want to get a hint, don't read them. </p><p><br/></p><p>Find the coefficient of x<sup>100</sup> in the Taylor series for the rational function which has </p><p><br/></p><p>numerator 1 </p><p>and denominator</p><p><br/></p><p>x<sup>41</sup> - x<sup>40</sup> - x<sup>36</sup> + x<sup>35</sup> -x<sup>31</sup> + x<sup>30</sup> + x<sup>26</sup> - x<sup>25</sup>- x<sup>16</sup> + x<sup>15</sup> + x<sup>11</sup> - x<sup>10</sup> + x<sup>6</sup> - x<sup>5</sup> -x+1</p><p><br/></p><p>For better readability see my pdf file with the problem in it <a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/taylorcoinsprob.pdf">here</a></p><p><br/></p><p>Is there a clever way to do the problem?  If the way to do it was to actually do the Taylor series then </p><p>1) I wouldn't post it</p><p>2) I probably could not do it (or it would take too long to bother)  though maybe there are freely available programs that could. </p><p><br/></p><p>So yes, there is a clever solution. At least I think it's clever. </p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-22T19:21:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-22T19:21:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T13:22:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/045</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/045" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-045 |  Reconstruction Algorithms for Low-Rank Tensors and Depth-3 Multilinear Circuits | 

	Vishwas Bhargava, 

	Shubhangi Saraf, 

	Ilya Volkovich</title>
    <summary>We give new and efficient black-box reconstruction algorithms for some classes of depth-$3$ arithmetic circuits. As a consequence, we obtain the first efficient algorithm for computing the tensor rank and for finding the optimal tensor decomposition as a sum of rank-one tensors when then input is a {\it constant-rank} tensor. More specifically, we provide efficient learning algorithms that run in randomized polynomial time over general fields and in deterministic polynomial time over $\mathbb R$ and $\mathbb C$ for the following classes:

\begin{enumerate}
    \item {\it Set-multilinear depth-$3$ circuits of constant top fan-in ($\Sigma\Pi\Sigma_{{\sqcup_j X_j}}(k)$ circuits)}. As a consequence of our algorithm, we obtain the first polynomial time algorithm for tensor rank computation and optimal tensor decomposition of constant-rank tensors. This result holds for $d$ dimensional tensors for any $d$, but is interesting even for $d=3$.
    \item {\it Sums of powers of constantly many linear forms ($\Sigma\!\wedge\!\Sigma(k)$ circuits)}.  As a consequence we obtain the first polynomial-time algorithm for tensor rank computation and optimal tensor decomposition of constant-rank symmetric tensors.
    \item {\it Multilinear depth-3 circuits of constant top fan-in (multilinear $\Sigma\Pi\Sigma(k)$ circuits)}. Our algorithm works over all fields of characteristic 0 or large enough characteristic. Prior to our work the only efficient algorithms known were over polynomially-sized finite fields \cite{KarninShpilka09}. 
\end{enumerate}
Prior to our work, the only polynomial-time or even subexponential-time algorithms known (deterministic or randomized) for subclasses of $\Sigma\Pi\Sigma(k)$ circuits that also work over large/infinite fields were for the setting when the top fan-in $k$ is at most $2$ \cite{Sin16, Sin20}.</summary>
    <updated>2021-03-22T18:47:56Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-22T18:47:56Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/044</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/044" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-044 |  SAT-based Circuit Local Improvement | 

	Alexander Kulikov, 

	Nikita Slezkin</title>
    <summary>Finding exact circuit size is a notorious optimization problem in practice. Whereas modern computers and algorithmic techniques allow to find a circuit of size seven in blink of an eye, it may take more than a week to search for a circuit of size thirteen. One of the reasons of this behavior is that the search space is enormous: the number of circuits of size $s$ is $s^{\Theta(s)}$, the number of Boolean functions on $n$ variables is $2^{2^n}$.

In this paper, we explore the following natural heuristic idea for decreasing the size of a given circuit: go through all its subcircuits of moderate size and check whether any of them can be improved by reducing to SAT. This may be viewed as a local search approach: we search for a smaller circuit in a ball around a given circuit. We report the results of experiments with various symmetric functions.</summary>
    <updated>2021-03-22T16:50:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-22T16:50:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/03/22/postdoctoral-associate-at-rutgers-university-dimacs-apply-by-april-5-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/03/22/postdoctoral-associate-at-rutgers-university-dimacs-apply-by-april-5-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral Associate at Rutgers University – DIMACS (apply by April 5, 2021)</title>
    <summary>DIMACS, the Center for Discrete Mathematics and Theoretical Computer Science, based at Rutgers University, invites applications for a transdisciplinary DATA-INSPIRE postdoc Applicants should be recent PhDs in computer science, math, or statistics, with a demonstrated interest in working across these disciplines. Website: https://jobs.rutgers.edu/postings/128123 Email: application@dimacs.rutgers.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>DIMACS, the Center for Discrete Mathematics and Theoretical Computer Science, based at Rutgers University, invites applications for a transdisciplinary DATA-INSPIRE postdoc<br/>
Applicants should be recent PhDs in computer science, math, or statistics, with a demonstrated interest in working across these disciplines.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://jobs.rutgers.edu/postings/128123">https://jobs.rutgers.edu/postings/128123</a><br/>
Email: application@dimacs.rutgers.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-22T15:29:55Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-22T15:29:55Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5387</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5387" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5387#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5387" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">QC ethics and hype: the call is coming from inside the house</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">For years, I’d sometimes hear discussions about the ethics of quantum computing research. Quantum ethics! When the debates weren’t purely semantic, over the propriety of terms like “quantum supremacy” or “ancilla qubit,” they were always about chin-strokers like “but what if cracking RSA encryption gives governments more power to surveil their citizens? or what if […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>For years, I’d sometimes hear discussions about the <em>ethics</em> of quantum computing research.  Quantum ethics!</p>



<p>When the debates weren’t purely semantic, over the <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450">propriety</a> of terms like “quantum supremacy” or “ancilla qubit,” they were always about chin-strokers like “but what if cracking RSA encryption gives governments more power to surveil their citizens?  or what if only a few big countries or companies get quantum computers, thereby widening the divide between haves and have-nots?”  Which, OK, conceivably these will someday be issues.  But, besides barely depending on any specific facts about quantum computing, these debates always struck me as oddly <em>safe</em>, because the moral dilemmas were so hypothetical and far removed from us in time.</p>



<p>I confess I may have even occasionally poked fun when asked to expound on quantum ethics.  I may have commented that quantum computers probably won’t kill anyone unless a dilution refrigerator tips over onto their head.  I may have asked forgiveness for feeding custom-designed oracles to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BQP">BQP</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/QMA">QMA</a>, without first consulting an ethics committee about the long-term effects on those complexity classes.</p>



<p>Now fate has punished me for my flippancy.  These days, I really <em>do</em> feel like quantum computing research has become an ethical minefield—but not for any of the reasons mentioned previously.  What’s new is that millions of dollars are now potentially available to quantum computing researchers, along with equity, stock options, and whatever else causes “ka-ching” sound effects and bulging eyes with dollar signs.  And in many cases, to have a shot at such riches, all an expert needs to do is profess optimism that quantum computing will have revolutionary, world-changing applications and have them <em>soon</em>.  Or at least, not object too strongly when others say that.</p>



<p>Some of today’s rhetoric will of course remind people of the D-Wave saga, which first brought this blog to prominence when it began in earnest in 2007.  Quantum computers, we hear now as then, will soon leave the Earth’s fastest supercomputers in the dust.  They’re going to harness superposition to try all the exponentially many possible solutions at once.  They’ll crack the Traveling Salesman Problem, and will transform machine learning and AI beyond recognition.  Meanwhile, simulations of quantum systems will be key to solving global warming and cancer.</p>



<p>Despite the parallels, though, this new gold rush <em>doesn’t</em> feel to me like the D-Wave one, which seems in retrospect like just a little dry run.  If I had to articulate what’s new in one sentence, it’s that this time “the call is coming from inside the house.”  Many of the companies making wildly overhyped claims are recognized leaders of the field.  They have brilliant quantum computing theorists and experimentalists on their staff with impeccable research records.  Some of those researchers are among my best friends.  And even when I wince at the claims of near-term applications, in many cases (especially with quantum simulation) the claims aren’t <em>obviously</em> false—we won’t know for certain until we try it and see!  It’s genuinely gotten harder to draw the line between defensible optimism and exaggerations verging on fraud.</p>



<p>Indeed, this time around virtually <em>everyone</em> in QC is “complicit” to a greater or lesser degree.  I, too, have accepted compensation to consult on quantum computing topics, to give talks at hedge funds, and in a few cases to serve as a scientific adviser to quantum computing startups.  I tell myself that, by 2021 standards, this stuff is all trivial chump change—a few thousands of dollars here or there, to expound on the same themes that I already discuss free of charge on this blog.  I actually get paid to <em>dispel</em> hype, rather than propagate it!  I tell myself that I’ve turned my back on the orders of magnitude more money available to those willing to hitch their scientific reputations to the aspirations of this or that specific QC company.  (Yes, this blog, and my desire to preserve its intellectual independence and credibility, might well be costing me millions!)</p>



<p>But, OK, some would argue that accepting <em>any</em> money from QC companies or QC investors just puts you at the top of a slope with unabashed snake-oil salesmen at the bottom.  With the commercialization of our field that started around 2015, there’s no bright line anymore marking the boundary between pure scientific curiosity and the pursuit of filthy lucre; it’s all just points along a continuum.  I’m not sure that these people are wrong.</p>



<p>As some of you might’ve seen already, IonQ, the trapped-ion QC startup that originated from the University of Maryland, is poised to have the <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-ionq-m-a-dmy-technology/quantum-computing-provider-ionq-to-go-public-via-2-billion-spac-deal-idUSKBN2B013Z">first-ever quantum computing IPO</a>—a so-called “SPAC IPO,” which while I’m a financial ignoramus, apparently involves merging with a shell company and thereby bypassing the SEC’s normal IPO rules.  Supposedly they’re seeking $650 million in new funding and a $2 billion market cap.  If you want to see what IonQ is saying about QC to prospective investors, <a href="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5e33152a051d2e7588f7571c/t/60459578b8c075444a656357/1615173012167/IonQ+Investor+Presentation+030721+vFF.pdf">click here</a>.  Lacking any choice in the matter, I’ll probably say more about these developments in a future post.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, <a href="https://psiquantum.com/">PsiQuantum</a>, the Palo-Alto-based optical QC startup, has <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/a5af3039-abbf-4b25-92e2-c40e5957c8cd">said</a> that it’s soon going to leave “stealth mode.”  And Amazon, Microsoft, Google, IBM, Honeywell, and other big players continue making large investments in QC—treating it, at least rhetorically, not at all like blue-sky basic research, but like a central part of their future business plans.</p>



<p>All of these companies have produced or funded excellent QC research.  And of course, they’re all heterogeneous, composed of individuals who might vehemently disagree with each other about the near- or long-term prospects of QC.  And yet all of them have, at various times, inspired reflections in me like the ones in this post.</p>



<p>I regret that this post has no clear conclusion.  I’m still hashing things out, solicing thoughts from my readers and friends.  Speaking of which: this coming Monday, March 22, at 8-10pm US Eastern time, I’ve decided to hold a discussion around these issues on <a href="https://www.joinclubhouse.com/">Clubhouse</a>—my “grand debut” on that app, and an opportunity to see whether I like it or not!  My friend Adam Brown will moderate the discussion; other likely participants will be John Horgan, George Musser, Michael Nielsen, and Matjaž Leonardis.  If you’re on Clubhouse, I hope to see you there!</p>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update (March 22):</span></strong> Read <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5387#comment-1883356">this comment</a> by “FB” if you’d like to understand how we got to this point.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-21T01:18:54Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-21T01:18:54Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Speaking Truth to Parallelism"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2021-03-22T23:54:23Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=18396</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/19/closing-an-erdos-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Closing an Erdős Problem</title>
    <summary>Whatever the problem, be part of the solution. Don’t just sit around raising questions and pointing out obstacles.—Tina Fey Daniela Kühn is the Mason Professor in Mathematics at the University of Birmingham. She works in extremal and probabilistic combinatorics. She has many honors, including giving an invited lecture at the International Congress of Mathematicians in […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Whatever the problem, be part of the solution. Don’t just sit around raising questions and pointing out obstacles.—Tina Fey</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/19/closing-an-erdos-problem/dh2/" rel="attachment wp-att-18399"><img alt="" class="alignright swp-image-18399" height="240" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/dh2.jpg?resize=180%2C240&amp;ssl=1" width="180"/></a></p>
<p>
Daniela Kühn is the Mason Professor in Mathematics at the University of Birmingham. She works in extremal and probabilistic combinatorics. She has many honors, including giving an invited lecture at the International Congress of Mathematicians in 2014.</p>
<p>
Today I thought we should look at a new result of hers.</p>
<p>
By the way, as I wrote this draft, I was excited to see that it was the second time we highlighted a researcher from Bi*ngham*. <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com">Previously</a> we highlighted Jessica Fridrich, from Binghamton University. OK, they are different places, in different countries, but the closeness in edit distance caught my eye.</p>
<p>
Kühn says <a href="https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/staff/profiles/maths/kuhn-daniela.aspx">here</a>: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Recently I have focused on sufficient conditions for Hamilton cycles in directed graphs, i.e. cycles which contain all the vertices of the directed graph. It is unlikely that there is a good characterization of all (directed) graphs containing a Hamilton cycle since the corresponding decision problem is NP-complete. So it is natural to ask for sufficient conditions for the existence of a Hamilton cycle. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Here is her <a href="https://silo.tips/download/hamiltonian-degree-sequences-in-digraphs">paper</a> on degree sequences on directed graphs that force Hamilton cycles. It is joint with Deryk Osthus and Andrew Treglown. </p>
<p/><h2> The Conjecture </h2><p/>
<p>
Paul Erdős is known for his conjectures as well as his countless results. Here are two of his open <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_conjectures_by_Paul_Erdos">ones</a> that are directly about graphs: </p>
<ol>
<li>The Erdős-Faber-Lovász conjecture on coloring unions of cliques.
</li><li>The Erdős-Hajnal conjecture that in a family of graphs defined by an excluded induced subgraph, every graph has either a large clique or a large independent set.
</li></ol>
<p>Of course math is tricky: A conjecture like the—</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Erdős-Szekeres conjecture on the number of points needed to ensure that a point set contains a large convex polygon. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>—could still be about graphs. Consider the graph that is <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\dots}"/></p>
<p>
Well, the conjecture (1) is now claimed to be solved, and so the list of open conjectures is one less. Kühn with co-authors Dong Yeap Kang, Tom Kelly, Abhishek Methuku, and Deryk Osthus have claimed to resolve it. I have no reason to doubt these top researchers—it’s just until it is refereed. Their <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2101.04698.pdf">paper</a> is cleverly titled: A Proof Of The Erdős-Faber-Lovász Conjecture. </p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/19/closing-an-erdos-problem/five/" rel="attachment wp-att-18401"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-18401" height="259" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/five.png?resize=388%2C259&amp;ssl=1" width="388"/></a></p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em>  By the way: See this <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/epcwebinar/">talk</a> on the paper by Kühn’s co-author Abhishek Methuku on this coming Monday March 22, 2021, 14:00 UTC. To see the talk on zoom you need to know the first six primes. Here is some help: </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/19/closing-an-erdos-problem/primes/" rel="attachment wp-att-18402"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-18402" height="187" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/primes.png?resize=269%2C187&amp;ssl=1" width="269"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
This conjecture, now almost 50 years old, states that a graph that consists of complete graphs of size <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> that barely overlap can be colored with <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> colors. Here barely overlap is they have no edge in common. </p>
<p>
That is: If <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{k}"/> complete graphs, each having exactly <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{k}"/> vertices, have the property that every pair of complete graphs has at most one shared vertex, then the union of the graphs can be properly colored with <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{k}"/> colors. The following picture should help you understand the conjecture:</p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/19/closing-an-erdos-problem/cj/" rel="attachment wp-att-18403"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-18403" height="418" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/cj.png?resize=390%2C418&amp;ssl=1" width="390"/></a></p>
<p>
The conjecture can be stated various ways:<br/>
<img alt="{\bullet}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\bullet}"/> If <img alt="{A_1,\dots, A_n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA_1%2C%5Cdots%2C+A_n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{A_1,\dots, A_n}"/> are sets of size <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> such that every pair of them shares at most one element, then the elements of each <img alt="{A_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{A_i}"/> can be colored by <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> colors so that all colors appear in each <img alt="{A_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{A_i}"/>.<br/>
<img alt="{\bullet}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\bullet}"/> If H is a linear hypergraph with <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> vertices, then the chromatic index of <img alt="{H}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BH%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{H}"/> is at most <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/>.</p>
<p>
The chromatic index of a hypergraph <img alt="{H}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BH%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{H}"/> is the smallest number of colors needed to color the edges of <img alt="{H}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BH%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{H}"/> so that any two edges that share a vertex have different colors.</p>
<p/><h2> Previous Results </h2><p/>
<p>
While Kühn’s paper solves the conjecture, there were many partial results before. These prefer to view the conjecture as one about hypergraphs. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> A linear hypergraph (also known as partial linear space) is a hypergraph with the property that every two hyperedges have at most one vertex in common. A hypergraph is said to be uniform if all of its hyperedges have the same number of vertices as each other. The <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> cliques of size <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> in the Erdős-Faber-Lovász conjecture may be interpreted as the hyperedges of an <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/>-uniform linear hypergraph that has the same vertices as the underlying graph. In this language, the Erdős-Faber-Lovász conjecture states that, given any <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/>-uniform linear hypergraph with <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> hyperedges, one may <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/>-color the vertices such that each hyperedge has one vertex of each color.</em></p><em>
</em><p><em>
A simple hypergraph is a hypergraph in which at most one hyperedge connects any pair of vertices and there are no hyperedges of size at most one. In the graph coloring formulation of the Erdős-Faber-Lovász conjecture, it is safe to remove vertices that belong to a single clique, as their coloring presents no difficulty; once this is done, the hypergraph that has a vertex for each clique, and a hyperedge for each graph vertex, forms a simple hypergraph. And, the hypergraph dual of vertex coloring is edge coloring. Thus, the Erdős-Faber-Lovász conjecture is equivalent to the statement that any simple hypergraph with <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> vertices has chromatic index (edge coloring number) at most <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\bullet }"/> William Chang and Gene Lawler in their <a href="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007/BF02126801.pdf">paper</a> proved one of the first bounds. The goal is <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> and they prove <img alt="{3/2n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B3%2F2n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{3/2n}"/>. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Call a hypergraph simple if for any pair <img alt="{u, v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%2C+v%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{u, v}"/> of distinct vertices, there is at most one edge incident to both <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{u}"/> and <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{v}"/>, and there are no edges incident to exactly one vertex. A conjecture of Erdős, Faber and Lovász is equivalent to the statement that the edges of any simple hypergraph on <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> vertices can be colored with at most <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> colors. We present a simple proof that the edges of a simple hypergraph on <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> vertices can be colored with at most <img alt="{3/2n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B3%2F2n%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{3/2n}"/> colors. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\bullet }"/> Jeff Kahn showed that the bound could be improved to <img alt="{n + o(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn+%2B+o%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n + o(n)}"/> colors in this <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/009731659290096D?via%3Dihub">paper</a>.</p>
<p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>
See Gil Kalai for his wonderful <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/01/14/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-17-amazing-the-erdos-faber-lovasz-conjecture-for-large-n-was-proved-by-dong-yeap-kang-tom-kelly-daniela-kuhn-abhishek-methuku-and-deryk-osthus/">comments</a> on this paper of Kühn and her co-authors.</p>
<p>
Of course we <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/17/science/abel-prize-mathematics.html">congratulate</a> Laci <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-00694-9">plus</a> Avi Wigderson on winning the <a href="https://www.abelprize.no/">2021 Abel Prize</a>.  We will write more about this in an upcoming post.</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-19T22:23:42Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-19T22:23:42Z</published>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="bounds"/>
    <category term="coloring"/>
    <category term="conjecture"/>
    <category term="Daniela Kuhn"/>
    <category term="Erdos conjecture"/>
    <category term="hypergraphs"/>
    <category term="Proof"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/043</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/043" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-043 |  Promise Problems Meet Pseudodeterminism | 

	Peter Dixon, 

	A.  Pavan, 

	N. V. Vinodchandran</title>
    <summary>The  Acceptance Probability Estimation Problem (APEP) is to additively approximate the acceptance probability of a Boolean circuit. This problem admits a probabilistic approximation scheme. A central question is whether we can design a pseudodeterministic approximation algorithm for this problem: a probabilistic polynomial-time algorithm that outputs a canonical approximation with high probability. Recently, it was shown that such an algorithm would imply that every approximation algorithm can be made pseudodeterministic (Dixon, Pavan, Vinodchandran; (ITCS 2021).    

The main conceptual contribution of this work is to establish that the existence of a pseudodeterministic algorithm for APEP is fundamentally connected to the relationship between probabilistic promise classes and the corresponding standard complexity classes. In particular, we show the following equivalence:  every promise problem in PromiseBPP has a solution in BPP if and only if APEP has a pseudodeterministic algorithm. Based on this intuition, we show that pseudodeterministic algorithms for APEP  can shed light on a few central topics in complexity theory such as circuit lowerbounds, probabilistic hierarchy theorems, and multi-pseudodeterminism.</summary>
    <updated>2021-03-18T18:14:27Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-18T18:14:27Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4504</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2021/03/18/finally-a-joy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Finally, a joy</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Rome we have an expression, mai una gioia (literally, “never (a moment of) joy”) that applies well to the present times. Yesterday, there was, finally, something to be joyous about: the announcement that two of my heroes, Laszlo Lovasz … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2021/03/18/finally-a-joy/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In Rome we have an expression, <em>mai una gioia</em> (literally, “never (a moment of) joy”) that applies well to the present times. Yesterday, there was, finally, something to be joyous about: the announcement that two of my heroes, Laszlo Lovasz and Avi Wigderson, will share the 2021 Abel Prize, one of the highest honors of mathematics.</p>
<p>The reader can find a very good article about them on <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/avi-wigderson-and-laszlo-lovasz-win-abel-prize-20210317/">Quanta Magazine</a>.</p>
<p>Instead of talking about their greatest accomplishment, here I would like to recall two beautiful and somewhat related results, that admit a short treatment.</p>
<p><span id="more-4504"/></p>
<p>Avi’s first paper was on the 3-coloring problem. He described a polynomial time algorithm that, given a 3-colorable graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, finds a valid coloring of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> with <img alt="{O(\sqrt n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Csqrt+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> colors, where <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is the number of vertices. The starting point is that if every vertex in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> had degree <img alt="{\leq \sqrt n -1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cleq+%5Csqrt+n+-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> then there is an easy way to color the graph with <img alt="{\sqrt n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> colors (look at the vertices in any order, choose for each vertex a color not already used for the neighbors that have already been considered).</p>
<p>What if there is some vertex <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> of degree <img alt="{\geq \sqrt n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cgeq+%5Csqrt+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>? Well, and this is the idea of the paper, the <em>neighbors of <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> must induce a bipartite subgraph</em>, so we can color the neighbors of <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> with 2 colors in a way that is consistent with all the edges between neighbors of <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, then remove the neighbors of <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and continue with the rest of the graph, committing to never use those two colors again. Every time we do this, we consume two colors but we get rid of <img alt="{\geq \sqrt n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cgeq+%5Csqrt+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> vertices, so this costs us at most <img alt="{2\sqrt n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5Csqrt+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> colors. When we are done, all remaining vertices have degree <img alt="{\leq \sqrt n-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cleq+%5Csqrt+n-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and we just need <img alt="{\sqrt n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> more colors as observed above.</p>
<p>In total, we used at most <img alt="{3\sqrt n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B3%5Csqrt+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> colors.</p>
<p>This remained the state of the art for approximate graph coloring for a few years, until Avrim Blum improved the bound for 3-colorable graphs to <img alt="{O(n^{0.4})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E%7B0.4%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and then to <img alt="{O(n^{3/8})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E%7B3%2F8%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> colors, using more sophisticated combinatorial arguments. Later, Karger, Motwani and Sudan devised an approximation algorithm that uses <img alt="{\tilde O(n^{1/4})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctilde+O%28n%5E%7B1%2F4%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> colors to color 3-colorable graphs, and is based on a semidefinite programming relaxation of the coloring problem, which is related to the Lovasz <em>theta function</em>. It is still open whether there is a polynomial time algorithm that uses <img alt="{n^{o(1)}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7Bo%281%29%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> colors.</p>
<p>The Lovasz theta function <img alt="{\theta (G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctheta+%28G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> of a graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is a convex relaxation of the maximum independent set problem in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. It is, or it can be formulated as, a semidefinite programming relaxation of the maximum independent set problem, and so it can be computed (up to arbitrarily good accuracy) in polynomial time.</p>
<p>Lovasz defined the theta function to study the <em>Shannon capacity of a graph</em>. This is a question that arises when one wants to find error-correcting codes for a channel that may introduce errors. Suppose that the channel carries an element of an alphabet <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> of size <img alt="{n=|V|}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%3D%7CV%7C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, and that certain pairs of alphabet elements can be “confused” by the channel, meaning that for certain pairs <img alt="{\{ a,b \}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%7B+a%2Cb+%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> the channel may output <img alt="{b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> given <img alt="{a}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> or viceversa. If we construct the graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> whose vertex set is <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and whose edges are the pairs of “confusable” pairs, then an independent set in this graph gives a set of length-1 codewords that are not confusable, and <img alt="{\log_2 \alpha(G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog_2+%5Calpha%28G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, where <img alt="{\alpha(G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%28G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is the size of a maximal independent set in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, is the number of bits that we can transmit in an errorless way by making one use of the channel. If we can access the channel <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> times, then an errorless code is an independent set in <img alt="{G^k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%5Ek%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, the graph that has vertex set <img alt="{V^k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%5Ek%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and such that <img alt="{((a_1,\ldots,a_k),(b_1,\ldots,b_k))}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28%28a_1%2C%5Cldots%2Ca_k%29%2C%28b_1%2C%5Cldots%2Cb_k%29%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is an edge if and only if all the pairs <img alt="{(a_i,b_i)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28a_i%2Cb_i%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> are edges of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. The number of bits of information per channel use that we can send is</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \frac 1k \log \alpha(G^k) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cfrac+1k+%5Clog+%5Calpha%28G%5Ek%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p> and so we are interested in</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \lim_{k\rightarrow \infty} (\alpha (G^k))^{1/k} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Clim_%7Bk%5Crightarrow+%5Cinfty%7D+%28%5Calpha+%28G%5Ek%29%29%5E%7B1%2Fk%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p> Nicely, we have</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \theta (G^k) = (\theta(G))^k " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Ctheta+%28G%5Ek%29+%3D+%28%5Ctheta%28G%29%29%5Ek+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p> so we have</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \theta(G) \geq \lim_{k\rightarrow \infty} (\alpha (G^k))^{1/k} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Ctheta%28G%29+%5Cgeq+%5Clim_%7Bk%5Crightarrow+%5Cinfty%7D+%28%5Calpha+%28G%5Ek%29%29%5E%7B1%2Fk%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p> and the theta function provides an upper bound to the Shannon capacity of a graph.</p>
<p>If we compute <img alt="{\theta (\bar G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctheta+%28%5Cbar+G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, where <img alt="{\bar G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbar+G%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is the complement of the graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> (that is, the graph whose edges are all the non-edges of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>), then we see that <img alt="{\theta(\bar G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctheta%28%5Cbar+G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is a relaxation of the maximum clique problem in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. Remarkably, <img alt="{\theta(\bar G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctheta%28%5Cbar+G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is also a <em>lower bound</em> to the chromatic number of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, and so it is <em>sandwiched</em> between the clique number and the chromatic number. Don Knuth has used this fact as a starting point for a wonderful <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/math/9312214">49-page treatise</a> on convex relaxations of the chromatic number and the clique number; here we will see a quick proof of this fact.</p>
<p>As you can see in Knuth’s survey, there are several equivalent ways to define the theta function. Below we define <img alt="{\theta(\bar G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctheta%28%5Cbar+G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> as a natural semidefinite programming relaxation of the maximum clique problem (we have a variable <img alt="{x_0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> plus one variable <img alt="{x_v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_v%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for every vertex <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>; all variables are vectors).</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \begin{array}{lr} \max \sum_{v\in V} || x_v||^2\\ s.t.\\ ||x_0||^2 = 1\\ \langle x_0,x_v \rangle = ||x_v||^2 &amp; \forall v\in V\\ \langle x_u,x_v \rangle = 0 &amp; \forall u\neq v: (u,v) \not\in E\\ \end{array}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Blr%7D+%5Cmax+%5Csum_%7Bv%5Cin+V%7D+%7C%7C+x_v%7C%7C%5E2%5C%5C+s.t.%5C%5C+%7C%7Cx_0%7C%7C%5E2+%3D+1%5C%5C+%5Clangle+x_0%2Cx_v+%5Crangle+%3D+%7C%7Cx_v%7C%7C%5E2+%26+%5Cforall+v%5Cin+V%5C%5C+%5Clangle+x_u%2Cx_v+%5Crangle+%3D+0+%26+%5Cforall+u%5Cneq+v%3A+%28u%2Cv%29+%5Cnot%5Cin+E%5C%5C+%5Cend%7Barray%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>To see that it is a relaxation, given a clique <img alt="{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, let <img alt="{x_0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> be any unit vector, and let <img alt="{x_v = x_0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_v+%3D+x_0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for <img alt="{v\in K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%5Cin+K%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and <img alt="{x_v = {\bf 0}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_v+%3D+%7B%5Cbf+0%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for <img alt="{v\not\in K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%5Cnot%5Cin+K%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. We satisfy all constraints and the objective function is <img alt="{|K|}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CK%7C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.</p>
<p>If we write the semidefinite dual of the above relaxation, we can see that we get a minimization problem which is a relaxation of the chromatic number problem (and which is equivalent to the relaxation used by Karger, Motwani and Sudan to improve on Avi’s result on 3-coloring), so that the “sandwich theorem” follows from weak duality.</p>
<p>The reader should try to write down the semidefinite dual and reason about why it relaxes the chromatic number problem. Below, we collapse the construction of the dual, the way of embedding colorings into dual solutions, and the proof of weak duality for semidefinite programming, into a short but mystifying “sum of squares” proof.</p>
<p>Suppose that <img alt="{V = \{ v_1,\ldots,v_n \}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV+%3D+%5C%7B+v_1%2C%5Cldots%2Cv_n+%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and let <img alt="{x_0,x_{v_1},\ldots,x_{v_n}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_0%2Cx_%7Bv_1%7D%2C%5Cldots%2Cx_%7Bv_n%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> be a feasible solution to the max clique relaxation defined above. Suppose that the graph is <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-colorable and let <img alt="{(C_1,\ldots,C_k)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28C_1%2C%5Cldots%2CC_k%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> be a partition of <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> into color classes. We have</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  0 \leq \sum_{i=1}^k \left \| -x_0 + \sum_{v\in C_i} x_v \right \|^2 " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++0+%5Cleq+%5Csum_%7Bi%3D1%7D%5Ek+%5Cleft+%5C%7C+-x_0+%2B+%5Csum_%7Bv%5Cin+C_i%7D+x_v+%5Cright+%5C%7C%5E2+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  = \sum_{i=1}^k \left( || x_0||^2 - 2 \sum_{v\in C_i} \langle x_0 , x_v \rangle + \sum_{u,v \in C_i} \langle x_u, x_v\rangle \right) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%3D+%5Csum_%7Bi%3D1%7D%5Ek+%5Cleft%28+%7C%7C+x_0%7C%7C%5E2+-+2+%5Csum_%7Bv%5Cin+C_i%7D+%5Clangle+x_0+%2C+x_v+%5Crangle+%2B+%5Csum_%7Bu%2Cv+%5Cin+C_i%7D+%5Clangle+x_u%2C+x_v%5Crangle+%5Cright%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  = \sum_{i=1}^k \left( 1 - \sum_{v\in C_i} || x_v||^2 \right) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%3D+%5Csum_%7Bi%3D1%7D%5Ek+%5Cleft%28+1+-+%5Csum_%7Bv%5Cin+C_i%7D+%7C%7C+x_v%7C%7C%5E2+%5Cright%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  = k - \sum_{v\in V} ||x_v||^2 " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%3D+k+-+%5Csum_%7Bv%5Cin+V%7D+%7C%7Cx_v%7C%7C%5E2+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p> so that the objective function always satisfies</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \sum_{v\in V} ||x_v||^2 \leq k " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Csum_%7Bv%5Cin+V%7D+%7C%7Cx_v%7C%7C%5E2+%5Cleq+k+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p> In particular, this is true for an optimal solution <img alt="{x_0,x_{v_1},\ldots,x_{v_k}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_0%2Cx_%7Bv_1%7D%2C%5Cldots%2Cx_%7Bv_k%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and for an optimal coloring, so we have that <img alt="{\theta(\bar G)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctheta%28%5Cbar+G%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is upper bounded by the chromatic number of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> as promised.</p>
<p>Above, we used various properties of feasible solutions, such as <img alt="{||x_0||^2 = 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7C%7Cx_0%7C%7C%5E2+%3D+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, <img alt="{\langle x_0, x_v \rangle = ||x_v||^2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clangle+x_0%2C+x_v+%5Crangle+%3D+%7C%7Cx_v%7C%7C%5E2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \sum_{u,v \in C_i } \langle x_u , x_v \rangle = \sum_{v\in C_i} || x_v||^2 " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Csum_%7Bu%2Cv+%5Cin+C_i+%7D+%5Clangle+x_u+%2C+x_v+%5Crangle+%3D+%5Csum_%7Bv%5Cin+C_i%7D+%7C%7C+x_v%7C%7C%5E2+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p> which follows from the fact that each color class is an independent set, and so all inner products <img alt="{\langle x_u, x_v \rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clangle+x_u%2C+x_v+%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for <img alt="{u,v \in C_i, u\neq v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%2Cv+%5Cin+C_i%2C+u%5Cneq+v%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> have to be equal to zero, because <img alt="{(u,v) \not\in E}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28u%2Cv%29+%5Cnot%5Cin+E%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-18T13:22:19Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-18T13:22:19Z</published>
    <category term="math"/>
    <category term="theory"/>
    <category term="things that are excellent"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/03/18/professor-at-tu-hamburg-apply-by-april-29-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/03/18/professor-at-tu-hamburg-apply-by-april-29-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Professor at TU Hamburg (apply by April 29, 2021)</title>
    <summary>TU Hamburg invites applications for a professorship (assistant professorship/W1 with tenure track to full professorship/W3) in Theoretical Computer Science. The focus is on logic and computability, models and algorithms for new computing architectures (cloud, in-memory, fine-grained complexity and others), model theory and game theory in verification, algorithmic foundations of quantum computing. Website: https://stellenportal.tuhh.de/jobposting/a25baa5724882150161c93dc5ad0f48777de95ad Email: berufungen@tuhh.de</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>TU Hamburg invites applications for a professorship (assistant professorship/W1 with tenure track to full professorship/W3) in Theoretical Computer Science. The focus is on logic and computability, models and algorithms for new computing architectures (cloud, in-memory, fine-grained complexity and others), model theory and game theory in verification, algorithmic foundations of quantum computing.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://stellenportal.tuhh.de/jobposting/a25baa5724882150161c93dc5ad0f48777de95ad">https://stellenportal.tuhh.de/jobposting/a25baa5724882150161c93dc5ad0f48777de95ad</a><br/>
Email: berufungen@tuhh.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-18T08:43:25Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-18T08:43:25Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5388</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5388" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5388#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5388" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Abel to win</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Many of you will have seen the happy news today that Avi Wigderson and László Lovász share this year’s Abel Prize (which now contends with the Fields Medal for the highest award in pure math). This is only the second time that the Abel Prize has been given wholly or partly for work in theoretical […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Many of you will have seen the happy news today that Avi Wigderson and László Lovász <a href="https://www.abelprize.no/c76389/seksjon/vis.html?tid=76390&amp;strukt_tid=76389">share this year’s Abel Prize</a> (which now contends with the Fields Medal for the highest award in pure math).  This is only the second time that the Abel Prize has been given wholly or partly for work in theoretical computer science, after <a href="https://www.abelprize.no/c54147/seksjon/vis.html?tid=54148">Szemerédi</a> in 2012.  See also the articles in <em><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/avi-wigderson-and-laszlo-lovasz-win-abel-prize-20210317/">Quanta</a></em> or the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/17/science/abel-prize-mathematics.html">NYT</a>, which actually say most of what I would’ve said for a lay audience about Wigderson’s and Lovász’s most famous research results and their importance (except, no, Avi hasn’t <em>yet</em> proved P=BPP, just taken some major steps toward it…).</p>



<p>On a personal note, Avi was both my and my wife Dana’s postdoctoral advisor at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton.  He’s been an <em>unbelievably</em> important mentor to both of us, as he’s been for dozens of others in the CS theory community.  Back in 2007, I also had the privilege of working closely with Avi for months on our <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/papers/alg.pdf">Algebrization</a> paper.  Now would be a fine time to revisit <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=2925">Avi’s Permanent Impact on Me</a> (or <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BLxC3rGeWBI">watch the YouTube video</a>), which is the talk I gave at IAS in 2016 on the occasion of Avi’s 60th birthday.</p>



<p>Huge congratulations to both Avi and László!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-18T03:19:46Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-18T03:19:46Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2021-03-22T23:54:23Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-9101842177146636334</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/9101842177146636334/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/i-read-news-today-oh-boy.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/9101842177146636334" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/9101842177146636334" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/i-read-news-today-oh-boy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>I read the news today oh boy</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p/><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-NMc_aH4Gb9o/YFJR2J9R5BI/AAAAAAAB61M/Mez6sk3EWO4mP5AZxnxUM_JszhYdaNZvACLcBGAsYHQ/s400/lovasz.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="150" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-NMc_aH4Gb9o/YFJR2J9R5BI/AAAAAAAB61M/Mez6sk3EWO4mP5AZxnxUM_JszhYdaNZvACLcBGAsYHQ/w200-h150/lovasz.jpg" width="200"/></a><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PzuRktxYKx4/YFJR4Z5NBrI/AAAAAAAB61Q/imp2GYxDJWwYxffkU9deF93T3-lA7m-ZgCLcBGAsYHQ/s260/avi.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="149" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PzuRktxYKx4/YFJR4Z5NBrI/AAAAAAAB61Q/imp2GYxDJWwYxffkU9deF93T3-lA7m-ZgCLcBGAsYHQ/w200-h149/avi.jpg" width="200"/></a></div></div><br/><br/>I'm absolutely elated that <a href="https://www.abelprize.no/c76389/seksjon/vis.html?tid=76390&amp;strukt_tid=76389">Lázló Lovász and Avi Wigderson won the Abel Prize</a>. More from the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/17/science/abel-prize-mathematics.html">New York Times</a>, <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/avi-wigderson-and-laszlo-lovasz-win-abel-prize-20210317/">Quanta Magazine</a> and <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/03/17/cheerful-news-in-difficult-times-the-abel-prize-is-awarded-to-laszlo-lovasz-and-avi-wigderson/">Gil Kalai</a>. Another example of how complexity theory and theoretical computer science has reached the upper echelons of mathematics.<p/><p>I'm horrified of the <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/3-dead-shooting-georgia-massage-parlor-suspect-loose-n1261262">spa shootings in Atlanta</a>. I've driven by those spas many times when I lived there. </p><p>I'm saddened by the <a href="https://www.mills.edu/announcement/index.php">closing of Mills College</a> in Oakland, California. I lived in a dorm Berkeley rented at Mills College during my <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2006/04/one-miserable-year.html">crazy year there</a>.</p><p>I've got mixed emotions about the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/17/obituaries/james-levine-dead.html">death of James Levine</a>. What he did musically with the Metropolitan opera and orchestra was nothing short of incredible. What he did to the young people he abused is inexcusable. I remember watching a Met taped videocast of Die Walküre with my daughter, enjoying the production but telling her "Do you realize we are watching an opera composed by an anti-Semite and conducted by a child molester?"  Can you separate art from artist?</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-17T19:57:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-17T19:57:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T13:22:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=21437</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/03/17/cheerful-news-in-difficult-times-the-abel-prize-is-awarded-to-laszlo-lovasz-and-avi-wigderson/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4" length="3587596664" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <link href="http://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4" length="2392494292" rel="enclosure" type="video/mp4"/>
    <title>Cheerful News in Difficult Times: The Abel Prize is Awarded to László Lovász and Avi Wigderson</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Abel Prize was awarded earlier today to László Lovász and Avi Wigderson “for their foundational contributions to theoretical computer science and discrete mathematics, and their leading role in shaping them into central fields of modern mathematics.” Congratulations to Laci … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/03/17/cheerful-news-in-difficult-times-the-abel-prize-is-awarded-to-laszlo-lovasz-and-avi-wigderson/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/laci-avi.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone  wp-image-21421" height="360" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/laci-avi.png?w=640" width="521"/></a></p>
<p>The Abel Prize was awarded earlier today to László Lovász and Avi Wigderson</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><em>“for their foundational contributions to theoretical computer science and discrete </em><em>mathematics, and their leading role in shaping them into central fields of modern </em><em>mathematics.”</em></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Congratulations to Laci and Avi, to their families, and to the communities of theoretical computer science and combinatorics. Let me quote one more sentence from the citation:</p>
<blockquote><p><span style="color: #993366;"><em>“They have both made fundamental contributions to understanding randomness in computation and in exploring the boundaries of efficient computation.” </em></span></p></blockquote>
<p>For the full citation and more material see<a href="https://www.abelprize.no/"> the Abel Prize page</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/lw12.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-21434" height="450" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/lw12.jpg" width="600"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Avi and Laci, Oslo 2012. (source, Oberwolfach pictures)</span></p>
<p>Both Avi and Laci are frequently mentioned over my blog. The post <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2009/12/06/four-derandomization-problems/">Four derandomization problems</a> is related to both. Here are a few posts on Laci: <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/02/05/extremal-combinatorics-v-posets/">Posets and the perfect graph theorem</a>; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2018/07/15/building-bridges-ii-and-rio-icm-2018/">Building bridges II</a>; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2010/10/15/mabruk-elon-india-and-more/">ICM2010</a>; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/12/25/lovaszs-two-families-theorem/">Laci’s theorem about two families of sets (and subspaces);</a> <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/08/13/plans-and-updates/">Building bridges I</a>. On Avi: <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2012/01/20/fractional-sylvester-gallai/">Fractional Sylvester Gallai</a>; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2016/07/07/avifest-avistories-and-amazing-cash-prizes/">Avifest 1</a>; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2017/09/27/layish/">Layish</a>; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2017/10/27/must-read-book-by-avi-wigderson/" rel="bookmark">Must-read book by Avi Wigderson</a> ;<a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/04/avi-wigdersons-integrating-computational-modeling-algorithms-and-complexity-into-theories-of-nature-marks-a-new-scientific-revolution-an-invitation-for-a-discussion/" rel="bookmark">Avi Wigderson’s: “Integrating computational modeling, algorithms, and complexity into theories of nature, marks a new scientific revolution!” (An invitation for a discussion.)</a> There were also two posts on conjectures by Laci that were recently solved (almost completely): The <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/01/14/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-17-amazing-the-erdos-faber-lovasz-conjecture-for-large-n-was-proved-by-dong-yeap-kang-tom-kelly-daniela-kuhn-abhishek-methuku-and-deryk-osthus/">EFL conjecture</a> and the <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/12/21/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-15-yuansi-chen-achieved-a-major-breakthrough-on-bourgains-slicing-problem-and-the-kannan-lovasz-and-simonovits-conjecture/">KLS conjecture</a>.</p>
<p>I will not write today about computer science or mathematics but rather I will show you some pictures and give some links. (I will add most of the pictures later today.)</p>
<p>Here is the link to <a href="https://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/">Building bridges II Laci’s 70th birthday conference</a>. There were lectures  by Noga Alon on <a href="https://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Alon.mp4">Lovász, vectors, graphs and codes</a>, by Lex Schrijver  <a href="https://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Schrijver.mp4">On ϑ and Θ</a> by Jennifer Chayes on <a href="https://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Jennifer Chayes - Graphons and Graphexes as Limits of Sparse Graphs.mp4">Graphons and Graphexes as Limits of Sparse Graphs</a>, by Santosh Vempala <a href="https://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Santosh Vempala - With or Without KLS.mp4">With or Without KLS</a> by Avi Wigderson <a href="https://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Avi Wigderson - Mathematics and Computation.mp4">Mathematics and Computation (through the lens of one problem and one algorithm)</a> by Eva Tardos on <a href="https://www.renyi.hu/conferences/ll70/program/videos/Eva Tardos - Small-loss bounds for online learning with partial information.mp4">Small-loss bounds for online learning with partial information</a> and many other inspiring lectures. (I linked here lectures directly related to Laci’s work.)</p>
<p>And here is a link to Avi’s 60th birthday conference: <a href="https://www.ias.edu/ideas/2016/avi-wigderson-60"><span class="field field--name-title field--type-string field--label-hidden">Avi Wigderson Is 60: A Celebration of Mathematics and Computer Science</span></a> with lectures by Noga Alon on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JV6-9ANYmN4" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Avi, Graphs, and Communication</a>, by Dorit Aharonov on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dnvDLyuLX08" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Quantum Physics and the Computational Lens</a> by Shafi Goldwasser on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ggEpvIziK2M" rel="noopener" target="_blank">New Pseudo-deterministic Algorithms</a>, by Nati Linial on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fGYkumoO4v0" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Transitions and Phase Transitions</a> by Alex Lubotzky on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=86ZW6h93jMI" rel="noopener" target="_blank">High Dimensional Expanders</a>, by Laci Lovasz on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dqQmlYC-Khc" rel="noopener" target="_blank">What is generic? </a>and also by Eyal Wigderson on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=immobLNNP28" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Brains are Better Computers than Computers</a> and by Einat Wigderson and me on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pMAAo3wlNCM" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Happy Days,</a> and many other inspiring talks.</p>
<p>(Update 1) Links: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/03/17/science/abel-prize-mathematics.html">NYT</a> (Kenneth Chang), <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/avi-wigderson-and-laszlo-lovasz-win-abel-prize-20210317">Quanta Magazine</a> (Kevin Hartnett), (and many other places); blogs:  <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2021/03/18/finally-a-joy/">In theory</a> (Finally, a joy), <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/i-read-news-today-oh-boy.html">Computational Complexity</a> (Ohh Boy), <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5388">Shtetl Optimized</a>, <a href="https://igorpak.wordpress.com/2021/03/17/2021-abel-prize/">Igor Pak.</a> Luca’s <a>post</a> describes very nicely how early results of Laci and Avi interlace. (Update 2) <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/26/congrats-avi-and-laci-on-the-abel-prize/">A very nice post on GLL</a> featuring Dorit Aharonov as the post’s “saint patron”, and connections to people and papers of quantum computation.</p>
<p>Trivia questions:</p>
<p>Who are these people? (1,2,3,4,5)</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/baodnn.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-21430" height="151" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/baodnn.png" width="441"/></a></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/posa-laczkovich-lovasz-berkes.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-21431" height="212" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/posa-laczkovich-lovasz-berkes.jpg?w=300" width="300"/></a></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/1966-vk-ll.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-21443" height="288" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/1966-vk-ll.jpg?w=211" width="203"/></a></p>
<p><img alt="NA" class="alignnone wp-image-21464" height="201" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/na-1.png" width="342"/></p>
<p><span id="more-21437"/></p>
<p><img alt="avi-noga-nurit-edna-king" class="alignnone wp-image-21466" height="307" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/avi-noga-nurit-edna-king.png" width="523"/></p>
<p>Who is in the picture?</p>
<p><strong>Answers:</strong> 1) (Graduating from the Technion) Baruch Schieber, Avi, Oded Goldreich, and David Peleg. 2) (Highschool (?) Lajos Posa, Miklós Laczkovich, Laci, and István Berkes 3) Kati and Laci 4) Noga and Avi (high school) 5) Avi showing in Noga’s birthday conference pictures of him and Noga in their casual dress and of King Harald, Nurit, and Edna.</p>
<p>Another trivia question: In what sense do both Laci’s and Avi’s youngest sons have the same father?  <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/220px-jacob_fox_cropped.jpg?resize=214%2C214"><img alt="220px-Jacob_fox_(cropped)" class="alignnone  wp-image-21494" height="104" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/220px-jacob_fox_cropped.jpg" width="92"/></a></p>
<p>Laci himself was a Ph. D. Student of Tibor Gallai and Avi’s Ph D advisor was Dick Lipton.</p>
<p>Now, let me share with you some family pictures.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/avi-tamar.jpeg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-21439" height="480" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/avi-tamar.jpeg" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>Avi with his oldest granddaughter Tamar</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/ll-and-family-1993.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-21440" height="341" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/ll-and-family-1993.jpg" width="520"/></a></p>
<p>Laci, Kati and their children 1993</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/e77.jpeg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-21442" height="427" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/e77.jpeg" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>Yuval, Avi, Einat, Edna, Tamar and Eyal</p>
<p>.<a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/avis-parents-e1615843824596.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-21415" height="763" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/avis-parents-e1615843824596.jpg?w=576" width="429"/></a></p>
<p>Avi’s parants</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/avihagai.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-21475" height="592" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/avihagai.png" width="434"/></a></p>
<p>Avi with my son Hagai</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/laci-dedication.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-21413" height="340" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/laci-dedication.png?w=640" width="471"/></a></p>
<p>Me with two recent books written by Lovasz. Top left, the dedication: “to Kati as all my books”.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/lacikati2.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-21424" height="480" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/lacikati2.jpg?w=640" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><img alt="Calgary2006" class="alignnone  wp-image-21498" height="525" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/calgary2006.jpg" width="379"/></p>
<p>Laci and Kati</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/aviw.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-21418" height="334" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/aviw.jpg?w=640" width="593"/></a></p>
<p>Both Avi’s parents were holocaust’s survivor. On the wall of his study there are pictures of family members who did not survive.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/baod.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-21423" height="177" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/baod.png" width="445"/></a></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/avi-book-cover.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-21426" height="484" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/avi-book-cover.png" width="355"/></a></p>
<p>The cover of Avi’s recent book. The book is available freely here <a href="https://www.math.ias.edu/avi/book" rel="nofollow">https://www.math.ias.edu/avi/book</a> !</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/bird.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-21428" height="540" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/bird.jpg" width="403"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Intermission: a beautiful bird</span></p>
<h2>More pictures</h2>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/hd.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone  wp-image-21476" height="339" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/hd.png?w=640" width="542"/></a></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/trip1.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone  wp-image-21477" height="361" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/trip1.png?w=640" width="511"/></a></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/1999-wolfprize.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-21453" height="426" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/1999-wolfprize.jpg?w=640" width="581"/></a></p>
<p>Above: Laci with the president of Israel, below Avi with the president of Switzerland</p>
<p><img alt="1994" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-21463" height="368" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/1994-1.png" width="450"/></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/ll-and-vera-sos.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-21454" height="400" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/ll-and-vera-sos.jpg" width="386"/></a></p>
<p>Laci with Vera Sós. Vera is Laci’s academic mother in law. Katalin Vesztergombi (Kati) was a Ph.D student of Vera Sós. Laci, Kati, and Vera were part of the early graph limits team from around 2005 in the happy summer days of MSR Redmond.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/lovasz-bme2002c.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-21455" height="361" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/lovasz-bme2002c.jpg?w=640" width="518"/></a></p>
<p><img alt="tkla" class="alignnone wp-image-21459" height="381" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/tkla.jpg" width="508"/></p>
<p>Laci, Kati, Noga Alon, and Terry Tao</p>
<p><img alt="AYE" class="alignnone wp-image-21470" height="413" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/aye.jpeg" width="550"/></p>
<p>Avi, Edna and Yuval, below Avi and Eyal</p>
<p><img alt="AE" class="alignnone wp-image-21471" height="593" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/ae.jpeg" width="445"/></p>
<p>Avi Sahar Tamar and Einat</p>
<p><img alt="ASTE" class="alignnone wp-image-21472" height="353" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/03/aste-1.jpeg" width="470"/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-17T11:03:10Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-17T11:03:10Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Convexity"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <category term="Updates"/>
    <category term="Abel Prize"/>
    <category term="Avi Wigderson"/>
    <category term="L&#xE1;szl&#xF3; Lov&#xE1;sz"/>
    <category term="Niels Henrik Abel"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=18348</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/03/17/happy-st-patricks-day-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Happy St. Patrick’s Day 2021</title>
    <summary>May the best day of your past be the worst day of your future. Purchased from Etsy Neil L. is a Leprechaun. He has been visiting me or Ken once every year since we started GLL. We had never seen a leprechaun before we began the blog—there must be some connection. Today we want to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>May the best day of your past be the worst day of your future.</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/leprechaunwearingamask.png?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-18351" height="180" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/leprechaunwearingamask.png?resize=150%2C180&amp;ssl=1" width="150"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Purchased from <a href="https://www.etsy.com/listing/958877295/leprechaun-wearing-a-mask-funny-st">Etsy</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><font color="green"/></p><font color="green">
<p>
Neil L. is a Leprechaun. He has been visiting me or Ken once every year since we started GLL. We had never seen a leprechaun before we began the blog—there must be some connection.</p>
<p>
Today we want to share the experience we had with him this morning of St. Patrick’s Day.</p>
<p>
Here is my best reconstruction of what happened:</p>
<p>
It was Tuesday, already St. Patrick’s Day in Ireland, and Ken and I were on a Zoom connection working late. We had agreed to skip any post highlighting Neil. We intended to highlight another female mathematician or computer scientist. And Neil is definitely not a female.</p>
<p>
We never know in advance whether or when Neil is coming, but this time we took some steps. First, I am not where I was, and I made the <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2015/03/17/leprechauns-will-find-you/">finding</a> task harder. Kathryn set up mirrors in my new study, since leprechauns fear being held by a stare. Ken is where he’s always been, but being still a few days from his first vaccination, knew Neil would respect the CDC guidelines.</p>
<p>
We thought all was well and were discussing Hilbert’s Tenth until Ken spotted the puff of green smoke in a mirror behind me. Before he could warn me I heard the familiar voice to my side:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <i>Top of the evening to ye.</i> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
I might have let him take off his mask and get comfortable, but instead I retorted, “Neil, thanks for visiting, but Ken and I have other plans. This whole month is dedicated to honor female researchers. So nice to see you as always, but …”</p>
<p>
Neil smiled—we could tell that through his mask—and said:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Well, we could talk about a certain female Leprechaun—one who just solved a big problem in complexity. A problem that rhymes with “slower hounds in crime.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><h2> Neil’s Dilemma </h2><p/>
<p>
I was doubly confused: once by the cryptic rhyme, but then because I realized Neil—masked or not—was simply, provably <b>lying</b>. I hesitated to confront Neil because I recalled a <a href="https://www.pinterest.com/pin/274015958551660685/">book</a> titled <em>Leprechauns Never Lie</em>, but Ken flashed the proof by sharing his screen over Zoom:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “Neil, there <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/no-female-leprechauns_n_1355121">are no</a> female leprechauns. We all <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/03/16/leprechauns-go-universal/">discussed</a> this two St. Patrick’s Days ago. Quoting my link: <i>there is no record in Irish folklore of leprechauns having a female counterpart in their ranks or even a solid record of how they procreate or reproduce.</i>” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Ken and I realized there was more than just the truth or female researchers at stake: a leprechaun caught in transgression must surrender his treasure. <em>His</em> treasure. But that was bound to make Neil extra tricky.</p>
<p>
Neil was right on that wavelength, because his first words in reply were:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “Before we proceed, there is a matter about my pot of gold that we must resolve. And it will tie to the larger matter at hand. I need expert help, and ye be the two best I know to ask.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
<a href="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/pot.png?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-18352" height="120" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/pot.png?resize=120%2C120&amp;ssl=1" width="120"/></a></p>
<p>
What would Neil need to ask <em>us</em>? We had always tried to pin him down into telling us the answer to P=NP. Remember, a leprechaun cannot lie, so his answer would rule. So we said, “what do you need to ask?”</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “I need to ask you about the meaning of P=NP.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><h2> Neil’s Question </h2><p/>
<p>
I bid Neil sit down and remove his mask to puff his pipe. I started to give the same answer I’ve given in countless classrooms: “P=NP means that a certain big class of problems could all be solved by an algorithm that runs in polynomial time. Polynomial time means…” But Ken cut in more pointedly:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “Neil, why do <b>you</b> need to know about P=NP? And to know <b>what</b> about it?” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Neil puffed on his pipe and gave what we could tell was an honest answer:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “We Leprechauns have started thinking about going modern—belonging to the 21st century. I plan on getting rid of my pot of gold coins and going into Bitcoins. Those pots are heavy to lug for us wee folk. But to judge if it be safe in our world, we need to know the gist and risks in your world.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
I switched gears and said the gist is that Bitcoin is based on a technology called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blockchain">blockchain</a> that creates an unambiguous single history of recorded transactions, including how the coin was earned in the first place. The history does not need to be maintained by any trusted party—it is decentralized, and any party can access it to provide a proof of a record. Ah, but if P=NP…</p>
<p>
Ken cut in: “If P <em>effectively</em> equals NP. Not the <img alt="{n^{100}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7B100%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n^{100}}"/> time for SAT or the huge constants from forbidden-minor sets kind of P=NP. If you can be really efficient at it then you can spoof a proof of an alternative history of records, one to your gain, or certainly put confidence in the other side’s version of events in doubt. Actually, something weaker than P=NP suffices.” We were next going to educate Neil on crypto, but he cut us off.</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “We ken that </em>cheana féin<em>—well already. But what if your world have <b>no unambiguous single histories</b> to begin with? How déan that change the effective meaning of P=NP?” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><h2> Law and Lore </h2><p/>
<p>
The essence of Neil’s question escaped us at first. We replied that the notion of “history” involved was like a computation by a deterministic Turing machine <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{M}"/>, and time is uniquely defined by its sequence of configurations <img alt="{I \vdash_M J \vdash_M K \vdash_M\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BI+%5Cvdash_M+J+%5Cvdash_M+K+%5Cvdash_M%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{I \vdash_M J \vdash_M K \vdash_M\dots}"/> Ah, Neil replied, cannot there be a <img alt="{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{K}"/> that is reached by two separate paths, <img alt="{J \vdash_M K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BJ+%5Cvdash_M+K%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{J \vdash_M K}"/> and <img alt="{J' \vdash_M K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BJ%27+%5Cvdash_M+K%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{J' \vdash_M K}"/>? If you are at <img alt="{I}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BI%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{I}"/> and yet to go to <img alt="{J}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BJ%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{J}"/> you may have no inkling of <img alt="{J'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BJ%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{J'}"/> at present—your present.</p>
<p>
Ken cut in by saying that every computation can be performed by a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reversible_computing">reversible</a> Turing machine <img alt="{M'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{M'}"/>—so that there is only one possible past history—and that <img alt="{M'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{M'}"/> is built from <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{M}"/> by propagating part of the computation’s history somewhat as blockchain does. But that did not help our argument with Neil. When Ken brought up the reversibility of quantum computation, Neil was ready with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consistent_histories">Consistent Histories</a> interpretation of quantum mechanics. The determinism of quantum evolution is at a “bird’s eye” level higher up, whereas in our “frog’s eye” experience the theory gives us probabilities over alternative histories <img alt="{J}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BJ%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{J}"/> and <img alt="{J'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BJ%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{J'}"/>, and <i>consistency</i> rather than <i>unique actuality</i> is the criterion for their viability.</p>
<p>
At this point I started to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appeal_to_the_stone#Origin">kick a stone</a> at Neil about there being just one flesh-and-blood real world, with natural laws and a unique history, but his next words cut to the quick:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “On what basis then did ye dun me for speaking o’ female leprechauns? On the basis of <b>lore</b>, ye said. But is that as unchanging as the stone ye would kick at me?” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Ken got what Neil was saying and flashed a topical item on his Zoom screen:</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/lynettewukie.png?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-18353" height="245" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/lynettewukie.png?resize=550%2C245&amp;ssl=1" width="550"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
“This came <em>after</em> our discussion two years <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/03/16/leprechauns-go-universal/">ago</a>—in which you referenced Notre Dame—but maybe you are right that its significance is <em>before</em>.”</p>
<p>
I told Neil I still don’t agree about histories, but I withdrew our claim on his gold. Ken showed his face back on Zoom and was looking impatient so I gave him the floor.</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “What Neil is on about is that many things we’d consider aspects of Leprechaun World are really theorized properties of our world. So we must ask, what if they are just one world?</em></p><em>
<p>
Take Bitcoin. Now it’s obvious why Neil and friends want to get involved with Bitcoin. There are so many more ways to play tricks with it than with pots of physical gold. We wrote <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2020/03/17/leprechauns-stay-home/">last year</a> and <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2012/03/17/leprechauns-are-tricky/">many</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2017/03/17/leprechauns-are-multiplying/">times</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2016/03/17/happy-st-patricks-day-2/">before</a> about the gaming and crypto tricks they can play. </p>
</em><p><em>
But it’s nothing that we can’t do ourselves. So leprechauns make their pots of gold vanish? We’ve done that via Bitcoin <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/01/12/technology/bitcoin-passwords-wallets-fortunes.html">quite</a> to <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/01/15/uk-man-makes-last-ditch-effort-to-recover-lost-bitcoin-hard-drive.html">perfection</a>—hundreds of millions of dollars poof!, no leprechauns involved.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><h2> Neil’s Slower Hounds </h2><p/>
<p>
Ken was about to say that this was the larger context of Neil’s question about P=NP but I recalled the second thing Neil said at the start and wanted something in return for letting go his gold. “Neil—I can grant female leprechauns but you said something else: that one proved a breakthrough in complexity. You said it rhymed with “slower hounds in crime”—ah, <em>lower bounds on time</em>. Neil puffed and said, </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “Aye.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
“Can you tell us what she proved? We answered your question—and since you raised this to begin with, it’s only fair.” Ken chimed in by asking, “no one we know in our field is a leprechaun, right?”</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “I cannae tell ye in the here of now, for a reason that ye conceded to me. Ye will appreciate something from <img alt="{J'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BJ%27%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{J'}"/> when ye reach <img alt="{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{K}"/> from <img alt="{J}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BJ%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{J}"/>. So I shall leave ye do what ye be doing.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Neil turned as if about to wisp away, but a cry from me stopped him: “No final trick this time?” He gave us both a look that was sad and loving at the same time, something we didn’t know leprechauns could do. But he said,</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “No trick that ye not be increasingly doing by yourselves.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
And with that he departed in a flash. The flash kicked onto my screen where Ken still was. In Ken’s place was an image I recognized as from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayeux_Tapestry">Bayeux</a> <a href="http://www.hs-augsburg.de/~harsch/Chronologia/Lspost11/Bayeux/bay_tama.html">Tapestry</a>—that great record of history a millennium ago—until I looked a little closer.</p>
<p>
<a href="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/bayeuxmeme2.png?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-18355" height="254" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/bayeuxmeme2.png?resize=340%2C254&amp;ssl=1" width="340"/></a></p>
<p>
</p><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>
Happy St. Patrick’s Day 2021, and may happier days be ahead.</p>
<p/></font><p><font color="green"><br/>
[some word changes]<br/>
</font></p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-03-17T05:47:30Z</updated>
    <published>2021-03-17T05:47:30Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="trick"/>
    <category term="Bitcoin"/>
    <category term="crypto"/>
    <category term="diversity"/>
    <category term="histories"/>
    <category term="leprechauns"/>
    <category term="Lynnette Wukie"/>
    <category term="metaphysics"/>
    <category term="Neil L."/>
    <category term="St. Patrick's Day"/>
    <category term="time"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2021-04-01T16:20:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
