<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2021-12-05T11:22:30Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2021/12/05/quarterly-theory-workshop-2021-junior-theorists-workshop/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2021/12/05/quarterly-theory-workshop-2021-junior-theorists-workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quarterly Theory Workshop: 2021 Junior Theorists Workshop</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">December 9-10, 2021 Virtual(on Gather.Town) Please register here(free): (https://forms.gle/Kpqe4xBb9fAzGBX78) to get access to the Gather.town login information (we will send it the day before the event). https://theory.cs.northwestern.edu/events/2021-junior-theorists-workshop/ The 2021 Junior Theorists Workshop is part of the Northwestern CS Quarterly Theory Workshop Series. The focus of this workshop will be on junior researchers in all areas … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2021/12/05/quarterly-theory-workshop-2021-junior-theorists-workshop/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Quarterly Theory Workshop: 2021 Junior Theorists Workshop</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-05T00:16:58Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-05T00:16:58Z</published>
    <category term="workshop"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:56Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/173</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/173" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-173 |  On the Structure of Learnability beyond P/poly | 

	Ninad Rajgopal, 

	Rahul Santhanam</title>
    <summary>Motivated by the goal of showing stronger structural results about the complexity of learning, we study the learnability of strong concept classes beyond P/poly, such as PSPACE/poly and EXP/poly. We show the following:


1. (Unconditional Lower Bounds for Learning)  Building on [KKO13], we prove unconditionally that BPE/poly cannot be weakly learned in polynomial time over the uniform distribution, even with membership and equivalence queries.

2. (Robustness of Learning) For the concept classes EXP/poly and PSPACE/poly, we show unconditionally that worst-case and average-case learning are equivalent, that PAC-learnability and learnability over the uniform distribution are equivalent, and that membership queries do not help in either case.

3. (Reducing Succinct Search to Decision for Learning) For the decision problems $R_{Kt}$ and $R_{KS}$ capturing the complexity of learning EXP/poly and PSPACE/poly respectively, we show a succinct search to decision reduction: for each of these problems, the problem is in BPP iff there is a probabilistic polynomial-time algorithm computing circuits encoding proofs for positive instances of the problem. This is shown via a more general result giving succinct search to decision results for PSPACE, EXP and NEXP, which might be of independent interest. 

4. (Implausibility of Oblivious Strongly Black-Box Reductions showing NP-hardness of learning NP/poly) We define a natural notion of hardness of learning with respect to oblivious strongly black-box reductions. We show that learning PSPACE/poly is PSPACE-hard with respect to oblivious strongly black-box reductions. On the other hand, if learning NP/poly is NP-hard with respect to oblivious strongly black-box reductions, the Polynomial Hierarchy collapses.</summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T22:32:21Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-04T22:32:21Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/172</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/172" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-172 |  Ideals, Determinants, and Straightening: Proving and Using Lower Bounds for Polynomial Ideals | 

	Robert Andrews, 

	Michael Forbes</title>
    <summary>We show that any nonzero polynomial in the ideal generated by the $r \times r$ minors of an $n \times n$ matrix $X$ can be used to efficiently approximate the determinant. Specifically, for any nonzero polynomial $f$ in this ideal, we construct a small depth-three $f$-oracle circuit that approximates the $\Theta(r^{1/3}) \times \Theta(r^{1/3})$ determinant in the sense of border complexity. For many classes of algebraic circuits, this implies that every nonzero polynomial in the ideal generated by $r \times r$ minors is at least as hard to approximately compute as the $\Theta(r^{1/3}) \times \Theta(r^{1/3})$ determinant. We also prove an analogous result for the Pfaffian of a $2n \times 2n$ skew-symmetric matrix and the ideal generated by Pfaffians of $2r \times 2r$ principal submatrices.

This answers a recent question of Grochow about complexity in polynomial ideals in the setting of border complexity. Leveraging connections between the complexity of polynomial ideals and other questions in algebraic complexity, our results provide a generic recipe that allows lower bounds for the determinant to be applied to other problems in algebraic complexity. We give several such applications, two of which are highlighted below.
	
$\bullet$ We prove new lower bounds for the Ideal Proof System of Grochow and Pitassi. Specifically, we give super-polynomial lower bounds for refutations computed by low-depth circuits. This extends the recent breakthrough low-depth circuit lower bounds of Limaye, Srinivasan, and Tavenas to the setting of proof complexity. Moreover, we show that for many natural circuit classes, the approximative proof complexity of our hard instance is governed by the approximative circuit complexity of the determinant.

$\bullet$ We construct new hitting set generators for the closure of low-depth circuits. For any $\varepsilon &gt; 0$, we construct generators with seed length $O(n^\varepsilon)$ that hit $n$-variate low-depth circuits. Our generators attain a near-optimal tradeoff between their seed length and degree, and are computable by low-depth circuits of near-linear size (with respect to the size of their output). This matches the seed length of the generators recently obtained by Limaye, Srinivasan, and Tavenas, but improves on the degree and circuit complexity of the generator.</summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T22:20:07Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-04T22:20:07Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-87710198105679668</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/87710198105679668/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=87710198105679668" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/87710198105679668" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/87710198105679668" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2021/12/theoretics-new-open-access-journal-in.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TheoretiCS: A new open-access journal in Theoretical Computer Science</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div class="separator" style="clear: both;"><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/a/AVvXsEjf7-wAXJmH9SiOAhxTj4m6svlchJtMYZVkNnWSoaPMvaVSAq3Xn8x902jjH_K7CEvubT8Rj09SwcNiKvpy0iVgtLuYyWk-fFvk7O4yoTyqumEJqRMVpJGM5ONAQMibKk6SKFPXaEtWQA09kSzd0RW8Yke8qd-RZiR-b5FI4JwvkPEU2ENrLw=s320" style="display: block; padding: 1em 0px; text-align: center;"><img alt="" border="0" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/a/AVvXsEjf7-wAXJmH9SiOAhxTj4m6svlchJtMYZVkNnWSoaPMvaVSAq3Xn8x902jjH_K7CEvubT8Rj09SwcNiKvpy0iVgtLuYyWk-fFvk7O4yoTyqumEJqRMVpJGM5ONAQMibKk6SKFPXaEtWQA09kSzd0RW8Yke8qd-RZiR-b5FI4JwvkPEU2ENrLw=s320" width="320"/></a></div><p> I am delighted to share with all the readers of this blog the news of the launch of <a href="https://theoretics-journal.org" target="_blank">TheoretiCS</a>, a new, top-quality, open-access journal dedicated to the whole of Theoretical Computer Science. The journey leading to the establishment of this new journal has been long and the fact that this path eventually reached its destination is due to the sterling efforts and foresight of a number of people within our community. The seeds of TheoretiCS were sown within the Council of the European Association for Theoretical Computer Science during my two terms as president of that association. At that time, <a href="https://www.cwi.nl/people/jos-baeten" target="_blank">Jos Baeten</a> and <a href="https://www.fi.muni.cz/usr/kucera/">Antonin Kucera</a> worked hard to try and set up an open-access journal of the association. That journal never saw the light of day, but the process that eventually led to TheoretiCS was afoot. After some time, <a href="https://ls1-www.cs.tu-dortmund.de/en/kontakt-thomas-schwentick" target="_blank">Thomas Schwentick</a> took the baton in the relay race and took decisive steps in turning the establishment of this new journal into a true community effort. It is fair to say that the launch of this journal has involved an unprecedented level of cooperation amongst <a href="https://theoretics.episciences.org/page/advisory-board" target="_blank">representatives of leading conferences from across the entire Theoretical Computer Science community</a>. I am immensely grateful to everyone who participated in that work for the effort they put into making TheoretiCS a reality and apologise for not mentioning all the colleagues who contributed explicitly in this post.   You can find more information on TheoretiCS in the text below, which I received from Jos Baeten, founding member-at-large of the Advisory Board of the Theoretics Foundation. </p><p>So, what can you do to support this new journal? There are at least two things that each of us can do and that I believe are important. </p><ol style="text-align: left;"><li>Help TheoretiCS reach its quality objectives by submitting your best work to it and by encouraging your colleagues to do so too. TheoretiCS aims at publishing articles of a very high quality, and at becoming a reference journal on par with the leading journals in the area. To be accepted, a paper must make a significant contribution of lasting value to a relevant area of TCS, and its presentation must be of high quality. This is elaborated upon in the guiding principles spelled out below. I let you reach your own conclusions about the quality and the breadth of the <a href="https://theoretics.episciences.org/page/editorial-board" target="_blank">editorial board of TheoretiCS</a>, which is stellar IMHO. <br/></li><li>Spread the news of the launch of TheoretiCS within your networks. Despite its many years of existence and the role it plays within our community, I still meet colleagues (even in Theoretical Computer Science) who do not know that <a href="https://www.dagstuhl.de/en/publications/lipics" target="_blank">LIPIcs</a> exists and who claim that publishing conference proceedings with commercial publishers is a sign of scientific quality. </li></ol><p>If you happen to be in a position to do so, you can support the <a href="https://theoretics.episciences.org/page/theoretics-foundation" target="_blank">TheoretiCS foundation</a>, which is a German not-for-profit organization, by making a donation. </p><p/><p>I look forward to seeing the developments of TheoretiCS. Even though predicting the future is difficult, I have no doubt that the journal will become a coveted outlet, with the help of the community it aims to serve. Welcome to TheoretiCS and good luck!</p><p/><p><br/>=== Additional information about the journal ===<br/><br/>---  Guiding principles and objectives  ---<br/><br/>- We believe that our field (and science in general) needs more 'virtuous' open-access journals, a whole eco-system of them, with various levels of specialization and of selectivity. We also believe that, along with the structuring role played by conferences in theoretical computer science, we collectively need to re-develop the practice of journal publications.<br/><br/>- The scope of TheoretiCS is the whole of Theoretical Computer Science, understood in an inclusive meaning (concretely: including, but not restricted to, the Theory of Computing and the Theory of Programming; or equivalently, the so-called TCS-A and TCS-B, reminiscent of Jan van Leeuwen's Handbook of Theoretical Computer Science).<br/><br/>- Our aim is to rapidly become a reference journal and to contribute to the unity of the Theoretical Computer Science global community. In particular, we will seek to publish only papers that make a very significant contribution to their respective fields, that strive to be accessible to a wider audience within theoretical computer science, and that are, generally, of a quality on par with the very best journals in the field.<br/><br/>- TheoretiCS adheres to the principles of 'virtuous' open-access: there is no charge to read the journal, nor to publish in it. The copyright of the papers remains with the authors, under a Creative Commons license.<br/><br/><br/>---  Editorial Board  ---<br/><br/>The inaugural Editors-in-Chief are Javier Esparza (TU München) and Uri Zwick (Tel Aviv U.). The entire Editorial Board can be seen at <a href="https://theoretics-journal.org">https://theoretics-journal.org</a> (see below as well).<br/><br/><br/>---  Organization and a bit of history  ---<br/><br/>The project built on the groundwork you laid in the Council of the EATCS, and started in 2019 and underwent a long gestation. From the start, we wanted to have a thorough discussion with a wide representation of the community, on how to best implement the guiding principles sketched above. It was deemed essential to make sure that all fields of theoretical computer science would feel at home in this journal, and that it would be recognized as a valid venue for publication all over the world.<br/><br/>This resulted in the creation of an Advisory Board, composed of representatives of most of the main conferences in the field (currently APPROX, CCC, COLT, CONCUR, CSL, FOCS, FoSSaCS, FSCD, FSTTCS, ICALP, ICDT, ITCS, LICS, MFCS, PODC, SoCG, SODA, STACS, STOC, TCC) and of so-called members-at-large. The composition of this Advisory Board, which may still evolve, can be consulted at <a href="https://theoretics-journal.org">https://theoretics-journal.org</a>.<br/><br/><br/>---  Logistics and answers to some natural questions  ---<br/><br/>- The journal is published by the TheoretiCS Foundation, a non-profit foundation established under German law. <br/><br/>- TheoretiCS is based on the platform episciences.org, in the spirit of a so-called overlay journal.<br/><br/>- The Advisory Board, together with the Editors-in-Chief and the Managing Editors, devolved much of their efforts to designing and implementing an efficient 2-phase review system: efficient in terms of the added-value it brings to the published papers and their authors, and of the time it takes. Yet, as this review system relies in an essential fashion on the work and expertise of colleagues (like in all classical reputable journals), we can not guarantee a fixed duration for the evaluation of the papers submitted to TheoretiCS.<br/><br/>- Being charge-free for authors and readers does not mean that there is no cost to publishing a journal. These costs are supported for the foreseeable future by academic institutions (at the moment, CNRS and Inria, in France; others may join).<br/><br/>- The journal will have an ISSN, and each paper will have a DOI. There will be no print edition.<br/><br/><br/>---  Editorial Board  ---<br/><br/>Editors-in-Chief<br/><br/>    Javier Esparza (Technische Universität München, Munich)<br/>    Uri Zwick (Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv)<br/><br/>Managing  Editors<br/><br/>    Antoine Amarilli (Institut polytechnique de Paris, Télécom Paris)<br/>    Nathanaël Fijalkow (CNRS, Bordeaux, and The Alan Turing Institute of Data Science, London)<br/><br/>Editors<br/><br/>    Martin Abadi, Google, USA<br/>    Andris Ambainis, U. of Latvia<br/>    Albert Atserias, UPC, Barcelona<br/>    Haris Aziz, UNSW, Sydney<br/>    David Basin, ETH Zürich<br/>    Patricia Bouyer, CNRS, Paris-Saclay<br/>    Nicolò Cesa-Bianchi, Università di Milano<br/>    Anuj Dawar, Cambridge University<br/>    Luc Devroye,  McGill University, Montreal<br/>    Jacob Fox, Stanford University<br/>    Mohsen Ghaffari, ETH Zürich<br/>    Georg Gottlob, Oxford University<br/>    Anupam Gupta, Carnegie-Mellon University<br/>    Venkatesan Guruswami, Carnegie-Mellon University<br/>    Johan Håstad, KTH, Stockholm<br/>    Ravi Kannan, Microsoft Research India, Bengaluru<br/>    Anna Karlin, University of Washington, Seattle<br/>    Ken-ichi Kawarabayashi, National Institute of Informatics, Tokyo<br/>    Valerie King, University of Victoria<br/>    Robert Kleinberg, Cornell University<br/>    Naoki Kobayashi, University of Tokyo<br/>    Elias Koutsoupias, Oxford University<br/>    Xavier Leroy, Collège de France, Paris<br/>    Katrina Ligett, Hebrew University, Jerusalem<br/>    Rupak Majumdar, MPI-SWS, Kaiserslautern<br/>    Joseph Mitchell, State University of New York at Stony Brook<br/>    Mehryar Mohri, Google and New York University<br/>    David Mount, University of Maryland<br/>    Anca Muscholl, Université de Bordeaux<br/>    Danupon Nanongkai, University of Copenhagen<br/>    Moni Naor, Weizmann Institute, Rehovot<br/>    Catuscia Palamidessi, Inria, Palaiseau<br/>    Michał Pilipczuk, University of Warsaw<br/>    Jean-Francois Raskin, Université Libre de Bruxelles<br/>    Peter Sanders, KIT, Karlsruhe<br/>    Davide Sangiorgi, Università di Bologna<br/>    Nitin Saxena, IIT Kanpur<br/>    Alistair Sinclair, UC Berkeley<br/>    Ola Svensson, EPF Lausanne<br/>    Gregory Valiant, Stanford University<br/>    Stephanie Weirich, University of Pennsylvania<br/>    Virginia V. Williams, Massachusetts Institute of Technology<br/>    James Worrell, Oxford University<br/>    Mihalis Yannakakis, Columbia University, New York<br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-04T12:59:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-04T12:59:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2021-12-04T13:00:14Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/04/motwani-postdoctoral-fellowship-at-stanford-computer-science-apply-by-december-15-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/04/motwani-postdoctoral-fellowship-at-stanford-computer-science-apply-by-december-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Motwani Postdoctoral Fellowship at Stanford Computer Science (apply by December 15, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The theory group at Stanford invites applications for the Motwani postdoctoral fellowship in theoretical computer science. Information and application instructions below. Applications will be accepted until the positions are filled, but review of applicants will begin after Dec 15. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/20711 Email: theory.stanford@gmail.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The theory group at Stanford invites applications for the Motwani postdoctoral fellowship in theoretical computer science. Information and application instructions below. Applications will be accepted until the positions are filled, but review of applicants will begin after Dec 15.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/20711">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/20711</a><br/>
Email: theory.stanford@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-04T09:17:47Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-04T09:17:47Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01365</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01365" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tesselating a Pascal-like tetrahedron for the subdivision of high order tetrahedral finite elements</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1638576000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Mark W. Lohry <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.01365">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Three-dimensional $N^{th}$ order nodal Lagrangian tetrahedral finite elements
($P_N$ elements) can be generated using Pascal's tetrahedron $\mathcal{H}$
where each node in 3D element space corresponds to an entry in $\mathcal{H}$.
For the purposes of visualization and post-processing, it is desirable to
"subdivide" these high-order tetrahedral elements into sub-tetrahedra which
cover the whole space without intersections and without introducing new
exterior edges or vertices. That is, the exterior triangulation of the element
should be congruent with the "natural" triangulation of the $2D$ Pascal's
triangle. This work attempts to describe that process of subdivision for
arbitrary $N$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T23:26:21Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01340</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01340" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Generalized Framework for Group Testing: Queries, Feedbacks and Adversaries</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1638576000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Klonowski:Marek.html">Marek Klonowski</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kowalski:Dariusz_R=.html">Dariusz R. Kowalski</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pajak:Dominik.html">Dominik Pajak</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.01340">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the Group Testing problem, the objective is to learn a subset K of some
much larger domain N, using the shortest-possible sequence of queries Q. A
feedback to a query provides some information about the intersection between
the query and subset K. Several specific feedbacks have been studied in the
literature, often proving different formulas for the estimate of the query
complexity of the problem, defined as the shortest length of queries' sequence
solving Group Testing problem with specific feedback. In this paper we study
what are the properties of the feedback that influence the query complexity of
Group Testing and what is their measurable impact. We propose a generic
framework that covers a vast majority of relevant settings considered in the
literature, which depends on two fundamental parameters of the feedback: input
capacity $\alpha$ and output expressiveness $\beta$. They upper bound the
logarithm of the size of the feedback function domain and image, respectively.
To justify the value of the framework, we prove upper bounds on query
complexity of non adaptive, deterministic Group Testing under some "efficient"
feedbacks, for minimum, maximum and general expressiveness, and complement them
with a lower bound on all feedbacks with given parameters $\alpha,\beta$. Our
upper bounds also hold if the feedback function could get an input twisted by a
malicious adversary, in case the intersection of a query and the hidden set is
bigger than the feedback capacity $\alpha$. We also show that slight change in
the feedback function may result in substantial worsening of the query
complexity. Additionally, we analyze explicitly constructed randomized
counterparts of the deterministic results. Our results provide some insights to
what are the most useful bits of information an output-restricted feedback
could provide, and open a number of challenging research directions.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T23:22:43Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01140</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01140" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the computational complexity of the Steiner $k$-eccentricity</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1638576000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Xingfu.html">Xingfu Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yu:Guihai.html">Guihai Yu</a>, Aleksandar Ilić, Sandi Klavžar <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.01140">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Steiner $k$-eccentricity of a vertex $v$ of a graph $G$ is the maximum
Steiner distance over all $k$-subsets of $V (G)$ which contain $v$. A linear
time algorithm for calculating the Steiner $k$-eccentricity of a vertex on
block graphs is presented. For general graphs, an $O(n^{\nu(G)+1}(n(G) + m(G) +
k))$ algorithm is designed, where $\nu(G)$ is the cyclomatic number of $G$. A
linear algorithm for computing the Steiner $3$-eccentricities of all vertices
of a tree is also presented which improves the quadratic algorithm from
[Discrete Appl.\ Math.\ 304 (2021) 181--195].
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T23:22:04Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01108</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01108" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A short note on the counting complexity of conjunctive queries</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1638576000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mengel:Stefan.html">Stefan Mengel</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.01108">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This note closes a minor gap in the literature on the counting complexity of
conjunctive queries by showing that queries that are not free-connex do not
have a linear time counting algorithm under standard complexity assumptions.
More generally, it is shown that the so-called quantified star size is a lower
bound for the exponent in the runtime of any counting algorithm for conjunctive
queries.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T23:21:50Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01104</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01104" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Constant-Factor Approximation Algorithm for Point Guarding an Art Gallery</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1638576000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vaezi:Arash.html">Arash Vaezi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Ghodsi:Mohammad.html">Mohammad Ghodsi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.01104">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a simple polygon $\cal P$, in the Art Gallery problem the goal is to
find the minimum number of guards needed to cover the entire $\cal P$, where a
guard is a point and can see another point $q$ when $\overline{pq}$ does not
cross the edges of $\cal P$.
</p>
<p>This paper studies a variant of the Art Gallery problem in which guards are
restricted to lie on a dense grid inside $\cal P$. In the general problem,
guards can be anywhere inside or on the boundary of $\cal P$. The general
problem is called the \emph{point} guarding problem. It was proved that the
point guarding problem is APX-complete, meaning that we cannot do better than a
constant-factor approximation algorithm unless $P = NP$.
</p>
<p>A huge amount of research is committed to the studies of combinatorial and
algorithmic aspects of this problem, and as of this time, we could not find a
constant factor approximation for simple polygons. The last best-known
approximation factor for point guarding a simple polygon was $\mathcal{O}(\log
(|OPT|))$ introduced by E. Bonnet and T. Miltzow in 2020, where $|OPT|$ is the
size of the optimal solution. Here, we propose an algorithm with a constant
approximation factor for the point guarding problem where the location of
guards is restricted to a grid. The running time of the proposed algorithm
depends on the number of cells of the grid. The approximation factor is
constant regardless of the grid we use, the running time could be
super-polynomial if the grid size becomes exponential.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01090</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01090" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Mirage of Universality in Cellular Automata</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1638576000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Theyssier:Guillaume.html">Guillaume Theyssier</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.01090">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This note is a survey of examples and results about cellular automata with
the purpose of recalling that there is no 'universal' way of being
computationally universal. In particular, we show how some cellular automata
can embed efficient but bounded computation, while others can embed unbounded
computations but not efficiently. We also study two variants of Boolean circuit
embedding, transient versus repeatable simulations, and underline their
differences. Finally we show how strong forms of universality can be hidden
inside some seemingly simple cellular automata according to some classical
dynamical parameters.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T23:20:51Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01042</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01042" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Gomory-Hu Trees in Quadratic Time</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1638576000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Tianyi.html">Tianyi Zhang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.01042">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Gomory-Hu tree [Gomory and Hu, 1961] is a succinct representation of pairwise
minimum cuts in an undirected graph. When the input graph has general edge
weights, classic algorithms need at least cubic running time to compute a
Gomory-Hu tree. Very recently, the authors of [AKL+, arXiv v1, 2021] have
improved the running time to $\tilde{O}(n^{2.875})$ which breaks the cubic
barrier for the first time. In this paper, we refine their approach and improve
the running time to $\tilde{O}(n^2)$. This quadratic upper bound is also
obtained independently in an updated version by the same group of authors
[AKL+, arXiv v2, 2021].
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T23:22:21Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.00828</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.00828" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Price of Differential Privacy under Continual Observation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1638576000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Palak Jain, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Raskhodnikova:Sofya.html">Sofya Raskhodnikova</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sivakumar:Satchit.html">Satchit Sivakumar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Smith:Adam.html">Adam Smith</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.00828">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the accuracy of differentially private mechanisms in the continual
release model. A continual release mechanism receives a sensitive dataset as a
stream of $T$ inputs and produces, after receiving each input, an accurate
output on the obtained inputs. In contrast, a batch algorithm receives the data
as one batch and produces a single output.
</p>
<p>We provide the first strong lower bounds on the error of continual release
mechanisms. In particular, for two fundamental problems that are widely studied
and used in the batch model, we show that the worst case error of every
continual release algorithm is $\tilde \Omega(T^{1/3})$ times larger than that
of the best batch algorithm. Previous work shows only a polylogarithimic (in
$T$) gap between the worst case error achievable in these two models; further,
for many problems, including the summation of binary attributes, the
polylogarithmic gap is tight (Dwork et al., 2010; Chan et al., 2010). Our
results show that closely related problems -- specifically, those that require
selecting the largest of a set of sums -- are fundamentally harder in the
continual release model than in the batch model.
</p>
<p>Our lower bounds assume only that privacy holds for streams fixed in advance
(the "nonadaptive" setting). However, we provide matching upper bounds that
hold in a model where privacy is required even for adaptively selected streams.
This model may be of independent interest.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T23:24:57Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.00792</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.00792" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Ideals, Determinants, and Straightening: Proving and Using Lower Bounds for Polynomial Ideals</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1638576000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Robert Andrews, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Forbes:Michael_A=.html">Michael A. Forbes</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.00792">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We show that any nonzero polynomial in the ideal generated by the $r \times
r$ minors of an $n \times n$ matrix $X$ can be used to efficiently approximate
the determinant. For any nonzero polynomial $f$ in this ideal, we construct a
small depth-three $f$-oracle circuit that approximates the determinant of size
$\Theta(r^{1/3})$ in the sense of border complexity. For many classes of
algebraic circuits, this implies that every nonzero polynomial in the ideal
generated by $r \times r$ minors is at least as hard to approximately compute
as the determinant of size $\Theta(r^{1/3})$. We also prove an analogous result
for the Pfaffian of a $2n \times 2n$ skew-symmetric matrix and the ideal
generated by Pfaffians of $2r \times 2r$ principal submatrices.
</p>
<p>This answers a recent question of Grochow about complexity in polynomial
ideals in the setting of border complexity. We give several applications of our
result, two of which are highlighted below.
</p>
<p>$\bullet$ We prove super-polynomial lower bounds for Ideal Proof System
refutations computed by low-depth circuits. This extends the recent
breakthrough low-depth circuit lower bounds of Limaye, Srinivasan, and Tavenas
to the setting of proof complexity. For many natural circuit classes, we show
that the approximative proof complexity of our hard instance is governed by the
approximative circuit complexity of the determinant.
</p>
<p>$\bullet$ We construct new hitting set generators for polynomial-size
low-depth circuits. For any $\varepsilon &gt; 0$, we construct generators with
seed length $O(n^\varepsilon)$ that attain a near-optimal tradeoff between
their seed length and degree, and are computable by low-depth circuits of
near-linear size (with respect to the size of their output). This matches the
seed length of the generators recently obtained by Limaye, Srinivasan, and
Tavenas, but improves on the generator's degree and circuit complexity.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-04T23:20:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/03/assistant-professor-quantum-computation-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-1-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/03/assistant-professor-quantum-computation-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-1-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor – Quantum Computation  at University of California – San Diego (apply by January 1, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) Department in the Jacobs School of Engineering (JSOE) (https://cse.ucsd.edu) and The Department of Mathematics within the Division of Physical Sciences at the University of California, San Diego (http://www.math.ucsd.edu) invite applications for a cross-campus hire for a tenure-track faculty position at the rank of Assistant Professor. Website: https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF03023 Email: nherrera@eng.ucsd.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) Department in the Jacobs School of Engineering (JSOE) (<a href="https://cse.ucsd.edu">https://cse.ucsd.edu</a>) and The Department of Mathematics within the Division of Physical Sciences at the University of California, San Diego (<a href="http://www.math.ucsd.edu">http://www.math.ucsd.edu</a>) invite applications for a cross-campus hire for a tenure-track faculty position at the rank of Assistant Professor.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF03023">https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF03023</a><br/>
Email: nherrera@eng.ucsd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-03T21:23:48Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-03T21:23:48Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8232</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2021/12/03/an-alarming-trend-in-k-12-math-education/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An alarming trend in K-12 Math Education</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is a blog post written by me (Boaz) with Edith Cohen. It is cross posted on Scott Aaronson’s blog. See also a thread on Twitter. See also the open letter, and fuller analysis of the CMF proposed revisions. Mathematical education at the K-12 level is critical for preparation for STEM careers. An ongoing challenge … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2021/12/03/an-alarming-trend-in-k-12-math-education/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">An alarming trend in K-12 Math Education</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This is a blog post written by me (Boaz) with Edith Cohen. It is cross posted on <a href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6146">Scott Aaronson’s blog</a>. See also <a href="https://twitter.com/boazbaraktcs/status/1466799615349608452?s=20">a thread on Twitter</a>.</p>



<p>See also the <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/k12mathmatters/home">open letter</a>, and <a href="https://bit.ly/cmfanalysis">fuller analysis</a> of the CMF proposed revisions.</p>



<p>Mathematical education at the K-12 level is critical for preparation for STEM careers. An ongoing challenge to the US K-12 system is to improve the preparation of students for advanced mathematics courses and expand access and enrollment in these courses. As stated by a <a href="https://www2.ed.gov/datastory/stem/algebra/index.html#WHYALGEBRAI">Department of Education report</a> <strong><em>“taking Algebra I before high school … can set students up for a strong foundation of STEM education and open the door for various college and career options.”</em></strong> The report states that while 80% of all students have access to Algebra I in middle school, only 24% enroll. This is also why the goal of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/07/education/algebra-project-bob-moses-empowers-students.html">Bob Moses’ Algebra Project</a> is to ensure that <strong>“every child must master algebra, preferably by eighth grade, for algebra is the gateway to the college-prep curriculum, which in turn is the path to higher education.” </strong></p>



<p>The most significant potential for growth is among African American or Latino students, among whom only 12% enroll in Algebra before high school. This untapped potential has longer-term implications for both society and individuals. For example, although African Americans and Latinos comprise 13% and 18% (respectively) of the overall US population, they only account for 4% and 11% of <a href="https://ira.asee.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/07/2018-Engineering-by-Numbers-Engineering-Statistics-UPDATED-15-July-2019.pdf">engineering degrees</a>. There is also a gap in access by income: Calculus is <a href="https://www.urban.org/urban-wire/unequal-access-calculus-could-hinder-low-income-and-black-students">offered</a> in 92% of schools serving the top income quartile but only in 77% of schools serving the bottom quartile (as measured by the share of students eligible for free or reduced-price lunch). Thus minority and low income students have less access to STEM jobs, which yield <a href="https://www.bls.gov/emp/tables/stem-employment.htm">more than double the median salary</a> of non-STEM jobs, and are projected to grow at a 50% higher rate over the next decade.</p>



<p>Given these disparities, we applaud efforts such as the <a href="https://algebra.org/wp/">Algebra Project</a>, the <a href="http://thecalculusproject.org/">Calculus Project</a>, and <a href="https://www.beammath.org">Bridge to Enter Advanced Mathematics</a> that increase access to advanced mathematical education to underserved students (in <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/07/education/algebra-project-bob-moses-empowers-students.html">Bob Moses’ words</a> <strong><em>“raise the floor”</em></strong>). However, we are concerned by recent approaches, such as the proposed <a href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ma/cf/">California Math Framework</a> (CMF) revisions,  that take the opposite direction.</p>



<p>See <a href="https://bit.ly/cmfanalysis">this document for a detailed analysis and critique of the CMF</a>, but the bottom line is that rather than trying to elevate under-served students, <strong>such “reforms” reduce access and options for all students</strong>. In particular, the CMF encourages schools to stop offering Algebra I in middle school, while placing obstacles (such as doubling-up, compressed courses, or outside-of-school private courses) in the way of those who want to take advanced math in higher grades. When similar reforms were implemented in San Francisco, they <a href="https://edsource.org/2021/one-districts-faulty-data-shouldnt-drive-californias-math-policy/663374">resulted</a> in an <strong><em>“inequitable patchwork scheme”</em></strong> of workarounds that affluent students could access but that their less privileged counterparts could not. The CMF also promotes<strong> trendy and shallow courses</strong> (such as a nearly math-free version of  “data science”) as recommended alternatives  to<strong> foundational mathematical courses</strong> such as Algebra and Calculus. These courses do not prepare students <a href="https://bit.ly/cmfanalysis">even for careers in data science itself</a>!</p>



<p>As educators and practitioners, we have seen first-hand the value of solid foundations in mathematics for pursuing college-level STEM education and a productive STEM career. </p>



<p>While well-intentioned, <strong>we believe that many of the changes proposed by the CMF are deeply misguided and will disproportionately harm under-resourced students</strong>. Adopting them would result in a student population that is less prepared to succeed in STEM and other 4-year quantitative degrees in college.  The CMF <a href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ma/cf/documents/mathfwchapter7.docx">states</a> that <strong><em>“many students, parents, and teachers encourage acceleration beginning in grade eight (or sooner) because of mistaken beliefs that Calculus is an important high school goal.”</em></strong> Students, parents, and teachers <strong><em>are not mistaken</em></strong>. Neither is the National Society of Black Engineers (NSBE), which set in 2015 a goal to double the number of African American students taking calculus by 2025. Calculus is not the only goal of K-12 math education, but it <em>is</em> important for students who wish to prepare for STEM in college and beyond. </p>



<p>We agree that calculus is not the “be-all and end-all” of high-school mathematics education. In particular, we encourage introducing options such as logic, probability, discrete mathematics, and algorithms design in the K-12 curriculum, as they can be valuable foundations for STEM education in college. However, when taught beyond a superficial level (which unfortunately is <em>not</em> the case in the CMF “data science” <a href="https://hsdatascience.youcubed.org/">proposals</a>), these topics are not any easier  than calculus. They require the same foundations of logic, algebra, and functions, and fluency with numbers and calculations. Indeed, the career paths with the highest potential for growth require <a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/the-era-of-the-mathematician-has-arrived-39ec20b24aa6">more and deeper mathematical preparation</a> than ever before. Calculus and other mathematical foundations are not important because they are admission requirements for colleges, or because they are relics of the <a href="https://freakonomics.com/podcast/math-curriculum/">“Sputnik era”</a>. They are important because they provide fundamental knowledge and ways of thinking that are necessary for success in these fast growing and in-demand fields.</p>



<p>We also fully support incorporating introductory data analysis and coding skills in the K-12 curriculum (and there are some <a href="https://coursekata.org/">good</a> <a href="https://cs50.harvard.edu/ap/2022/">approaches</a> for doing so).  But we strongly disagree with marketing such skills as replacing foundational skills in algebra and calculus when preparing for 4-year college degrees in STEM and other quantitative fields. These topics are important and build on basic math foundations but are not a replacement for such foundations any more than social media skills can replace reading and writing foundations. </p>



<p>Given the above, we, together with <strong>more than 150 scientists, educators, and practitioners in STEM</strong>, have signed an <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/k12mathmatters/home"><strong>open letter expressing our concerns with such trends</strong></a>. The signatories include STEM faculty in public and private universities and practitioners from industry. They include educators with decades of experience teaching students at all levels, as well as researchers that won the highest awards in their fields, including the Fields Medal, the Nobel Prize, and the Turing Award. Signers also include people vested in mathematical high-school education, such as Adrian Mims (founder of <a href="http://thecalculusproject.org/">The Calculus Project</a>) and Jelani Nelson (UC Berkeley EECS professor and founder of <a href="https://www.addiscoder.com/">AddisCoder</a>) who have spearheaded projects to increase access to underserved populations.</p>



<p>We encourage you to read the letter, and if you are a US-based STEM professional or educator, consider signing it as well: <a href="https://bit.ly/mathedletter">https://bit.ly/mathedletter</a><br/></p>



<p>Unfortunately, in recent years, debates on US education have become politicized. The letter is not affiliated with any political organization, and we believe that the issues we highlight transcend current political debates. After all, expanding access to mathematical education is both socially just and economically wise.</p>



<p><strong>Note: </strong>This blog post reflects our — Boaz &amp; Edith’s — opinions; the text of the letter speaks for itself. Similarly, any comments below by us or other letter signers reflect their personal opinions. </p>



<p><strong>Note 2:</strong>  The “<a href="https://www.beammath.org/">Bridge to Enter Advanced Mathematics” (BEAM)</a> project is currently having a 10x match program for new donors (and πx match for returning donors). If you want to support projects that make a real difference in expanding access to math, take a look at <a href="https://www.beammath.org/donate">https://www.beammath.org/donate</a> . Another project worth supporting is (co signer) Adrian Mims’ <a href="https://thecalculusproject.org/">calculus project</a> <a href="https://secure.actblue.com/donate/thecalculusproject">https://secure.actblue.com/donate/thecalculusproject</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-03T16:00:28Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-03T16:00:28Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6146</id>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6146" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6146#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=6146" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">An alarming trend in K-12 math education: a guest post and an open letter</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Today, I’m turning over Shtetl-Optimized to an extremely important guest post by theoretical computer scientists Boaz Barak of Harvard and Edith Cohen of Google (cross-posted on the windows on theory blog). In addition to the post below, please read—and if relevant, consider signing—our open letter about math education in the US, which now has over […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Today, I’m turning over <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em> to an extremely important guest post by theoretical computer scientists <a href="https://www.boazbarak.org/">Boaz Barak</a> of Harvard and <a href="http://www.cohenwang.com/edith/">Edith Cohen</a> of Google (<a href="https://windowsontheory.org/?p=8232">cross-posted</a> on the <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/">windows on theory</a> blog).  In addition to the post below, please read—and if relevant, consider signing—our <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/k12mathmatters/home"><strong>open letter</strong></a> about math education in the US, which now has over 150 signatories, including Fields Medalists, Turing Award winners, and Nobel laureates.  Finally, check out our <a href="https://bit.ly/cmfanalysis">fuller analysis</a> of what the California Mathematics Framework is poised to do and why it’s such an urgent crisis for math education.  I’m particularly grateful to my colleagues for their writing efforts, since I would never have been able to discuss what’s happening in such relatively measured words. <em>–Scott Aaronson</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>Mathematical education at the K-12 level is critical for preparation for STEM careers. An ongoing challenge to the US K-12 system is to improve the preparation of students for advanced mathematics courses and expand access and enrollment in these courses. As stated by a <a href="https://www2.ed.gov/datastory/stem/algebra/index.html#WHYALGEBRAI">Department of Education report</a> <strong><em>“taking Algebra I before high school … can set students up for a strong foundation of STEM education and open the door for various college and career options.”</em></strong> The report states that while 80% of all students have access to Algebra I in middle school, only 24% enroll. This is also why the goal of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/07/education/algebra-project-bob-moses-empowers-students.html">Bob Moses’ Algebra Project</a> is to ensure that <strong>“every child must master algebra, preferably by eighth grade, for algebra is the gateway to the college-prep curriculum, which in turn is the path to higher education.”</strong></p>



<p>The most significant potential for growth is among African American or Latino students, among whom only 12% enroll in Algebra before high school. This untapped potential has longer-term implications for both society and individuals. For example, although African Americans and Latinos comprise 13% and 18% (respectively) of the overall US population, they only account for 4% and 11% of <a href="https://ira.asee.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/07/2018-Engineering-by-Numbers-Engineering-Statistics-UPDATED-15-July-2019.pdf">engineering degrees</a>. There is also a gap in access by income: Calculus is <a href="https://www.urban.org/urban-wire/unequal-access-calculus-could-hinder-low-income-and-black-students">offered</a> in 92% of schools serving the top income quartile but only in 77% of schools serving the bottom quartile (as measured by the share of students eligible for free or reduced-price lunch). Thus minority and low income students have less access to STEM jobs, which yield <a href="https://www.bls.gov/emp/tables/stem-employment.htm">more than double the median salary</a> of non-STEM jobs, and are projected to grow at a 50% higher rate over the next decade.</p>



<p>Given these disparities, we applaud efforts such as the <a href="https://algebra.org/wp/">Algebra Project</a>, the <a href="http://thecalculusproject.org/">Calculus Project</a>, and <a href="https://www.beammath.org">Bridge to Enter Advanced Mathematics</a> that increase access to advanced mathematical education to underserved students. However, we are concerned by recent approaches, such as the proposed <a href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ma/cf/">California Math Framework</a> (CMF) revisions,  that take the opposite direction.</p>



<p>See <a href="https://bit.ly/cmfanalysis">this document for a detailed analysis and critique of the CMF</a>, but the bottom line is that rather than trying to elevate under-served students, <strong>such “reforms” reduce access and options for all students</strong>. In particular, the CMF encourages schools to stop offering Algebra I in middle school, while placing obstacles (such as doubling-up, compressed courses, or outside-of-school private courses) in the way of those who want to take advanced math in higher grades. When similar reforms were implemented in San Francisco, they <a href="https://edsource.org/2021/one-districts-faulty-data-shouldnt-drive-californias-math-policy/663374">resulted</a> in an <strong><em>“inequitable patchwork scheme”</em></strong> of workarounds that affluent students could access but that their less privileged counterparts could not. The CMF also promotes<strong> trendy and shallow courses</strong> (such as a nearly math-free version of  “data science”) as recommended alternatives  to<strong> foundational mathematical courses</strong> such as Algebra and Calculus. These courses do not prepare students <a href="https://bit.ly/cmfanalysis">even for careers in data science itself</a>!</p>



<p>As educators and practitioners, we have seen first-hand the value of solid foundations in mathematics for pursuing college-level STEM education and a productive STEM career. </p>



<p>While well-intentioned, <strong>we believe that many of the changes proposed by the CMF are deeply misguided and will disproportionately harm under-resourced students</strong>. Adopting them would result in a student population that is less prepared to succeed in STEM and other 4-year quantitative degrees in college.  The CMF <a href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ma/cf/documents/mathfwchapter7.docx">states</a> that <strong><em>“many students, parents, and teachers encourage acceleration beginning in grade eight (or sooner) because of mistaken beliefs that Calculus is an important high school goal.”</em></strong> Students, parents, and teachers <strong><em>are not mistaken</em></strong>. Neither is the National Society of Black Engineers (NSBE), which set in 2015 a goal to double the number of African American students taking calculus by 2025. Calculus is not the only goal of K-12 math education, but it <em>is</em> important for students who wish to prepare for STEM in college and beyond. </p>



<p>We agree that calculus is not the “be-all and end-all” of high-school mathematics education. In particular, we encourage introducing options such as logic, probability, discrete mathematics, and algorithms design in the K-12 curriculum, as they can be valuable foundations for STEM education in college. However, when taught beyond a superficial level (which unfortunately is <em>not</em> the case in the CMF “data science” <a href="https://hsdatascience.youcubed.org/">proposals</a>), these topics are not any easier  than calculus. They require the same foundations of logic, algebra, and functions, and fluency with numbers and calculations. Indeed, the career paths with the highest potential for growth require <a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/the-era-of-the-mathematician-has-arrived-39ec20b24aa6">more and deeper mathematical preparation</a> than ever before. Calculus and other mathematical foundations are not important because they are admission requirements for colleges, or because they are relics of the <a href="https://freakonomics.com/podcast/math-curriculum/">“Sputnik era”</a>. They are important because they provide fundamental knowledge and ways of thinking that are necessary for success in these fast growing and in-demand fields.</p>



<p>We also fully support incorporating introductory data analysis and coding skills in the K-12 curriculum (and there are some <a href="https://coursekata.org/">good</a> <a href="https://cs50.harvard.edu/ap/2022/">approaches</a> for doing so).  But we strongly disagree with marketing such skills as replacing foundational skills in algebra and calculus when preparing for 4-year college degrees in STEM and other quantitative fields. These topics are important and build on basic math foundations but are not a replacement for such foundations any more than social media skills can replace reading and writing foundations. </p>



<p>Given the above, we, together with <strong>more than 150 scientists, educators, and practitioners in STEM</strong>, have signed an <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/k12mathmatters/home"><strong>open letter expressing our concerns with such trends</strong></a>. The signatories include STEM faculty in public and private universities and practitioners from industry. They include educators with decades of experience teaching students at all levels, as well as researchers that won the highest awards in their fields, including the Fields Medal and the Turing Award. Signers also include people vested in mathematical high-school education, such as Adrian Mims (founder of <a href="http://thecalculusproject.org/">The Calculus Project</a>) and Jelani Nelson (UC Berkeley EECS professor and founder of <a href="https://www.addiscoder.com/">AddisCoder</a>) who have spearheaded projects to increase access to underserved populations.</p>



<p>We encourage you to read the letter, and if you are a US-based STEM professional or educator, consider signing it as well: <a href="https://bit.ly/mathedletter">https://bit.ly/mathedletter</a></p>



<p>Unfortunately, in recent years, debates on US education have become politicized. The letter is not affiliated with any political organization, and we believe that the issues we highlight transcend current political debates. After all, expanding access to mathematical education is both socially just and economically wise.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><strong>Note: </strong>The above guest post reflects the views of its authors, Boaz Barak and Edith Cohen.  Any comments below by them, me, or other signatories reflect their own views, not necessarily those of the entire group. <em>–SA</em></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-03T15:59:29Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-03T15:59:29Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <icon>https://scottaaronson.blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-Jacket-32x32.gif</icon>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T16:19:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://gradientscience.org/editing/</id>
    <link href="https://gradientscience.org/editing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Editing a Classifier</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a class="bbutton" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01008" style="float: left; width: 45%;">
<i class="fas fa-file-pdf"/>
    Paper
</a>
<a class="bbutton" href="https://github.com/MadryLab/EditingClassifiers" style="float: left; width: 45%;">
<i class="fab fa-github"/>
   Code
</a>
<br/></p>

<p><i>In our <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01008">recent work</a>, we develop a framework for modifying the
behavior of a classifier by directly rewriting its internal prediction rules.
This allows a model designer to adapt the model to new setting or remove
specific spurious correlations with virtually no additional data collection or
further model training. </i></p>

<h2 id="motivation">Motivation</h2>
<p>Modern machine learning classifiers work because they are able to extract
predictive correlations from large, relatively uncurated datasets. However, as
has been pointed out
<a href="https://people.csail.mit.edu/torralba/research/bias/">re</a>-<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1807.04975">pea</a>-<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1812.06707">te</a>-<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.09994">dly</a>,
many of these correlations are spurious or context-specific. That is, while
they are predictive on the training dataset, they need not necessarily be
predictive in the real-world settings where we wish to deploy our models. For
instance, a useful example to keep in mind throughout this post is that of
“cars on snow”: if a model relies on the presence of “road” to recognize a car
(because most cars in the training set are on the road) it might have trouble
recognizing cars when they drive through snow.</p>

<p>So, what can we do about that?</p>

<h2 id="editing-classifiers-setting-up-the-problem">Editing classifiers: Setting up the problem</h2>
<p>A natural idea is to modify the model after training, but how exactly would we
do that? The canonical method for modifying such a “buggy” ML model once it
has been trained is to collect additional data that captures the classifier’s
intended behavior and then use that data to fine-tune the model. However,
collecting such data might be tricky and/or expensive. More importantly, this
is an <em>indirect</em> process, i.e., we are specifying model behavior only through
training examples—which is what gave rise to undesired correlations in the
first place.</p>

<p>In order to develop a more reliable process, we want to allow a model designer
to <em>directly</em> edit model’s “inner mechanics”. In other words, we want the
designer to be able to specify <em>how</em> a model should predict on broad families
of inputs (and not just what it should predict on a specific, fixed set of
training inputs).</p>

<p>Conceptually, we can think of the model as operating based on some <em>prediction
rules</em>. For instance, “if grass is present, then this is likely an image of a
cow” or “if a wheel is present, this is likely an image of a car”. From that
perspective, our goal is to enable the designer to interact with these rules
and rewrite how these <em>concepts</em> (e.g., “car”, “wheel”) are associated with
each other. Crucially, we need for such rewrites to <em>generalize</em>, i.e., if one
modifies how the concept “wheel” is perceived by the model, then this
modification should apply to all instances containing a wheel.</p>

<h2 id="a-concrete-editing-methodology">A concrete editing methodology</h2>
<p>So, how do we turn this conceptual framework into an actual tool? Our
method—which we will describe now—builds on the recent work of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.15646">Bau et al.
2020</a> that developed a method for editing
generative models.</p>

<p><strong>Concepts as vectors.</strong> Our point of start is figuring out  a way to capture
high-level concepts via concrete objects that  we can manipulate. The object of
choice is latent vectors. Indeed, as it turns out, it is possible to find directions in
the latent representation of the model that capture different visual concepts (e.g.,
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.11279">TCAV</a> or <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1704.05796">Network
Dissection</a>). Moreover, as Bau et al. found,
it is possible to find such directions based only on a few images. This can be
done by simply selecting the pixels corresponding to the desired concept and
then aggregating the latent representations of these pixels via PCA.</p>

<p><strong>Layers as associative memory.</strong> Next, we want to develop a way to modify how
the classifier processes these high-level concepts (captured by vectors). For
this, we view each layer of the network as a linear associative memory: i.e., a
mapping of each latent vector in its input (the key) to another latent vector in its
output—the value. From that perspective, if we have a vector $k$ capturing some
high-level concept in the latent representation space <em>before</em> some layer $L$,
and a vector $v$ capturing another concept <em>after</em> $L$, then we can modify the
weights $W$ of that layer to map one concept to another, i.e., have that</p>

\[v \simeq Wk.\]

<p>Importantly, to ensure that this update does not affect how other concepts are
being processed, we restrict it to only a rank-one change in the weights W. You
can find a more detailed description in the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.15646">original
paper</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Rewriting classifiers.</strong> With these primitives in place, we can focus our
attention on editing classifiers. How would we modify a model to recognize cars
on snow as it would if they were on the road? At a high-level, we need to
ensure that the model treats the concept of “snow” the same way it treats the
concept of “road”. To this end, we start from a picture of a car (on a road),
manually annotate the part that depicts “road”, and then replace this part by
copy-pasting a snow texture on it.</p>

<p>Now, fixing any layer $L$, we use the selected pixels to compute a “snow” vector
$k$ <em>before</em> that layer and a “road” vector $v$ <em>after</em> that layer. Then, in order
to perform our edit we simply update the weights of that layer so that it
(approximately) maps the vector $k$ to the vector $v$. And that’s it! We can leave
the rest of the model as-is, since the snowy part of the image will be
processed as if it depicted a road.</p>

<p><img class="bigimg" src="https://gradientscience.org/assets/editing/pipeline.png" style="width: 80%;"/></p>
<div class="footnote"> <strong> Editing methodology.</strong> We modify a
layer of the classifier so that the concept "snow" before the layer gets mapped
to "road" after the layer using a single synthetic example.</div>

<h2 id="does-editing-work">Does editing work?</h2>

<p>Let’s now try to apply this methodology to a couple of real world test cases.
In both cases, we will perform these updates based on a <em>single</em> exemplar that
we manually modified.</p>

<p><strong>Scenario 1: Vehicles on snow.</strong> We start with our running example of
vehicles-on-snow. For that, we form a test set through searching
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/">Flickr</a> for images of “&lt;vehicle&gt; on snow” for a
number of different vehicles corresponding to ImageNet classes. We observe that
the performance of our ImageNet model on these new images is not great. Can we now
improve the model on this test set via a targeted edit?</p>

<p><img class="bigimg" src="https://gradientscience.org/assets/editing/snow_edit.png" style="width: 90%;"/></p>
<div class="footnote"> <strong>Adapting the model to snowy environments.</strong>
By mapping the concept "snow" to "road" we aim to improve the model's
ability to recognize vehicles driving through snow.</div>

<p>To check that, we form an exemplar by taking a picture of a “police van” (a
class that is not in our test set) on a road and replacing the road with a snow
texture. It turns out that by then  editing the model to map “snow” to “road”
using our method we can indeed improve the performance on our snowy test set!
Also, note that the vehicle in our exemplar belongs to a class that is not part
of the test set, so we can see that our edit generalized to other instances of
the concepts used.</p>

<p><img class="bigimg" src="https://gradientscience.org/assets/editing/snow_results.png" style="width: 80%;"/></p>
<div class="footnote"> <strong>Editing performance on vehicles-on-snow edits.</strong> 
Editing consistently improves model accuracy across classes. In contrast,
fine-tuning using the same data cannot correct any of the predictions.</div>

<p>It is worth contrasting this with the performance of fine-tuning, i.e., when we
simply fine-tune the whole model on this exemplar. There seems to be no
performance improvement in this case.</p>

<p><strong>Scenario 2: Typographic-attacks.</strong> We then take a look at the recent
typographic attacks of <a href="https://distill.pub/2021/multimodal-neurons/">[Goh et al.,
2021]</a>: putting a handwritten “ipod” label on
different household objects causes a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.00020">CLIP</a>
classifier to classify them as iPods! Here is our reproduction:</p>

<p><img class="bigimg" src="https://gradientscience.org/assets/editing/ipod.png" style="width: 80%;"/></p>
<div class="footnote"> <strong>Typographic attacks.</strong> 
Placing a handwritten note with the text "ipod" on various household objects
causes a CLIP-trained model to incorrectly predict "ipod".</div>

<p>Now, we will try to edit this classifier to make it ignore this misleading text
and thus predict the underlying object correctly. To do so, we start from an
unrelated image of a can opener and synthetically create two version of that
image: one where we paste an “ipod” label and one where we paste a blank label.
We then edit the model to map “ipod” to “blank” and we find that this corrects
the model predictions on all images, making the model impervious to this
typographic-attack!</p>

<p><img class="bigimg" src="https://gradientscience.org/assets/editing/ipod_edit.png" style="width: 90%;"/></p>
<div class="footnote"> <strong>Mitigating typographic attacks via editing.</strong> 
Mapping the text ipod to "blank" allows us to correct all model mistakes caused
by the misleading text, recovering the underlying object prediction.</div>

<p>In contrast, fine-tuning is not a reliable solution. While it can fix some
mistakes (potentially by adjusting class biases), it often causes the model to
incorrectly associate other objects with the fine-tuning label and/or decreases
model performance on actual ipod images.</p>

<h2 id="large-scale-synthetic-evaluation">Large-scale synthetic evaluation</h2>
<p>While the two examples that we looked at so far might be compelling, we want to
stress test our method on a wider variety of settings. Unfortunately, manually
identifying interesting scenarios and collecting the corresponding datasets is
a daunting task. We thus focus on creating <em>synthetic</em> editing test cases.</p>

<p>Specifically, we want to setup scenarios in which we transform a specific
concept (e.g., “wheel”) in a consistent manner across classes. This way, if the
editing process is successful, performing the edit using a few of these images
should significantly improve the performance of the model on other transformed
images.</p>

<p>To setup such scenarios in a scalable manner, we leverage a pipeline based on
pre-trained instance segmentation models and style transfer (we manually
collect a set of textures to use as styles).</p>

<p><img class="bigimg" src="https://gradientscience.org/assets/editing/synthetic.png" style="width: 90%;"/></p>
<div class="footnote"> <strong>Creating synthetic test cases.</strong> 
By leveraging pre-trained instance segmentation models and style transfer, we
can transform concepts in large existing datasets. This allows us to create
editing test cases in a scalable way.</div>

<p>With this pipeline in place, we evaluate editing across a wide range of
examples and measure how many of the errors caused by these transformations get
corrected. As a baseline, we compare ourselves to fine-tuning of either the
whole network, or of all the layers after the one that we perform editing on.</p>

<p><img class="bigimg" src="https://gradientscience.org/assets/editing/results.png" style="width: 95%;"/></p>
<div class="footnote"> <strong>Editing performance.</strong> Editing
consistently corrects the mistakes caused by the transformations we apply. In
fact, this is true even for classes that are different from the one used to
perform the edit. In contrast, fine-tuning does not generalize in the same way
and only corrects mistakes on images of the same class.</div>

<p>Looking at these results, we can observe that when measuring the impact of
editing and fine-tuning on images of the same class used during editing, both
methods perform reasonably well. However, when we focus on images of <em>other</em>
classes—which would reflect actual generalization—editing continues to
correct errors while fine-tuning often causes more errors than it fixes!</p>

<h2 id="beyond-editing-synthetic-test-cases-as-counterfactuals">Beyond editing: Synthetic test cases as counterfactuals</h2>
<p>While we developed the above pipeline with the goal of  benchmarking editing
methods in mind, it turns out to be useful more broadly. In fact, it
provides us with a scalable way to evaluate models on <em>counterfactuals</em>, i.e.,
to test how the model’s  prediction changes when a given concept of interest is
transformed. Such counterfactuals-based analysis can be used to get a
better understanding of which concepts are important for the model to recognize
each class as well as to reveal model sensitivities across classes.</p>

<p><img class="bigimg" src="https://gradientscience.org/assets/editing/analysis.png" style="width: 95%;"/></p>
<div class="footnote"> <strong>Counterfactual-based model analysis. </strong> 
Using the synthetic transformations we described we can analyze how model
predictions are sensitive to the presence of various objects.</div>

<h2 id="moving-forward">Moving forward</h2>
<p>In this post, we described a framework for directly editing classification
models. We saw how such editing can be a powerful and versatile primitive for
correcting model behavior with minimal data gathering and human labor.
However, we are still only starting to understand what is possible
through this framework. What other model edits would be useful to have?
How can we “localize” our edits so that they only apply to a specific context?
How do we edit multiple prediction rules at once?</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://gradientscience.org/</id>
      <author>
        <name>Gradient Science</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://gradientscience.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gradientscience.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Research highlights and perspectives on machine learning and optimization from MadryLab.</subtitle>
      <title>gradient science</title>
      <updated>2021-12-04T23:26:59Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=592</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2021/12/02/tcs-talk-wednesday-december-8-guy-blanc-stanford/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, December 8 — Guy Blanc, Stanford</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk (and last of the semester!) will take place this coming Wednesday, December 8th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). Guy Blanc from Stanford will speak about “Properly learning decision trees in almost polynomial time” (abstract below). You can reserve a spot as […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk (and last of the semester!) will take place this coming Wednesday, December 8th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~gblanc/"><strong>Guy Blanc</strong></a> from Stanford will speak about “<em>Properly learning decision trees in almost polynomial time</em>” (abstract below).</p>
<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/next-tcs-talk">the online form</a>. Registration is <em>not</em> required to attend the interactive talk, and the link will be posted on the website the day prior to the talk; however, by registering in the form, you will receive a reminder, along with the link. (The recorded talk will also be posted <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/past-talks">on our website</a> afterwards) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/suggest-a-talk">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/">the website</a>.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Abstract: We give an <img alt="n^{O(\log\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7BO%28%5Clog%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-time membership query algorithm for properly and agnostically learning decision trees under the uniform distribution over <img alt="\{-1,1\}^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%7B-1%2C1%5C%7D%5En&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. Even in the realizable setting, the previous fastest runtime was <img alt="n^{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, a consequence of a classic algorithm of Ehrenfeucht and Haussler.</p>
<p>Our algorithm shares similarities with practical heuristics for learning decision trees, which we augment with additional ideas to circumvent known lower bounds against these heuristics. To analyze our algorithm, we prove a new structural result for decision trees that strengthens a theorem of O’Donnell, Saks, Schramm, and Servedio. While the OSSS theorem says that every decision tree has an influential variable, we show how every decision tree can be “pruned” so that every variable in the resulting tree is influential.</p>
<p>Joint work with Jane Lange, Mingda Qiao, and Li-Yang Tan (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.00637">arXiv:2109.00637</a>). To appear in FOCS 2021.</p></blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-02T21:26:26Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-02T21:26:26Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/171</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/171" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-171 |  Algorithms and Lower Bounds for Comparator Circuits from Shrinkage | 

	Bruno Pasqualotto Cavalar, 

	Zhenjian Lu</title>
    <summary>Comparator circuits are a natural circuit model for studying bounded fan-out computation whose power sits between nondeterministic branching programs and general circuits. Despite having been studied for nearly three decades, the first superlinear lower bound against comparator circuits was proved only recently by Gál and Robere (ITCS 2020), who established a $\Omega((n/\log n)^{1.5})$ lower bound on the size of comparator circuits computing an explicit function of $n$ bits. 

In this paper, we initiate the study of average-case complexity and circuit analysis algorithms for comparator circuits. Departing from previous approaches, we exploit the technique of shrinkage under random restrictions to obtain a variety of new results for this model. Among our results, we show 

- Average-case Lower Bounds. For every $k = k(n)$ with $k \geq \log n$, there exists a polynomial-time computable function $f_k$ on $n$ bits such that, for every comparator circuit $C$ with at most $n^{1.5}/O(k\cdot \sqrt{\log n})$ gates, we have 
 
\[ \text{Pr}_{x\in\left\{ 0,1 \right\}^n}\left[C(x)=f_k(x)\right]\leq \frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{2^{\Omega(k)}}. \]

This average-case lower bound matches the worst-case lower bound of Gál and Robere by letting $k=O(\log n)$. 

- #SAT Algorithms. There is an algorithm that counts the number of satisfying assignments of a given comparator circuit with at most $n^{1.5}/O\!\left(k\cdot \sqrt{\log n}\right)$ gates, in time $2^{n-k}\cdot\text{poly}(n)$, for any $k\leq n/4$. The running time is non-trivial when $k=\omega(\log n)$. 

- Pseudorandom Generators and MCSP Lower Bounds. There is a pseudorandom generator of seed length $s^{2/3+o(1)}$ that fools comparator circuits with $s$ gates. Also, using this PRG, we obtain an $n^{1.5-o(1)}$ lower bound for MCSP against comparator circuits.</summary>
    <updated>2021-12-02T15:39:46Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-02T15:39:46Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6143</id>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6143" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6143#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=6143" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Two new talks and an interview</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">A talk to UT Austin’s undergraduate math club (handwritten PDF notes) about Hao Huang’s proof of the Sensitivity Conjecture, and its implications for quantum query complexity and more. I’m still not satisfied that I’ve presented Huang’s beautiful proof as clearly and self-containedly as I possibly can, which probably just means I need to lecture on […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ol><li>A <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/talks/sensitivity.pdf">talk to UT Austin’s undergraduate math club</a> (handwritten PDF notes) about <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.00847">Hao Huang’s proof of the Sensitivity Conjecture</a>, and its implications for quantum query complexity and more.  I’m <em>still</em> not satisfied that I’ve presented Huang’s beautiful proof as clearly and self-containedly as I possibly can, which probably just means I need to lecture on it a few more times.</li><li>A <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/talks/aar-china.ppt">Zoom talk at the QPQIS conference in Beijing</a> (PowerPoint slides), setting out my most recent thoughts about Google’s and USTC’s quantum supremacy experiments and the continuing efforts to spoof them classically.</li><li>An <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2021/12/256937-exploring-the-promise-of-quantum-computing/fulltext">interview with me in <em>Communications of the ACM</em></a>, mostly about BosonSampling and the quantum lower bound for the collision problem.</li></ol>



<p>Enjoy y’all!</p>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-02T07:16:55Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-02T07:16:55Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <icon>https://scottaaronson.blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-Jacket-32x32.gif</icon>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2021-12-03T16:19:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19386</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/12/01/the-new-journal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The New Journal</title>
    <summary>Publish and be damned!—attributed to the Duke of Wellington after a blackmail over memoirs Seminar src Paul Beame is a Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the University of Washington. He is known for work in logical complexity and lower bounds—in proving, for example, time-space tradeoffs. He is also interested in […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Publish and be damned!—attributed to the Duke of Wellington after a blackmail over memoirs</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/12/01/the-new-journal/beame/" rel="attachment wp-att-19388"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-19388" height="132" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/Beame.jpg?resize=120%2C132&amp;ssl=1" width="120"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Seminar <a href="https://cse.ucsd.edu/research/paul-beame-theory-seminar">src</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Paul Beame is a Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the University of Washington. He is known for work in logical complexity and lower bounds—in proving, for example, time-space tradeoffs. He is also interested in the practical applications of symbolic model checking for the verification of software specifications.</p>
<p>
Today we are glad to convey the announcement he forwarded of the creation of a new open-access journal dedicated to Theoretical Computer Science. </p>
<p>
The <a href="https://theoretics-journal.org">new journal</a> is called <font color="red"><b>TheoretiCS</b></font> and lists the following <em>distinguished endorsers</em> who are top leaders in all of theory: </p>
<ul>
<li>
Noga Alon <p/>
</li><li>
Shafi Goldwasser <p/>
</li><li>
Donald Knuth <p/>
</li><li>
Robert Tarjan <p/>
</li><li>
Leslie Valiant <p/>
</li><li>
Moshe Vardi <p/>
</li><li>
Andrew Yao
</li></ul>
<p>
They have just thrown their <a href="https://theoretics-journal.org">page</a> open for business today, December 1. </p>
<p>
There used to be an independent self-publishing fair held every year in London called “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Publish_and_Be_Damned">Publish and Be Damned</a>.” The association of <font color="red"><b>TheoretiCS</b></font> with the computing section of <a href="https://arxiv.org/corr">ArXiv</a> might smack of self-publishing but this journal is in every further respect the opposite:</p>
<ul>
<li>
It uses the <em>overlay journal</em> platform <a href="https://episciences.org/">Episciences</a>, whose mission is to “add value to these archives by attaching a scientific caution to the validated papers.” <p/>
</li><li>
It has a large and capable board of editors who will work the way the other major established print and online journals do.
</li></ul>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Editors </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Paul wrote us a direct e-mail and emphasized two points at the start (with our light editing):</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> </em></p><em>
<ol>
<li>
The aim of <font color="red"><b>TheoretiCS</b></font> to publish articles of a very high quality, to become a reference journal on par with the leading journals in all of Theoretical Computer Science, and <p/>
</li><li>
The [internationally] inclusive view of Theoretical Computer Science that this journal represents, which is evident in the choice of two excellent co-editors-in-chief and an outstanding inaugural editorial board.
</li></ol>
</em><p><em/>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
He adds that it was thanks to the leadership of Thomas Schwentick and others, including helping to gain <a href="https://theoretics.episciences.org/page/theoretics-foundation">sponsorship</a>, and the hard work of the co-editors-in-chief, managing editors, and the rest of the Advisory Board, that this new journal launch was made possible.</p>
<p>
The Chief Editors are:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Javier Esparza, Technische Universität München <p/>
</li><li>
Uri Zwick, Tel Aviv University.
</li></ul>
<p>
The editorial board is: </p>
<ul>
<li>
Martin Abadi, Google (Alphabet), USA <p/>
</li><li>
Andris Ambainis, U. of Latvia <p/>
</li><li>
Albert Atserias, UPC, Barcelona <p/>
</li><li>
Haris Aziz, UNSW, Sydney <p/>
</li><li>
David Basin, ETH, Zurich <p/>
</li><li>
Patricia Bouyer, CNRS, Paris-Saclay <p/>
</li><li>
Nicolo Cesa-Bianchi, Universitá di Milano <p/>
</li><li>
Anuj Dawar, Cambridge University <p/>
</li><li>
Luc Devroye, McGill University, Montreal <p/>
</li><li>
Jacob Fox, Stanford University <p/>
</li><li>
Mohsen Ghaffari, ETH, Zurich <p/>
</li><li>
Georg Gottlob, Oxford University <p/>
</li><li>
Anupam Gupta, Carnegie-Mellon University <p/>
</li><li>
Venkatesan Guruswami, Carnegie-Mellon University <p/>
</li><li>
Johan Håstad, KTH, Stockholm <p/>
</li><li>
Ravi Kannan, Microsoft Research India, Bengaluru <p/>
</li><li>
Anna Karlin, University of Washington, Seattle <p/>
</li><li>
Ken-ichi Kawarabayashi, National Institute of Informatics, Tokyo <p/>
</li><li>
Valerie King, University of Victoria <p/>
</li><li>
Robert Kleinberg, Cornell University <p/>
</li><li>
Naoki Kobayashi, University of Tokyo <p/>
</li><li>
Elias Koutsoupias, Oxford University <p/>
</li><li>
Xavier Leroy, College de France <p/>
</li><li>
Katrina Ligett, Hebrew University <p/>
</li><li>
Rupak Majumdar, MPI-SWS, Kaiserslautern <p/>
</li><li>
Joseph Mitchell, Stony Brook University <p/>
</li><li>
Mehryar Mohri, Google and New York University <p/>
</li><li>
David Mount, University of Maryland <p/>
</li><li>
Anca Muscholl, Université de Bordeaux <p/>
</li><li>
Danupon Nanongkai, University of Copenhagen <p/>
</li><li>
Moni Naor, Weizmann Institute, Rehovot <p/>
</li><li>
Catuscia Palamidessi, Inria Palaiseau <p/>
</li><li>
Michal Pilipczuk, University of Warsaw <p/>
</li><li>
Jean-Francois Raskin, Université Libre de Bruxelles <p/>
</li><li>
Peter Sanders, KIT, Karlsruhe <p/>
</li><li>
Davide Sangiorgi, Universitá di Bologna <p/>
</li><li>
Nitin Saxena, IIT Kanpur <p/>
</li><li>
Alistair Sinclair, UC Berkeley <p/>
</li><li>
Ola Svensson, EPF Lausanne <p/>
</li><li>
Gregory Valiant, Stanford University <p/>
</li><li>
Stephanie Weirich, University of Pennsylvania <p/>
</li><li>
Virginia V. Williams, Massachusetts Institute of Technology <p/>
</li><li>
James Worrell, Oxford University <p/>
</li><li>
Mihalis Yannakakis, Columbia University
</li></ul>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Why A New Journal? </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Indeed. The announcement adds:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> – We believe that our field (and science in general) needs more ‘virtuous’ open-access journals, a whole eco-system of them, with various levels of specialization and of selectivity. We also believe that, along with the structuring role played by conferences in theoretical computer science, we collectively need to re-develop the practice of journal publications. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
There is a long, historical, good point here. Thirty years ago, David S. Johnson moved personal mountains to compile the <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/book/10.1145/117006">STOC/FOCS Bibliography</a>, whose essential subtitle <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/book/10.1145/117006">(preliminary version)</a> spoke a truth expanded in the blurb by Michael Loui:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “Many computer scientists believe, erroneously, that it is sufficient to publish their papers in conferences, particularly prestigious conferences such as STOC and FOCS—and neglect to publish them in journals. In contrast, this bibliography emphasizes the benefits of archival publication in rigorously refereed journals. Often, the journal version corrects errors, provides more details, and extends the results of the conference paper.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
ArXiv, however, has put more weight in the other end of this boat. It is the easy end to step into and ride; your humble bloggers confess a few instances ourselves. After noting he’d already used the STOC/FOCS Bibliography to locate journal versions of papers, Michael—again, writing in <b>1991</b>—finished by saying,</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “Compiling and maintaining [this and other similar] bibliographies would require the continual cooperation of many authors and journal editors, but the results would be worth the effort.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
We interpret what Paul is saying along these lines.  It may not be a completely new kind of journal—it goes for continuity with the kind we know—or a completely new mission for a journal.  But it is responding to new contexts and environments for journals, like watercraft in a 007 movie.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> More Aims </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The announcement also declares these purposes:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> </em></p><em>
<ul>
<li>
The scope of <font color="red"><b>TheoretiCS</b></font> is the whole of Theoretical Computer Science, understood in an inclusive meaning (concretely: including, but not restricted to, the Theory of Computing and the Theory of Programming; or equivalently, the so-called TCS-A and TCS-B, reminiscent of Jan van Leeuwen et al.’s Handbook of Theoretical Computer Science). <p/>
</li><li>
Our aim is to rapidly become a reference journal and to contribute to the unity of the Theoretical Computer Science global community. In particular, we will seek to publish only papers that make a very significant contribution to their respective fields, that strive to be accessible to a wider audience within theoretical computer science, and that are, generally, of a quality on par with the very best journals in the field. <p/>
</li><li>
<font color="red"><b>TheoretiCS</b></font> adheres to the principles of ‘virtuous’ open-access: there is no charge to read the journal, nor to publish in it. The copyright of the papers will remain with the authors, under a Creative Commons license.
</li></ul>
</em><p><em>
</em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Some further points and history are given in full in the <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/12/theoretics-new-tcs-journal.html">posting</a> on Lance and Bill’s blog.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We are excited by the creation of <font color="red"><b>TheoretiCS</b></font>. We especially like the ability to freely read articles and also to freely submit articles. We look forward to see the articles that will appear in the journal. Please submit some of your new results. Good luck. </p>
<p>
We certainly hope to see some of the following in the journal soon: </p>
<ul>
<li>
A Super Linear Lower Bound on the Circuit Size for 3-SAT. <p/>
</li><li>
A Simple Quantum Algorithm for Almost All Cases of the Halting Problem. <p/>
</li><li>
Graph Isomorphism is in Polynomial Time.
</li></ul>
<p>
What do you hope to see soon in <font color="red"><b>TheoretiCS</b></font>?</p>
<p/><p><br/>
[Further information about principals added; less emphasis on Beame]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-02T02:48:19Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-02T02:48:19Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Javier Esparza"/>
    <category term="new journal"/>
    <category term="Paul Beame"/>
    <category term="publishing"/>
    <category term="TheoretiCS"/>
    <category term="Theory"/>
    <category term="Uri Zwick"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:20:57Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=970</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2021/12/01/pitassi-more-and-more-im-starting-to-wonder-whether-p-equals-np/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Pitassi: “More and more, I’m starting to wonder whether P equals NP.”</title>
    <summary>It’s refreshing to hear other people are joining our “ranks,” especially after some have said that my belief that P=NP is a publicity stunt. (For context, you may want to read the first two sentences of my post.) I got the quote from the Simons Institute Newsletter, which points to a longer MIT Technology Review […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>It’s refreshing to hear other people are joining our “ranks,” especially after some have said that <a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2018/02/16/i-believe-pnp/">my belief that P=NP</a> is a <a href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2018/02/np-is-hard.html">publicity stunt</a>. (For context, you may want to read the first two sentences of my post.)  I got the quote from the <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/news/50-year-old-problem-eludes-theoretical-computer-science">Simons Institute Newsletter</a>, which points to a longer <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2021/10/27/1037123/p-np-theoretical-computer-science">MIT Technology Review</a> article to which I don’t have access.  The newsletter article mentions two well-known surprising results (also on my list), and another cool one which came after my post and that I was thinking of adding.  For more surprising results, see my list.  What do you believe?</p>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-01T16:57:12Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-01T16:57:12Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="lower bounds"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:29Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/01/postdoc-in-theory-group-at-epfl-apply-by-december-31-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/01/postdoc-in-theory-group-at-epfl-apply-by-december-31-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc in Theory Group at EPFL (apply by December 31, 2021)</title>
    <summary>EPFL invites applications for postdoctoral positions in the Theory Group. Applications will be reviewed by theory faculty (as listed on https://theory.epfl.ch/). EPFL is located in Lausanne and ranks among the world’s top scientific universities. Postdoctoral positions come with a competitive salary for 1 year (83’600 CHF with yearly increments), renewable up to a maximum of […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>EPFL invites applications for postdoctoral positions in the Theory Group. Applications will be reviewed by theory faculty (as listed on <a href="https://theory.epfl.ch/">https://theory.epfl.ch/</a>).</p>
<p>EPFL is located in Lausanne and ranks among the world’s top scientific universities. Postdoctoral positions come with a competitive salary for 1 year (83’600 CHF with yearly increments), renewable up to a maximum of 4 years.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://recruiting.epfl.ch/Vacancies/2123/Description/2">https://recruiting.epfl.ch/Vacancies/2123/Description/2</a><br/>
Email: tcs-postdoc@groupes.epfl.ch</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-01T14:26:08Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-01T14:26:08Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-490294947597886220</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/490294947597886220/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/12/theoretics-new-tcs-journal.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/490294947597886220" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/490294947597886220" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/12/theoretics-new-tcs-journal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TheoretiCS: A New TCS Journal</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><i>Guest Post from Paul Beame on behalf of the TheoretiCS Foundation</i></p><p>I am writing to let you know of the launch today of <a href="https://theoretics-journal.org">TheoretiCS</a>, a new fully open-access journal dedicated to Theoretical Computer Science developed by the members of our community that I have been involved in and for which I gave a brief pre-announcement about at STOC.</p><p>This journal has involved an unprecedented level of cooperation of representatives of leading conferences from across the entire Theoretical Computer Science spectrum. This includes representatives from STOC, FOCS, SODA, CCC, PODC, SoCG, TCC, COLT, ITCS, ICALP, which may be more familiar to readers of your blog, as well as from LICS, CSL, CONCUR, ICDT, MFCS and a number of others.</p><p><b>Two Points of Emphasis</b></p><p/><ul style="text-align: left;"><li>Our quality objective - TheoretiCS aims at publishing articles of a very high quality, and at becoming a reference journal on par with the leading journals in all of Theoretical Computer Science</li><li>The inclusive view of Theoretical Computer Science that this journal represents, which is evident in the choice of two excellent co-editors-in-chief, Javier Esparza and Uri Zwick, and an outstanding <a href="https://theoretics.episciences.org/page/editorial-board">inaugural editorial board</a>.</li></ul><p/><p><b>Guiding principles and objectives</b></p><p/><ul style="text-align: left;"><li>We believe that our field (and science in general) needs more 'virtuous' open-access journals, a whole eco-system of them, with various levels of specialization and of selectivity. We also believe that, along with the structuring role played by conferences in theoretical computer science, we collectively need to re-develop the practice of journal publications.</li><li>The scope of TheoretiCS is the whole of Theoretical Computer Science, understood in an inclusive meaning (concretely: including, but not restricted to, the Theory of Computing and the Theory of Programming; or equivalently, the so-called TCS-A and TCS-B, reminiscent of Jan van Leeuwen et al.'s Handbook of Theoretical Computer Science).</li><li>Our aim is to rapidly become a reference journal and to contribute to the unity of the Theoretical Computer Science global community. In particular, we will seek to publish only papers that make a very significant contribution to their respective fields, that strive to be accessible to a wider audience within theoretical computer science, and that are, generally, of a quality on par with the very best journals in the field.</li><li>TheoretiCS adheres to the principles of 'virtuous' open-access: there is no charge to read the journal, nor to publish in it. The copyright of the papers remains with the authors, under a Creative Commons license.</li></ul><p/><p><b>Organization and a bit of history</b></p><p>The project started in 2019 and underwent a long gestation. From the start, we wanted to have a thorough discussion with a wide representation of the community, on how to best implement the guiding principles sketched above. It was deemed essential to make sure that all fields of theoretical computer science would feel at home in this journal, and that it would be recognized as a valid venue for publication all over the world.</p><p>This resulted in the creation of an <a href="https://theoretics.episciences.org/page/advisory-board">Advisory Board</a>, composed of representatives of most of the main conferences in the field (currently APPROX, CCC, COLT, CONCUR, CSL, FOCS, FoSSaCS, FSCD, FSTTCS, ICALP, ICDT, ITCS, LICS, MFCS, PODC, SoCG, SODA, STACS, STOC, TCC) and of so-called members-at-large. </p><p><b>Logistics and answers to some natural questions</b></p><p/><ul style="text-align: left;"><li>The journal is published by the TheoretiCS Foundation, a non-profit foundation established under German law. Thomas Schwentick, Pascal Weil, and Meena Mahajan are officers of the foundation.</li><li>TheoretiCS is based on the platform <a href="https://episciences.org/">episciences.org</a>, in the spirit of a so-called overlay journal.</li><li>The Advisory Board, together with the Editors-in-Chief and the Managing Editors, spent much of their efforts in designing and implementing an efficient 2-phase review system: efficient in terms of the added-value it brings to the published papers and their authors, and of the time it takes. Yet, as this review system relies in an essential fashion on the work and expertise of colleagues (like in all classical reputable journals), we can not guarantee a fixed duration for the evaluation of the papers submitted to TheoretiCS.</li><li>Being charge-free for authors and readers does not mean that there is no cost to publishing a journal. These costs are supported for the foreseeable future by academic institutions (at the moment, CNRS and Inria, in France; others may join).</li><li>The journal will have an ISSN, and each paper will have a DOI. There will be no print edition.</li></ul><p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-01T14:06:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-01T14:06:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T03:05:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/01/t-tt-faculty-at-the-university-of-arizona-apply-by-december-8-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/01/t-tt-faculty-at-the-university-of-arizona-apply-by-december-8-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>T/TT faculty at The University of Arizona (apply by December 8, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Systems and Industrial Engineering at the University of Arizona invites applications for a tenure-track position in Software Engineering. Areas of interest include (1) Software Requirements Analysis and Testing, (2) Software Assurance, Quality, and Reliability, (3) Formal Methods in Software Engineering, (4) Software Project Management, and (5) AI in Software Engineering. Website: https://arizona.csod.com/ux/ats/careersite/4/home/requisition/7321?c=arizona […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Systems and Industrial Engineering at the University of Arizona invites applications for a tenure-track position in Software Engineering. Areas of interest include (1) Software Requirements Analysis and Testing, (2) Software Assurance, Quality, and Reliability, (3) Formal Methods in Software Engineering, (4) Software Project Management, and (5) AI in Software Engineering.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://arizona.csod.com/ux/ats/careersite/4/home/requisition/7321?c=arizona">https://arizona.csod.com/ux/ats/careersite/4/home/requisition/7321?c=arizona</a><br/>
Email: son@sie.arizona.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-01T09:46:09Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-01T09:46:09Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>http://benjamin-recht.github.io/2021/12/01/unblinding/</id>
    <link href="http://benjamin-recht.github.io/2021/12/01/unblinding/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What were the effects of the Bangladesh mask intervention?</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>There’s been a bit of a social-media back-and-forth between us and Jason Abaluck about the design and statistical significance of the <a href="https://www.poverty-action.org/sites/default/files/publications/Mask_Second_Stage_Paper_20211108.pdf.pdf">Bangladesh Mask RCT</a>. To focus and hone the discussion on some crucial details, we just posted a <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2112.01296">short note</a> where we re-analyzed the data from this trial using standard non-parametric paired statistics tests on treatment-village pairs. In this blog, we summarize those results, highlighting potentially significant biases in the study. Importantly, we found that the behavior of unblinded staff when enrolling study participants was one of the most highly significant differences between treatment and control groups. The significant impacts on staff and participant behavior urge caution in interpreting small differences in the study outcomes which depended on survey responses.</p>

<p>Let’s first review the full study protocol, as it’s a cluster RCT and hence a bit more complicated than the typical trials with which many are familiar. First 600 villages in Bangladesh were paired based on COVID-case data, population density, and population size. Each paired village was assigned to treatment or control at random. Next, observers were sent to the treatment and control villages to enroll households in the study. Importantly, observers <em>were not blinded</em> to the treatment assignment in each village. The observers were also tasked with giving out the masks in the intervention villages, so they knew if the village was assigned to treatment or control. Households were approached by the observers and the households either (a) consented to participate, (b) declined to participate, or (c) were marked “unreachable” by the unblinded observers. The study team then proceeded to implement a mask promotion intervention in the treatment villages. In both villages, participants were asked to report COVID-like symptoms. Those who reported symptoms were asked to volunteer blood draws for serology. The primary endpoint was evaluated based on the number of these blood draws that tested positive for COVID antibodies.</p>

<p>As we have noted before, despite 300:300 randomization of the 600 villages, there was a notable imbalance in the size of the consenting populations between the control and treatment groups. The control group contained 156,938 individuals while the treatment group contained 170,497 individuals. The total absolute numbers of symptomatic seropositives in the treatment and control villages was 1086 and 1106, respectively. This difference is too small to be significant if participants had been individually randomized. In the study, an effect is asserted for the <em>relative rate</em> of symptomatic seropositives, i.e., normalized by population denominators. We note that the 10% decrease reported in the fraction of individuals who become symptomatic seropositives is not driven primarily by a decrease in the numerator of this fraction of symptomatic seropositives, but instead by the increase in the denominator.</p>

<p>What is the right way to test whether attributes differ between the treatment and control groups? If we have an attribute that we observe in every village, we can assess the hypothesis “a control village is equally likely to have a larger value of the attribute than its control pair than it is to have a smaller value.” Since the villages were paired, a standard non-parametric test for such questions is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wilcoxon_signed-rank_test">Wilcoxon signed-rank test</a>. This test is nice because we need not worry about using sophisticated models or variance correction techniques. Instead, we can just try to assess if bulk statistics are plausibly different in the treatment and control groups. Let’s use this test to gain insights about the mask study.</p>

<p>First, let’s look at the count in each village of individuals who reported COVID-19 symptoms and tested positive for covid-antibodies. The null hypothesis is that it is equally likely for a paired village to have more symptomatic seropositive in control as in treatment. According to the Wilcoxon signed rank test, the p-value is 0.97 and we cannot reject the null hypothesis. What about the <em>rate</em> of symptomatic seropositivity? Was the percentage of infections in the control group higher than in the treatment? Again, we cannot reject the null as the p-value of the Wilcoxon test is 0.25. In our writeup, we found similar results when restricting attention to subgroups assigned to cloth masks and surgical masks, and also in the population of individuals over 60. Based on these tests, we cannot assert that the intervention affected the primary endpoint of symptomatic seroprevalence. However, there are behavioral effects that are significantly different between treatment and control.</p>

<p class="center"><img alt="Boxplots of different village features" src="http://www.argmin.net/assets/village_attribute_boxplots.png" width="100%"/></p>

<p>From our analysis, it is quite clear that more mask wearing was observed in the treatment group rather than the control group (p&lt;$10^{-47}$). Moreover, there was a large difference in observed social distancing (p&lt;$10^{-15}$). It is notable—even if one did not expect any effect from masks at all—that the increase in observed physical distancing did not translate to clearer differences in symptomatic seropositivity between treatment and control groups.</p>

<p>Second, the populations of the treatment and control groups themselves are very different. One of the main difficulties in running a mask trial is the issue of blinding. You certainly cannot run a blinded intervention as people know whether or not they are wearing masks. But in such unblinded studies, it is critical that the populations sampled to be surveyed are identical before the unblinding occurs.</p>

<p>Here is where things get a bit subtle. The villages were assigned to treatment at random, but the households were not. The surveyors who handed out masks knew in advance the treatment assignment of their villages. This knowledge alone induced a highly significant difference. <em>The fraction of households approached in each village is significantly different in treatment and control</em> (p&lt;$10^{-11}$). This selection bias induced a large imbalance in the size of the treatment and control groups, and may have affected the overall seropositivity counts. Interestingly we found that the rate of consent for symptom surveys and the rate of consent for blood draws were indistinguishable between treatment and controls. The main significant difference was due to the behavior of the study staff.</p>

<p class="center"><img alt="Boxplots of survey interactions" src="http://www.argmin.net/assets/survey_boxplots.png" width="100%"/></p>

<p>That the unblinded staff behaved differently in the different types of villages is not surprising and similar experimenter behavior has blemished randomized trials since their inception. We can’t know the exact cause of the difference in households reached, but perhaps the staff put just a little bit more effort into soliciting responses in the treatment group because they were excited about testing their intervention. Whatever the case, this behavioral difference created a large population difference between the groups: whereas 3,394 of 68,514 households were unreachable in the treatment group, 4,970 of 65,536 households were unreachable in control. This is a difference of over four thousand people, far exceeding the 20 case difference in symptomatic seropositivity.</p>

<p>Our analysis suggests that the impact of the mask intervention was highly effective at modifying behaviors (distancing, mask-wearing, symptom reporting), but that any effect on actual symptomatic seropositivity was much more subtle. In particular, whatever effects the intervention had on the rate of symptomatic seropositivity in the villages was certainly not large relative to other factors contributing to variance in this parameter across villages.
We suggest that the very large causal effects on consent rates and thus population denominators urge caution in interpreting the small differences we see in symptomatic seropositivity between treatment and controls, which are not statistically significant according to standard nonparametric paired tests.</p>

<p><em>Code to reproduce the figures in this post and those in our technical <a href="https://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~brecht/papers/CPR_mask_note.pdf">note</a> can be found <a href="https://github.com/mchikina/maskRCTnote">here</a>.</em></p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-12-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>http://benjamin-recht.github.io/</id>
      <author>
        <name>Ben Recht</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://benjamin-recht.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://benjamin-recht.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Musings on systems, information, learning, and optimization.</subtitle>
      <title>arg min blog</title>
      <updated>2021-12-04T23:27:52Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/30/associate-or-full-professor-uc-san-diego-cse-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-1-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/30/associate-or-full-professor-uc-san-diego-cse-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-1-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Associate or Full Professor – UC San Diego CSE at University of California – San Diego (apply by January 1, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The UC San Diego Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) invites applications for multiple tenured faculty positions at the Associate or Full Professor rank. The department is looking for exceptional candidates in all areas of Computer Science and Engineering. Applicants must have a Ph.D. in computer science or a related area at the time […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The UC San Diego Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) invites applications for multiple tenured faculty positions at the Associate or Full Professor rank. The department is looking for exceptional candidates in all areas of Computer Science and Engineering. Applicants must have a Ph.D. in computer science or a related area at the time of application.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF03001">https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF03001</a><br/>
Email: nherrera@eng.ucsd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-30T21:36:33Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-30T21:36:33Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/30/assistant-professor-at-uc-san-diego-cse-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-1-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/30/assistant-professor-at-uc-san-diego-cse-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-1-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor at UC San Diego CSE at University of California – San Diego (apply by January 1, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The UC San Diego Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) invites applications for multiple tenure-track faculty positions at the Assistant Professor rank. The department is looking for exceptional candidates in all areas of Computer Science &amp; Engineering. A Ph.D. or advancement to candidacy in Computer Science &amp; Engineering or related disciplines is required at […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The UC San Diego Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) invites applications for multiple tenure-track faculty positions at the Assistant Professor rank. The department is looking for exceptional candidates in all areas of Computer Science &amp; Engineering. A Ph.D. or advancement to candidacy in Computer Science &amp; Engineering or related disciplines is required at the time of application</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF03000">https://apol-recruit.ucsd.edu/JPF03000</a><br/>
Email: nherrera@eng.ucsd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-30T21:33:34Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-30T21:33:34Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/11/30/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/11/30/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>Joanne Cohn and the email list that led to arXiv (\(\mathbb{M}\)). If, like me, you thought arXiv was started by Paul Ginsparg, you’re mistaken. Ginsparg deserves a lot of credit for setting up most of arXiv’s infrastructure but he only did it after Cohn gave him a ball to run with.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/PT.6.4.20211108a">Joanne Cohn and the email list that led to arXiv</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107291497920204652">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> If, like me, you thought arXiv was started by Paul Ginsparg, you’re mistaken. Ginsparg deserves a lot of credit for setting up most of arXiv’s infrastructure but he only did it after Cohn gave him a ball to run with.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I ran across a reference to French mathematical artist Sylvie Pic in Étienne Ghys’ online book ‘‘<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.06373">A Singular Mathematical Promenade</a>’’ <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107297267002982515">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>)</span> and am intrigued by her work but can only find snippets here and there. A few links: <a href="https://les-traces-habiles.org/tag/sylvie-pic/">les traces habiles</a>, <a href="http://www.documentsdartistes.org/artistes/pic/repro7-1.html">documents d’artistes</a>, <a href="https://artuk.org/discover/artists/pic-sylvie-b-1957">Sucharda’s Still Life (2006)</a>, and a Google Books link to an essay by Pic about her work: <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=i2qnl1P9pyEC&amp;pg=PA253">“Some Aspects of the Use of Geometry in My Artistic Work”, in ‘‘The Visual Mind II’’</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w2T12mnk7tg">Colouring Graphs and Fermat’s Conjecture</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107302448008422359">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> How Issai Schur used graph Ramsey theory to prove that the Fermat equation \(x^n+y^n=z^n\) has solutions <span style="white-space: nowrap;">modulo \(p\)</span> for all but finitely many <span style="white-space: nowrap;">primes \(p\).</span> Another Some1 math-explainer video, I think?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://discrete-notes.github.io/contraction-sequences">Contraction sequences</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107308282315835268">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> This introduces twin-width, a hot topic in graph structure theory and structure-based algorithms, more broadly than you might get from its research papers. Twin-width is based on repeated merging pairs of vertices with similar neighborhoods, aiming for each cluster to be nonuniformly connected to very few other clusters, but other kinds of width can be formulated in this way and this view leads to an alternative proof of Courcelle’s theorem.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Szemer%C3%A9di_regularity_lemma">Szemerédi regularity lemma</a> now <a href="https://www.isa-afp.org/entries/Szemeredi_Regularity.html">formalized in Isabelle</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107314263241628934">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/wtgowers/status/1459271456865591298">via</a>).</span> This is the result that every graph’s vertices can be partitioned into few subsets so that the subgraph between most pairs of subsets resemble random graphs of varying densities. It’s not the Robertson–Seymour theorem or the strong perfect graph theorem, but still it’s good to see some serious graph theory getting attention from the proof assistant crowd.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://gallery.bridgesmathart.org/exhibitions/2022-joint-mathematics-meetings">The 2022 JMM mathematical art gallery is already online</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107319825945929357">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> although I’m not sure, maybe it’s still being populated with more to come later. The <a href="http://gallery.bridgesmathart.org/exhibitions/2022-joint-mathematics-meetings/kkshir">rotating hexagon cluster mechanism by Khushbu Kshirsagar</a> makes me want to see something like it for a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smoothed_octagon">rotating cluster of smoothed octagons</a>, but I guess that would require a more complicated design.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>This is a symmetric view of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whitehead_link">Whitehead link</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107325158960438533">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> which in its more usual view (an alternating link formed by overlaying a circle and a figure-eight) is not as obviously symmetric. Redrawn from Fig.22 of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.01472v1">Skopenkov’s “A user’s guide to basic knot and link theory”</a> and also available <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Symmetric_Whitehead_link.svg">in more garish colors at Wikimedia commons</a>.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Symmetric Whitehead link" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2021/symmetric-Whitehead-link.svg"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://cameroncounts.wordpress.com/2021/11/23/two-pointers/">Two pointers</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107330222887192739">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> Peter Cameron warns that accessibility requirements for course lecture notes and the ability to format mathematics in those notes may be on a collision course, because the non-mathematicians who formulate accessibility requirements don’t realize how inadequate non-LaTeX solutions are. Also that requirements for making research data public are being taken to silly levels for research in fields like mathematics where there may well be no data to make public.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://blog.plover.com/math/consecutive-squarefull.html">Consecutive squareful numbers</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@mjd/107324651548000153">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> It’s easy to prove by Chinese remaindering that arbitrarily long sequences of non-squarefree numbers exist, but there’s some interesting work on how to find the first such sequence quickly.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JvhSRCfCHb4">Strategy on an infinite chessboard between an angel and a devil</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@FreddyR/107334208631308281">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> Video clearly explaining the solution to Conway’s angel vs devil problem. There’s a strategy-stealing trick in there, so although you get an explicit algorithm for the angel to escape a weaker adversary, this method only proves the existence of an algorithm for escaping the devil without showing how.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Three new Wikipedia Good Articles <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107347230356711269">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span></p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feedback_arc_set">Feedback arc set</a>, edges touching all cycles in a digraph, with applications to sports ranking, chemical engineering, baboon psychology, etc.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opaque_set">Opaque set</a>, points or curves blocking all visibility across a shape, with the shortest solution mostly still unknown.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No-three-in-line_problem">No-three-in-line problem</a>, the largest grid set without three points in line, conjecturally \(\approx 1.814n\) despite all experimental evidence pointing <span style="white-space: nowrap;">to \(2n\).</span></p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Fractal Kitty, newly on Mathstodon, <a href="https://fractalkitty.com/mathbirbs/">makes playing cards with birds for numbers and plane curves, knots, graphs, and groups as suits</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@fractalkitty/107345972732518709">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.gwern.net/Variables">Top-ten underused Greek letter variables on arXiv</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107359400309951476">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2">via</a>).</span></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You’re probably familiar with <a href="https://littlefreelibrary.org/">Little Free Libraries</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107363373181037563">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> outdoor bookshelf-boxes on sticks that have popped up like mushrooms all over neighborhoods like mine (we have five) to make it easy to find good homes for books you’d like others to find or don’t want to keep yourself. One of our neighbors has taken it a step further, making a little free dog-stick library, in active use judging by its changing numbers of sticks from week to week.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Dog stick library in University Hills, Irvine, California" src="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/dsl/DogStickLibrary-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://theoretics.episciences.org/">TheoretiCS</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107369179583359231">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>)</span> is a new diamond-open-access journal in all areas of theoretical computer science. It is being run as an overlay of arXiv, through the Episciences platform for such overlays, with Javier Esparza and Uri Zwick as editors-in-chief and a large and distinguished editorial board.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-30T18:39:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-30T18:39:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2021-12-01T02:40:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/30/assistant-professor-in-computer-science-at-faculty-of-computer-science-hse-university-apply-by-january-9-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/30/assistant-professor-in-computer-science-at-faculty-of-computer-science-hse-university-apply-by-january-9-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor in Computer Science at Faculty of Computer Science, HSE University (apply by January 9, 2022)</title>
    <summary>We welcome applications for full-time, tenure-track positions of assistant professor in all areas of computer science. Candidates must hold a recent PhD in computer science or related fields by an internationally recognized university; Teaching experience is strongly desirable; Knowledge of Russian is not required. Website: https://iri.hse.ru/ru/TTfcs_21_22AP Email: iri@hse.ru</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We welcome applications for full-time, tenure-track positions of assistant professor in all areas of computer science.<br/>
Candidates must hold a recent PhD in computer science or related fields by an internationally recognized university; Teaching experience is strongly desirable;<br/>
Knowledge of Russian is not required.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://iri.hse.ru/ru/TTfcs_21_22AP">https://iri.hse.ru/ru/TTfcs_21_22AP</a><br/>
Email: iri@hse.ru</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-30T10:48:38Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-30T10:48:38Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/29/assistant-professor-at-university-of-toronto-apply-by-january-10-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/29/assistant-professor-at-university-of-toronto-apply-by-january-10-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor at University of Toronto (apply by January 10, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at the University of Toronto is conducting three open-area searches for full-time tenure stream positions. The appointment will be at the rank of Assistant Professor and will commence on July 1, 2022, or shortly thereafter. We start reviewing applications on December 6, 2021. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/19687 Email: recruit@cs.toronto.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at the University of Toronto is conducting three open-area searches for full-time tenure stream positions. The appointment will be at the rank of Assistant Professor and will commence on July 1, 2022, or shortly thereafter. We start reviewing applications on December 6, 2021.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/19687">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/19687</a><br/>
Email: recruit@cs.toronto.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-29T16:38:44Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-29T16:38:44Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>http://benjamin-recht.github.io/2021/11/29/cluster-power/</id>
    <link href="http://benjamin-recht.github.io/2021/11/29/cluster-power/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The cult of statistical significance and the Bangladesh Mask RCT.</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In the last post, <a href="https://www.argmin.net/2021/11/23/mask-rct-revisited/">I argued that the effect size in the Bangladesh Mask RCT was too small to inform policy making</a>. I deliberately avoided diving into statistical significance as arguments about p-values quickly devolve into scientific gish gallop. Statistical validity is the most overrated form of experimental validity, and it crowds out more important questions of effect size, bias, design, and applicability.</p>

<p>But shoot, sometimes Byzantine academic arguments are fun. And, though they are always wrong, sometimes they are useful. In this blog I want to discuss how we analyze statistical validity in cluster randomized controlled trials. It is quite subtle and sensitive, and should give us pause about these experimental designs. The sample sizes needed for validating large effects in cluster randomized trials can be absurdly high, and running a clean trial with millions of participants is likely impossibly difficult and almost never worth doing.</p>

<p>To review in the <a href="https://www.poverty-action.org/sites/default/files/publications/Mask_Second_Stage_Paper_20211108.pdf.pdf">Bangladesh Mask RCT</a> there were $n_C=$163,861 individuals from $k_C=$300 villages in the control group. There were $n_T=$178,322 individuals from $k_T=$300 villages in the intervention group. The main end point of the study was whether their intervention reduced the number of individuals who reported covid-like symptoms and tested seropositive at some point during the trial. There were $i_C=$1,106 symptomatic individuals confirmed seropositive in the control group and $i_T=$1,086 such individuals in the treatment group.</p>

<p>What can we say about the statistical significance of this 20 case difference? Most would guess this difference is not significant. Indeed, in a balanced design with $n_T=n_C$ and 180,000 individuals in each arm, this study would not be statistically significant. Let’s imagine we ran an experiment where we could treat the outcomes of each individual as independent, identically distributed random variables. What is the p-value associated with the null hypothesis that the prevalence of infections in the control group is less than or equal to the prevalence in the treatment group? A simple statistical test of this hypothesis is the z-test for proportions. For the z-test, the p-value when the groups are balanced is 0.3.</p>

<p>The authors claim a balanced design, but, though the number of treatment and control villages are indeed equal, the number of <em>individuals</em> in the treatment group is 1.1x bigger than the control group. <a href="https://www.argmin.net/2021/11/23/mask-rct-revisited/">As I mentioned in the previous post</a>, this discrepancy can likely be explained by the large differential in response rates between the groups: 1.05x fewer households were approached for surveys in control and the control group responded at 1.07x lower rate than treatment. The most significant difference between the treatment and control group may very well be the consent rate of the household survey. For the medical statistics experts, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intention-to-treat_analysis">the intention to treat principle</a> says that the  individuals who are unreachable or who refuse to be surveyed must be counted in the study. Omitting them invalidates the study.</p>

<p>But the issues of significance remain even if we forgive this large imbalance in the study. If we re-run the z-test with the $n_C$ and $n_T$ in the study data, the p-value is now 0.009, which would be quite significant at the standard p &lt; 0.05 threshold. However, the individual outcomes are <em>not</em> independent. The trial was cluster-randomized, so everyone in the same village received the same intervention. This means that the outcomes inside a village are correlated, and they are likely more correlated inside a village than outside.</p>

<p>To capture the correlation among intra-cluster participants, statisticians use the notion of the <a href="https://www.povertyactionlab.org/resource/power-calculations"><em>intra-cluster correlation coefficient</em></a> $\rho$. $\rho$ is a scalar between 0 and 1 that measures the relative variance within clusters and between clusters. When $\rho=1$, all of the responses in each cluster are identical. When $\rho=0$, the clustering has no effect, and we can treat our assignment as purely randomized. Once we know $\rho$ we can compute an <em>effective sample size</em>: if the villages are completely correlated, the number of samples in the study would be 600. If they were independent, the number of samples would be over 340,000. The number of effective samples is equal to the total number of samples divided by the <em>design effect</em>:</p>

\[{\small
    DE = 1+\left(\frac{n_T+n_C}{k_T+k_C}-1\right)\rho \,.
}\]

<p>What is the design effect of the Bangladesh RCT? Measuring the intra-cluster correlation $\rho$ is nontrivial: the true value of $\rho$ depends on both potential outcomes in an experiment and needs to be estimated using some side experiment or previous trials at baseline. $\rho$ is often inferred from secondary covariates of earlier experiments on a similar population. We don’t have a pre-specified estimate, but can cheat a bit here and estimate $\rho$ from the provided data in the control villages. A standard ANOVA calculation says that the observed symptomatic seropositivity in the control villages has an intra-village correlation of $\rho=$0.007. This value isn’t particularly unreasonable. Some practitioners suggest that because of behavioral contagion alone, $\rho$ should be <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1466680">between 0.01 and 0.02 for human studies.</a> <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0013998#pone.0013998-Carrat2">This cluster RCT on mask use to prevent influenza in households</a> uses $\rho=$0.24.  As a sanity check, the intra-village correlation of reported systems is 0.03. So let’s stick with $\rho=$0.007 and see where it takes us.</p>

<p>For the Bangladesh RCT, assuming $\rho=$0.007, the design effect is about 5. This reduces the effective sample size from over 340,000 to just under 70,000. What happens with our z-test? We simply take the z-score and divide by the square root of the design effect, yielding a p-value of 0.14. The result is not statistically significant once we take into account the intra-cluster correlation. In order to “achieve” statistical significance, $\rho$ would need to be less than 0.001 and the design effect would have to be less than 2.2.</p>

<p>We can also do similar design-effect adjustments for relative risk reduction. Recall the relative risk reduction is the ratio of the rate of infection in the treatment group to the rate of infection in the control group</p>

\[{\small
    RR = \frac{i_T/n_T}{i_C/n_C}\,.
}\]

<p>A small $RR$ corresponds to a large reduction in risk. For the mask study, the estimated risk reduction is $RR=$0.9.  If the assignments of every individual to treatment and control were random, we could compute error bars on the log of the risk ratio. The log risk ratio is</p>

\[{\small
    \ell RR = \log \frac{i_T/n_T}{i_C/n_C}\,,
}\]

<p>and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Relative_risk#Inference">a standard estimate of the standard error $SE$ of $\ell RR$</a> is</p>

\[{\small
    SE = \sqrt{ \frac{1}{i_T} + \frac{1}{i_C} - \frac{1}{n_T}- \frac{1}{n_C}}\,.
}\]

<p>In the mask study, $SE=$0.043. Using a Gaussian approximation, our confidence interval would then be</p>

\[{\scriptsize
    [\exp(\ell RR - 1.96 SE), \exp(\ell RR + 1.96 SE)] = [0.83, 0.98]\,.
}\]

<p>The way we interpret the confidence interval (and I’ll likely screw this up) is that if the Gaussian approximation were true, and all of the individual assignments to treatment and control were independent, and we repeated the experiment many times, the true risk ratio would fall inside the confidence interval 95% of the time. This calculation suggests that the confidence interval (barely) excludes a risk ratio of 1. However, this calculation does not take into account the cluster effects.  Assuming again that $\rho=$0.007, when we adjust our confidence intervals for cluster effects, we get the larger interval</p>

\[{\scriptsize
    \left[\exp(\ell RR - 1.96 SE \sqrt{DE}), \exp(\ell RR + 1.96 SE \sqrt{DE} )\right] = [0.75, 1.09]\,.
}\]

<p>Again, a standard cluster RCT analysis would not be able to reject a null effect for the complex masking intervention. In terms of my most-loathed statistic of efficacy, the confidence interval ranges from -9% to 25% after adjustment.</p>

<p>Note that even the strong claims made in the paper about subgroups are not significant once intra-cluster correlation is accounted for. A commonly quoted result is that surgical masks dramatically reduced infections for individuals over 60 years old. In this case, $n_C =$14,826, $n_T$=16,088, $i_C=$157 and $i_T=$124. The estimated effectiveness is 27%. However, with a design effect of 5, the p-value for the z-test here is 0.13 and the confidence intervals for the efficacy are -23% to 57%. So again, one can’t rest on statistical significance to argue this effect is real.</p>

<p>As a last statistical grumble, all of these corrections don’t even account for the multiple hypothesis testing in the manuscript where nearly 200 hypotheses were evaluated. <strong>After a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bonferroni_correction">Bonferroni correction</a> and accounting for design effect, none of the p-values would be less than 0.5.</strong></p>

<p>How large would the trial have to be in order to have statistical significance? We can focus on the z-test, and ask how many samples would be needed to reject the null hypothesis 95% of the time when the relative risk is 0.9, the prevalence in the control group is 0.076, and the intra-cluster correlation is 0.007. The answer is <strong><em>1.1 million people</em></strong>, over 3 times larger than the actual study size.</p>

<p>When a power calculation reveals a trial needs more than a million subjects, researchers need to pause to think if they are asking the right question. It is likely impossible to conduct a precise experiment that rules out all confounding at such a scale. The number of people needed to run such a trial is huge, and maintaining data quality would be both prohibitively difficult and expensive. Any trial has potential harms to its subjects, and the larger the sample size, the more likely harm may occur. Ensuring beneficence and informed consent at this scale is likely impossible. And if one really expects the clinical significance to be this small, why invest all of these resources into running an RCT instead of looking for more powerful interventions?</p>

<p><em>For those interested in seeing how I computed all of the numbers in this post and the <a href="https://www.argmin.net/2021/11/23/mask-rct-revisited/">last post</a>, <a href="https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/url/argmin.net/code/revisiting-bd-mask-rct.ipynb">here is a Jupyter notebook.</a></em></p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>http://benjamin-recht.github.io/</id>
      <author>
        <name>Ben Recht</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://benjamin-recht.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://benjamin-recht.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Musings on systems, information, learning, and optimization.</subtitle>
      <title>arg min blog</title>
      <updated>2021-12-04T23:27:52Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6105624713426867173</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6105624713426867173/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/11/open-4-colorability-for-graphs-of.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6105624713426867173" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6105624713426867173" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/11/open-4-colorability-for-graphs-of.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Open: 4  colorability for graphs of bounded genus or bounded crossing number (has this been asked before?)</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> I have  co-authored (with Nathan Hayes, Anthony Ostuni, Davin Park) an open problems column  on the topic of this post. It is <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/users/gasarch/open/cross.pdf">here</a>.</p><p>Let g(G) be the genus of a graph and cr(G) be the crossing number of a graph.</p><p>As usual chi(G) is the chromatic number of a graph. </p><p>KNOWN to most readers of this blog:</p><p>{G: \chi(G) \le 2} is in P</p><p>{G: \chi(G) \le 3 and g(G)\le 0 } is NPC (planar graph 3-col)</p><p>{G : \chi(G) \le 4 and g(G) \le 0} is in P (it's trivial since all planar graphs are 4-col)</p><p>{G: \chi(G) \le 3 and cr(G) \le 0} is NPC (planar graph 3-col)</p><p>{G: \chi(G) \le 4 and cr(G) \le 0} is in P (trivial since all planar graphs are 4-col)</p><p>LESS WELL KNOWN BUT TRUE (and brought to my attention by my co-authors and also Jacob Fox and Marcus Schaefer) </p><p>For all g\ge 0 and r\ge 5, {G : \chi(G) \le r and g(G) \le g} is in P</p><p>For all c\ge 0 and r\ge 5, {G : \chi(G) \le r and cr(G) \le c} is in P </p><p>SO I asked the question: for various r,g,c what is the complexity of the following sets:</p><p>{G: \chi(G) \le r AND g(G) \le g} </p><p>{G: \chi(G) \le r AND cr(G) \le c}</p><p>SO I believe the status of the following sets is open</p><p>{G : \chi(G) \le 4 and g(G)\le 1} (replace 1 with 2,3,4,...)</p><p>{G : \chi(G) \le 4 and cr(G)\le 1} (replace 1 with 2,3,4...) </p><p><br/></p><p>QUESTIONS</p><p>1) If anyone knows the answer to these open questions, please leave comments. </p><p>2) The paper pointed to above mentions all of the times I read of someone asking questions like this. There are not many, and the problem does not seem to be out there. Why is that?</p><p>a) It's hard to find out who-asked-what-when. Results are published, open problems often are not. My SIGACT News open problems column gives me (and others) a chance to write down open problems; however, such venues are rare. So it's possible that someone without a blog or an open problems column raised these questions before. (I checked cs stack exchange- not there- and I posted there but didn't get much of a response.) </p><p>b) Proving NPC seems hard since devising gadgets with only one crossing is NOT good enough since you use the gadget many times. This may have discouraged people from thinking about it. </p><p>c) Proving that the problems are in P (for the r\ge 6 case) was the result of using a hard theorem in graph theory from 2007. The authors themselves did not notice the algorithmic result. The first published account of the algorithmic result might be my open problems column.  This may be a case of the graph theorists and complexity theorists not talking to each other, though that is surprising since there is so much overlap that I thought there was no longer a distinction. </p><p>d) While I think this is a natural question to ask, I may be wrong. See <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/05/what-is-natural-question-who-should.html">here</a> for a blog post about when I had a natural question and found out why I may be wrong about the problems naturalness. </p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-28T21:47:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-28T21:47:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T03:05:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/170</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/170" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-170 |  Pseudorandom Self-Reductions for NP-Complete Problems | 

	Reyad Abed Elrazik, 

	Robert Robere, 

	Assaf Schuster, 

	Gal Yehuda</title>
    <summary>A language $L$ is random-self-reducible if deciding membership in $L$ can be reduced (in polynomial time) to deciding membership in $L$ for uniformly random instances. It is known that several "number theoretic" languages (such as computing the permanent of a matrix) admit random self-reductions. Feigenbaum and Fortnow showed that NP-complete languages are not non-adaptively random-self-reducible unless the polynomial-time hierarchy collapses, giving suggestive evidence that NP may not admit random self-reductions. Hirahara and Santhanam introduced a weakening of random self-reductions that they called pseudorandom self-reductions, in which a language $L$ is reduced to a distribution that is computationally indistinguishable from the uniform distribution. They then showed that the Minimum Circuit Size Problem (MCSP) admits a non-adaptive pseudorandom self-reduction, and suggested that this gave further evidence that MCSP is "distinguished" from standard NP-Complete problems.

We show that, in fact, the NP-Complete Clique problem admits a non-adaptive pseudorandom self-reduction, assuming the planted clique conjecture. More generally we show the following. Call a property of graphs $\pi$ hereditary if $G \in \pi$ implies $H \in \pi$ for every induced subgraph of $G$. We show that for any infinite hereditary property $\pi$, the problem of finding a maximum induced subgraph $H \in \pi$ of a given graph $G$ admits a non-adaptive pseudorandom self-reduction.</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-28T10:18:31Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-28T10:18:31Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=585</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2021/11/25/tcs-talk-wednesday-december-1-william-kuszmaul-mit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, December 1 — William Kuszmaul, MIT</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, December 1th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). William Kuszmaul from MIT will speak about “Linear Probing Revisited: Tombstones Mark the Demise of Primary Clustering” (abstract below). You can reserve a spot as an individual or […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, December 1th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/williamkuszmaul"><strong>William Kuszmaul</strong></a> from MIT will speak about “<em>Linear Probing Revisited: Tombstones Mark the Demise of Primary Clustering</em>” (abstract below).</p>
<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/next-tcs-talk">the online form</a>. Registration is <em>not</em> required to attend the interactive talk, and the link will be posted on the website the day prior to the talk; however, by registering in the form, you will receive a reminder, along with the link. (The recorded talk will also be posted <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/past-talks">on our website</a> afterwards) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/suggest-a-talk">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/">the website</a>.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Abstract: The linear-probing hash table is one of the oldest and most widely used data structures in computer science. However, linear probing also famously comes with a major drawback: as soon as the hash table reaches a high memory utilization, elements within the hash table begin to cluster together, causing insertions to become slow. This phenomenon, now known as “primary clustering”, was first captured by Donald Knuth in 1963; at a load factor of <img alt="1 - 1/x" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1+-+1%2Fx&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, the expected time per insertion becomes <img alt="\Theta(x^2)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5CTheta%28x%5E2%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, rather than the more desirable <img alt="\Theta(x)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5CTheta%28x%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.</p>
<p>We show that there is more to the story than the classic analysis would seem to suggest. It turns out that small design decisions in how deletions are implemented have dramatic effects on the asymptotic performance of insertions. If these design decisions are made correctly, then even a hash table that is continuously at a load factor <img alt="1 - \Theta(1/x)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1+-+%5CTheta%281%2Fx%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> can achieve average insertion time <img alt="\tilde{O}(x)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctilde%7BO%7D%28x%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. A key insight is that the tombstones left behind by deletions cause a surprisingly strong “anti-clustering” effect, and that when insertions and deletions are one-for-one, the anti-clustering effects of deletions actually overpower the clustering effects of insertions.</p>
<p>We also present a new variant of linear probing, which we call “graveyard hashing”, that completely eliminates primary clustering on any sequence of operations. If, when an operation is performed, the current load factor is <img alt="1 - 1/x" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1+-+1%2Fx&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for some <img alt="x" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, then the expected cost of the operation is <img alt="O(x)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=O%28x%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. One corollary is that, in the external-memory model with a data block size of <img alt="B" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=B&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, graveyard hashing offers the following remarkable guarantee: at any load factor <img alt="1-1/x" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1-1%2Fx&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> satisfying <img alt="x = o(B)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x+%3D+o%28B%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, graveyard hashing achieves <img alt="1 + o(1)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1+%2B+o%281%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> expected block transfers per operation. Past external-memory hash tables have only been able to offer a <img alt="1+o(1)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1%2Bo%281%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> guarantee when the block size <img alt="B" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=B&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is at least <img alt="\Omega(x^2)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5COmega%28x%5E2%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.</p>
<p>Based on joint work with Michael A. Bender and Bradley C. Kuszmaul (<a href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/_wp_link_placeholder">arXiv:2107.01250</a>). To appear in FOCS 2021.</p></blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-25T22:02:37Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-25T22:02:37Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:21:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19356</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/11/24/best-to-dean-mynatt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Best To Dean Mynatt</title>
    <summary>Plus updates on gender disparity, equity, and POPL 2022 IPaT page Beth Mynatt is heading north to become the new Dean of Computer Science at Northeastern University. Georgia Tech will miss her; she has been a key part of Tech for over twenty years. Northeastern is getting a great leader, a valued colleague, and an […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Plus updates on gender disparity, equity, and POPL 2022</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/11/24/best-to-dean-mynatt/bm/" rel="attachment wp-att-19358"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-19358" height="150" src="https://i1.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/bm.png?resize=150%2C150&amp;ssl=1" width="150"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">IPaT <a href="https://news.gatech.edu/expert/elizabeth-mynatt">page</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Beth Mynatt is heading north to become the new Dean of Computer Science at Northeastern University. Georgia Tech will miss her; she has been a key part of Tech for over twenty years. Northeastern is getting a great leader, a valued colleague, and an excellent PhD graduate of Georgia Tech.</p>
<p>
Today we hail her work on solving problems of <em>aging</em> and compare to what we do in theory. These musings wend toward solving problems of the kind raised in our previous <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/11/13/popl-2022-et-tu-brute/">post</a>, on which we have an update from POPL General Chair Rajeev Alur that comes full circle to a Dean at Northeastern.<br/>
<span id="more-19356"/></p>
<p>
One aspect of aging is having a long memory of a field. When Ken and I were young, it was all about what humans can do with computers. Now it is much more about what computers can do with humans. <em>With</em> humans, not just <em>for</em> humans—the aspect of collaboration is key. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Aging… </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Beth worked on various projects over her time at Tech. In 1999–2000, she was part of a team that launched the Aware Home Research Initiative (<a href="https://www.cc.gatech.edu/fce/house/house.html">AHRI</a>), “whose goal is to develop the requisite technologies to create a home environment that can both perceive and assist its occupants.” She has led the Institute of People and Technology (IPaT) since 2011, its inaugural year, where her team has helped to support numerous, impactful research programs for faculty across Georgia Tech. </p>
<p>
To show how leadership and persistent work pay dividends, she is a co-PI on a new multi-institution grant led by Tech’s Sonia Chernova to build intelligent systems that support aging. The five-year, $20 million grant from the National Science Foundation, sponsored also by Amazon and Google, will go to create the NSF AI Institute for Collaborative Assistance and Responsive Interaction for Networked Groups (<a href="http://ai-caring.org/">AI-CARING</a>). The <a href="https://www.cc.gatech.edu/news/649114/new-ai-institute-builds-tech-support-aging">announcement</a> says:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> The institute aims to develop new longitudinal, collaborative AI systems that work with aging adults including those diagnosed with mild cognitive impairment, and their caregivers. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The AI-CARING front page says that they </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “will develop a discipline focused on personalized, longitudinal, collaborative AI, enabling the development of AI systems that learn personalized models of user behavior, understand how people’s behavior changes over time, and integrate that knowledge to support people and AIs working together. These networked Human-AI teams will work with elderly adults and their caregivers in order to provide sustainable long-term care solutions.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p>
As someone who is not young, I can definitely see why this is important. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Missed the … </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I sometimes feel that we in theory have missed the boat. The issue is that our problems are weighty—P=NP anyone?—but they do not directly impact practical computing. The areas that Beth is interested in, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ubiquitous_computing">ubiquitous computing</a>, have by definition had a large impact on real computing. The snippet from MIT’s <a href="http://oxygen.csail.mit.edu/Overview.html">Project Oxygen</a> quoted by Wikipedia expresses the direction of impact:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> In the future, computation will be human centered. It will be freely available everywhere, like batteries and power sockets, or oxygen in the air we breathe. … [C]onfigurable generic devices, either handheld or embedded in the environment, will bring computation to us, whenever we need it and wherever we might be. … We won’t have to type, click, or learn new computer jargon. Instead, we’ll communicate naturally, using speech and gestures that describe our intent … and leave it to the computer to carry out our will. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This may conjure a “Star Trek” vision, but some people already live with substantial parts of this reality. Is there a market for P=NP? On the “equals” side, we can think of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sneakers_(1992_film)">couple</a> of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travelling_Salesman_(2012_film)">movies</a> featuring interested parties. For the “not equal” side, not so much?</p>
<p>
If pressed to think of a theory result that “launched a thousand ships” of practical effort, Peter Shor’s theorem about factoring belonging to quantum polynomial time springs to mind. But the ship of universal quantum computing needed to get it under steam won’t come in for decades.  It is <em>quantum devices with rudimentary computational features</em> that we see ruling in the meantime, while quantum communication protocols backed by quantum information theory are <a href="https://thequantuminsider.com/2021/06/23/11-global-banks-probing-the-wonderful-world-of-quantum-technologies/">banked on</a> now. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Solutions Business </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I, Ken writing from here, have often winced at the way the word “solutions” is used in business advertising. To a theorist, <em>solutions</em> are what make a conjecture become a theorem, what we grade in theory courses, what enjoyers of puzzles pursue for recreation. </p>
<p>
I described a <em>solution</em> of the more practical kind in my “Pandemic Lag” <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/07/30/pandemic-lag/">post</a> last July. It solves the problem of estimating the true current strength of rapidly developing young players (such as I was once) whose official ratings have been largely frozen for over a year and a half by the lack of in-person chess during the pandemic. Online play is not officially rated. </p>
<p>
For example, if a preteen’s frozen rating is <b>1575</b>, my formula will currently add 25 Elo points times 19 months of the pandemic to make <b>2050</b>. Players with higher ratings and longer track records are adjusted less. In some recent instances, when such kids have defeated players with more-established ratings near 2200, people seeing the 1500s rating in the official tournament table have raised questions. My answer is based on the average performance of <em>many</em> children keen enough to compete in similar-level championship events. Thus my computer-intensive studies are safeguarding the welfare of minors.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Gender Gap and Pipeline in Chess </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
My rating solution raises another problem of the kind addressed in our last <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/11/13/popl-2022-et-tu-brute/">post</a>. For a fresh instance, on Monday I submitted my final report on the European Team Championship. This ten-day tournament finished Sunday with the <a href="https://www.chess.com/news/view/alireza-firouzja-youngest-chess-player-ever-to-break-2800">sensation</a> of Alireza Firouzja becoming the youngest player ever rated over 2800, six months younger than world champion Magnus Carlsen was in 2009. (Carlsen will <a href="https://www.fide.com/news/1445">defend</a> his title starting Friday in Dubai against the Russian Ian Nepomniachtchi.)</p>
<p>
My intrinsic rating performance projections for the men’s/open section were all accurate to within 10 Elo points, within two-sigma error bars about <img alt="{\pm 25}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpm+25%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. When restricted to the 32 juniors (out of 191 total players) whose ratings I adjusted, all projections were within 23 Elo points of the results and their average was within <b>2</b> Elo points—on adjustments averaging 80 Elo points per the 32 players. </p>
<p>
In the women’s section, my gender-neutral formula adjusted up 39 of the 153 female players by an average of 169 Elo. The prescribed amount was larger because their ratings (average 2168) were lower than the 32 junior males’ ratings (average 2419) to begin with. The formula overshot their performance by 113 Elo, and accounted for the bulk of a 36 Elo average shortfall of my projections for the women’s section overall. This continues a pattern of observing not only a lower starting point, but also a lower first derivative when compared to males of the <em>same</em> rating, in tournaments with high junior participation where my adjustments are involved.</p>
<p>
The <em>Queen’s Gambit</em> miniseries magnified awareness of the disparity—witness the <a href="https://womensagenda.com.au/latest/whats-behind-the-gender-imbalance-in-top-level-chess/">article</a> a year ago by the Australian economist and grandmaster David Smerdon, “What’s behind the gender imbalance in top-level chess?” My work offers a new way to pinpoint when and where the male and female pipelines diverge. I do not see how it could <em>solve</em> the disparity, however. Even converting my big spreadsheets of test results into publications is a tall ask—for one, they are considered sensitive data. </p>
<p>
I have discoursed about the theory of my predictive model on this blog, and could say more about the thrill of empirical success in ways much of theory doesn’t reach. But this is still short of solving human problems in the manner of Dick’s intro, let alone solving the gender gap. On that, we’re grateful to have a communication from Rajeev Alur, General Chair of POPL, on how the statistics we noted came about and what the conference is doing.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> More About POPL 2022 </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Rajeev began by observing that POPL PCs in previous years have been closer to the percentages we quoted for STOC and FOCS: </p>
<ul>
<li>
2021: 15.4% (8/52) <p/>
</li><li>
2020: 14.8% (8/54) <p/>
</li><li>
2019: 11.5% (6/52) <p/>
</li><li>
2018: 23.1% (12/52) <p/>
</li><li>
2017: 17.2% (5/29) <p/>
</li><li>
2016: 21.4% (6/28) <p/>
</li><li>
2015: 20.0% (6/30)
</li></ul>
<p>
A more private figure that he gave us permission to divulge is that the proportion of PC <em>invitations</em> this year was just under 20% for women. Had they accepted at the same rate as the men, there would have been 12 women on the committee this year, as there was in the first year the PC size was expanded in 2018. </p>
<p>
He went on to note an issue also raised in comments to our last post, namely that among the smaller population of women the same people are asked multiple times, leading to more declines. We can put the scaling problem another way: nearly doubling the committee size in 2018 also doubled the ratio of women being invited to their total number. Not all effects of scaling-up keep equal proportion. The root cause of course is not only the smaller population but its smaller first derivative: as Rajeev noted, the latest figures from the Computing Research Association in 2019 show that out of 417 PhDs in POPL-core areas, only 42 (10%) were female.</p>
<p>
The main thing that they are doing is to take the kind of steps pointed up in the quotation from Valerie King in our post. As shown in the POPL 2022 Overview schedule on their <a href="https://popl22.sigplan.org/">front page</a>, they have special lunch and breakfast events for women and LGTBQ attendees (the latter held since <a href="https://popl20.sigplan.org/track/POPL-2020-lgbtq-lunch">2020</a>) and mentoring workshops for graduate and undergraduate level students. POPL 2022 is the first to appoint a special Chair for organizing these events, Jennifer Paykin, who we note gave a special quantum-for-POPL <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nVMm0PrF-j8">presentation</a> in 2020. </p>
<p>
Next year’s POPL PC will be chaired by <a href="https://www.khoury.northeastern.edu/people/amal-ahmed/">Amal Ahmed</a>. Coincidentally, she is Associate Dean for Graduate Programs at Northeastern’s Khoury College where Beth Mynatt will be Dean. <a href="https://alexandrasilva.org/#/main.html">Alexandra Silva</a>, who was on the POPL 2020 PC and on the POPL 2021 Organizing Committee as Accessibility Chair, is one of three Keynote Speakers this year. Hope for the pipeline picking up was raised by the 2021 SIGPLAN Robin Milner Award for Junior Researchers going to <a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~emina/">Emina Torlak</a> of UW. </p>
<p>
Of course, it will take a long time to translate the promotion of opportunity into closer parity. The low dip this year is what we noticed, but the long time effect is what our post highlighted at the end. Again we thank Rajeev for bringing both the time range and effort by SIGPLAN and POPL into greater context.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We’ve tried to “zoom out” where theory people are used to zooming in. How can that change perspectives on our field?</p>
<p>
We are also thankful for how our field has branched out and wish everyone a happy Thanksgiving.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
[fixed name in POPL section]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-25T04:48:54Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-25T04:48:54Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="chess"/>
    <category term="detection"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="aging"/>
    <category term="assistive computing"/>
    <category term="Beth Mynatt"/>
    <category term="Gender equity"/>
    <category term="gender gap"/>
    <category term="POPL 2022"/>
    <category term="Problems"/>
    <category term="projections"/>
    <category term="Rajeev Alur"/>
    <category term="solutions"/>
    <category term="Thanksgiving"/>
    <category term="Theory"/>
    <category term="women in computing"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:20:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-6494812234459505156</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/6494812234459505156/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=6494812234459505156" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/6494812234459505156" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/6494812234459505156" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2021/11/inria-innovation-prize-2021-to-mateescu.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Inria Innovation Prize 2021 to Mateescu, Garavel, Lang and Serwe</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I just learnt that <a href="https://convecs.inria.fr/people/Radu.Mateescu/">Radu Mateescu</a>, <a href="http://convecs.inria.fr/people/Hubert.Garavel/">Hubert Garavel</a>, <a href="http://convecs.inria.fr/people/Frederic.Lang/">Frédéric Lang</a> and <a href="http://convecs.inria.fr/people/Wendelin.Serwe/">Wendelin Serwe</a> from the <a href="http://convecs.inria.fr/">Construction of Verified Concurrent Systems</a> (Convecs) project team at INRIA Grenoble – Rhône-Alpes Centre have been recently awarded the <a href="https://www.inria.fr/en/convecs-team-safety-modeling-distributed-parallel-systems" target="_blank">Inria Innovation Prize – Académie des sciences – Dassault Systèmes</a>. Their work contributes to the development of the <a href="https://cadp.inria.fr/" target="_blank">CADP toolbox</a> for modelling and verifying parallel and distributed systems. The aim of that project is to automatically detect design flaws in highly complex systems. </p><p>Readers of this blog will be as delighted as I am by this news. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Construction_and_Analysis_of_Distributed_Processes" target="_blank">CADP</a> is one of the tools from the concurrency community that has the longest history, dating back to its early releases in 1989. It has been used to good effect in a variety of applications, is still under continuous development and makes excellent use  in practice of classic tools from concurrency theory. By way of example, let me mention the recent successes by the Convecs team in dealing with difficult challenges posed by <a href="http://ls5-www.cs.tu-dortmund.de/cms/de/mitarbeiter/prof/Bernhard_Steffen.html" target="_blank">Bernhard Steffen</a> and his team on the evaluation of CTL and LTL formulae on large products of automata. (See, for instance, the news items <a href="http://cadp.inria.fr/news12.html" target="_blank">here</a> and <a href="http://cadp.inria.fr/news13.html#section-3" target="_blank">here</a>.) Traditional model checkers fail on those challenges because the state space of the product automata is too large for them. However, a wise use of bisimulations and congruence results allows CADP to solve many of those challenges. Interested readers might also wish to peruse the slides at </p><ul style="text-align: left;"><li><a href="http://cadp.inria.fr/ftp/presentations/Mazzanti-RERS-18.pdf">http://cadp.inria.fr/ftp/presentations/Mazzanti-RERS-18.pdf</a> </li><li><a href="http://cadp.inria.fr/ftp/presentations/Lang-RERS-19.pdf">http://cadp.inria.fr/ftp/presentations/Lang-RERS-19.pdf</a> and</li><li><a href="http://cadp.inria.fr/ftp/presentations/Lang-RERS-20.pdf">http://cadp.inria.fr/ftp/presentations/Lang-RERS-20.pdf</a>. </li></ul>Congratulations to the whole CADP team and to the concurrency community for this award!</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-24T22:50:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-24T22:50:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2021-12-04T13:00:14Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/169</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/169" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-169 |  Hypercontractivity on High Dimensional Expanders: a Local-to-Global Approach for Higher Moments | 

	Max Hopkins, 

	Mitali Bafna, 

	Tali Kaufman, 

	Shachar Lovett</title>
    <summary>Hypercontractivity is one of the most powerful tools in Boolean function analysis. Originally studied over the discrete hypercube, recent years have seen increasing interest in extensions to settings like the $p$-biased cube, slice, or Grassmannian, where variants of hypercontractivity have found a number of breakthrough applications including the resolution of Khot’s 2-2 Games Conjecture (Khot, Minzer, Safra FOCS 2018). In this work, we develop a new theory of hypercontractivity on high dimensional expanders (HDX), an important class of expanding complexes that has recently seen similarly impressive applications in both coding theory and approximate sampling. Our results lead to a new understanding of the structure of Boolean functions on HDX, including a tight analog of the KKL Theorem and a new characterization of non-expanding sets. 

Unlike previous settings satisfying hypercontractivity, HDX can be asymmetric, sparse, and very far from products, which makes the application of traditional proof techniques challenging. We handle these barriers with the introduction of two new tools of independent interest: a new explicit combinatorial Fourier basis for HDX that behaves well under restriction, and a new local-to-global method for analyzing higher moments. Interestingly, unlike analogous second moment methods that apply equally across all types of expanding complexes, our tools rely inherently on simplicial structure. This suggests a new distinction among high dimensional expanders based upon their behavior beyond the second moment.</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-24T08:19:32Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-24T08:19:32Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/168</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/168" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-168 |  Hypercontractivity on High Dimensional Expanders: Approximate Efron-Stein Decompositions for $\epsilon$-Product Spaces | 

	Tom Gur, 

	Noam Lifshitz, 

	Siqi Liu</title>
    <summary>We prove hypercontractive inequalities on high dimensional expanders. As in the settings of the p-biased hypercube, the symmetric group, and the Grassmann scheme, our inequalities are effective for global functions, which are functions that are not significantly affected by a restriction of a small set of coordinates. As applications, we obtain Fourier concentration, small-set expansion, and Kruskal-Katona theorems for high dimensional expanders. Our techniques rely on a new approximate Efron-Stein decomposition for high dimensional link expanders.</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-24T08:10:52Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-24T08:10:52Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-12-05T11:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
