<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-03-11T18:22:00Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/031</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/031" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-031 |  Algebraic Branching Programs, Border Complexity, and Tangent Spaces | 

	Markus Bläser, 

	Christian Ikenmeyer, 

	Meena Mahajan, 

	Anurag Pandey, 

	Nitin Saurabh</title>
    <summary>Nisan showed in 1991 that the width of a smallest noncommutative single-(source,sink) algebraic branching program (ABP) to compute a noncommutative polynomial is given by the ranks of specific matrices. This means that the set of noncommutative polynomials with ABP width complexity at most $k$ is Zariski-closed, an important property in geometric complexity theory. It follows that approximations cannot help to reduce the required ABP width.

It was mentioned by Forbes that this result would probably break when going from single-(source,sink) ABPs to trace ABPs. We prove that this is correct. Moreover, we study the commutative monotone setting and prove a result similar to Nisan, but concerning the analytic closure. We observe the same behavior here: The set of polynomials with ABP width complexity at most $k$ is closed for single-(source,sink) ABPs and not closed for trace ABPs. The proofs reveal an intriguing connection between tangent spaces and the vector space of flows on the ABP.
We close with additional observations on VQP and the closure of VNP which allows us to establish a separation between the two classes.</summary>
    <updated>2020-03-11T08:31:35Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-11T08:31:35Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:20:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/03/11/more-uniqueness-sudoku</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/03/11/more-uniqueness-sudoku.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>More on uniqueness in Sudoku</title>
    <summary>My first post on this blog, lo these nearly 15 years ago, discussed a program I had written to try to solve Sudoku puzzles deductively (rather than by the easier computational method, backtracking), with the goal of being able to automatically grade the puzzles and automatically generate explanations for how to solve a given puzzle. And a few months later I posted again, on deduction rules that take advantage of the assumption that a puzzle has a unique solution, by ruling out choices that would cause any solution consistent with them to become non-unique. Since then, that part of my solver has been relatively stable, although I have added other rules for Nishio and 2SAT and posted here about more general uniqueness deduction rules in map-coloring puzzles.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2005/07/20/updated-python-library.html">My first post on this blog</a>, lo these nearly 15 years ago, discussed a program I had written to try to solve Sudoku puzzles deductively (rather than by the easier computational method, backtracking), with the goal of being able to automatically grade the puzzles and automatically generate explanations for how to solve a given puzzle. And a few months later I posted again, on <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2005/10/15/assuming-uniqueness-in.html">deduction rules that take advantage of the assumption that a puzzle has a unique solution</a>, by ruling out choices that would cause any solution consistent with them to become non-unique. Since then, that part of my solver has been relatively stable, although I have added other rules for <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2012/02/23/solving-single-digit-sudoku.html">Nishio</a> and <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2009/04/26/sudoku-and-2sat.html">2SAT</a> and posted here about <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/07/28/any-order-puzzle.html">more general uniqueness deduction rules in map-coloring puzzles</a>.</p>

<p>I’ve also occasionally been using my program to generate puzzles for me to work on, and today it found an interesting test case, a puzzle that it thought would be much more difficult than it turned out to be for me. This mis-rating happened because the uniqueness deduction rules I’m using in my own deductions are stronger than the ones in my program (although some of its other rules are stronger than I typically apply myself). In its initial state, the puzzle looks like:</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Sudoku puzzle" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/ambig-sudoku-givens.svg"/></p>

<p>My program tells me that it’s at the second highest level of difficulty that it knows about: it has to resort to using 2SAT, but it can successfully solve it that way. (The highest level is for puzzles where it is forced to use backtracking.) Usually, for me, puzzles at that level require me to use written notes to keep track of the deductions, rather than doing it all in my head, but not this time. Using more-or-less standard reasoning, one can fill in the cells of the puzzle to reach the state:</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Partially solved Sudoku puzzle" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/ambig-sudoku-partial.svg"/></p>

<p>This is where my program gets stuck and has to resort to more powerful deduction rules. But as a human solving this puzzle, here is what I see: In row 3, the two empty cells must contain the pair of digits 3 and 5. In the center right block of nine cells, the two empty cells must again be 3 and 5. And in the center block of cells, the 5 digit is confined to three cells aligned with those two pairs of empty cells. If the 3 digit were also confined to the same three cells in the center block, it and the five would have to occupy the two diagonally aligned cells out of the three, because otherwise they would line up and prevent one of the other pairs of 3-5 cells from having any value. But then the 3-5 cells in row 3, the center block, and column 7 would form a closed system (shown by the red squares below): nothing else outside those cells could affect which of those six cells contains 3, and which contains 5. Within that closed system, there are two solutions, obtained from each other by swapping the locations of the 3 and the 5. But that would violate the assumption of uniqueness.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Closed system of cells in a partially solved Sudoku puzzle" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/ambig-sudoku-closed.svg"/></p>

<p>Even if the 7 in the center cell weren’t there, the same reasoning would apply. Since this closed system with a non-unique solution would happen automatically if we confine the digit 3 to the same three center-block cells as the digit 5, the digit 3 must be elsewhere in the center block, which can only mean that it is in column 4. Once we make this deduction, the rest of the puzzle falls into place.</p>

<p>My program only has built into it a couple of ad-hoc rules to prevent closed systems of four cells with two solutions, and it misses the one in this example because it involves six cells. It’s making me think that I need a more general description of the possible closed systems (at least the ones involving only two digit values, like this), in order to match the deductions I’m making by hand and make my program’s difficulty estimates more accurate.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103803219892010865">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-11T00:06:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-11T00:06:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T07:27:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04873</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04873" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Moving Target Monte Carlo</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583884800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Haoyun Ying, Keheng Mao, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mosegaard:Klaus.html">Klaus Mosegaard</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04873">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods are popular when considering
sampling from a high-dimensional random variable $\mathbf{x}$ with possibly
unnormalised probability density $p$ and observed data $\mathbf{d}$. However,
MCMC requires evaluating the posterior distribution $p(\mathbf{x}|\mathbf{d})$
of the proposed candidate $\mathbf{x}$ at each iteration when constructing the
acceptance rate. This is costly when such evaluations are intractable. In this
paper, we introduce a new non-Markovian sampling algorithm called Moving Target
Monte Carlo (MTMC). The acceptance rate at $n$-th iteration is constructed
using an iteratively updated approximation of the posterior distribution
$a_n(\mathbf{x})$ instead of $p(\mathbf{x}|\mathbf{d})$. The true value of the
posterior $p(\mathbf{x}|\mathbf{d})$ is only calculated if the candidate
$\mathbf{x}$ is accepted. The approximation $a_n$ utilises these evaluations
and converges to $p$ as $n \rightarrow \infty$. A proof of convergence and
estimation of convergence rate in different situations are given.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-11T01:22:02Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04863</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04863" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Circulation Control for Faster Minimum Cost Flow in Unit-Capacity Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583884800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Axiotis:Kyriakos.html">Kyriakos Axiotis</a>, Aleksander Mądry, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vladu:Adrian.html">Adrian Vladu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04863">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present an $m^{11/8+o(1)} \log W$-time algorithm for solving the minimum
cost flow problem in graphs with unit capacity, where $W$ is the absolute
maximum weight of an edge in the graph. For sparse graphs, this improves over
the best known running time for this problem and, by well-known reductions,
also implies improved running times for the shortest path problem with negative
weights, minimum cost bipartite $\boldsymbol{\mathit{b}}$-matching when
$\|\boldsymbol{\mathit{b}}\|_1 = O(m)$, and recovers the running time of the
currently fastest algorithm for maximum flow in graphs with unit capacities
(Liu-Sidford).
</p>
<p>Our algorithm relies on developing an interior point method--based framework
which acts on the space of circulations in the underlying graph. From the
combinatorial point of view, this framework can be viewed as iteratively
improving the cost of a suboptimal solution by pushing flow around
circulations. These circulations are derived by computing a regularized version
of the standard Newton step, which can be done efficiently due to recent
developments on computing $\ell_p$-norm minimizing flows
(Kyng-Peng-Sachdeva-Wang). We obtain our faster algorithm by combining this
approach with a customized preconditioning method, which aims to ensure that
the graph on which these circulations are computed has sufficiently large
conductance.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-11T01:22:13Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04834</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04834" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Algebraic Branching Programs, Border Complexity, and Tangent Spaces</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583884800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bl=auml=ser:Markus.html">Markus Bläser</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Ikenmeyer:Christian.html">Christian Ikenmeyer</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mahajan:Meena.html">Meena Mahajan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pandey:Anurag.html">Anurag Pandey</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saurabh:Nitin.html">Nitin Saurabh</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04834">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Nisan showed in 1991 that the width of a smallest noncommutative
single-(source,sink) algebraic branching program (ABP) to compute a
noncommutative polynomial is given by the ranks of specific matrices. This
means that the set of noncommutative polynomials with ABP width complexity at
most $k$ is Zariski-closed, an important property in geometric complexity
theory. It follows that approximations cannot help to reduce the required ABP
width.
</p>
<p>It was mentioned by Forbes that this result would probably break when going
from single-(source,sink) ABPs to trace ABPs. We prove that this is correct.
Moreover, we study the commutative monotone setting and prove a result similar
to Nisan, but concerning the analytic closure. We observe the same behavior
here: The set of polynomials with ABP width complexity at most $k$ is closed
for single-(source,sink) ABPs and not closed for trace ABPs. The proofs reveal
an intriguing connection between tangent spaces and the vector space of flows
on the ABP. We close with additional observations on VQP and the closure of VNP
which allows us to establish a separation between the two classes.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-11T01:20:23Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04740</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04740" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Drawing Graphs with Circular Arcs and Right Angle Crossings</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583884800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chaplick:Steven.html">Steven Chaplick</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/F=ouml=rster:Henry.html">Henry Förster</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kryven:Myroslav.html">Myroslav Kryven</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wolff:Alexander.html">Alexander Wolff</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04740">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In a RAC drawing of a graph, vertices are represented by points in the plane,
adjacent vertices are connected by line segments, and crossings must form right
angles. Graphs that admit such drawings are RAC graphs. RAC graphs are
beyond-planar graphs and have been studied extensively. In particular, it is
known that a RAC graph with n vertices has at most 4n - 10 edges. We introduce
a superclass of RAC graphs, which we call arc-RAC graphs. In an arc-RAC
drawing, edges are drawn as circular arcs whereas crossings must still form
right angles. We provide a Tur\'an-type result showing that an arc-RAC graph
with n vertices has at most 14n - 12 edges and that there are n-vertex arc-RAC
graphs with 4.5n - o(n) edges.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04605</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04605" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Maximizing Happiness in Graphs of Bounded Clique-Width</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583884800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bliznets:Ivan.html">Ivan Bliznets</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sagunov:Danil.html">Danil Sagunov</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04605">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Clique-width is one of the most important parameters that describes
structural complexity of a graph. Probably, only treewidth is more studied
graph width parameter. In this paper we study how clique-width influences the
complexity of the Maximum Happy Vertices (MHV) and Maximum Happy Edges (MHE)
problems. We answer a question of Choudhari and Reddy '18 about
parameterization by the distance to threshold graphs by showing that MHE is
NP-complete on threshold graphs. Hence, it is not even in XP when parameterized
by clique-width, since threshold graphs have clique-width at most two. As a
complement for this result we provide a $n^{\mathcal{O}(\ell \cdot
\operatorname{cw})}$ algorithm for MHE, where $\ell$ is the number of colors
and $\operatorname{cw}$ is the clique-width of the input graph. We also
construct an FPT algorithm for MHV with running time
$\mathcal{O}^*((\ell+1)^{\mathcal{O}(\operatorname{cw})})$, where $\ell$ is the
number of colors in the input. Additionally, we show $\mathcal{O}(\ell n^2)$
algorithm for MHV on interval graphs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-11T01:21:49Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04578</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04578" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal-size problem kernels for $d$-Hitting Set in linear time and space</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583884800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bevern:Ren=eacute=_van.html">René van Bevern</a>, Pavel V. Smirnov <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04578">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We improve two linear-time data reduction algorithms for the d-Hitting Set
problem to work in linear space, thus obtaining the first algorithms for
computing problem kernels of asymptotically optimal size $O(k^d)$ for d-Hitting
Set in linear time and space. We experimentally compare the two algorithms to a
classical data reduction algorithm of Weihe and evaluate their combinations.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-11T01:22:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04523</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04523" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Elder-rule-staircodes for Augmented Metric Spaces</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583884800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cai:Chen.html">Chen Cai</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kim:Woojin.html">Woojin Kim</a>, Facundo Memoli, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wang:Yusu.html">Yusu Wang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04523">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>An augmented metric space $(X, d_X, f_X)$ is a metric space $(X, d_X)$
equipped with a function $f_X: X \to \mathbb{R}$. It arises commonly in
practice, e.g, a point cloud $X$ in $\mathbb{R}^d$ where each point $x\in X$
has a density function value $f_X(x)$ associated to it. Such an augmented
metric space naturally gives rise to a 2-parameter filtration. However, the
resulting 2-parameter persistence module could still be of wild representation
type, and may not have simple indecomposables.
</p>
<p>In this paper, motivated by the elder-rule for the zeroth homology of a
1-parameter filtration, we propose a barcode-like summary, called the
elder-rule-staircode, as a way to encode the zeroth homology of the 2-parameter
filtration induced by a finite augmented metric space. Specifically, given a
finite $(X, d_X, f_X)$, its elder-rule-staircode consists of $n = |X|$ number
of staircase-like blocks in the plane. We show that the fibered barcode, the
fibered merge tree, and the graded Betti numbers associated to the zeroth
homology of the 2-parameter filtration induced by $(X, d_X, f_X)$ can all be
efficiently computed once the elder-rule-staircode is given. Furthermore, for
certain special cases, this staircode corresponds exactly to the set of
indecomposables of the zeroth homology of the 2-parameter filtration. Finally,
we develop and implement an efficient algorithm to compute the
elder-rule-staircode in $O(n^2\log n)$ time, which can be improved to
$O(n^2\alpha(n))$ if $X$ is from a fixed dimensional Euclidean space
$\mathbb{R}^d$, where $\alpha(n)$ is the inverse Ackermann function.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-11T01:20:57Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04438</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04438" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the computational complexity of uncapacitated multi-plant lot-sizing problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583884800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>J. O. Cunha, H. H. Kramer, R. A. Melo <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04438">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Production and inventory planning have become crucial and challenging in
nowadays competitive industrial and commercial sectors, especially when
multiple plants or warehouses are involved. In this context, this paper
addresses the complexity of uncapacitated multi-plant lot-sizing problems. We
consider a multi-item uncapacitated multi-plant lot-sizing problem with fixed
transfer costs and show that two of its very restricted special cases are
already NP-hard. Namely, we show that the single-item uncapacitated multi-plant
lot-sizing problem with a single period and the multi-item uncapacitated
two-plant lot-sizing problem with fixed transfer costs are NP-hard.
Furthermore, as a direct implication of the proven results, we also show that a
two-echelon multi-item lot-sizing with joint setup costs on transportation is
NP-hard.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-11T01:21:39Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2020/03/10/workshop-in-quantum-information-complexity-cryptography/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2020/03/10/workshop-in-quantum-information-complexity-cryptography/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Workshop in Quantum Information, Complexity &amp; Cryptography</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">June 11-12, 2020 University of York, UK https://sites.google.com/york.ac.uk/quicc/quicc We are organising a two-day event at the University of York in collaboration with York Interdisciplinary Centre for Cyber Security, which brings researchers in Quantum Information, Complexity and Cryptography together. The goal is to cover recent topics in these areas and facilitate interactions between them. The event … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2020/03/10/workshop-in-quantum-information-complexity-cryptography/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Workshop in Quantum Information, Complexity &amp; Cryptography</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T17:40:42Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-10T17:40:42Z</published>
    <category term="workshop"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:21:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4671</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4671" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4671#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4671" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">National disgrace</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">In this blog’s now 15-year-history, at Waterloo and then MIT and now UT Austin, I’ve tried to make it clear that I blog always as Scott, never as Dr. Aaronson of Such-and-Such Institution. (God knows I’ve written a few things that a prudent dean might prefer that I hadn’t—though if I couldn’t honestly say that, […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In this blog’s now 15-year-history, at Waterloo and then MIT and now UT Austin, I’ve tried to make it clear that I blog <em>always</em> as Scott, never as Dr. Aaronson of Such-and-Such Institution.  (God knows I’ve written a few things that a prudent dean might prefer that I hadn’t—though if I couldn’t honestly say that, in what sense would I even enjoy “academic freedom”?)  Today, though, for <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3167">only about</a> the second time, I’m also writing as a professor motivated by a duty of care toward his students.</p>



<p>A week ago, most of my grad students were in the Bay Area for a workshop; they then returned and spent a week hanging around the CS building like normal.  Yesterday I learned that at least one of those students developed symptoms consistent with covid19.  Of course, it’s much more likely to be a boring cold or flu—but still, in any sane regime, just to be certain, such a person would <strong>promptly get tested</strong>.</p>



<p>After quarantining himself, my student called the “24/7 covid19 hotline” listed in an email from the university’s president, but found no one answering the phone over the weekend.  Yesterday he finally got through—only to be told, flatly, that he couldn’t be tested due to insufficient capacity.  When I heard this, I asked my department chair and dean to look into the matter, and received confirmation that yeah, it sucks, but this is the situation.</p>



<p>If it’s true that, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/09/opinion/coronavirus-testing-new-york.html?fbclid=IwAR24o0pcDW2n6usYpyIC-bPhGUhoIkYAcvS_R4QvPv8yEdp0KsEF1XJWQv8">as I’ve read</a>, the same story is currently playing itself out all over the country, then this presumably isn’t the fault of anyone in UT’s health service or the city of Austin.  Rather, as they say in the movies, it goes all the way to the top, to the CDC director and ultimately the president—or rather, to the festering wound that now sits where the top used to be.</p>


<p>Speaking of movies, over the weekend Dana and I watched <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Contagion-Marion-Cotillard/dp/B006IVBSBU">Contagion</a>, as apparently many people are now doing.  I confess that I’d missed it when it came out in 2011.  I think it’s a cinematic masterpiece.  It freely violates many of the rules of movie narrative: characters are neither done in by their own hubris, nor saved by their faith or by being A-list stars.  But <em>Contagion</em> is also more than a glorified public service announcement about the importance of washing your hands.  It wants to show you the reality of the human world of its characters, and <em>also</em> the reality of a virus, and how the two realities affect each other despite obeying utterly different logic.  It will show a scene that’s important to the charaters for human reasons, and then it will show you the same scene again, except this time making you focus on whose hand touched which surface in which order.<br/><!--StartFragment--></p>
<p>But for all its excellence and now-obvious prescience, there are two respects in which Contagion failed to predict the reality of 2020.  The first is just a lucky throw of the RNA dice: namely, that the real coronavirus is perhaps an order of magnitude less fatal than the movie virus, and for some unknown reason it spares children.  But the second difference is terrifying.  All the public health authorities in the movie are ultra-empowered and competent.  They do badass things like injecting themselves with experimental vaccines.  If they stumble, it’s only in deeply understandable ways that any of us might (e.g., warning their own loved ones to evacuate a city before warning the public).</p>
<p>In other words, when the scriptwriters, writing their disaster movie, tried to imagine the worst, they failed to imagine a US government that would essentially abandon the public, by</p>
<p>(1) botching a simple test that dozens of other countries performed without issue,<br/>(2) preventing anyone else from performing their own tests, and then<br/>(3) turning around and using the lack of positive test results to justify its own inaction.</p>
<p>They failed to imagine a CDC that might as well not exist for all it would do in its hour of need: one that <a href="https://twitter.com/paulg/status/1236967513008877568">didn’t even bother to update its website on weekends</a>, and stopped publishing data once the data became too embarrassing.  The scriptwriters <em>did</em> imagine a troll gleefully spreading lies about the virus online, endangering anyone who listened to him.  They failed to imagine a universe where that troll was the president.</p>


<p>“I mean, don’t get me wrong,” they told me.  “Trump is a racist con artist, a demagogue, the precise thing that Adams and Hamilton and Franklin tried to engineer our republic to avoid.  Just, don’t get so <em>depressed</em> about it all the time!  Moaning about how we’re trapped in a <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3294">freakishly horrible</a> branch of the wavefunction, blah blah.  I mean look on the bright side!  What an incredible run of luck we’ve had, that we elected a president with the mental horizons of a sadistic toddler, and yet <em>in three years he hasn’t caused even one apocalypse</em>.  You’re alive and healthy, your loved ones are alive and healthy.  It could be a lot worse!”</p>



<p>The above, I suspect, is a sentiment that will now forever date any writing containing it to January 2020 or earlier.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-10T17:07:03Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-10T17:07:03Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Adventures in Meatspace"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Rage Against Doofosity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T17:22:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://theorydish.blog/?p=1559</id>
    <link href="https://theorydish.blog/2020/03/10/cacm-through-the-lens-of-a-passionate-theoretician/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>CACM – Through the Lens of a Passionate Theoretician</title>
    <summary>Spending time in insulation? Nothing more to watch on Netflix? Looking for something to read instead? My CACM article, about Avi Wigderson‘s excellent book and about the reach of computation appeared recently. Enjoy!</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Spending time in insulation? Nothing more to watch on Netflix? Looking for something to read instead? <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2020/3/243025-through-the-lens-of-a-passionate-theoretician/fulltext">My CACM article</a>, about <a href="https://www.math.ias.edu/avi/">Avi Wigderson</a>‘s <a href="https://www.math.ias.edu/avi/book">excellent book</a> and about the reach of computation appeared recently. Enjoy!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-10T16:14:07Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-10T16:14:07Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Omer Reingold</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://theorydish.blog</id>
      <logo>https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/cropped-nightdish1.jpg?w=32</logo>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Stanford's CS Theory Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Theory Dish</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:21:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-2996231259381150068</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/2996231259381150068/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/theorist-paul-r-young-passed-away.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2996231259381150068" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2996231259381150068" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/theorist-paul-r-young-passed-away.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Theorist Paul R Young passed away</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the early days of theoretical computer science, say 1960-1990 the main tools used were logic.<br/>
This made sense since, early on:<br/>
<br/>
a) Some of the basic notions like DTIME(T(n)), P, NP used Turing Machines in their definitions<br/>
<br/>
b) Some of the basic notions like reductions were modeled after similar concepts in<br/>
computability theory.<br/>
<br/>
One of the people who did much work in the interface between Logic and TCS was Paul Young.<br/>
He <a href="https://news.cs.washington.edu/2020/03/05/remembering-paul-young-1936-2019/">passed away</a> in December. Here are some highlights of his work:<br/>
<br/>
1) One of the first books that covered both computability and complexity:<br/>
<br/>
An Introduction to the general theory of Algorithms<br/>
by Machtey and Young.<br/>
<br/>
2) In Computability theory all many-one complete sets are computably isomorphic. Berman and<br/>
Hartmanis conjectured that the poly-many-one degree of the NP-complete sets was the same. This<br/>
would mean that all NP-complete sets were poly-isom (all of the known ones are).<br/>
<br/>
Mahaney and Young in the paper<br/>
<br/>
<i>Reductions Among Polynomial Isomorphism Types</i><br/>
<br/>
showed that every many-one poly degree either has one degree or has an infinite number of<br/>
degrees in a very complicated way.<br/>
<br/>
3) Recall that a <i>Cook Reduction from A to B </i>allows many queries to B, whereas a <i>Karp Reduction</i><br/>
only allows one query and your answer must be the same sense as the query.<br/>
Are there  cases where a Cook reduction is faster? Yes, from the paper<br/>
<br/>
<i>Cook reducibility is faster than Karp Reducibility</i><br/>
<br/>
by Longpre and Young<br/>
<br/>
(The original title was going to be <i>Cook is Faster than Karp</i>, but it was changed since it invoked<br/>
images of Cook and Karp in a footrace.  Hmmm. Which one would be faster?)<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
4) The <i>Boolean Hierarchy </i>is a hierarchy of iterations of NP sets. What if instead of starting with P<br/>
one started with RP (Randomized Poly time). What an intriguing notion! To find out read<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<i>Generalized Boolean Hierarchies over RP</i><br/>
<br/>
by  Alberto Bertoni, Danilo Bruschi, Deborah Joseph, Meera Sitharam, Paul Young<br/>
<br/>
5) There are many more, mostly on the theme of the interaction of logic and computer science.<br/>
<br/>
                       I saw him speak on some of these topics and was inspired by how much one could<br/>
take notions of computability and translate them into complexity theory.  The field has gone in a<br/>
different direction since then (more combinatorial) but we still use many of the basic concepts<br/>
like reducibility.  As such we all owe a debit to Paul Young.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-10T11:42:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-10T11:42:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T07:58:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04280</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04280" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Adjacency Labelling for Planar Graphs (and Beyond)</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583798400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Vida Dujmović, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Esperet:Louis.html">Louis Esperet</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Joret:Gwena=euml=l.html">Gwenaël Joret</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gavoille:Cyril.html">Cyril Gavoille</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Micek:Piotr.html">Piotr Micek</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Morin:Pat.html">Pat Morin</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04280">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We show that there exists an adjacency labelling scheme for planar graphs
where each vertex of an $n$-vertex planar graph $G$ is assigned a
$(1+o(1))\log_2 n$-bit label and the labels of two vertices $u$ and $v$ are
sufficient to determine if $uv$ is an edge of $G$. This is optimal up to the
lower order term and is the first such asymptotically optimal result. An
alternative, but equivalent, interpretation of this result is that, for every
$n$, there exists a graph $U_n$ with $n^{1+o(1)}$ vertices such that every
$n$-vertex planar graph is an induced subgraph of $U_n$. These results
generalize to bounded genus graphs, apex-minor-free graphs, bounded-degree
graphs from minor closed families, and $k$-planar graphs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T23:20:23Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04254</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04254" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>b-Coloring Parameterized by Clique-Width</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583798400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jaffke:Lars.html">Lars Jaffke</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lima:Paloma_T=.html">Paloma T. Lima</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lokshtanov:Daniel.html">Daniel Lokshtanov</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04254">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We provide a polynomial-time algorithm for b-Coloring on graphs of constant
clique-width. This unifies and extends previously known polynomial-time results
on several graph classes, and answers open questions posed by Campos and Silva
[Algorithmica, 2018] and Bonomo et al. [Graphs Combin., 2009]. This constitutes
the first result concerning structural parameterizations of this problem. We
show that the problem is FPT when parameterized by the vertex cover number on
general graphs, and on chordal graphs when parameterized by the number of
colors. Additionally, we observe that our algorithm for graphs of bounded
clique-width can be adapted to solve the Fall Coloring problem within the same
runtime bound.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04101</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04101" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Smoothed Analysis of Trie Height by Star-like PFAs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583798400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Eckhardt:Stefan.html">Stefan Eckhardt</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kosub:Sven.html">Sven Kosub</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nowak:Johannes.html">Johannes Nowak</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.04101">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Tries are general purpose data structures for information retrieval. The most
significant parameter of a trie is its height $H$ which equals the length of
the longest common prefix of any two string in the set $A$ over which the trie
is built. Analytical investigations of random tries suggest that ${\bf E}(H)\in
O(\log(\|A\|))$, although $H$ is unbounded in the worst case. Moreover, sharp
results on the distribution function of $H$ are known for many different random
string sources. But because of the inherent weakness of the modeling behind
average-case analysis---analyses being dominated by random data---these results
can utterly explain the fact that in many practical situations the trie height
is logarithmic. We propose a new semi-random string model and perform a
smoothed analysis in order to give a mathematically more rigorous explanation
for the practical findings. The perturbation functions which we consider are
based on probabilistic finite automata (PFA) and we show that the transition
probabilities of the representing PFA completely characterize the asymptotic
growth of the smoothed trie height. Our main result is of dichotomous
nature---logarithmic or unbounded---and is certainly not surprising at first
glance, but we also give quantitative upper and lower bounds, which are derived
using multivariate generating function in order to express the computations of
the perturbing PFA. A direct consequence is the logarithmic trie height for
edit perturbations(i.e., random insertions, deletions and substitutions).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03959</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03959" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Adaptive Fibonacci and Pairing Heaps</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583798400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Frohmader:Andrew.html">Andrew Frohmader</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.03959">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This brief note presents two adaptive heap data structures and conjectures on
running times.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03892</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03892" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>COPT: Coordinated Optimal Transport on Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583798400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dong:Yihe.html">Yihe Dong</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sawin:Will.html">Will Sawin</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.03892">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We introduce COPT, a novel distance metric between graphs defined via an
optimization routine, computing a coordinated pair of optimal transport maps
simultaneously. This is an unsupervised way to learn general-purpose graph
representations, it can be used for both graph sketching and graph comparison.
COPT involves simultaneously optimizing dual transport plans, one between the
vertices of two graphs, and another between graph signal probability
distributions. We show both theoretically and empirically that our method
preserves important global structural information on graphs, in particular
spectral information, making it well-suited for tasks on graphs including
retrieval, classification, summarization, and visualization.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03830</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03830" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Fast Loaded Dice Roller: A Near-Optimal Exact Sampler for Discrete Probability Distributions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583798400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saad:Feras_A=.html">Feras A. Saad</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Freer:Cameron_E=.html">Cameron E. Freer</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rinard:Martin_C=.html">Martin C. Rinard</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mansinghka:Vikash_K=.html">Vikash K. Mansinghka</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.03830">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper introduces a new algorithm for the fundamental problem of
generating a random integer from a discrete probability distribution using a
source of independent and unbiased random coin flips. We prove that this
algorithm, which we call the Fast Loaded Dice Roller (FLDR), is highly
efficient in both space and time: (i) the size of the sampler is guaranteed to
be linear in the number of bits needed to encode the input distribution; and
(ii) the expected number of bits of entropy it consumes per sample is at most 6
bits more than the information-theoretically optimal rate. We present fast
implementations of the linear-time preprocessing and near-optimal sampling
algorithms using unsigned integer arithmetic. Empirical evaluations on a broad
set of probability distributions establish that FLDR is 2x-10x faster in both
preprocessing and sampling than multiple baseline algorithms, including the
widely-used alias and interval samplers. It also uses up to 10000x less space
than the information-theoretically optimal sampler, at the expense of less than
1.5x runtime overhead.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03801</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03801" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Multiset Synchronization with Counting Cuckoo Filters</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583798400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Shangsen Li, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Luo:Lailong.html">Lailong Luo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Guo:Deke.html">Deke Guo</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.03801">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Set synchronization is a fundamental task in distributed applications and
implementations. Existing methods that synchronize simple sets are mainly based
on compact data structures such as Bloom filter and its variants. However,
these methods are infeasible to synchronize a pair of multisets which allow an
element to appear for multiple times. To this end, in this paper, we propose to
leverage the counting cuckoo filter (CCF), a novel variant of cuckoo filter, to
represent and thereafter synchronize a pair of multisets. The cuckoo filter
(CF) is a minimized hash table that uses cuckoo hashing to resolve collisions.
CF has an array of buckets, each of which has multiple slots to store element
fingerprints. Based on CF, CCF extends each slot as two fields, the fingerprint
field and the counter field. The fingerprint field records the fingerprint of
element which is stored by this slot; while the counter field counts the
multiplicity of the stored element. With such a design, CCF is competent to
represent any multiset. After generating and exchanging the respective CCFs
which represent the local multi-sets, we propose the query-based and the
decoding-based methods to identify the different elements between the given
multisets. The comprehensive evaluation results indicate that CCF outperforms
the counting Bloom filter (CBF) when they are used to synchronize multisets, in
terms of both synchronization accuracy and the space-efficiency, at the cost of
a little higher time-consumption.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03632</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03632" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Complexity of Planning</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583798400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Solovey:Kiril.html">Kiril Solovey</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.03632">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This chapter is devoted to the study of complexity of complete (or exact)
algorithms for robot motion planning. The term ``complete'' indicates that an
approach is guaranteed to find the correct solution (a motion path or
trajectory in our setting), or to report that none exists otherwise (in case
that for instance, no feasible path exists). Complexity theory is a fundamental
tool in computer science for analyzing the performance of algorithms, in terms
of the amount of resources they require. (While complexity can express
different quantities such as space and communication effort, our focus in this
chapter is on time complexity.) Moreover, complexity theory helps to identify
``hard'' problems which require an excessive amount of computation time to
solve. In the context of motion planning, complexity theory can come in handy
in various ways, some of which are illustrated here.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03605</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03605" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Clustering powers of sparse graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583798400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Jaroslav Nešetřil, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mendez:Patrice_Ossona_de.html">Patrice Ossona de Mendez</a>, Michał Pilipczuk, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhu:Xuding.html">Xuding Zhu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.03605">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We prove that if $G$ is a sparse graph --- it belongs to a fixed class of
bounded expansion $\mathcal{C}$ --- and $d\in \mathbb{N}$ is fixed, then the
$d$th power of $G$ can be partitioned into cliques so that contracting each of
these clique to a single vertex again yields a sparse graph. This result has
several graph-theoretic and algorithmic consequences for powers of sparse
graphs, including bounds on their subchromatic number and efficient
approximation algorithms for the chromatic number and the clique number.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03595</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2003.03595" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Fine-Grained Complexity of Computing the Tutte Polynomial of a Linear Matroid</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1583798400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bj=ouml=rklund:Andreas.html">Andreas Björklund</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kaski:Petteri.html">Petteri Kaski</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2003.03595">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We show that computing the Tutte polynomial of a linear matroid of dimension
$k$ on $k^{O(1)}$ points over a field of $k^{O(1)}$ elements requires
$k^{\Omega(k)}$ time unless the #ETH---a counting extension of the Exponential
Time Hypothesis of Impagliazzo and Paturi [CCC 1999] due to Dell et al. [ACM
TALG 2014]---is false. This holds also for linear matroids that admit a
representation where every point is associated to a vector with at most two
nonzero coordinates. Moreover, we also show that the same is true for computing
the Tutte polynomial of a binary matroid of dimension $k$ on $k^{O(1)}$ points
with at most three nonzero coordinates in each point's vector. These two
results stand in sharp contrast to computing the Tutte polynomial of a
$k$-vertex graph (that is, the Tutte polynomial of a graphic matroid of
dimension $k$---which is representable in dimension $k$ over the binary field
so that every vector has exactly two nonzero coordinates), which is known to be
computable in $2^k k^{O(1)}$ time [Bj\"orklund et al., FOCS 2008]. Our
lower-bound proofs proceed in three steps: (i) a classic connection due to
Crapo and Rota [1970] between the number of tuples of codewords of full support
and the Tutte polynomial of the matroid associated with the code; (ii) an
earlier-established \#ETH-hardness of counting the solutions to a bipartite
$(d,2)$-CSP on $n$ vertices in $d^{o(n)}$ time; and (iii) new embeddings of
such CSP instances as questions about codewords of full support in a linear
code. We complement these lower bounds with a matching upper-bound algorithm
design that computes the Tutte polynomial of a linear matroid of dimension $k$
on $k^{O(1)}$ points in $k^{O(k)}$ arithmetic operations in the base field.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-03-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/030</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/030" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-030 |  Barriers for Rectangular Matrix Multiplication | 

	Matthias Christandl, 

	François Le Gall, 

	Vladimir Lysikov, 

	Jeroen Zuiddam</title>
    <summary>We study the algorithmic problem of multiplying large matrices that are rectangular. We prove that the method that has been used to construct the fastest algorithms for rectangular matrix multiplication cannot give optimal algorithms. In fact, we prove a precise numerical barrier for this method. Our barrier improves the previously known barriers, both in the numerical sense, as well as in its generality. We prove our result using the asymptotic spectrum of tensors. More precisely, we crucially make use of two families of real tensor parameters with special algebraic properties: the quantum functionals and the support functionals. In particular, we prove that any lower bound on the dual exponent of matrix multiplication $\alpha$ via the big Coppersmith-Winograd tensors cannot exceed 0.625.</summary>
    <updated>2020-03-09T15:23:38Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-09T15:23:38Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:20:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4322</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/03/09/i-have-been-practicing-for-this-my-whole-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>I have been practicing for this my whole life</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the coronavirus epidemic advances in Italy with a 25-30% growth rate (meaning that the numbers are doubling every 3-4 days), and after two weeks of “lockdown-lite” in Northern Italy seems to have made no difference, the Italian government imposed … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/03/09/i-have-been-practicing-for-this-my-whole-life/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>As the coronavirus epidemic advances in Italy with a 25-30% growth rate (meaning that the numbers are doubling every 3-4 days), and after two weeks of “lockdown-lite” in Northern Italy seems to have made no difference, the Italian government imposed on Sunday morning a stricter lockdown on the region of Lombardy and some cities outside the region including Venice. Several people have reached out to ask how things are going, so here is a brief recap. </p>
<p><span id="more-4322"/></p>
<p>First of all, I would like to give a shoutout to Taiwan, which is currently the country that has done the <a href="https://www.zmescience.com/other/pieces/how-taiwan-managed-to-avoid-a-coronavirus-outbreak/">best job stopping an outbreak</a>. The Taiwanese have several things going for them: the SARS scare made the government plan for the next epidemic, instead of making it up as it would go along, and their preparedness was impressive. The plan focused on isolation, contact-tracing, and people being careful: kudos to the Taiwanese for how well they complied. From the little that I have learned about Taiwan after living there for two months a couple of years ago, the Taiwanese are not rule-followers the way the Swiss or the Singaporean can be. But if they bend or break rules, they do that after a lot of consideration for how this impacts others. Basically, people <i>care about strangers</i>, a disposition that helps a lot in controlling an epidemic (and which is not a big part of the Italian national mood).</p>
<p>But let’s talk about me. This is my mood right now:<br/>
<img alt="self_isolate" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4326" src="https://lucatrevisan.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/self_isolate.png?w=584"/></p>
<p>(Image credit: <a href="https://xkcd.com/">xkcd</a> by Randall Munroe)</p>
<p>Since we are past isolation-and-contact-tracing, the main goal is to reduce person-to-person contact so that we can stop the exponential growth. For the past two weeks, besides the usual recommendations (do not kiss hello and goodbye, do not shake hands, wash hands frequently, do not touch your face) the government recommended keeping a one-meter distance from other people. There has been some inventive ways to keep going under these requirements. For example cinemas (in the regions in which they were not required to shut down) sold tickets for at most a third of the seats, asking people to leave two empty seats between any occupied seats. </p>
<p>Last Saturday, before the newest set of regulations were in place, I went out for a drink. The bar had cordoned off the counter area</p>
<p> <img alt="IMG_9383" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4328" src="https://lucatrevisan.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/img_9383.jpg?w=584"/></p>
<p>They asked everybody who came in to seat down, at one of a few well-separated tables. Gloves-wearing servers took orders and brought some food (instead of the usual buffet). Once all tables were taken, a server stood outside preventing other people from coming in.</p>
<p>As we were drinking our aperitivi at a safe distance from each other, news began to leak of the new measures, which the government eventually announced at 2am Sunday morning. The leak suggested that Lombardy, Venice, and other places, would be included in the so-called <i>red zone</i>, which was a group of small towns that had been completely isolated for the past two weeks (nobody could go in and out except ambulances, trash collection trucks, and deliveries). In a development that might not have happened in Taiwan, a few hundred people rushed to train stations in Milan and Venice to flee South.</p>
<p>The actual regulations allowed travel in and out of the places affected by the new lockdown, but only for <i>demonstrated work or health reasons</i>. This is what the regulation said, but how would people prove their reason? The Italian genius for bureaucracy started cranking in the next few hours, and now, at train stations, people are required to sign an affidavit stating the existence of such a reason before boarding a train:</p>
<p><img alt="affidavit" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4329" src="https://lucatrevisan.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/affidavit.jpeg?w=584"/></p>
<p>In the locked-down cities, all bars and restaurants have to close by 6pm, and all places where people may congregate (including churches, gyms, swimming pools, in addition to museums, schools and universities which were already closed) are closed all day. Even funeral and weddings are banned. Grocery stores will have to ensure that people stay within a meter of each other, making people wait outside and enter in small groups if necessary.</p>
<p>What about me? I am procrastinating on writing blog posts about online optimization and on reviewing papers for ICALP, I have started reading William Gibson’s latest novel <i>Agency</i> and watching the tv series <i>Pose</i>, and I am cooking every meal. Considering that I like to sleep and that I am spending a fair amount of time on the phone, I have got the whole day covered.</p>
<p>What is next? At this point in Lombardy about a person in 2,500, or 0.04% of the population, is infected, and we have run out of ICU beds. The rate of infection in Wuhan peaked at about 0.6% of the population, and this was well past the point at which they had run out of hospital beds in general. Hopefully, here we will peak well below that. On the other hand, left to its own devices, in the absence of any containment measures, I have seen estimates that the disease would peak a bit higher than a flu epidemic, at 20% or even 60% of the population.</p>
<p>So, find the Taiwanese in yourself, think about others, and wash those hands.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-09T12:24:27Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-09T12:24:27Z</published>
    <category term="Milan"/>
    <category term="Taiwan"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:20:15Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16767</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/08/the-virtue-of-closed-problems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Virtue of Closed Problems</title>
    <summary>A new condition in property testing Composite crop of src1, src2 Maryam Aliakbarpour and Sandeep Silwal are PhD students at MIT. They have a joint paper titled, “Testing Properties of Multiple Distributions with Few Samples.” Aliakbarpour is advised by Ronitt Rubinfeld. Silwal has a different advisor, Piotr Indyk. Could we test which advisor is better […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>A new condition in property testing</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/aliakbarpoursilwal.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16769" height="125" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/aliakbarpoursilwal.png?w=181&amp;h=125" width="181"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Composite crop of <a href="https://risingstars18-eecs.mit.edu/participant-aliakbarpour/">src1</a>, <a href="http://sandeepsilwal.com/">src2</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Maryam Aliakbarpour and Sandeep Silwal are PhD students at MIT. They have a joint <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1911.07324.pdf">paper</a> titled, “Testing Properties of Multiple Distributions with Few Samples.” Aliakbarpour is advised by Ronitt Rubinfeld. Silwal has a different advisor, Piotr Indyk. Could we test which advisor is better by sampling? Haha, not a chance…</p>
<p>
Today we will discuss this paper as an example of the power of computer science theory.</p>
<p>
Aliakbarpour and Silwal (AS) prove results on property testing, which is of course a long studied area in statistics, in mathematics, and in complexity theory. Many problems of property testing are open; many are very hard problems, and some are really impossible—such as distinguishing slight differences between distributions. With all due respect, the brilliance of their paper is not in solving open problems. Rather it is how they modify property testing in a novel manner. </p>
<p>
Their proofs are clever, are technically strong, but we feel more importantly is how they change the problems. That is, they show how to add a new constraint to property testing, where: </p>
<ol>
<li>
The constraint is reasonable and appears to be natural; <p/>
</li><li>
The constraint is powerful and allows efficient algorithms where previously none were possible.
</li></ol>
<p>Let’s look at this more closely.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Opening a Closed Problem </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We all know about open problems and closed problems. There are however two kinds of closed problems: ones that have been settled and ones that have been proved impossible to settle. We also know that one can often take an open problem and define a meaningful subcase of it that can be solved. What may be less obvious is how one can do the same with the latter kind of closed problem.</p>
<p>
The work of AS is a perfect example of this phenomenon. They take a problem that is unsolvable and change it to one that is solvable. The details of their results are less important than their change to the underlying problem. One of the key insights throughout theory is that we often have made major progress by changing the ground rules. The AS work is a particularly clear case of this. </p>
<p/><h2> The New Condition </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
AS call it the <i>structural condition</i>. They postulate a consistency type of condition on property testing. Suppose that one is interesting in testing whether or not a collection of slot-machines are fair. That is, are they set to cheat players or not? This is known to be hard to do with few tests. But after adding their new constraint it becomes quite efficient.</p>
<p>
Among some examples to convey their definition, they postulate a row of slot machines in a casino that are supposed to give the same distribution of prizes <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{j}"/> with known <em>fair</em> probabilities <img alt="{q(j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%28j%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q(j)}"/>. As usual with property testing we want to distinguish between two hypotheses that are some distance apart: one that the machines conform to the fair distribution <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> and an alternative hypothesis that each is far from fair. There are two relevant factors:</p>
<ol>
<li>
We do not get to make many tests on one machine of our choosing. The best we can do is watch people try the machines. They may try different machines and so give only a few sample results per machine. <p/>
</li><li>
There are cases of this situation 1 where although each machine is far from fair the joint distribution of a few samples cannot be told apart from fair. The authors mention a trivial case where <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> is uniform and we get just one result from each machine, results all different from each other. These cannot be told apart. But there are less-trivial cases.
</li></ol>
<p>
Such situations are common with real-word data. The authors mention cases of medical data when one gets just one or a few blood readings from patients with disparate situational factors that can bias their samples. The joint effect of the biases may completely mask the systematic population tendency one is trying to test for. This is the setting in which the problem of distinguishing has been regarded as impossible, case closed. In the slot-machine example, Aliakbarpour and Silwal state their structural condition informally as follows:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Our goal is to test whether all the machines were fair … or they are far from being fair. In this case, we can naturally assume that if the machines are unfair, the house will assign a lower probability to the expensive prizes, and higher probability to cheap ones. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Of course, the house <em>could</em> cheat players without cheating in this uniform manner. More subtle rigging of the machines in different ways could mask the lowered expectation. But what AS are saying is: <i>Provided the house cheats in this consistent manner, then they can be discovered quickly</i>. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Formal Definition and Proof Idea </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The formal definition is that each of the true source distributions is biased the same way in the same components as the expected (“fair”) distribution:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Definition 1</b> <em> A sequence <img alt="{p^1,\dots, p^m}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%5E1%2C%5Cdots%2C+p%5Em%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p^1,\dots, p^m}"/> of distributions on a discrete domain <img alt="{[n]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Bn%5D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{[n]}"/> obeys the structural condition relative to the distribution <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> if there is a subset <img alt="{A \subset [n]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA+%5Csubset+%5Bn%5D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A \subset [n]}"/> such that for all <img alt="{i \in [m]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi+%5Cin+%5Bm%5D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i \in [m]}"/> and <img alt="{j \in [n]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj+%5Cin+%5Bn%5D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{j \in [n]}"/>: </em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{cases} p^i(j) \geq q(j) &amp; \text{if } j \in A\\ p^i(j) \leq q(j) &amp; \text{otherwise}. \end{cases} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Bcases%7D+p%5Ei%28j%29+%5Cgeq+q%28j%29+%26+%5Ctext%7Bif+%7D+j+%5Cin+A%5C%5C+p%5Ei%28j%29+%5Cleq+q%28j%29+%26+%5Ctext%7Botherwise%7D.+%5Cend%7Bcases%7D+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{cases} p^i(j) \geq q(j) &amp; \text{if } j \in A\\ p^i(j) \leq q(j) &amp; \text{otherwise}. \end{cases} "/></p>
</em><p><em/>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The term “structural condition” is vanilla and perhaps saying the <img alt="{p^i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%5Ei%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p^i}"/> are “conformally biased” relative to <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> would be more descriptive. A major point which the authors emphasize right afterward is that the set <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> is <em>unknown</em>. There are exponentially many possibilities for what <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> could be—so we cannot try to guess it. Rather, proofs using this condition need to exploit how all the <img alt="{p^{i}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%5E%7Bi%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p^{i}}"/> distributions conform to the same <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/>. The slot-machine example arguably does not reflect this point in full—because we can know in advance what the major and minor prizes of a slot machine are (including “no prize” among the latter). The medical-data examples and others certainly do, however.</p>
<p>
We can convey briefly and intuitively how this condition is used for the case where <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> is uniform distribution on <img alt="{[n]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Bn%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{[n]}"/>—which is quite general as testing for many distributions can be efficiently mapped into this case. A key property of uniform distribution is that among all distributions on <img alt="{[n]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Bn%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{[n]}"/>, it minimizes the probability of getting <em>collisions</em> from repeated samples. This idea has yielded the most effective test statistics for problems when there is only one distribution <img alt="{p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p}"/>. When there are multiple <img alt="{p^i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%5Ei%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p^i}"/> the effectiveness can be blunted in instances like the one in the previous section—the instances that are impossible. </p>
<p>
However, AS show that their structural condition is just what’s needed to bridge the gap that keeps the impossible cases from being distinguished. Realizing that the compounded complications of having multiple <img alt="{p^i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%5Ei%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p^i}"/> can be resolved by this stroke is their act of brilliance. Their paper applies it successfully to two other problem settings—identity testing and closeness testing—and also shows meaningful instances that obey and are resolved by their definition but that escape an older condition involving product distributions. As usual, we say to see the <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1911.07324.pdf">paper</a> for the details.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Consequences in Crypto and Inference? </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
It remains our place to ask, in which other cases might the AS condition arise and what uses might it have? I can think first of one implication for adversarial strategies in cryptography. It goes like this:</p>
<p>
We can view the AS theorems as saying that anyone who wishes to cheat others should <b>not</b> be consistent. Being consistent according to some utility criterion—<em>even an unknown one</em>—makes it easier for others to detect that they are cheating. </p>
<p>
Following their slot-machine example suggests this: Arrange the machines in total to cheat players. But make it so that they are not consistent. They can set some prizes up in probability and some lower, and importantly, do this differently on different machines. They could even make some machines pay out more than the legal expectation—while still giving a small profit to the casino so it does not become too obvious to customers that those machines are “lucky.” There is safety in non-conformity alone. </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \S " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5CS+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \S "/></p>
<p>
Ken notices a similarity to the chess-modeling situation he began describing in this recent <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/11/29/predicating-predictivity/">post</a>. Instead of prizes of known value, in chess we have distributions over possible moves whose values are <em>not</em> so readily apparent to the player—that’s what makes chess challenging to play. </p>
<p>
In his case, giving any chess position <img alt="{t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t}"/> and a player <img alt="{P}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P}"/> having that position, he postulates a true distribution <img alt="{p^t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%5Et%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p^t}"/> of moves <img alt="{P}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BP%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{P}"/> would make and wants to compare that with the distribution <img alt="{q^t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%5Et%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q^t}"/> projected by his model. Now there can be many positions <img alt="{t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t}"/> with different characteristics, but Ken can treat the distributions <img alt="{q^t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%5Et%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q^t}"/> coming from his model as one fixed point of reference <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/>, and he can give different positions the same ranks of legal moves <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/> (best), then <img alt="{2,\dots, n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%2C%5Cdots%2C+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2,\dots, n}"/>. If positions have different numbers of legal moves he can pad them out by treating illegal moves the same as completely losing blunders. </p>
<p>
So he has a situation like this: different <img alt="{p^t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%5Et%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p^t}"/> and one <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> over a bunch of positions. Ken knows his model not only varies in accuracy but is biased in ways explained in that post. It appears that this bias is highly conformal. The model is trained to make the projection <img alt="{q(1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%281%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q(1)}"/> of the probability of the first move accurate on average. Then the tendency is that the projections of the second-best and third-best moves are off one way, and the projections of all the other moves are off the other way. This is like having <img alt="{A = \{2,3\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA+%3D+%5C%7B2%2C3%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A = \{2,3\}}"/> or its complement most of the time. The new statistical tests that Ken is crafting also live under the specter of impossibility. A co-worker has demonstrated that they <em>fail</em> in cases randomly generated from normal distributions. But so far they are appearing to succeed in Ken’s more-structured situations from his real-world chess data. On this we will stay tuned.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Does the AS paper say something about cryptography? How widely does their condition apply?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-09T03:58:12Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-09T03:58:12Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="detection"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="distributions"/>
    <category term="impossible"/>
    <category term="Maryam Aliakbarpour"/>
    <category term="Property testing"/>
    <category term="sampling"/>
    <category term="Sandeep Silwal"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/03/08/mathematics-books-women</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/03/08/mathematics-books-women.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Mathematics books by women</title>
    <summary>It’s International Women’s Day, and The Aperiodical has a new piece up on “Books about Maths by Women”. One of my own projects for the last few weeks has been to create Wikipedia articles on noteworthy mathematics books, and so far roughly half of the creations have included at least one woman among their authors. They are (alphabetical by title):</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>It’s International Women’s Day, and <em>The Aperiodical</em> has a new piece up on “<a href="https://aperiodical.com/2020/03/iwd-2020-books-about-maths-by-women/">Books about Maths by Women</a>”. One of my own projects for the last few weeks has been to create Wikipedia articles on noteworthy mathematics books, and so far roughly half of the creations have included at least one woman among their authors. They are (alphabetical by title):</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Calculating_Machines">The Calculating Machines</a></em> (1992), by Ernst Martin, translated and edited by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peggy_A._Kidwell">Peggy A. Kidwell</a> and Michael R. Williams. A history of pre-World-War-II mechanical calculators.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Closing_the_Gap:_The_Quest_to_Understand_Prime_Numbers">Closing the Gap: The Quest to Understand Prime Numbers</a></em> (2017), by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicky_Neale">Vicky Neale</a>. History and recent developments in the twin prime conjecture.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Combinatorics_of_Finite_Geometries">Combinatorics of Finite Geometries</a></em> (1986; 2nd ed. 1997), by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynn_Batten">Lynn Batten</a>. An undergraduate textbook on finite projective planes, finite affine planes, and other finite geometries.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complexities:_Women_in_Mathematics">Complexities: Women in Mathematics</a></em> (2005), edited by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bettye_Anne_Case">Bettye Anne Case</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complexities:_Women_in_Mathematics">Anne M. Leggett</a>. A celebration of women in mathematics featuring the stories of over 80 women.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crocheting_Adventures_with_Hyperbolic_Planes">Crocheting Adventures with Hyperbolic Planes</a></em> (2009; 2nd ed. 2018), by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daina_Taimina">Daina Taimina</a>. How to make hyperbolic surfaces out of crochet, and what we can learn mathematically from tactile interactions with these surfaces.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Difference_Equations:_From_Rabbits_to_Chaos">Difference Equations: From Rabbits to Chaos</a></em> (2005), by Paul Cull, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Flahive">Mary Flahive</a>, and Robby Robson, an undergraduate textbook on finite difference equations, population dynamics, and related topics.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Guide_to_the_Classification_Theorem_for_Compact_Surfaces">A Guide to the Classification Theorem for Compact Surfaces</a></em> (2013), by Jean Gallier and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dianna_Xu">Dianna Xu</a>. An exposition of the result that the topology of a two-dimensional surface can be completely described by its orientability, Euler characteristic, and number of punctures.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Introduction_to_Tropical_Geometry">Introduction to Tropical Geometry</a></em> (2015) by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diane_Maclagan">Diane Maclagan</a> and Bernd Sturmfels. What happens if you do algebraic geometry in an arithmetic where the two basic operations are addition and minimization, instead of multiplication and addition?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathematics_in_Ancient_Egypt:_A_Contextual_History">Mathematics in Ancient Egypt: A Contextual History</a></em> (2016), by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annette_Imhausen">Annette Imhausen</a>. The length of time covered by this history is greater than the length of time since it happened. Its focus is on putting Egyptian mathematics into the context of the society of the times, rather than (as in earlier studies) trying to translate it into modern mathematical concepts and analyze the mathematical foundations of Egyptian calculational methods.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pearls_in_Graph_Theory">Pearls in Graph Theory: A Comprehensive Introduction</a></em> (1990), by Gerhard Ringel and <a href="https://www.legacy.com/obituaries/skagitvalleyherald/obituary.aspx?n=nora-anne-hartsfield&amp;pid=153284332&amp;fhid=5497">Nora Hartsfield</a>. A collection of the authors’ favorite topics in graph theory, although not as comprehensive as the title makes out.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poincar%C3%A9_and_the_Three-Body_Problem">Poincaré and the Three-Body Problem</a></em> (1997), by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/June_Barrow-Green">June Barrow-Green</a>. The history surrounding Poincaré’s work on the the three-body problem, which led to chaos theory, began a long dispute between mathematicians and  astronomers over the convergence of series, and was a big part of Poincaré’s own fame.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proofs_That_Really_Count">Proofs That Really Count: the Art of Combinatorial Proof</a></em> (2003), by Arthur Benjamin and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jennifer_Quinn">Jennifer Quinn</a>. An exposition of the concept of bijective proofs, in which one proves the equality of two integer formulas by showing that both count the same set of mathematical objects.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quasicrystals_and_Geometry">Quasicrystals and Geometry</a></em> (1995), by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marjorie_Senechal">Marjorie Senechal</a>. An investigation of the relation between the mathematical properties of aperiodic tilings like the Penrose tiling, and physical quasicrystals whose X-ray diffraction patterns show systems of Bragg peaks with five-way symmetry.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symmetry_in_Mechanics">Symmetry in Mechanics: A Gentle, Modern Introduction</a></em> (2001), by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephanie_Singer">Stephanie Singer</a>. How to use symplectic geometry to reduce the solution of the two-body problem from twelve dimensions (three for the position and momentum of each body) to two, leading to an elegant derivation of Kepler’s laws of planetary motion.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taking_Sudoku_Seriously">Taking Sudoku Seriously: The math behind the world’s most popular pencil puzzle</a></em> (2011), by Jason Rosenhouse and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laura_Taalman">Laura Taalman</a>. An exploration of various topics in mathematics related to Sudoku puzzles and their solution, including Latin squares, graph coloring, algorithms for solving systems of polynomials, and extremal combinatorics.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_numeris_triangularibus_et_inde_de_progressionibus_arithmeticis:_Magisteria_magna">Thomas Harriot’s Doctrine of Triangular Numbers</a></em> (2009), by Thomas Harriot, edited and translated by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janet_Beery">Janet Beery</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jackie_Stedall">Jackie Stedall</a>. An important precursor to the invention of calculus by Newton, using finite differences instead of infinitesimal differences.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treks_Into_Intuitive_Geometry">Treks into Intuitive Geometry: The World of Polygons and Polyhedra</a></em> (2015), by Jin Akiyama and Kiyoko Matsunaga. A Socratic dialogue on tessellations, polyhedra, polygonal dissections, and polyhedral unfoldings.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viewpoints:_Mathematical_Perspective_and_Fractal_Geometry_in_Art">Viewpoints: Mathematical Perspective and Fractal Geometry in Art</a></em> (2011), by Marc Frantz and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annalisa_Crannell">Annalisa Crannell</a>. An undergraduate general-education textbook on perspective geometry and fractal structure in art.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>There are many more I could include, but haven’t yet (including most of the <em>Aperiodical</em> list). Many of these books are award-winners, but to a large extent inclusion in this list is driven by my personal taste in books, so many of these are somewhat specialized rather than being general-audience books. But the main criterion for inclusion on Wikipedia is that everything must have multiple in-depth sources, and everything in the article must come from those sources. For books those sources are not the book itself, but (typically) published book reviews. The bare minimum is two reviews, but I’ve been aiming for books with at least four. So for instance I would have liked to include <em>Geometry: The Line and the Circle</em> (2019), by Maureen T. Carroll and Elyn Rykken, but I could find only <a href="https://www.maa.org/press/maa-reviews/geometry-the-line-and-the-circle">one review of it</a>, and that’s not enough. To all the book reviewers out there: your efforts are appreciated, and helpful.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103788964314558993">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-08T11:40:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-08T11:40:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T07:27:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1270</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1270" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for February 2020</title>
    <summary>Despite a wealth of February conference deadlines, papers were fairly sparse. We found two EDIT: three EDIT EDIT: four papers for the month of February, please share if we missed any relevant papers. Monotone probability distributions over the Boolean cube can be learned with sublinear samples, by Ronitt Rubinfeld and Arsen Vasilyan (arXiv). By now, […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Despite a wealth of February conference deadlines, papers were fairly sparse. We found <s>two</s> <s>EDIT: three</s> EDIT EDIT: four papers for the month of February, please share if we missed any relevant papers.</p>



<p><strong>Monotone probability distributions over the Boolean cube can be learned with sublinear samples</strong>, by Ronitt Rubinfeld and Arsen Vasilyan (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.03415">arXiv</a>). By now, it is well known that assuming an (unknown) distribution enjoys some sort of structure can lead to more efficient algorithms for learning and testing. Often one proves that the structure permits a convenient representation, and exploits this representation to solve the problem at hand. This paper studies the learning of monotone distributions over the Boolean hypercube. The authors exploit and extend a structural statement about monotone Boolean <em>functions</em> by <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-662-43948-7_20">Blais, Håstad, Servedio, and Tan</a>, using it to provide sublinear algorithms for estimating the support size, distance to uniformity, and the distribution itself.</p>



<p><strong>Locally Private Hypothesis Selection</strong>, by Sivakanth Gopi, Gautam Kamath, Janardhan Kulkarni, Aleksandar Nikolov, Zhiwei Steven Wu, and Huanyu Zhang (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09465">arXiv</a>). Given a collection of \(k\) distributions and a set of samples from one of them, can we identify which distribution it is? This paper studies this problem (and an agnostic generalization of it) under the constraint of <em>local differential privacy</em>. The authors show that this problem requires \(\Omega(k)\) samples, in contrast to the \(O(\log k)\) complexity in the non-private model. Furthermore, they give \(\tilde O(k)\)-sample upper bounds in various interactivity models.</p>



<p><strong>Efficient Distance Approximation for Structured High-Dimensional Distributions via Learning</strong>, by Arnab Bhattacharyya, Sutanu Gayen, Kuldeep S. Meel, and N. V. Vinodchandran (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.05378">arXiv</a>). Given samples from two distributions, can you estimate the total variation distance between them? This paper gives a framework for solving this problem for <em>structured</em> distribution classes, including Ising models, Bayesian networks, Gaussians, and causal models. The approach can be decomposed properly learning the distributions, followed by estimating the distance between the two hypotheses. Challenges arise when densities are hard to compute exactly.</p>



<p><strong>Profile Entropy: A Fundamental Measure for the Learnability and Compressibility of Discrete Distributions</strong>, by Yi Hao and Alon Orlitsky (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.11665">arXiv</a>). The histogram of a dataset is the collection of frequency counts of domain elements. The <em>profile</em> of a dataset can be succinctly described as the histogram of the histogram. Recent works have shown that, in some sense, discarding information about your dataset by looking solely at the profile can be beneficial for certain problems in which it is “universal”. This work explores two new quantities, the entropy and dimension of the profile, which turn out to play a key role in quantifying the performance of estimators based on the profile.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-08T02:54:24Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-08T02:54:24Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam Kamath</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T02:21:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4664</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4664" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4664#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4664" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Coronavirus: the second-weirdest solution?</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Many people have suggested coating handles, doorknobs and so forth with virus-killing copper tape. It’s a shame that this isn’t being tried on a wider scale. In the meantime, though, here’s a related but different idea that I had last night. Imagine we could coat every doorknob, every light switch, every railing, every other surface […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Many people have suggested coating handles, doorknobs and so forth with <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/LwcKYR8bykM6vDHyo/coronavirus-justified-practical-advice-thread">virus-killing copper tape</a>.  It’s a shame that this isn’t being tried on a wider scale.  In the meantime, though, here’s a related but different idea that I had last night.</p>



<p>Imagine we could coat every doorknob, every light switch, every railing, every other surface that people might touch in public buildings, with some long-lasting disgusting, sticky, slimy substance.  For a variety of reasons, one probably wouldn’t use actual excrement, although it wouldn’t hurt if the substance <em>looked like</em> that.  Or it could be a sickly neon green or red, to make it impossible to conceal when you’d gotten the substance on your hands.</p>



<p>What would be the result?  Of course, people would avoid touching these surfaces.  If they had to, they’d do so with a napkin or glove whenever possible.  If they had to touch them bare-handedly, they’d rush to wash their hands with soap as soon as possible afterwards.  Certainly they wouldn’t touch their faces before having washed their hands.</p>



<p>In short, they’d show exactly the behaviors that experts agree are among the most helpful, if our goal is to slow the spread of the coronavirus.  In effect, we’d be plugging an unfortunate gap in our evolutionary programming—namely, that the surfaces where viruses can thrive aren’t intuitively disgusting to us, as (say) vomit or putrid meat are—by <em>making</em> those surfaces disgusting, as they ought to be in the middle of a pandemic.</p>



<p>Note that, even if it <em>somehow</em> turns out to be infeasible to coat all the touchable surfaces in public buildings with disgusting goo, you might still derive great personal benefit from <em>imagining</em> them so covered.  If you manage to pull that off, it will yield just the right heuristic for when and how often you should now be washing your hands (and avoiding touching your face), without no need for additional conscious reflection.</p>



<p>Mostly, having the above thoughts made me grateful for my friend <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robin_Hanson">Robin Hanson</a>.  For as long Robin is around, <a href="https://twitter.com/robinhanson/status/1235020994110205953">tweeting</a> and <a href="http://www.overcomingbias.com/2020/02/consider-controlled-infection.html">blogging</a> from his unique corner of mindspace, no one will ever be able to say that <em>my</em> ideas for how to control the coronavirus were the world’s weirdest or most politically tone-deaf.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-06T22:21:52Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-06T22:21:52Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Embarrassing Myself"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Procrastination"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T17:22:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/029</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/029" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-029 |  Geometric Rank of Tensors and Subrank of Matrix Multiplication | 

	Guy Moshkovitz, 

	Swastik Kopparty, 

	Jeroen Zuiddam</title>
    <summary>Motivated by problems in algebraic complexity theory (e.g., matrix multiplication) and extremal combinatorics (e.g., the cap set problem and the sunflower problem), we introduce the geometric rank as a new tool in the study of tensors and hypergraphs. We prove that the geometric rank is an upper bound on the subrank of tensors and the independence number of hypergraphs. We prove that the geometric rank is smaller than the slice rank of Tao, and relate geometric rank to the analytic rank of Gowers and Wolf in an asymptotic fashion. As a first application, we use geometric rank to prove a tight upper bound on the (border) subrank of the matrix multiplication tensors, matching Strassen's well-known lower bound from 1987.</summary>
    <updated>2020-03-06T15:03:24Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-06T15:03:24Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:20:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=19462</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/03/06/a-new-polytcs-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A new PolyTCS blog!</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A new PolyTCS blog The PolyTCS Project is a new blog to run collaborative Theoretical Computer Science projects. The initiative is by two graduate students Rupei Xu and Chloe Yang. The logo was designed by Grigory Yaroslavtsev. At this stage … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/03/06/a-new-polytcs-blog/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A new PolyTCS blog</p>
<div class="site-logo"><a class="custom-logo-link" href="https://polytcs.wordpress.com/" rel="home"><img alt="The PolyTCS Project" class="custom-logo" height="96" src="https://polytcs.files.wordpress.com/2019/10/cropped-notequal.png?w=264&amp;h=96" width="264"/></a></div>
<p class="site-title"><a href="https://polytcs.wordpress.com/" rel="home">The PolyTCS Project</a> is a new blog to run collaborative Theoretical Computer Science projects. The initiative is by two graduate students <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/xurupei/">Rupei Xu</a> and Chloe Yang. The logo was designed by Grigory Yaroslavtsev.</p>
<p>At this stage the blog raised possible projects to pursue.  A few days ago Rupei Xu discussed a second possible exciting project:   Project 2: <a href="https://polytcs.wordpress.com/2020/03/06/is-semi-definite-programming-sdp-polynomial-time-solvable/">Is Semi-Definite Programming (SDP) Polynomial-Time Solvable?</a> The first project-proposal (Nov 1, 2019 by Jiapeng Zhang) was <a href="https://polytcs.wordpress.com/2019/11/01/the-entropy-influence-conjecture/">Project 1: The Entropy-Influence Conjecture</a>.</p>
<p>(Here is a <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2014/03/15/could-we-have-felt-evidence-for-sdp-p/">2014  post on GLL</a> on the problem of Project 2, and here is <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2007/08/16/gil-kalai-the-entropyinfluence-conjecture/">my 2007 post on WN</a> on the problem of Project 1.)</p>
<p class="site-title">Good luck!!!</p>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-06T14:05:32Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-06T14:05:32Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Mathematics over the Internet"/>
    <category term="Chloe Yang"/>
    <category term="Grigory Yaroslavtsev"/>
    <category term="Rupei Xi"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/03/06/postdoc-at-national-university-of-singapore-apply-by-april-15-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/03/06/postdoc-at-national-university-of-singapore-apply-by-april-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at National University of Singapore (apply by April 15, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Two post-doctoral positions are available for work on developing statistical and computational guarantees for causal inference algorithms. I am looking for candidates with strong publication records either in theoretical computer science and statistics or in causal inference. Please email me regarding your interest, along with your CV and names of two references. . Website: https://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/~arnab/causal-postdoc.html […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Two post-doctoral positions are available for work on developing statistical and computational guarantees for causal inference algorithms. I am looking for candidates with strong publication records either in theoretical computer science and statistics or in causal inference. Please email me regarding your interest, along with your CV and names of two references. .</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/~arnab/causal-postdoc.html">https://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/~arnab/causal-postdoc.html</a><br/>
Email: arnabb@nus.edu.sg</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-06T09:06:13Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-06T09:06:13Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:20:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4649</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4649" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4649#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4649" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Turn down the quantum volume</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Several people asked me to comment on the recent announcement by Honeywell that they’ll soon have what they call “the most powerful” quantum computer (see here for press release, here for Forbes article, here for paper). I’m glad that Honeywell, which many people might know as an air-conditioner manufacturer, has entered the race for trapped-ion […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Several people asked me to comment on the recent announcement by Honeywell that they’ll soon have what they call “the most powerful” quantum computer (see <a href="https://www.honeywell.com/en-us/newsroom/news/2020/03/behind-the-scenes-of-a-major-quantum-breakthrough">here for press release</a>, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/moorinsights/2020/03/03/honeywell-surprisingly-announces-it-will-be-releasing-the-most-powerful-quantum-computer-in-the-world/#c271c5114b4a">here for <em>Forbes</em> article</a>, <a href="https://www.honeywell.com/content/dam/honeywell/files/Beta_10_Quantum_3_3_2020.pdf">here for paper</a>).  </p>



<p>I’m glad that Honeywell, which many people might know as an air-conditioner manufacturer, has entered the race for trapped-ion QC.  I wish them success.  I’ve known about what they were doing in part because Drew Potter, my friend and colleague in UT Austin’s physics department, took a one-year leave from UT to contribute to their effort.</p>



<p>Here I wanted to comment about one detail in Honeywell’s announcement: namely, the huge emphasis on “quantum volume” as the central metric for judging quantum computing progress, and the basis for calling their own planned device the “most powerful.”  One journalist asked me to explain why quantum volume is such an important measure.  I had to give her an honest answer: I don’t know whether it is.</p>



<p>Quantum volume was invented a few years ago by a group at IBM.  According to one of <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1811.12926.pdf">their papers</a>, it can be defined roughly as 2<sup>k</sup>, where k is the largest number such that you can run a k-qubit random quantum circuit, with depth k and with any-to-any connectivity, and have at least (say) 2/3 probability of measuring an answer that passes some statistical test.  (In the paper, they use what Lijie Chen and I named <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.05903">Heavy Output Generation</a>, though Google’s Linear Cross-Entropy Benchmark is similar.)</p>



<p>I don’t know why IBM takes the “volume” to be 2<sup>k</sup> rather than k itself.  Leaving that aside, though, the idea was to invent a single “goodness measure” for quantum computers that can’t be gamed <em>either</em> by building a huge number of qubits that don’t maintain nearly enough coherence (what one might call “the D-Wave approach”), <em>or</em> by building just one perfect qubit, <em>or</em> by building qubits that behave well in isolation but don’t interact easily.  Note that the any-to-any connectivity requirement makes things harder for architectures with nearest-neighbor interactions only, like the 2D superconducting chips being built by Google, Rigetti, or IBM itself.</p>



<p>You know the notion of a researcher’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H-index">h-index</a>—defined as the largest h such that she’s published h papers that garnered h citations each?  Quantum volume is basically an h-index for quantum computers.  It’s an attempt to take several different yardsticks of experimental progress, none terribly useful in isolation, and combine them into one “consumer index.”</p>



<p>Certainly I sympathize with the goal of broadening people’s focus beyond the “but how many qubits does it have?” question—since the answer to that question is meaningless without further information about what the qubits can <em>do</em>.  From that standpoint, quantum volume seems like a clear step in the right direction.</p>



<p>Alas, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodhart%27s_law">Goodhart’s Law</a> states that “as soon as a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure.”  That happened years ago with the h-index, which now regularly pollutes academic hiring and promotion decisions, to the point where <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.09496">its inventor expressed regrets</a>.  Quantum volume is now looking to me like another example of Goodhart’s Law at work.</p>



<p>The position of Honeywell’s PR seems to be that, if they can build a device that can apply 6 layers of gates to 6 qubits, with full connectivity and good fidelity, that will then count as “the world’s most powerful quantum computer,” since it will have the largest volume.  One problem here is that such a device could be simulated by maintaining a vector of only 2<sup>6</sup>=64 amplitudes.  This is nowhere near quantum supremacy (i.e., beating classical computers at some well-defined task), which is a necessary though not sufficient condition for doing anything useful.</p>



<p>Think of a university that achieves an average faculty-to-student ratio of infinity by holding one class with zero students.  It gets the “best score” only by exploiting an obvious defect in the scoring system.</p>



<p>So what’s the alternative?  The policy <em>I</em> prefer is simply to tell the world all your system specs, as clearly as you can, with no attempts made to bury the lede.  How many qubits do you have?  With what coherence times?  With what connectivity?  What are the 1- and 2-qubit gate fidelities?  What depth of circuit can you do?  What resources do the standard classical algorithms need to simulate your system?  Most importantly: what’s the main drawback of your system, the spec that’s the <em>worst</em>, the one you most need to improve?  What prevents you from having a scalable quantum computer right now?  And are you going to tell me, or will you make me scour Appendix III.B in your paper, or worse yet, ask one of your competitors?</p>



<p>I confess that the answers to the above questions are hard to summarize in a single number (unless you, like, concatenated binary encodings of them or something).  But they <em>can</em> be ineffably combined, to produce a progress metric that one of my postdocs suggested calling “quantum scottness,” and which roughly equals the number of expressions of wide-eyed surprise minus the number of groans.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-05T21:36:59Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-05T21:36:59Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T17:22:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-940496487994761300</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/940496487994761300/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/a-new-college-of-computing-at-illinois.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/940496487994761300" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/940496487994761300" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/03/a-new-college-of-computing-at-illinois.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A New College of Computing at Illinois Tech</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;">
<a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-4o0elQGFp-c/XmAhjkpOpKI/AAAAAAABxio/I6qGUp1ot6UA8rJtL2GLvRDcZU3YEZhaQCLcBGAsYHQ/s1600/IllinoisTech_MiesCampus.jpg" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"><img border="0" height="266" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-4o0elQGFp-c/XmAhjkpOpKI/AAAAAAABxio/I6qGUp1ot6UA8rJtL2GLvRDcZU3YEZhaQCLcBGAsYHQ/s400/IllinoisTech_MiesCampus.jpg" width="400"/></a></div>
<br/>
In 1890, Chicago South Side pastor Frank Gunsaulus gave a sermon where he said that with a million dollars he could build a school where students of all backgrounds could prepare for meaningful roles in a changing industrial society. One of the congregants, Philip Armour, came up to him after the service and told Gunsaulus that "if you give me five years of your time, I will give you the money." Thus was born the Armour Institute of Technology, the forerunner of the Illinois Institute of Technology.<br/>
<br/>
Today Illinois Tech enters a new chapter, <a href="https://www.iit.edu/news/illinois-tech-creates-college-computing-fuel-chicagos-tech-rise">announcing a College of Computing</a>, and I am honored to have been asked to serve as its inaugural dean. The college will take on a horizontal mission, to infuse computation and data science thinking throughout the curriculum in every discipline, while understanding the power, limitations and social implications of the technologies they create. We will significantly grow computing to produce the talent needed for a growing Chicago tech community. The college will develop an agile curriculum to continually reevaluate our offerings as computing technology continues to advance, and develop education as a life-long process where our alumni can always count on Illinois Tech to continually reskill to advance their careers.<br/>
<br/>
We will do it all by keeping the core principle of the original "million-dollar sermon," as important as ever, to prepare students of all backgrounds for meaningful roles in a changing technological society.<br/>
<div>
<br/></div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-05T14:35:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-05T14:35:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T07:58:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=395</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2020/03/04/tcs-talk-wednesday-march-11-thomas-steinke-ibm-research-almaden/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, March 11 — Thomas Steinke, IBM Research Almaden</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, March 11th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 18:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). Thomas Steinke from IBM Research Almaden will speak about “Reasoning About Generalization via Conditional Mutual Information” (abstract below). Please make sure you reserve a spot for your group […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, March 11th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 18:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). <strong>Thomas Steinke</strong> from IBM Research Almaden will speak about “<em>Reasoning About Generalization via Conditional Mutual Information</em>” (abstract below).</p>
<p>Please make sure you reserve a spot for your group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk/live-seat-reservation">the online form</a>. In view of the recent travel restrictions and coronavirus precautions, in particular, do not hesitate to reserve a seat even for a group <i class="moz-txt-slash">of size one</i>: there should be enough room for everyone, so don’t be shy!</p>
<p>As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/">the website</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Abstract: We provide an information-theoretic framework for studying the generalization properties of machine learning algorithms. Our framework ties together existing approaches, including uniform convergence bounds and recent methods for adaptive data analysis. Specifically, we use Conditional Mutual Information (CMI) to quantify how well the input (i.e., the training data) can be recognized given the output (i.e., the trained model) of the learning algorithm. We show that bounds on CMI can be obtained from VC dimension, compression schemes, differential privacy, and other methods. We then show that bounded CMI implies various forms of generalization.</p>
<p>Based on joint work with Lydia Zakynthinou.</p></blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-05T01:16:38Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-05T01:16:38Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:21:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4643</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4643" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4643#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4643" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">A coronavirus poem</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">These next few months, every time I stop myself from touching my face by force of will, Let me remind myself that the same willpower is available to diet, to exercise, to throw myself into a project, to keep calm amid screaming, to introduce myself to strangers, to decrease the fraction of my life spent […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>These next few months, every time I stop myself from touching my face by force of will,</p>



<p>Let me remind myself that the same willpower is available to diet, to exercise, to throw myself into a project, to keep calm amid screaming, to introduce myself to strangers, to decrease the fraction of my life spent getting upset that someone was mean to my ingroup on social media, or otherwise to better myself as a human specimen.</p>



<p>Yea, let all of these things be just as easy for me as it was not to touch my face.</p>



<p>Ah, but what if I forget, what if I do keep touching my face in the next few months?</p>



<p>In one plausible scenario, with at least ~0.1% probability and probably higher depending on my age, a cheap answer will be available to that question: namely, that I’ll no longer be around to ponder the implications.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-04T02:13:12Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-04T02:13:12Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Embarrassing Myself"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Self-Help"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T17:22:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4635</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4635" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4635#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4635" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Paperz</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Soon, all anyone will want to talk about is quarantines, food shortages, N95 masks, the suspension of universities and of scientific conferences. (As many others have pointed out, this last might actually be a boon to scientific productivity—as it was for a young Isaac Newton when Cambridge was closed for the bubonic plague, so Newton […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Soon, all anyone will want to talk about is quarantines, food shortages, N95 masks, the suspension of universities and of scientific conferences.  (As many others have pointed out, this last might actually be a boon to scientific productivity—as it was for a young Isaac Newton when Cambridge was closed for the bubonic plague, so Newton went home and invented calculus and mechanics.)</p>



<p>Anyway, before that all happens, I figured I’d get in a last post about quantum information and complexity theory progress.</p>



<p>Hsin-Yuan Huang, Richard Kueng, and John Preskill have a nice preprint entitled <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.08953">Predicting Many Properties of a Quantum System from Very Few Measurements</a>.  In it they take <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.01053">shadow tomography</a>, which I proposed a couple years ago, and try to bring it closer to practicality on near-term devices, by restricting to the special case of non-adaptive, one-shot measurements, on separate copies of the state ρ that you’re trying to learn about.  They show that this is possible using a number of copies that depends logarithmically on the number of properties you’re trying to learn (the optimal dependence), not at all on the Hilbert space dimension, and linearly on a new “shadow norm” quantity that they introduce.</p>



<p>Rahul Ilango, Bruno Loff, and Igor Oliveira announced the pretty spectacular-sounding result that the <a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/021/">Minimum Circuit Size Problem (MCSP) is NP-complete for multi-output functions</a>—that is, for Boolean functions f with not only many input bits but many outputs.  Given the 2<sup>n</sup>-sized truth table of a Boolean function f:{0,1}<sup>n</sup>→{0,1}, the original MCSP simply asks for the size of the smallest Boolean circuit that computes f.  This problem was studied in the USSR as early as the 1950s; whether it’s NP-complete has stood for decades as one of the big open problems of complexity theory.  We’ve known that if you could quickly solve MCSP then you could also invert any one-way function, but we’ve also known technical barriers to going beyond that to a flat-out NP-hardness result, at least via known routes.  Before seeing this paper, I’d never thought about whether MCSP for many-output functions might somehow be easier to classify, but apparently it is!</p>



<p>Hamoon Mousavi, Seyed Nezhadi, and Henry Yuen have now taken the MIP*=RE breakthrough even a tiny step further, by showing that <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.10490">“zero-gap MIP*”</a> (that is, quantum multi-prover interactive proofs with an arbitrarily small gap between the completeness and soundness probabilities) takes you <strong>even beyond the halting problem</strong> (i.e., beyond Recursively Enumerable or RE), and up to the second level of the arithmetical hierarchy (i.e., to the halting problem for Turing machines with oracles for the original halting problem).  This answers a question that someone asked <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4512#comment-1829033">in the comments section of this blog</a>.</p>



<p>Several people asked me for comment on the paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.07730">What limits the simulation of quantum computers?</a>, by Yiqing Zhou, Miles Stoudenmire, and Xavier Waintal.  In particular, does this paper refute or weaken Google’s quantum supremacy claim, as the paper does <em>not</em> claim to do (but, rather coyly, also does not claim <em>not</em> to do)?  Short answer: No, it doesn’t, or not now anyway.</p>



<p>Longer, more technical answer: The quoted simulation times, just a few minutes for quantum circuits with 54 qubits and depth 20, <em>assume Controlled-Z gates rather than iSWAP-like gates.</em> Using tensor network methods, the classical simulation cost with the former is roughly the square root of the simulation cost with the latter (~2<sup>k</sup> versus ~4<sup>k</sup> for some parameter k related to the depth).  As it happens, Google switched its hardware from Controlled-Z to iSWAP-like gates a couple years ago precisely because they realized this—I had a conversation about it with Sergio Boixo at the time.  Once this issue is accounted for, the quoted simulation times in the new paper seem to be roughly in line with what was previously reported by, e.g., Johnnie Gray and Google itself.</p>



<p>Oh yeah, I enjoyed <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09524">Quantum Homeopathy Works</a>.  Cool result, and the title is actually a pretty accurate description of the contents.</p>



<p>To end with a community announcement: as many of you might know, the American Physical Society’s March Meeting, which was planned for this week in Denver, was abruptly cancelled due to the coronavirus (leaving thousands of physicists out their flights and hotel rooms—many had even already arrived there).  However, my colleague Michael Biercuk kindly alerted me to a <a href="https://virtualmarchmeeting.com/">“virtual March Meeting”</a> that’s been set up online, with recorded talks and live webinars.  Even after the pandemic passes, is this a model that we should increasingly move to?  I wouldn’t have thought so ten or fifteen years ago, but today every schlep across the continent brings me a step closer to shouting “yes”…</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-03T18:03:12Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-03T18:03:12Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-03-10T17:22:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16757</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/03/03/dyson-as-a-mathematician/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dyson as a Mathematician</title>
    <summary>With a lemma from 1947 that might be useful today? Cropped from article on his letters Freeman Dyson passed away last February 28th, one day short of the leap day, February 29th. He was one of the great physicists, one of the great writers about science, and one of the great thinkers of all time. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>With a lemma from 1947 that might be useful today?</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/dysonyoung.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16759" height="220" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/03/dysonyoung.jpg?w=148&amp;h=220" width="148"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Cropped from <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/04/17/books/review/freeman-dyson-maker-of-patterns.html">article</a> on his letters</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Freeman Dyson passed away last February 28th, one day short of the leap day, February 29th. He was one of the great physicists, one of the great writers about science, and one of the great thinkers of all time. He is missed.</p>
<p>
Today we wish to discuss a tiny part of Dyson’s contributions to mathematics—and ask whether it has been developed further. </p>
<p><span id="more-16757"/></p>
<p>
Dyson did so much in so many areas of science that we will leave it to others to discuss it. We covered a puzzle of his years ago <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2014/09/09/a-challenge-from-dyson/">here</a>. He famously showed that quantum electrodynamics (QED) is a consistent theory—in particular showing that different theories connecting quantum mechanics and special relativity were the same. He published many interesting books about science in general. He speculated about aliens, about space travel, and much more.</p>
<p>
Our focus is on a beautiful result of his proved in 1947. A result about rational numbers. Nothing grandiose, nothing about infinite visions, nothing about worlds that we cannot easily imagine. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Approximations To Numbers </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
For over 2000 years we have known that <img alt="{\sqrt{2}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7B2%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{2}}"/> is not expressible as a rational fraction. This is sometimes credited to Hippasus of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hippasus">Metapontum</a>. The obvious question, at least to math types, is how close can we make it to a rational number? The answer is interesting, with many consequences. And includes some top mathematicians such as Johann Dirichlet, Joseph Liouville, Axel Thue, Carl Siegel, Dyson, and Klaus Roth.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <b>Hippasus:</b> The value <img alt="{\sqrt{2}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7B2%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{2}}"/> is not rational.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <b>Folklore:</b> The value <img alt="{\sqrt{2}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7B2%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{2}}"/> like all algebraic numbers <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> can be algorithmically approximated by rationals. Note that <img alt="{\sqrt{2}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7B2%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{2}}"/> is algebraic since it satisfies the equation 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x^{2} - 2 = 0, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x%5E%7B2%7D+-+2+%3D+0%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  x^{2} - 2 = 0, "/></p>
<p>with <img alt="{D=2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BD%3D2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{D=2}"/>. The number <img alt="{D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BD%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{D}"/> is called the <em>degree</em> of <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/>.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <b>Dirichlet:</b> The value <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> can be well approximated. That is 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{1}{q^{2}}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cleft%7C+%5Calpha+-+%5Cfrac%7Bp%7D%7Bq%7D+%5Cright%7C+%5Cle+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Bq%5E%7B2%7D%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{1}{q^{2}}, "/></p>
<p>can be done for infinitely many <img alt="{p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p}"/> and <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/>.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <b>Liouville:</b> The value <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> cannot be too well approximated. That is 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{c}{q^{v}}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cleft%7C+%5Calpha+-+%5Cfrac%7Bp%7D%7Bq%7D+%5Cright%7C+%5Cle+%5Cfrac%7Bc%7D%7Bq%5E%7Bv%7D%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{c}{q^{v}}, "/></p>
<p>cannot be done for infinitely many <img alt="{p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p}"/> and <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> and some constant <img alt="{c &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c &gt; 0}"/> provided <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> is larger than <img alt="{D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BD%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{D}"/>.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <b>Thue:</b> The value <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> cannot be too well approximated. That is 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{c}{q^{v}}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cleft%7C+%5Calpha+-+%5Cfrac%7Bp%7D%7Bq%7D+%5Cright%7C+%5Cle+%5Cfrac%7Bc%7D%7Bq%5E%7Bv%7D%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{c}{q^{v}}, "/></p>
<p>cannot be done for infinitely many <img alt="{p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p}"/> and <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> and some constant <img alt="{c &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c &gt; 0}"/> provided <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> is larger than <img alt="{D/2+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BD%2F2%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{D/2+1}"/>.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <b>Siegel:</b> The value <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> cannot be too well approximated. That is 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{c}{q^{v}}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cleft%7C+%5Calpha+-+%5Cfrac%7Bp%7D%7Bq%7D+%5Cright%7C+%5Cle+%5Cfrac%7Bc%7D%7Bq%5E%7Bv%7D%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{c}{q^{v}}, "/></p>
<p>cannot be done for infinitely many <img alt="{p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p}"/> and <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> for some constant <img alt="{c&gt;0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%3E0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c&gt;0}"/> provided <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> is larger than <img alt="{2\sqrt{D}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5Csqrt%7BD%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2\sqrt{D}}"/>.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <b>Dyson:</b> The value <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> cannot be too well approximated. That is 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{c}{q^{v}}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cleft%7C+%5Calpha+-+%5Cfrac%7Bp%7D%7Bq%7D+%5Cright%7C+%5Cle+%5Cfrac%7Bc%7D%7Bq%5E%7Bv%7D%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{c}{q^{v}}, "/></p>
<p>cannot be done for infinitely many <img alt="{p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p}"/> and <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> for some constant <img alt="{c &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c &gt; 0}"/> provided <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> is larger than <img alt="{\sqrt{2D}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7B2D%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{2D}}"/>.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <b>Roth:</b> The value <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> cannot be too well approximated. That is 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{1}{q^{v}}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cleft%7C+%5Calpha+-+%5Cfrac%7Bp%7D%7Bq%7D+%5Cright%7C+%5Cle+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Bq%5E%7Bv%7D%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \left| \alpha - \frac{p}{q} \right| \le \frac{1}{q^{v}}, "/></p>
<p>cannot be done for infinitely many <img alt="{p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p}"/> and <img alt="{q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q}"/> provided <img alt="{D \geq 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BD+%5Cgeq+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{D \geq 2}"/> and <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> is larger than <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/>.</p>
<p>
Note that the last result is best possible in the sense that Dirichlet achieved <img alt="{v = D = 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv+%3D+D+%3D+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v = D = 2}"/>, although slightly stronger statements than Roth can be made by using logarithms.</p>
<p>
To illustrate these formulas, Liouville proved that the following number is transcendental:</p>
<p/><p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  \sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{1}{10^{k!}} &amp;=&amp; 0.110001000000000000000001000000000000000000000000000000000000\\  &amp;&amp; 00000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000001\dots \end{array} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Brcl%7D++%5Csum_%7Bk%3D1%7D%5E%7B%5Cinfty%7D+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B10%5E%7Bk%21%7D%7D+%26%3D%26+0.110001000000000000000001000000000000000000000000000000000000%5C%5C+%09%26%26+00000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000001%5Cdots+%5Cend%7Barray%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}  \sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \frac{1}{10^{k!}} &amp;=&amp; 0.110001000000000000000001000000000000000000000000000000000000\\  &amp;&amp; 00000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000001\dots \end{array} "/></p>
<p>
Note that the exponent in Liouville’s number grows as <img alt="{k! \approx \exp(k\log k)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%21+%5Capprox+%5Cexp%28k%5Clog+k%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k! \approx \exp(k\log k)}"/>. The later formulas improve this to simply exponential in <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k}"/>. For instance, </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \sum_{k=1}^{\infty}\frac{1}{10^{2^k}} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Csum_%7Bk%3D1%7D%5E%7B%5Cinfty%7D%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B10%5E%7B2%5Ek%7D%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \sum_{k=1}^{\infty}\frac{1}{10^{2^k}} "/></p>
<p>is transcendental. We’ll leave it to our readers to figure out which formula gives this consequence and will give the historical answer at the end. </p>
<p/><h2> A Key Lemma </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
What we wish to highlight from Dyson’s 1947 <a href="https://projecteuclid.org/euclid.acta/1485888462">paper</a> is the main lemma for his proof. He called it the key new idea in his paper and also said it might have independent interest. We agree, and we abstract some of its statement into the following definitions. </p>
<p>
Suppose we have a polynomial <img alt="{f(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y)}"/>. Call a point <img alt="{(x_0,y_0)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x_0%2Cy_0%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(x_0,y_0)}"/> a <em>zero of order <img alt="{(p,q)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28p%2Cq%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(p,q)}"/></em> if <img alt="{0 \leq m \leq p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0+%5Cleq+m+%5Cleq+p%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0 \leq m \leq p}"/> and <img alt="{0 \leq n \leq q}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0+%5Cleq+n+%5Cleq+q%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0 \leq n \leq q}"/> implies </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \frac{\partial^m}{\partial x} \frac{\partial^n}{\partial y}f(x = x_0, y = y_0) = 0. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%5Em%7D%7B%5Cpartial+x%7D+%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%5En%7D%7B%5Cpartial+y%7Df%28x+%3D+x_0%2C+y+%3D+y_0%29+%3D+0.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \frac{\partial^m}{\partial x} \frac{\partial^n}{\partial y}f(x = x_0, y = y_0) = 0. "/></p>
<p>Since this includes the case <img alt="{m = n = 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bm+%3D+n+%3D+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{m = n = 0}"/>, the point <img alt="{(x_0,y_0)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x_0%2Cy_0%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(x_0,y_0)}"/> must be a zero of <img alt="{f(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y)}"/> as well as of all the partial derivatives. For example, when </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  f(x,y) = xy - x - y + 1, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++f%28x%2Cy%29+%3D+xy+-+x+-+y+%2B+1%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  f(x,y) = xy - x - y + 1, "/></p>
<p>the point <img alt="{(1,1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%281%2C1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(1,1)}"/> is a zero of order <img alt="{(1,0)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%281%2C0%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(1,0)}"/> and of order <img alt="{(0,1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%280%2C1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(0,1)}"/> but not of order <img alt="{(1,1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%281%2C1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(1,1)}"/>. The diagonal-step nature of this example plays into the next definition. We follow Dyson in numbering from zero.</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Definition 1</b> <em> A “<img alt="{\lambda}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clambda%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\lambda}"/>-staircase” for <img alt="{f(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y)}"/> is given by points <img alt="{(x_0,y_0),\dots,(x_r,y_r)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x_0%2Cy_0%29%2C%5Cdots%2C%28x_r%2Cy_r%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(x_0,y_0),\dots,(x_r,y_r)}"/> and nonnegative reals <img alt="{t_0,\dots,t_r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_0%2C%5Cdots%2Ct_r%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_0,\dots,t_r}"/> such that for all <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/> and <img alt="{n \leq t_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn+%5Cleq+t_i%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n \leq t_i}"/>, </em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  (x_i,y_i) \quad\text{is a zero of order} \quad (\lfloor\lambda(t_i - n)\rfloor, n). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%28x_i%2Cy_i%29+%5Cquad%5Ctext%7Bis+a+zero+of+order%7D+%5Cquad+%28%5Clfloor%5Clambda%28t_i+-+n%29%5Crfloor%2C+n%29.+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  (x_i,y_i) \quad\text{is a zero of order} \quad (\lfloor\lambda(t_i - n)\rfloor, n). "/></p>
</em><p><em>It is understood that the <img alt="{x_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_i%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x_i}"/> are distinct and the <img alt="{y_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By_i%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y_i}"/> are distinct, but they need not be distinct from each other. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The parameter <img alt="{\lambda}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clambda%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\lambda}"/> is the steepness of the staircase. The idea is to make the staircase quite steep by taking both <img alt="{\lambda}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clambda%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\lambda}"/> and the degree <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> of <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> to be large. This is controlled by a parameter <img alt="{\delta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdelta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\delta}"/> that is inverse to <img alt="{\lambda}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clambda%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\lambda}"/> and chosen to meet the hypotheses of the key lemma:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Lemma 2</b> <em><a name="key"/> Suppose <img alt="{(x_0,y_0),\dots,(x_r,y_r)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x_0%2Cy_0%29%2C%5Cdots%2C%28x_r%2Cy_r%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(x_0,y_0),\dots,(x_r,y_r)}"/> and <img alt="{t_0,\dots,t_r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_0%2C%5Cdots%2Ct_r%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_0,\dots,t_r}"/> constitute a <img alt="{\lambda}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clambda%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\lambda}"/>-staircase for a bivariate polynomial <img alt="{f(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y)}"/> of degree <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> in <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> and degree <img alt="{s}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s}"/> in <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/>, where for each <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{i}"/>, <img alt="{0 \leq i \leq r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0+%5Cleq+i+%5Cleq+r%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0 \leq i \leq r}"/>, </em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \lfloor t_i \rfloor \leq \min\{s, \frac{u+1}{\lambda} - 1\}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Clfloor+t_i+%5Crfloor+%5Cleq+%5Cmin%5C%7Bs%2C+%5Cfrac%7Bu%2B1%7D%7B%5Clambda%7D+-+1%5C%7D.+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \lfloor t_i \rfloor \leq \min\{s, \frac{u+1}{\lambda} - 1\}. "/></p>
<p>Suppose <img alt="{\delta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdelta%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\delta}"/> is a positive real number such that: </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \lambda &gt; \frac{2}{\delta}, \quad \text{and}\quad \delta \geq \frac{2s}{r(u+1)}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Clambda+%3E+%5Cfrac%7B2%7D%7B%5Cdelta%7D%2C+%5Cquad+%5Ctext%7Band%7D%5Cquad+%5Cdelta+%5Cgeq+%5Cfrac%7B2s%7D%7Br%28u%2B1%29%7D.+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \lambda &gt; \frac{2}{\delta}, \quad \text{and}\quad \delta \geq \frac{2s}{r(u+1)}. "/></p>
<p>Then <a name="bound"/></p><a name="bound">
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \lambda \sum_{i=0}^r (1 + \lfloor t_i \rfloor)(t_i - \frac{1}{2}\lfloor t_i \rfloor) \leq (s+1)(u+1)(1 + \frac{1}{2}r(r+1)\delta). \ \ \ \ \ (1)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Clambda+%5Csum_%7Bi%3D0%7D%5Er+%281+%2B+%5Clfloor+t_i+%5Crfloor%29%28t_i+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%5Clfloor+t_i+%5Crfloor%29+%5Cleq+%28s%2B1%29%28u%2B1%29%281+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7Dr%28r%2B1%29%5Cdelta%29.+%5C+%5C+%5C+%5C+%5C+%281%29&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \lambda \sum_{i=0}^r (1 + \lfloor t_i \rfloor)(t_i - \frac{1}{2}\lfloor t_i \rfloor) \leq (s+1)(u+1)(1 + \frac{1}{2}r(r+1)\delta). \ \ \ \ \ (1)"/></p>
</a></em><p><em><a name="bound"/> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Interpretation and Application </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Dyson supplied the following interpretation in his paper. The left-hand side of (<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/#bound">1</a>) approximately counts the number of zeroes in the staircase—approximately because <img alt="{\lambda}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clambda%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\lambda}"/> is left as a real number. We want a good upper bound on this number</p>
<p>
A polynomial <img alt="{f(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y)}"/> of degree <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> in <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> and <img alt="{s}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s}"/> in <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/> may have up to <img alt="{(u+1)(s+1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28u%2B1%29%28s%2B1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(u+1)(s+1)}"/> non-zero coefficieints. Thus <img alt="{(u+1)(s+1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28u%2B1%29%28s%2B1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(u+1)(s+1)}"/> is intuitively the maximum number of zeroes that could be arranged “on purpose” by the choice of <img alt="{f}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f}"/>. </p>
<p>
We want to minimize the number af additional zeroes that could exist. Lemma <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/#key">2</a> says that this is limited by the factor <img alt="{(1 + \frac{1}{2}r(r+1)\delta)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%281+%2B+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7Dr%28r%2B1%29%5Cdelta%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(1 + \frac{1}{2}r(r+1)\delta)}"/>. We want to make this factor approach <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/>. We can do so by making <img alt="{\delta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdelta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\delta}"/> arbitrarily small. By the condition <img alt="{\lambda &gt; \frac{2}{\delta}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clambda+%3E+%5Cfrac%7B2%7D%7B%5Cdelta%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\lambda &gt; \frac{2}{\delta}}"/> this entails choosing <img alt="{\lambda}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clambda%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\lambda}"/> large. The other requirement to chooise <img alt="{\delta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdelta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\delta}"/> is that it must majorize </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \frac{2s}{r(u+1)}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cfrac%7B2s%7D%7Br%28u%2B1%29%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \frac{2s}{r(u+1)}. "/></p>
<p>We need <img alt="{\delta r^2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdelta+r%5E2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\delta r^2}"/> to be small yet bigger than </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \frac{2sr}{u+1}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cfrac%7B2sr%7D%7Bu%2B1%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \frac{2sr}{u+1}. "/></p>
<p>This means making <img alt="{\frac{u}{s} &gt; 2r - \frac{1}{s}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bu%7D%7Bs%7D+%3E+2r+-+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Bs%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\frac{u}{s} &gt; 2r - \frac{1}{s}}"/>. For whatever number <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> of points we are concerned with, we can meet this by making the degree <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> in <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> be larger than the degree <img alt="{s}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s}"/> in <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/> by the factor <img alt="{2r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2r%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2r}"/>. That is all we need to do for <img alt="{\delta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdelta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\delta}"/> and <img alt="{\lambda}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clambda%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\lambda}"/> to exist that will allow us to apply the lemma. </p>
<p>
Thus the upshot is that suitably “lopsided” polynomials, together with a connected region of their partial derivatives, cannot have too many more than the prescribed number of zeroes, counting multiplicity of the orders of the zeroes. The proof of the lemma works by successive applications of reasoning about determinants and linear independence of polynomials that serve as components of <img alt="{f(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y)}"/>. It is fairly long-winded and ends with some painstaking estimates. </p>
<p>
The application supposes for sake of contradiction that there are infinitely many fractions <img alt="{\frac{p}{q}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bp%7D%7Bq%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\frac{p}{q}}"/> giving closer approximations to <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> than the theorem statement allows. It suffices to consider the case where <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> is an algebraic integer—that is, a root of a univariate polynomial <img alt="{g(z)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bg%28z%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{g(z)}"/> with integer coefficients. The supposition yields candidate polynomials <img alt="{f(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y)}"/> as differences of two polynomials, one derived from <img alt="{g}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bg%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{g}"/> and the other from the closely approximating fractions. The <img alt="{f(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y)}"/> have both a large staircase of zeroes and a bounded space of possible coefficients, which imposes constraints on the degrees in <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> and <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/>. These elements can be manipulated, using the approximating fractions on one hand and the fact of <img alt="{g}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bg%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{g}"/> (and hence its degree) being fixed on the other hand, to create the lopsided form of <img alt="{f(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{f(x,y)}"/> in which the hypotheses of lemma <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/#key">2</a> take effect. The lemma then cranks out a contradiction.</p>
<p>
At the end of his proof, Dyson deftly explains how taking <img alt="{t = 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt+%3D+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t = 1}"/>, where <img alt="{t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t}"/> results from the process that selects the sequence <img alt="{t_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_i}"/> for the lemma, yields Siegel’s theorem. Thus his framework affords an extra <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2011/08/05/give-me-a-lever/">lever</a> for manipulating ratios, in his case the ratio <img alt="{\frac{s}{t}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bs%7D%7Bt%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\frac{s}{t}}"/>. Tending the ratio to <img alt="{\sqrt{r/2}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7Br%2F2%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{r/2}}"/> rather than to <img alt="{s}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s}"/> produces his theorem.</p>
<p>
Our point of interest is whether Dyson’s setup can be used to attack other questions about polynomials in complexity theory. We have not yet formed an understanding of how specific it is to the approximation application. Perhaps for complexity we would want to generalize it from polynomials in 2 to <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> variables. There could be some relation to the <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/>-variable techniques used for integer multiplication as we covered <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/">here</a>, but again we’re just at the point of asking. Dyson ends his paper with the opinion that</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “such an investigation … would not be in any way a hopeless undertaking.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Have there been useful extensions of Dyson’s lemma, as opposed to improvements by Roth and others to his approximation bounds? Has Dyson’s “non-hopeless investigation” been brought to fruition? What other applications would it have? What are the closest techniques that have been used in complexity theory?</p>
<p>
The search for proving transcendental numbers has gone in other directions. These are represented in a survey <a href="http://www.its.caltech.edu/~matilde/NumberTheoryFormalLanguages.pdf">paper</a> by Jeffrey Shallit, which grew into the <a href="https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/~shallit/asas.html">book</a> <em>Automatic Sequences</em> with Jean-Paul Allouche. To answer our reader question above, in the book they trace the transcendence of <img alt="{\sum_k 10^{-2^k}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csum_k+10%5E%7B-2%5Ek%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sum_k 10^{-2^k}}"/> to a 1916 <a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/tran/1916-017-04/S0002-9947-1916-1501054-4/S0002-9947-1916-1501054-4.pdf">paper</a> by Aubrey Kempner which uses a different technique.</p>
<p>[Edit: Fixed Roth bound on degree.]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-03T17:33:10Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-03T17:33:10Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="trick"/>
    <category term="algebraic numbers"/>
    <category term="approximation"/>
    <category term="Freeman Dyson"/>
    <category term="in memoriam"/>
    <category term="polynomials"/>
    <category term="transcendental"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=736</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2020/03/02/conferences-in-an-era-of-expensive-carbon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Conferences in an Era of Expensive Carbon</title>
    <summary>At least there’s that: I live in a world where some people care about it and publish their viewpoint in the latest CACM. Read it on your next flight. Some interesting things that won’t shock anyone: There’s a nice picture with different environmental costs based on the location of the conference. It also shows that […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>At least there’s that: I live in a world where some people care about it and publish their <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2020/3/243024-conferences-in-an-era-of-expensive-carbon/abstract">viewpoint in the latest CACM</a>. Read it on your next flight.  Some interesting things that won’t shock anyone:</p>



<p>There’s a nice picture with different environmental costs based on the location of the conference.  It also shows that people like to go to nearby conferences, one of the reasons why “The impulse to ignore the issue is entirely understandable.”  For more perspective see some of our earlier posts for example <a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2020/02/18/working-remotely-will-be-the-most-significant-transformation-since-agriculture/">here</a> and <a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2020/01/01/publish-and-perish/">here</a>.</p>



<p>The viewpoint also reports on a recent switch from in-person to online program committees for flagship conferences (POPL and ICFP), following a recent trend.  For starters we continue to suggest that <a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2017/07/28/stocfocs-pc-meetings-does-nature-of-decisions-justify-cost/">STOC and FOCS do the same, because the nature of decisions does not justify the cost.</a> The latter post also includes hard numbers on the added value of a physical meeting (with respect to accept/reject decisions — of course one can value at infinity meeting in person luminaries in your field, but that can be done in other ways and should not be tied to PC meetings).</p>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-03-02T15:44:29Z</updated>
    <published>2020-03-02T15:44:29Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="Utopia"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-03-11T18:21:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
