<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-08-26T05:21:43Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08938</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08938" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Mixed Linear Layouts: Complexity, Heuristics, and Experiments</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Philipp de Col, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Klute:Fabian.html">Fabian Klute</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/N=ouml=llenburg:Martin.html">Martin Nöllenburg</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08938">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A $k$-page linear graph layout of a graph $G = (V,E)$ draws all vertices
along a line $\ell$ and each edge in one of $k$ disjoint halfplanes called
pages, which are bounded by $\ell$. We consider two types of pages. In a stack
page no two edges should cross and in a queue page no edge should be nested by
another edge. A crossing (nesting) in a stack (queue) page is called a
conflict. The algorithmic problem is twofold and requires to compute (i) a
vertex ordering and (ii) a page assignment of the edges such that the resulting
layout is either conflict-free or conflict-minimal. While linear layouts with
only stack or only queue pages are well-studied, mixed $s$-stack $q$-queue
layouts for $s,q \ge 1$ have received less attention. We show NP-completeness
results on the recognition problem of certain mixed linear layouts and present
a new heuristic for minimizing conflicts. In a computational experiment for the
case $s, q = 1$ we show that the new heuristic is an improvement over previous
heuristics for linear layouts.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:23:42Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08911</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08911" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Parameterized Algorithms for Book Embedding Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bhore:Sujoy.html">Sujoy Bhore</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Ganian:Robert.html">Robert Ganian</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Montecchiani:Fabrizio.html">Fabrizio Montecchiani</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/N=ouml=llenburg:Martin.html">Martin Nöllenburg</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08911">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A k-page book embedding of a graph G draws the vertices of G on a line and
the edges on k half-planes (called pages) bounded by this line, such that no
two edges on the same page cross. We study the problem of determining whether G
admits a k-page book embedding both when the linear order of the vertices is
fixed, called Fixed-Order Book Thickness, or not fixed, called Book Thickness.
Both problems are known to be NP-complete in general. We show that Fixed-Order
Book Thickness and Book Thickness are fixed-parameter tractable parameterized
by the vertex cover number of the graph and that Fixed-Order Book Thickness is
fixed-parameter tractable parameterized by the pathwidth of the vertex order.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:25:04Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08905</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08905" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Maximizing Ink in Partial Edge Drawings of k-plane Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hummel:Matthias.html">Matthias Hummel</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Klute:Fabian.html">Fabian Klute</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nickel:Soeren.html">Soeren Nickel</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/N=ouml=llenburg:Martin.html">Martin Nöllenburg</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08905">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Partial edge drawing (PED) is a drawing style for non-planar graphs, in which
edges are drawn only partially as pairs of opposing stubs on the respective
end-vertices. In a PED, by erasing the central parts of edges, all edge
crossings and the resulting visual clutter are hidden in the undrawn parts of
the edges. In symmetric partial edge drawings (SPEDs), the two stubs of each
edge are required to have the same length. It is known that maximizing the ink
(or the total stub length) when transforming a straight-line graph drawing with
crossings into a SPED is tractable for 2-plane input drawings, but NP-hard for
unrestricted inputs. We show that the problem remains NP-hard even for 3-plane
input drawings and establish NP-hardness of ink maximization for PEDs of
4-plane graphs. Yet, for k-plane input drawings whose edge intersection graph
forms a collection of trees or, more generally, whose intersection graph has
bounded treewidth, we present efficient algorithms for computing maximum-ink
PEDs and SPEDs. We implemented the treewidth-based algorithms and show a brief
experimental evaluation.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08882</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08882" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Simultaneous Representation of Proper and Unit Interval Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rutter:Ignaz.html">Ignaz Rutter</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Strash:Darren.html">Darren Strash</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Stumpf:Peter.html">Peter Stumpf</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vollmer:Michael.html">Michael Vollmer</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08882">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In a confluence of combinatorics and geometry, simultaneous representations
provide a way to realize combinatorial objects that share common structure. A
standard case in the study of simultaneous representations is the sunflower
case where all objects share the same common structure. While the recognition
problem for general simultaneous interval graphs -- the simultaneous version of
arguably one of the most well-studied graph classes -- is NP-complete, the
complexity of the sunflower case for three or more simultaneous interval graphs
is currently open. In this work we settle this question for proper interval
graphs. We give an algorithm to recognize simultaneous proper interval graphs
in linear time in the sunflower case where we allow any number of simultaneous
graphs. Simultaneous unit interval graphs are much more 'rigid' and therefore
have less freedom in their representation. We show they can be recognized in
time O(|V|*|E|) for any number of simultaneous graphs in the sunflower case
where G = (V, E) is the union of the simultaneous graphs. We further show that
both recognition problems are in general NP-complete if the number of
simultaneous graphs is not fixed. The restriction to the sunflower case is in
this sense necessary.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:22:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08881</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08881" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Complexity and Geometry of Sampling Connected Graph Partitions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Lorenzo Najt, Daryl DeFord, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Solomon:Justin.html">Justin Solomon</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08881">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we prove intractability results about sampling from the set of
partitions of a planar graph into connected components. Our proofs are
motivated by a technique introduced by Jerrum, Valiant, and Vazirani. Moreover,
we use gadgets inspired by their technique to provide families of graphs where
the "flip walk" Markov chain used in practice for this sampling task exhibits
exponentially slow mixing. Supporting our theoretical results we present some
empirical evidence demonstrating the slow mixing of the flip walk on grid
graphs and on real data. Inspired by connections to the statistical physics of
self-avoiding walks, we investigate the sensitivity of certain popular sampling
algorithms to the graph topology. Finally, we discuss a few cases where the
sampling problem is tractable. Applications to political redistricting have
recently brought increased attention to this problem, and we articulate open
questions about this application that are highlighted by our results.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:20:23Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08871</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08871" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Variants of the Segment Number of a Graph</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Okamoto:Yoshio.html">Yoshio Okamoto</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ravsky:Alexander.html">Alexander Ravsky</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wolff:Alexander.html">Alexander Wolff</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08871">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The \emph{segment number} of a planar graph is the smallest number of line
segments whose union represents a crossing-free straight-line drawing of the
given graph in the plane. The segment number is a measure for the visual
complexity of a drawing; it has been studied extensively.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we study three variants of the segment number: for planar
graphs, we consider crossing-free polyline drawings in 2D; for arbitrary
graphs, we consider crossing-free straight-line drawings in 3D and
straight-line drawings with crossings in 2D. We establish lower and upper
bounds on the new variants of the segment number, mostly for cubic graphs,
depending on the connectivity of the given graph. We also construct an infinite
family of planar graphs where the classical segment number is asymptotically
twice as large as each of the new variants of the segment number.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:36:19Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08857</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08857" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the edge-vertex ratio of maximal thrackles</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Oswin Aicholzer, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kleist:Linda.html">Linda Kleist</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Klemz:Boris.html">Boris Klemz</a>, Felix Schröder, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vogtenhuber:Birgit.html">Birgit Vogtenhuber</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08857">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A drawing of a graph in the plane is a thrackle if every pair of edges
intersects exactly once, either at a common vertex or at a proper crossing.
Conway's conjecture states that a thrackle has at most as many edges as
vertices. In this paper, we investigate the edge-vertex ratio of maximal
thrackles, that is, thrackles in which no edge between already existing
vertices can be inserted such that the resulting drawing remains a thrackle.
For maximal geometric and topological thrackles, we show that the edge-vertex
ratio can be arbitrarily small. When forbidding isolated vertices, the
edge-vertex ratio of maximal geometric thrackles can be arbitrarily close to
the natural lower bound of 1/2. For maximal topological thrackles without
isolated vertices, we present an infinite family with an edge-vertex ratio of
5/6.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:37:11Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08762</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08762" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Revisiting Consistent Hashing with Bounded Loads</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:John.html">John Chen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Coleman:Ben.html">Ben Coleman</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Shrivastava:Anshumali.html">Anshumali Shrivastava</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08762">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Dynamic load balancing lies at the heart of distributed caching. Here, the
goal is to assign objects (load) to servers (computing nodes) in a way that
provides load balancing while at the same time dynamically adjusts to the
addition or removal of servers. One essential requirement is that the
assignment time (or hashing time) should be independent of the number of
servers. Addition or removal of small servers should not require us to
recompute the complete assignment. A popular and widely adopted solution is the
two-decade-old Consistent Hashing (CH). Recently, an elegant extension was
provided to account for server bounds. In this paper, we identify that existing
methodologies for CH and its variants suffer from cascaded overflow, leading to
poor load balancing. This cascading effect leads to decreasing performance of
the hashing procedure with increasing load. To overcome the cascading effect,
we propose a simple solution to CH based on recent advances in fast minwise
hashing. We show, both theoretically and empirically, that our proposed
solution is significantly superior for load balancing and is optimal in many
senses.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:32:15Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08731</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08731" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Stronger counterexamples to the topological Tverberg conjecture</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Avvakumov:S=.html">S. Avvakumov</a>, R. Karasev, A. Skopenkov <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08731">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Denote by $\Delta_N$ the $N$-dimensional simplex. A map $f\colon
\Delta_N\to\mathbb R^d$ is an almost $r$-embedding if $f\sigma_1\cap\ldots\cap
f\sigma_r=\emptyset$ whenever $\sigma_1,\ldots,\sigma_r$ are pairwise disjoint
faces. A counterexample to the topological Tverberg conjecture asserts that if
$r$ is not a prime power and $d\ge2r+1$, then there is an almost $r$-embedding
$\Delta_{(d+1)(r-1)}\to\mathbb R^d$. We improve this by showing that if $r$ is
not a prime power and $N:=(d+1)r-r\Big\lceil\dfrac{d+2}{r+1}\Big\rceil-2$, then
there is an almost $r$-embedding $\Delta_N\to\mathbb R^d$. For the $r$-fold van
Kampen--Flores conjecture we also produce counterexamples which are stronger
than previously known. Our proof is based on generalizations of the
Mabillard--Wagner theorem on construction of almost $r$-embeddings from
equivariant maps, and of the \"Ozaydin theorem on existence of equivariant
maps.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:37:43Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08708</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08708" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The QuaSEFE Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Angelini:Patrizio.html">Patrizio Angelini</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/F=ouml=rster:Henry.html">Henry Förster</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hoffmann:Michael.html">Michael Hoffmann</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kaufmann:Michael.html">Michael Kaufmann</a>, Stephen Kobourov, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liotta:Giuseppe.html">Giuseppe Liotta</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Patrignani:Maurizio.html">Maurizio Patrignani</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08708">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We initiate the study of Simultaneous Graph Embedding with Fixed Edges in the
beyond planarity framework. In the QuaSEFE problem, we allow edge crossings, as
long as each graph individually is drawn quasiplanar, that is, no three edges
pairwise cross. We show that a triple consisting of two planar graphs and a
tree admit a QuaSEFE. This result also implies that a pair consisting of a
1-planar graph and a planar graph admits a QuaSEFE. We show several other
positive results for triples of planar graphs, in which certain structural
properties for their common subgraphs are fulfilled. For the case in which
simplicity is also required, we give a triple consisting of two quasiplanar
graphs and a star that does not admit a QuaSEFE. Moreover, in contrast to the
planar SEFE problem, we show that it is not always possible to obtain a QuaSEFE
for two matchings if the quasiplanar drawing of one matching is fixed.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:27:39Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08691</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08691" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On VR Spatial Query for Dual Entangled Worlds</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Shao-Heng Ko, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lin:Ying=Chun.html">Ying-Chun Lin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lai:Hsu=Chao.html">Hsu-Chao Lai</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lee:Wang=Chien.html">Wang-Chien Lee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yang:De=Nian.html">De-Nian Yang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08691">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>With the rapid advent of Virtual Reality (VR) technology and virtual tour
applications, there is a research need on spatial queries tailored for
simultaneous movements in both the physical and virtual worlds. Traditional
spatial queries, designed mainly for one world, do not consider the entangled
dual worlds in VR. In this paper, we first investigate the fundamental
shortest-path query in VR as the building block for spatial queries, aiming to
avoid hitting boundaries and obstacles in the physical environment by
leveraging Redirected Walking (RW) in Computer Graphics. Specifically, we first
formulate Dual-world Redirected-walking Obstacle-free Path (DROP) to find the
minimum-distance path in the virtual world, which is constrained by the RW cost
in the physical world to ensure immersive experience in VR. We prove DROP is
NP-hard and design a fully polynomial-time approximation scheme, Dual Entangled
World Navigation (DEWN), by finding Minimum Immersion Loss Range (MIL Range).
Afterward, we show that the existing spatial query algorithms and index
structures can leverage DEWN as a building block to support kNN and range
queries in the dual worlds of VR. Experimental results and a user study with
implementation in HTC VIVE manifest that DEWN outperforms the baselines with
smoother RW operations in various VR scenarios.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:32:40Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08623</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08623" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Exact inference under the perfect phylogeny model</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ray:Surjyendu.html">Surjyendu Ray</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jia:Bei.html">Bei Jia</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Safavi:Sam.html">Sam Safavi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Opijnen:Tim_van.html">Tim van Opijnen</a>, Ralph Isberg, Jason Rosch, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bento:Jos=eacute=.html">José Bento</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08623">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Motivation: Many inference tools use the Perfect Phylogeny Model (PPM) to
learn trees from noisy variant allele frequency (VAF) data. Learning in this
setting is hard, and existing tools use approximate or heuristic algorithms. An
algorithmic improvement is important to help disentangle the limitations of the
PPM's assumptions from the limitations in our capacity to learn under it.
Results: We make such improvement in the scenario, where the mutations that are
relevant for evolution can be clustered into a small number of groups, and the
trees to be reconstructed have a small number of nodes. We use a careful
combination of algorithms, software, and hardware, to develop EXACT: a tool
that can explore the space of all possible phylogenetic trees, and performs
exact inference under the PPM with noisy data. EXACT allows users to obtain not
just the most-likely tree for some input data, but exact statistics about the
distribution of trees that might explain the data. We show that EXACT
outperforms several existing tools for this same task. Availability:
https://github.com/surjray-repos/EXACT
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:24:33Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08551</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08551" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Clustered Hierarchical Entropy-Scaling Search of Astronomical and Biological Data</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Najib Ishaq, George Student, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Daniels:Noah_M=.html">Noah M. Daniels</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08551">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Both astronomy and biology are experiencing explosive growth of data,
resulting in a "big data" problem standing in the way of a "big data"
opportunity for discovery. One common task on such data sets is the problem of
approximate search, or $\rho-$nearest neighbors search. We present a
hierarchical search algorithm for such data sets that takes advantage of
particular geometric properties apparent in both astronomical and biological
data sets, namely the metric entropy and fractal dimensionality of the data. We
present CHESS (Clustered Hierarchical Entropy-Scaling Search), a
GPU-accelerated search tool with no loss in specificity or sensitivity,
demonstrating a $6.4\times$ speedup over linear search on the Sloan Digital Sky
Survey's APOGEE data set and a $3.97\times$ speedup on the GreenGenes 16S
metagenomic data set, as well as asymptotically fewer comparisons on APOGEE
when compared to the FALCONN locality-sensitive hashing library. CHESS allows
for implicit data compression, which we demonstrate on the APOGEE data set. We
also discuss an extension allowing for efficient k-nearest neighbors search.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:22:16Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08483</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08483" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Improved bounds for the sunflower lemma</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566777600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Alweiss:Ryan.html">Ryan Alweiss</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lovett:Shachar.html">Shachar Lovett</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wu:Kewen.html">Kewen Wu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Jiapeng.html">Jiapeng Zhang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08483">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A sunflower with $r$ petals is a collection of $r$ sets so that the
intersection of each pair is equal to the intersection of all. Erd\H{o}s and
Rado proved the sunflower lemma: for any fixed $r$, any family of sets of size
$w$, with at least about $w^w$ sets, must contain a sunflower. The famous
sunflower conjecture is that the bound on the number of sets can be improved to
$c^w$ for some constant $c$. In this paper, we improve the bound to about
$(\log w)^w$. In fact, we prove the result for a robust notion of sunflowers,
for which the bound we obtain is tight up to lower order terms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-26T01:20:44Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8615276220589503260</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/8615276220589503260/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/08/are-you-math-genius-can-you-fix-my.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8615276220589503260" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8615276220589503260" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/08/are-you-math-genius-can-you-fix-my.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>`Are you a math genius?' `Can you fix my Iphone?' `What do you think about Facebook and Privacy?'</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><br/>
When I meet non-math people and tell them I am a computer science professor I get a range of responses. Here are some and my responses.<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
1) <i>Are you a math genius?</i><br/>
<br/>
Here is the answer I give:<br/>
<br/>
<i>I know some things in math, frankly obscure things, that most people in math don't know. On the other hand, I probably can't help your teenage daughter with her trigonometry homework.  Academics, like most people, forget what they don't use, and there are some things in math I rarely use, so I've forgotten them.</i><br/>
<br/>
I wonder how a Fields' Medal winner would answer the question.<br/>
<br/>
Although the above is the answer I give I really think its an ill defined and pointless question. Its very hard to measure genius or even define what it means (there are exceptions). After a certain age, what you've done is more important than how smart you allegedly are.  <br/>
<br/>
2)<i> Can you fix my iPhone?</i><br/>
<br/>
That's an easy one: <i>No. I work on the math end of computer science.</i> I don't elaborate.<br/>
<br/>
3) <i>What do you think of Facebook and  privacy?</i><br/>
<br/>
This is an odd one. I DO have opinions on this but they are NOT better informed just because I'm a comp sci professor. Since I don't have a Facebook account my opinions might be worse informed. So how do I respond? I show them<br/>
<br/>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cqggW08BWO0">this Onion News Network Video about how the CIA created Facebook </a><br/>
<br/>
Some think it's real. They may be right.<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-25T17:39:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-25T17:39:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:03:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/111</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/111" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-111 |  Noisy Beeps | 

	Klim Efremenko, 

	Gillat Kol, 

	Raghuvansh Saxena</title>
    <summary>We study the effect of noise on the $n$-party beeping model. In this model, in every round, each party may decide to either `beep' or not. All parties hear a beep if and only if at least one party beeps. The beeping model is becoming increasingly popular, as it offers a very  simple abstraction of wireless networks and is very well suited for studying biological phenomena. Still, the noise resilience of the beeping model is yet to be understood.

Our main result is a lower bound, showing that making protocols in the beeping model resilient to noise may have a large performance overhead. Specifically, we give a protocol that works over the (noiseless) beeping model, and prove that any scheme that simulates this protocol over the beeping model with correlated stochastic noise will blow up the number of rounds by an $\Omega(\log n)$ multiplicative factor.

We complement this result by a matching upper bound, constructing a noise-resilient simulation scheme with $\mathcal{O}(\log n)$ overhead for any noiseless beeping protocol.</summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T06:39:55Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-25T06:39:55Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/110</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/110" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-110 |  Improved bounds for the sunflower lemma | 

	Jiapeng Zhang, 

	Shachar Lovett, 

	Ryan Alweiss, 

	Kewen Wu</title>
    <summary>A sunflower with $r$ petals is a collection of $r$ sets so that the
intersection of each pair is equal to the intersection of all. Erd\H{o}s and Rado proved the sunflower lemma: for any fixed $r$, any family of sets of size $w$, with at least about $w^w$ sets, must contain a sunflower. The famous sunflower conjecture is that the bound on the number of sets can be improved to $c^w$ for some constant $c$. In this paper, we improve the bound to about $(\log w)^w$. In fact, we prove the result for a robust notion of sunflowers, for which the bound we obtain is tight up to lower order terms.</summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T06:38:51Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-25T06:38:51Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08411</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08411" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Generalized Metric Repair on Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566691200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fan:Chenglin.html">Chenglin Fan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gilbert:Anna_C=.html">Anna C. Gilbert</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Raichel:Benjamin.html">Benjamin Raichel</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sonthalia:Rishi.html">Rishi Sonthalia</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Buskirk:Gregory_Van.html">Gregory Van Buskirk</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08411">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Many modern data analysis algorithms either assume or are considerably more
efficient if the distances between the data points satisfy a metric. These
algorithms include metric learning, clustering, and dimension reduction. As
real data sets are noisy, distances often fail to satisfy a metric. For this
reason, Gilbert and Jain and Fan et al. introduced the closely related sparse
metric repair and metric violation distance problems. The goal of these
problems is to repair as few distances as possible to ensure they satisfy a
metric. Three variants were considered, one admitting a polynomial time
algorithm. The other variants were shown to be APX-hard, and an
$O(OPT^{1/3})$-approximation was given, where $OPT$ is the optimal solution
size.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we generalize these problems to no longer consider all
distances between the data points. That is, we consider a weighted graph $G$
with corrupted weights $w$, and our goal is to find the smallest number of
weight modifications so that the resulting weighted graph distances satisfy a
metric. This is a natural generalization and is more flexible as it takes into
account different relationships among the data points. As in previous work, we
distinguish among the types of repairs permitted and focus on the increase only
and general versions. We demonstrate the inherent combinatorial structure of
the problem, and give an approximation-preserving reduction from MULTICUT.
Conversely, we show that for any fixed constant $\varsigma$, for the large
class of $\varsigma$-chordal graphs, the problems are fixed parameter
tractable. Call a cycle broken if it contains an edge whose weight is larger
than the sum of all its other edges, and call the amount of this difference its
deficit. We present approximation algorithms, one which depends on the maximum
number of edges in a broken cycle, and one which depends on the number of
distinct deficit values.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08384</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08384" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Covering convex bodies and the Closest Vector Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566691200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nasz=oacute=di:M=aacute=rton.html">Márton Naszódi</a>, Moritz Venzin <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08384">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present algorithms for the $(1+\epsilon)$-approximate version of the
closest vector problem for certain norms. The currently fastest algorithm
(Dadush and Kun 2016) for general norms has running time of $2^{O(n)}
(1/\epsilon)^n$. We improve this substantially in the following two cases.
</p>
<p>For $\ell_p$-norms with $p&gt;2$ (resp. $p \in [1,2]$) fixed, we present an
algorithm with a running time of $2^{O(n)} (1/\epsilon)^{n/2}$ (resp. $2^{O(n)}
(1/\epsilon)^{n/p}$). This result is based on a geometric covering problem,
that was introduced in the context of CVP by Eisenbrand et al.: How many convex
bodies are needed to cover the ball of the norm such that, if scaled by two
around their centroids, each one is contained in the $(1+\epsilon)$-scaled
homothet of the norm ball? We provide upper bounds for this problem by
exploiting the \emph{modulus of smoothness} of the $\ell_p$-balls. Applying a
covering scheme, we can boost any $2$-approximation algorithm for CVP to a
$(1+\epsilon)$-approximation algorithm with the improved run time, either using
a straightforward sampling routine or using the deterministic algorithm of
Dadush for the construction of an epsilon net.
</p>
<p>Furthermore, we consider polyhedral and zonotopal norms. For centrally
symmetric polytopes (resp. zonotopes) with $O(n)$ facets (resp. generated by
$O(n)$ line segments), we provide a deterministic
$O(\log_2(1/\epsilon))^{O(n)}$ time algorithm. This generalizes the result of
Eisenbrand et al. which applies to the $\ell_\infty$-norm.
</p>
<p>As it is the case for the covering procedure of Eisenbrand et al., our
approach boosts any constant factor approximation algorithm to a
$(1+\epsilon)$-approximate algorithm. By assuming the existence of a
$poly(n)$-space and $2^{O(n)}$ time algorithm for 2-approximate CVP, the space
complexity of our algorithm can be reduced to a polynomial.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08365</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08365" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal Morphs of Planar Orthogonal Drawings II</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566691200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Goethem:Arthur_van.html">Arthur van Goethem</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Speckmann:Bettina.html">Bettina Speckmann</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Verbeek:Kevin.html">Kevin Verbeek</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08365">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Van Goethem and Verbeek recently showed how to morph between two planar
orthogonal drawings $\Gamma_I$ and $\Gamma_O$ of a connected graph $G$ while
preserving planarity, orthogonality, and the complexity of the drawing during
the morph. Necessarily drawings $\Gamma_I$ and $\Gamma_O$ must be equivalent,
that is, there exists a homeomorphism of the plane that transforms $\Gamma_I$
into $\Gamma_O$. Van Goethem and Verbeek use $O(n)$ linear morphs, where $n$ is
the maximum complexity of the input drawings. However, if the graph is
disconnected their method requires $O(n^{1.5})$ linear morphs. In this paper we
present a refined version of their approach that allows us to also morph
between two planar orthogonal drawings of a disconnected graph with $O(n)$
linear morphs while preserving planarity, orthogonality, and linear complexity
of the intermediate drawings.
</p>
<p>Van Goethem and Verbeek measure the structural difference between the two
drawings in terms of the so-called spirality $s = O(n)$ of $\Gamma_I$ relative
to $\Gamma_O$ and describe a morph from $\Gamma_I$ to $\Gamma_O$ using $O(s)$
linear morphs. We prove that $s+1$ linear morphs are always sufficient to morph
between two planar orthogonal drawings, even for disconnected graphs. The
resulting morphs are quite natural and visually pleasing.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T23:25:21Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08347</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08347" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On Explicit Branching Programs for the Rectangular Determinant and Permanent Polynomials</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566691200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>V. Arvind, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chatterjee:Abhranil.html">Abhranil Chatterjee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Datta:Rajit.html">Rajit Datta</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mukhopadhyay:Partha.html">Partha Mukhopadhyay</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08347">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the arithmetic circuit complexity of some well-known family of
polynomials through the lens of parameterized complexity. Our main focus is on
the construction of explicit algebraic branching programs (ABP) for determinant
and permanent polynomials of the \emph{rectangular} symbolic matrix in both
commutative and noncommutative settings. The main results are:
</p>
<p>1. We show an explicit $O^{*}({n\choose {\downarrow k/2}})$-size ABP
construction for noncommutative permanent polynomial of $k\times n$ symbolic
matrix. We obtain this via an explicit ABP construction of size
$O^{*}({n\choose {\downarrow k/2}})$ for $S_{n,k}^*$, noncommutative
symmetrized version of the elementary symmetric polynomial $S_{n,k}$.
</p>
<p>2. We obtain an explicit $O^{*}(2^k)$-size ABP construction for the
commutative rectangular determinant polynomial of the $k\times n$ symbolic
matrix.
</p>
<p>3. In contrast, we show that evaluating the rectangular noncommutative
determinant over rational matrices is $W[1]$-hard.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T23:20:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08273</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08273" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Representing Graphs and Hypergraphs by Touching Polygons in 3D</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566691200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Evans:William.html">William Evans</a>, Paweł Rzążewski, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saeedi:Noushin.html">Noushin Saeedi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Shin:Chan=Su.html">Chan-Su Shin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wolff:Alexander.html">Alexander Wolff</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08273">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Contact representations of graphs have a long history.
</p>
<p>Most research has focused on problems in 2d, but 3d contact representations
have also been investigated, mostly concerning fully-dimensional geometric
objects such as spheres or cubes. In this paper we study contact
representations with convex polygons n~3d. We show that every graph admits such
a representation.
</p>
<p>Since our representations use super-polynomial coordinates, we also construct
representations on grids of polynomial size for specific graph classes
(bipartite, subcubic). For hypergraphs, we represent their duals, that is, each
vertex is represented by a point and each edge by a polygon.
</p>
<p>We show that even regular and quite small hypergraphs do not admit such
representations. On the other hand, the Steiner triple systems $S(2,3,7)$ and
$S(2,3,9)$ can be represented.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T23:24:46Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08266</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08266" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Interactive Duplicate Search in Software Documentation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566691200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>D. V. Luciv, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Koznov:D=_V=.html">D. V. Koznov</a>, A. A. Shelikhovskii, K. Yu. Romanovsky, G. A. Chernishev, A. N. Terekhov, D. A. Grigoriev, A. N. Smirnova, D. V. Borovkov, A. I. Vasenina <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08266">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Various software features such as classes, methods, requirements, and tests
often have similar functionality. This can lead to emergence of duplicates in
their descriptive documentation. Uncontrolled duplicates created via copy/paste
hinder the process of documentation maintenance. Therefore, the task of
duplicate detection in software documentation is of importance. Solving it
makes planned reuse possible, as well as creating and using templates for
unification and automatic generation of documentation. In this paper, we
present an interactive process for duplicate detection that involves the user
in order to conduct meaningful search. It includes a new formal definition of a
near duplicate, a pattern-based, and the proof of its completeness. Moreover,
we demonstrate the results of experimenting on a collection of documents of
several industrial projects.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T23:21:08Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08151</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08151" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Multi-level Graph Drawing using Infomap Clustering</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566691200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hong:Seok=Hee.html">Seok-Hee Hong</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Eades:Peter.html">Peter Eades</a>, Marnijati Torkel, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wang:Ziyang.html">Ziyang Wang</a>, David Chae, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hong:Sungpack.html">Sungpack Hong</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Langerenken:Daniel.html">Daniel Langerenken</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chafi:Hassan.html">Hassan Chafi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08151">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Infomap clustering finds the community structures that minimize the expected
description length of a random walk trajectory; algorithms for infomap
clustering run fast in practice for large graphs. In this paper we leverage the
effectiveness of Infomap clustering combined with the multi-level graph drawing
paradigm. Experiments show that our new Infomap based multi-level algorithm
produces good visualization of large and complex networks, with significant
improvement in quality metrics.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T23:22:14Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08129</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08129" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Extending Simple Drawings</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566691200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Arroyo:Alan.html">Alan Arroyo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Derka:Martin.html">Martin Derka</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Parada:Irene.html">Irene Parada</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08129">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Simple drawings of graphs are those in which each pair of edges share at most
one point, either a common endpoint or a proper crossing. In this paper we
study the problem of extending a simple drawing $D(G)$ of a graph $G$ by
inserting a set of edges from the complement of $G$ into $D(G)$ such that the
result is a simple drawing. In the context of rectilinear drawings, the problem
is trivial. For pseudolinear drawings, the existence of such an extension
follows from Levi's enlargement lemma. In contrast, we prove that deciding if a
given set of edges can be inserted into a simple drawing is NP-complete.
Moreover, we show that the maximization version of the problem is APX-hard. We
also present a polynomial-time algorithm for deciding whether one edge $uv$ can
be inserted into $D(G)$ when $\{u,v\}$ is a dominating set for the graph $G$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T23:26:54Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08111</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08111" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Engineering Faster Sorters for Small Sets of Items</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1566691200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Jasper Marianczuk <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08111">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Sorting a set of items is a task that can be useful by itself or as a
building block for more complex operations. The more sophisticated and fast
sorting algorithms become asymptotically, the less efficient they are for small
sets of items due to large constant factor. This thesis aims to determine if
there is a faster way to sort base case sizes than using insertion sort. For
that we looked at sorting networks and how to implement them efficiently.
Because sorting networks need to be implemented explicitly for each input size,
providing networks for larger sizes becomess less efficient. That is why we
modified Super Scalar Sample Sort to break down larger sets into sizes that can
in turn be sorted by sorting networks. We show that the task of sorting only
small sets can be greatly improved by at least 25% when using sorting networks
compared to insertion sort, but that when integrating them into other sorting
algorithms the speed-up is hindered by the limited L1 instruction cache size.
On a machine with 64KiB of L1 instruction cache we achieved over 6% of
improvement when using sorting networks as a base case sorter instead of
insertion sort.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-08-25T23:21:06Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-08-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3407</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/08/24/2020-call-for-profiles-of-sigecom-job-market-candidates/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>2020 Call for profiles of SIGecom job market candidates</title>
    <summary>Continuing the tradition from 2016, 2017, 2018, and 2019, this year there will be an article in the upcoming edition of the SIGecom Exchanges, profiling junior job market candidates (both for postdoc and faculty positions) of the SIGecom community for 2019-2020. These profiles will include the candidates’ thesis title, research summary, brief biography, and citations to three representative papers, as well as links to each candidate’s homepage and CV. To be considered, each candidate should complete the submission form by September […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div>Continuing the tradition from <a href="http://www.sigecom.org/exchanges/volume_14/1/PROFILES.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">2016</a>, <a href="http://www.sigecom.org/exchanges/volume_15/1/PROFILES.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">2017</a>, <a href="http://www.sigecom.org/exchanges/volume_16/1/PROFILES.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">2018</a>, and <a href="http://www.sigecom.org/exchanges/volume_17/1/PROFILES.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank" title="http://www.sigecom.org/exchanges/volume_17/1/PROFILES.pdf">2019</a>, this year there will be an article in the upcoming edition of the SIGecom Exchanges, profiling junior job market candidates (both for postdoc and faculty positions) of the SIGecom community for 2019-2020. These profiles will include the candidates’ thesis title, research summary, brief biography, and citations to three representative papers, as well as links to each candidate’s homepage and CV.</div>
<div/>
<div>To be considered, each candidate should complete the <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Xv7dfnaHOXgKKPs3cyaBKcWKq0QLTHwQhOJ6T0pGnJc" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank" title="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1Xv7dfnaHOXgKKPs3cyaBKcWKq0QLTHwQhOJ6T0pGnJc">submission form</a> by <b>September 2</b>, and then submit the final version of their LaTeX source files (a link to which is provided in the form) by <b>September 5</b>. The article will be co-edited by Vasilis Gkatzelis and myself. Please forward this call to whoever you think would be interested.</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-24T14:57:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-24T14:57:19Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Hartline</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/109</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/109" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-109 |  Decoding Downset codes over a finite grid | 

	Utkarsh Tripathi, 

	Srikanth Srinivasan, 

	S Venkitesh</title>
    <summary>In a recent paper, Kim and Kopparty (Theory of Computing, 2017) gave a deterministic algorithm for the unique decoding problem for polynomials of bounded total degree over a general grid $S_1\times\cdots \times S_m.$ We show that their algorithm can be adapted to solve the unique decoding problem for the general family of Downset codes. Here, a downset code is specified by a family $\mathcal{D}$ of monomials closed under taking factors: the corresponding code is the space of evaluations of all polynomials that can be written as linear combinations of monomials from $\mathcal{D}.$</summary>
    <updated>2019-08-23T13:39:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-23T13:39:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/108</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/108" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-108 |  Beating the probabilistic lower bound on perfect hashing | 

	Chaoping Xing, 

	chen yuan</title>
    <summary>For an interger $q\ge 2$, a perfect $q$-hash code $C$  is a  block code over $\ZZ_q:=\ZZ/ q\ZZ$ of length $n$ in which every subset $\{\bc_1,\bc_2,\dots,\bc_q\}$ of $q$ elements is separated, i.e., there exists $i\in[n]$ such that $\{\proj_i(\bc_1),\proj_i(\bc_2),\dots,\proj_i(\bc_q)\}=\ZZ_q$, where $\proj_i(\bc_j)$ denotes the $i$th position of $\bc_j$. Finding the maximum size $M(n,q)$ of  perfect $q$-hash codes of length $n$, for given $q$ and $n$, is  a fundamental problem in combinatorics, information theory, and computer science. In this paper, we are interested in asymptotical behavior of this problem. More precisely speaking, we will focus on the quantity $R_q:=\limsup_{n\rightarrow\infty}\frac{\log_2 M(n,q)}n$.

A well-known probabilistic argument shows an existence lower bound on $R_q$, namely $R_q\ge\frac1{q-1}\log_2\left(\frac1{1-q!/q^q}\right)$ \cite{FK,K86}.  This is still the best-known lower bound till now except for the case $q=3$  for which K\"{o}rner and Matron \cite{KM} found that the concatenation technique could lead to a perfect $3$-hash code beating this the probabilistic lower bound. The improvement on the lower bound on $R_3$ was discovered in 1988 and there has been no any progress on lower bound on $R_q$ for more than 30 years despite of some work on upper bounds on $R_q$.
 In this paper we show that this  probabilistic lower bound can be improved for $q=4,8$ and all odd integers between $3$ and $25$, and \emph{every sufficiently large odd} $q$. Our idea is based on a modified concatenation which is different from the classical concatenation for which both the inner and outer codes are separated. However, for our concatenation we do not require that the inner code is a perfect $q$-hash code. This gives  a more flexible choice of inner codes and hence we are able to beat the  probabilistic  existence lower bound on $R_q$.</summary>
    <updated>2019-08-23T13:37:39Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-23T13:37:39Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=14329</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/23/amazing-ryan-alweiss-shachar-lovett-kewen-wu-jiapeng-zhang-made-dramatic-progress-on-the-sunflower-conjecture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Amazing:  Ryan Alweiss, Shachar Lovett, Kewen Wu, Jiapeng Zhang made dramatic progress on the Sunflower Conjecture</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">WOW! The new paper https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08483 improved bounds for the sunflower lemma gives the most dramatic progress on the sunflower conjecture since it was asked. Congratulations to Ryan Alweiss, Shachar Lovett, Kewen Wu, Jiapeng Zhang. (Written on my smartphone will expand … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/23/amazing-ryan-alweiss-shachar-lovett-kewen-wu-jiapeng-zhang-made-dramatic-progress-on-the-sunflower-conjecture/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>WOW! The new paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08483" rel="nofollow">https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08483</a> improved bounds for the sunflower lemma gives the most dramatic progress on the sunflower conjecture since it was asked. Congratulations to Ryan Alweiss, Shachar Lovett, Kewen Wu, Jiapeng Zhang.</p>
<p>(Written on my smartphone will expand it when reconnected to my laptop.)  (Reconnected) Rather, I will write about it again in a few weeks. Let me mention now that while the old difficult and ingenious improvements stayed in the neighborhood of Erdos and Rado <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/09/28/extremal-combinatorics-iii-some-basic-theorems/">initial upper bound</a> the new result is in the neighborhood of the conjecture! (And is tight for a certain robust version of the problem!)</p>
<p>Let me also mention that we <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?s=sunflower+conjecture">discussed</a> the sunflower conjecture here many times and polymath10 (<a href="http://michaelnielsen.org/polymath1/index.php?title=The_Erdos-Rado_sunflower_lemma">wiki page</a>,  <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2015/11/03/polymath10-the-erdos-rado-delta-system-conjecture">first post</a>, <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2017/01/17/polymath10-conclusion/">last post</a>) was devoted to the problem.)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-23T05:47:59Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-23T05:47:59Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/08/22/serpentine-belts</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/08/22/serpentine-belts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Serpentine belts</title>
    <summary>Many car engines use a serpentine belt, passing across multiple pulleys and tensioner wheels, to transmit mechanical power and timing information from the car’s crankshaft to its alternator, engine fan, water pump, air conditioning, steering pump, and other systems. Another (usually separate) belt, the timing belt, similarly connects the crankshaft to the camshaft, which controls and drives the timing of the engine’s valves. The Volvo bus engine below shows both of these belts:</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Many car engines use a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serpentine_belt">serpentine belt</a>, passing across multiple pulleys and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tensioner">tensioner wheels</a>, to transmit mechanical power and timing information from the car’s crankshaft to its alternator, engine fan, water pump, air conditioning, steering pump, and other systems. Another (usually separate) belt, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timing_belt_(camshaft)">timing belt</a>, similarly connects the crankshaft to the camshaft, which controls and drives the timing of the engine’s valves.
The <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Belt_drive_systen_01.JPG">Volvo bus engine</a> below shows both of these belts:</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Timing and serpentine belts of a Volvo bus engine; CC-BY-SA photo by Miya.m from https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Belt_drive_systen_01.JPG" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/Volvo-bus-engine-belts.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="60%"/></p>

<p>But suppose you encounter such an engine with its belt removed. How can you tell where to run the belt to connect it all back together again? There may be many different orderings in which you can connect a given set of wheels by a belt. On a real engine (such as the one in a Ford Escort on which I loosely modeled the top image below), you might get a little more information from which of the wheels are ribbed (inside the belt) and which are smooth (outside the belt) but even that extra information won’t always give you a unique solution:</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Two serpentine belts for the Ford Escort" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/escort.svg"/></p>

<p>Connecting wheels with belts like this is the topic of my latest preprint, “Existence and hardness of conveyor belts” (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.07668">arXiv:1908.07668</a>, with a large group of co-authors merging groups from the University of Washington and the Bellairs workshops). The name isn’t really accurate, because most conveyor belts have simpler geometry, but that’s what the question was called in past work. At least we managed to avoid the misspelling “conveyer” of some of that work.</p>

<p>To be tight, a belt for a system of disjoint disks (representing the pulleys and wheels) must be a smooth simple closed curve, made by connecting arcs of the disks with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tangent_lines_to_circles#Tangent_lines_to_two_circles">bitangents</a> between pairs of disks. It was already known that some systems of disks have no belt, and conjectured that unit disks always have one. Our work shows that it’s -complete to tell whether a belt exists, that they do exist for certain special systems of disks (e.g. when no vertical line crosses multiple disks), and that by adding a linear number of extra disks one can always make a belt exist.</p>

<p>The question of how many different belts can connect the same system of disks (posed to me by co-author Sara Billey) was to a large extent the inspiration for <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/03/12/counting-polygon-triangulations.html">my earlier paper on counting triangulations</a>. If counting simple polygons through a set of points is hard, then so is counting belts for tiny disks. And when I couldn’t prove that counting simple polygons is hard, I turned to other problems for which the proof was easier.</p>

<p>As part of this project I wrote <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/drawbelts.py">a little Python program to draw systems of disks and their belts</a>, used for the image above and for some of the images in the paper. It doesn’t find which belts are possible itself; instead, you have to specify the belt by listing the disks that it touches in order (allowing repetitions although some of the versions of the problem that we studied do not) and specifying for each disk which direction it turns when the belt touches it (equivalently, whether it is inside or outside the belt). To use it, you’ll need my <a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/PADS/">PADS Python library</a>, or at least <a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/PADS/SVG.py">the package in it for generating SVG files</a>.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102664433496197083">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-22T21:19:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-22T21:19:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-08-23T04:36:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3404</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/08/21/papafest-schedule-announced/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PapaFest schedule announced</title>
    <summary>The schedule for PapaFest (celebrating Christos Papadimitriou) has been posted at http://papafest.cs.columbia.edu/ When/where: September 6-8, 2019, at Columbia University in Davis Auditorium. (Register at the URL above, for free.) Confirmed speakers: Sanjeev Arora, Michael Collins, Michael Jordan, Anna Karlin, Jon Kleinberg, Elias Koutsoupias, Adi Livnat, Noam Nisan, Prabhakar Raghavan, Scott Shenker, Eva Tardos, John Tsitsiklis, Leslie […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The schedule for PapaFest (celebrating Christos Papadimitriou) has been posted at <a href="http://papafest.cs.columbia.edu/">http://papafest.cs.columbia.edu/</a></p>
<p>When/where: September 6-8, 2019, at Columbia University in Davis Auditorium. (Register at the URL above, for free.)</p>
<p>Confirmed speakers: Sanjeev Arora, Michael Collins, Michael Jordan, Anna Karlin, Jon Kleinberg, Elias Koutsoupias, Adi Livnat, Noam Nisan, Prabhakar Raghavan, Scott Shenker, Eva Tardos, John Tsitsiklis, Leslie Valiant, Umesh Vazirani, and Santosh Vempala.</p>
<p>There will also be two panels led by Richard Karp and Jitendra Malik, and a rock concert by Errors in Bars on Saturday night!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-21T15:12:07Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-21T15:12:07Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>timroughgarden</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/08/21/assistant-professor-tenure-track-and-professor-positions-in-computer-science-at-institute-of-science-and-technology-austria-apply-by-october-31-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/08/21/assistant-professor-tenure-track-and-professor-positions-in-computer-science-at-institute-of-science-and-technology-austria-apply-by-october-31-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant professor (tenure-track) and professor positions in computer science at Institute of Science and Technology Austria (apply by October 31, 2019)</title>
    <summary>We invite applications in all areas of computer science for several open positions. Female researchers are strongly encouraged to apply. Website: https://ist.ac.at/en/jobs/faculty/ Email: professors@ist.ac.at</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We invite applications in all areas of computer science for several open positions. Female researchers are strongly encouraged to apply.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://ist.ac.at/en/jobs/faculty/">https://ist.ac.at/en/jobs/faculty/</a><br/>
Email: <a href="mailto:professors@ist.ac.at" rel="noopener" target="_blank"> professors@ist.ac.at</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-21T11:55:31Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-21T11:55:31Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=17855</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/21/the-argument-against-quantum-computers-a-cern-colloquium-and-a-new-paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Argument against Quantum Computers – a CERN Colloquium and a New Paper</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Let me announce my CERN colloquium this Thursday, August 22, 2019, 16:30-17:30 entitled “The argument against quantum computers.” If you are at CERN or the neighborhood, please please come to the lecture. (Tea and coffee will be served at 16:00. … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/21/the-argument-against-quantum-computers-a-cern-colloquium-and-a-new-paper/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Let me announce <a href="https://indico.cern.ch/event/839574/?fbclid=IwAR0JHF8kcQ_tQKJrbJcNYTu9lQvMjOEvcSk6Jsh_Tq4uH4EbjeaDz7qv30k">my CERN colloquium</a> this Thursday, August 22, 2019, 16:30-17:30 entitled “The argument against quantum computers.” If you are at CERN or the neighborhood, please please come to the lecture. (Tea and coffee will be served at 16:00. ) If you are further away, there is a <a href="https://webcast.web.cern.ch/event/i839574">live broadcast</a>.</p>
<p>A few weeks ago I uploaded to the arXive a new paper with the same title “<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02499">The argument against quantum computers</a>“. The paper will appear in the volume: Quantum, Probability, Logic: Itamar Pitowsky’s Work and Influence, Springer, Nature (2019), edited by Meir Hemmo and Orly Shenker. A short abstract for the lecture and the paper is:</p>
<blockquote><p><em><strong><span style="color: #008080;">We give a computational complexity argument against the feasibility of quantum computers. We identify a very low complexity class of probability distributions described by noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers, and explain why it will allow neither good-quality quantum error-correction nor a demonstration of “quantum supremacy.”  Some general principles governing the behavior of noisy quantum systems are derived.</span></strong></em></p></blockquote>
<p>The new paper and lecture have the same title as my 2018 <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/gil-kalais-argument-against-quantum-computers-20180207/">interview</a> with Katia Moskvitch at Quanta Magazine (see also <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2018/02/08/my-argument-against-quantum-computers-an-interview-with-katia-moskvitch-on-quanta-magazine/">this post</a>).  Note that Christopher Monroe has recently <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/gil-kalais-argument-against-quantum-computers-20180207/#comment-4559220424">contributed a very interesting comment</a> to the Quanta article. My paper is dedicated to the memory of Itamar Pitowsky, and for more on Itamar see the post <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2010/02/15/itamar-pitowski-probability-in-physics-where-does-it-come-from/" rel="bookmark">Itamar Pitowsky: Probability in Physics, Where does it Come From?</a> See also this <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/09/two-important-quantum-announcements/">previous post</a> for two other quantum events in Jerusalem: a seminar in the first semester and a winter school on <a href="http://ias.huji.ac.il/SchoolCSE4">The Mathematics of Quantum Computation </a> on December 15 – December 19, 2019.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/sasb.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17856" height="481" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/sasb.png?w=640&amp;h=481" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #ff0000;">A slide from a lecture by Scott Aaronson where he explains why soap bubble computers cannot solve the NP-complete Steiner-tree problem. Noisy intermediate scale quantum (NISQ) circuits are <em>computationally </em>much more primitive than Scott’s soap bubble computers and this will prevent them from achieving neither “quantum supremacy” nor good quality quantum error correcting codes.  </span></strong><span style="color: #ff0000;">(<a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4199">source</a> for the picture)</span></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/entn.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17860" height="360" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/entn.png?w=640&amp;h=360" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #ff0000;">Low-entropy quantum states give probability distributions described by low degree polynomials, and very low-entropy quantum states give chaotic behavior. Higher entropy enables classical information. </span></strong></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/cern.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17862" height="371" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/cern.png?w=640&amp;h=371" width="640"/></a></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-21T01:26:28Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-21T01:26:28Z</published>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Physics"/>
    <category term="Quantum"/>
    <category term="CERN"/>
    <category term="Quantum computers"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16180</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/08/20/our-trip-to-monte-carlo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Our Trip To Monte Carlo</title>
    <summary>Why does randomness help? Kathryn Farley is my dear wife. She and I are currently on a cruise through the Mediterranean. Our trip started in Barcelona and is stopping daily at various cities as we journey to Rome. “Tough duty,” but we are trying to enjoy it. Today I wish to talk about our visit […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Why does randomness help?</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/kathrynmontecarlo2.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16183" height="180" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/kathrynmontecarlo2.png?w=141&amp;h=180" width="141"/></a></p>
<p>
Kathryn Farley is my dear wife. She and I are currently on a cruise through the Mediterranean. Our trip started in Barcelona and is stopping daily at various cities as we journey to Rome. “Tough duty,” but we are trying to enjoy it. </p>
<p>
Today I wish to talk about our visit to Monte Carlo. </p>
<p>
Our ship, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MV_Seabourn_Encore">Encore</a>, just docked there Sunday. The day was warm and clear, and we spent some time exploring the city. We did manage to avoid losing any money at the famous casino. Our secret was simple: do not play, do not gamble, do not lose.</p>
<p>
Over lunch I started to explain to Kathryn why Monte Carlo is an important city for complexity theorists. I felt a bit like we were at a theory shrine.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Why Randomness Helps </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Indeed. I realized that it is not so simple to explain why randomness helps. Kathryn has a Ph.D in theatre. She is smart, is a member of Mensa, but is not a complexity theorist. How do I explain that randomness is powerful? Indeed.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/randkinmontecarlo2.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-16186" height="251" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/randkinmontecarlo2.png?w=300&amp;h=251" width="300"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
I started to explain, but my examples were lame. I think she got the main idea, but I also think that I did not do a great job. Russell Impagliazzo has a nice <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/sites/default/files/docs/6119/doesrandomnesshelp.pdf">explanation</a> on the role of randomness—I wish Russell had been there to help explain randomness to Kathryn. </p>
<p>
After lunch I started to think more about the role of randomness. I looked at our friends over at Wikipedia and discovered they had a pretty good <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Applications_of_randomness">page</a>. Some reasons are:</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>Games</i></p>
<p>
Randomness was first investigated in the context of gambling. Dice, playing cards, roulette wheels, all have been studied by those interested in gambling. Clearly, betting on the roll of dice, deal of cards, or spin of the wheel, only makes sense when these actions are unpredictable. Random. </p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>Political</i></p>
<p>
Randomness is often used to create “fairness”. For example, in the US and UK, juror selection is done by a lottery. </p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>Science</i></p>
<p>
Monte Carlo methods in physics and computer science require random numbers.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>Cryptography</i></p>
<p>
Random keys for encryption algorithms should be unpredictable. Random. Otherwise, they can be guessed by others. The password “password” is usually not allowed.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet }"/> <i>Arts</i></p>
<p>
Kathryn is interested in the arts: in plays and in painting and other fine arts. Some theories of art claim that all art is random. One thinks of artists like Jackson Pollock with his famous drip paintings. He was a major player in the abstract expressionist movement.</p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/jpollock.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-16188" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/jpollock.png?w=600"/></a></p>
<p/><h2> Pseudo or True? </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Ken has been paying intensive devotions at the same shrine. As he wrote in the previous <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/08/15/predicting-chess-and-horses/">post</a>, he has been conducting millions of randomized tests of his new chess model. </p>
<p>
Why random? What he needs to do is show that his model will not tend to “cry wolf” by giving a too-high <img alt="{z}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bz%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{z}"/>-score to a set of games in a tournament by an honest player. He wants to show that his model is equally tempered no matter the rating of the player. So he runs trials at different rating levels ranging from Elo 1000 for novice players to Elo 2800 which is championship level. To show that the <img alt="{z}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bz%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{z}"/>-scores given by his model conform to a normal bell curve, he needs to do 10,000s or 100,000s of tests at each level. </p>
<p>
The problem is there just don’t exist enough games. Most large tournaments give only the games played on their “top boards” which use special auto-recording equipment, and the losers on those boards in one round may play on lower boards in the next round. Thus out of about 60,000 player-tournament pairs Ken can track each year, most are only partial samples. So what Ken does is generate “synthetic players” by randomly taking subsets of (say) 9 games—from his data set of 1,000 or so games for each level—and randomly choosing white or black for each game. This is a common <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resampling_(statistics)#Subsampling">resampling</a> technique, and it uses Monte Carlo.</p>
<p>
Ken uses pseudo-random generators (PRGs). He starts a C++ library PRG on a seed <img alt="{s}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s}"/> based on the current time. The fact that the choices are deterministic once <img alt="{s}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s}"/> is given might allow him to reproduce an entire run exactly (after a model tweak) by preserving the <img alt="{s}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s}"/> it used. This is a paradox: we might want our “random” bits to be deterministic. Monte Carlo with predestined loaded dice.</p>
<p>
From time to time on this blog we have mused about what a world <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2013/08/23/a-world-without-randomness/">without</a> randomness or with <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/04/01/the-entropy-of-baseball/">reduced</a> entropy would be like. We were struck a few weeks ago when the noted physics blogger Sabine Hossenfelder wrote about “<a href="http://backreaction.blogspot.com/2019/07/the-forgotten-solution-superdeterminism.html">superdeterminism</a>.” That post provoked a few hundred comments in her blog, as did her <a href="http://backreaction.blogspot.com/2019/08/the-problem-with-quantum-measurements.html">post</a> last week on the quantum measurement problem—including long exchanges with Peter Shor. Ken and I don’t know which side to take, but I can say that the side of a ship is a great place to think about possible real effects of these differences.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
What is your take on randomness? Do you employ it? How “true” do you need it to be? </p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-20T16:24:54Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-20T16:24:54Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="art"/>
    <category term="cruise"/>
    <category term="Kathryn Farley"/>
    <category term="Monte Carlo"/>
    <category term="Peter Shor"/>
    <category term="Physics"/>
    <category term="quantum"/>
    <category term="randomized algorithms"/>
    <category term="randomness"/>
    <category term="Sabine Hossenfelder"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/08/20/algorithms-postdoc-at-university-of-california-berkeley-apply-by-october-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/08/20/algorithms-postdoc-at-university-of-california-berkeley-apply-by-october-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Algorithms Postdoc at University of California Berkeley (apply by October 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>Multiple Postdoctoral positions available to work on Fine-grained Complexity, Approximation Algorithms and Additive Combinatorics. Please email directly to Barna with resume and contact information of three references. The start date is flexible. Website: https://barnasaha.net/ Email: barnas@berkeley.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Multiple Postdoctoral positions available to work on Fine-grained Complexity, Approximation Algorithms and Additive Combinatorics. Please email directly to Barna with resume and contact information of three references. The start date is flexible.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://barnasaha.net/">https://barnasaha.net/</a><br/>
Email: barnas@berkeley.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-20T04:00:50Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-20T04:00:50Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=17848</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/19/equiangular-lines-with-a-fixed-angle-and-other-breakthroughs-from-yufei-zhaos-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Equiangular lines with a fixed angle and other breakthroughs from Yufei Zhao’s blog</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Today I would like to report about some breakthroughs in the area of combinatorics, and about blog posts in Yufei Zhao’s blog that describe these remarkable results (better than I can). Many of the coauthors in these breakthroughs are undergraduate … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/19/equiangular-lines-with-a-fixed-angle-and-other-breakthroughs-from-yufei-zhaos-blog/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Today I would like to report about some breakthroughs in the area of combinatorics, and about blog posts in <a href="https://yufeizhao.wordpress.com/">Yufei Zhao’s blog</a> that describe these remarkable results (better than I can). <span style="color: #993366;"><strong>Many of the coauthors in these breakthroughs are undergraduate students</strong>.</span></p>
<h2><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.12466">Equiangular lines with a fixed angle</a></h2>
<h3>by Zilin Jiang, Jonathan Tidor, Yuan Yao, Shengtong Zhang and Yufei Zhao.</h3>
<p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.12466">Paper </a>; <a href="https://yufeizhao.wordpress.com/2019/07/29/equiangular-lines-with-a-fixed-angle/">blog post</a> (end of July, 2019)</p>
<p>A collection of equiangular lines is a collection of lines so that the angles between every pair of lines in the same?</p>
<p>Here are two classical questions:</p>
<ol>
<li>What is the maximum number of equiangular lines in <img alt="\mathbb R^d" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+R%5Ed&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\mathbb R^d"/>?</li>
<li>Given an angle <img alt="\alpha" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\alpha"/> what is the maximum number of equiangular lines in <img alt="\mathbb R^d" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+R%5Ed&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\mathbb R^d"/>? so that the angle between every two lines is <img alt="\alpha?" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha%3F&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\alpha?"/></li>
</ol>
<p>In 2000 Dom de Caen found for the first time an equiangular set of lines in <img alt="d" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="d"/> space of size <img alt="cd^2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=cd%5E2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="cd^2"/>. (The crucial observation that one of the graphs in the Cameron–Seidel association scheme has a certain eigenvalue of large multiplicity.  Prior to this construction, the largest sets had sizes of order <img alt="d^{3/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d%5E%7B3%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="d^{3/2}"/>.  In de Caen’s example the lines have angles approaching 90 degrees, and question 2 for a fixed value of <img alt="\alpha" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Calpha&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\alpha"/> led to very different bounds. (For another result by Dom, see <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2011/06/15/the-combinatorics-of-cocycles-and-borsuks-problem/">this post</a>.)</p>
<p>There were some important progress on this problem by Igor Balla, Felix Dräxler, Peter Keevash, and Benny Sudakov, as featured in this  <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/a-new-path-to-equal-angle-lines-20170411/">Quanta Magazine article</a> written by Kevin Hartnett. Zilin, Jonathan, Yuan, Shengtong, and Yufei  finished off the problem in a clean and crisp manner, in a 10-page paper with a self-contained proof. On the way they proved the following very interesting theorem.</p>
<p><strong>Theorem:</strong> A bounded degree graph must have sublinear second eigenvalue multiplicity.</p>
<h2><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.10482">Impartial digraphs</a></h2>
<h3>by Yufei Zhao and Yunkun Zhou.</h3>
<p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.10482">Paper</a>, <a href="https://yufeizhao.wordpress.com/2019/06/27/impartial-digraphs/">blog post</a> (end of June 2019)</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/yzb.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17875" height="386" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/yzb.png?w=640&amp;h=386" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><strong>Abstract</strong>: We prove a conjecture of Fox, Huang, and Lee that characterizes directed graphs <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="H"/> that have constant density in all tournaments: they are disjoint unions of trees that are each constructed in a certain recursive way.</p>
<p>“Constant density in all tournaments” means that for some <img alt="n_0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n_0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="n_0"/> (and hence for all <img alt="n \ge n_0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n+%5Cge+n_0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="n \ge n_0"/>, every tournament with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="n"/> vertices has the same number of copies of <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="H"/>. (On the nose!)</p>
<p>This result is related to the famous Sidorenko’s conjecture. Let me copy its description from the paper:</p>
<p>For undirected graphs, conjectures of Sidorenko and Erdős–Simonovits (commonly referred to as Sidorenko’s conjecture) say that for every bipartite graph <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="H"/>, the <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="H"/>-density in a graph of fixed density is minimized asymptotically by a random graph. Lately the conjecture has been proved for many families of <img alt="H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="H"/> though the conjecture remains open in general. In particular, the case <img alt="H = K_{5,5}\backslash C_{10}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H+%3D+K_%7B5%2C5%7D%5Cbackslash+C_%7B10%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="H = K_{5,5}\backslash C_{10}"/> is open.</p>
<h2><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/yz.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17879" height="427" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/08/yz.jpg?w=640&amp;h=427" width="640"/></a></h2>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><strong>Yufei Zhao</strong></span></p>
<h2>More</h2>
<p>Let me describe briefly three additional posts on Yufei’s blog with two results from 2018 and one result from 2014.</p>
<h3>Ashwin Sah, Mehtaab Sawhney, David Stoner, and Yufei Zhao  <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1809.09462">A reverse Sidorenko inequality</a>; (<a href="https://yufeizhao.wordpress.com/2018/09/25/a-reverse-sidorenko-inequality/">blog post</a>) ; <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.04021">The number of independent sets in an irregular graph</a>; <a href="https://yufeizhao.wordpress.com/2018/05/12/the-number-of-independent-sets-in-an-irregular-graph/">blog post</a>.</h3>
<p>These are two remarkable papers by the same team of researchers. The paper  on the number of independent sets in a regular graph settled a famous 2001 conjecture by Jeff Kahn. An earlier breakthrough on the problem was made by Zhao in 2009 when he was an undergraduate student.</p>
<h3><a href="http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/eyal/">Eyal Lubetzky</a> and Yufei Zhao,  <em><a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1402.6011">On the variational problem for upper tails of triangle counts in sparse random graphs</a></em>. <a href="https://yufeizhao.wordpress.com/2014/02/25/upper-tail/">Blog post</a>.</h3>
<p>Recently  I wrote a post <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/07/23/matan-harel-frank-mousset-and-wojciech-samotij-and-the-the-infamous-upper-tail-problem/" rel="bookmark">Matan Harel, Frank Mousset, and Wojciech Samotij and the “the infamous upper tail” problem</a> describing a major breakthrough on the infamous upper tail problem. Over the years I heard a lot of lectures and private explanation on upper tails and the remarkable related mathematics. I remember lectures by Kim and Vu from the early 2000’s and by Varadhan from ICM 2010 describing (among other things) the fundamental paper by  <a href="http://www.ams.org/mathscinet-getitem?mr=2825532">Chatterjee and Varadhan</a>,  and later works by  <a href="http://www.ams.org/mathscinet-getitem?mr=2925307">DeMarco and Kahn, </a> and by  <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1401.3495">Chatterjee and Dembo</a>  and Lubetzky and Zhao and others. But when I wrote the post I realized my knowledge is too sparse for giving a thorough description, and I decided not to wait and write a short post. This post by Yufei describes some of the history very nicely as well as the major papers by Eyal and Yufei from 2012 and 2014.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-08-19T18:33:52Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-19T18:33:52Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Ashwin Sah"/>
    <category term="David Stoner"/>
    <category term="Eyal Lubetzky"/>
    <category term="Jonathan Tidor"/>
    <category term="Mehtaab Sawhney"/>
    <category term="Shengtong Zhang"/>
    <category term="Yuan Yao"/>
    <category term="Yufei Zhao"/>
    <category term="Yunkun Zhou"/>
    <category term="Zilin Jiang"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/107</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/107" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-107 |  The Power of a Single Qubit: Two-way Quantum/Classical Finite Automata and the Word Problem for Linear Groups | 

	Zachary Remscrim</title>
    <summary>The two-way quantum/classical finite automaton (2QCFA), defined by Ambainis and Watrous, is a model of quantum computation whose quantum part is extremely limited; however, as they showed, 2QCFA are surprisingly powerful: a 2QCFA, with a single qubit, can recognize, with one-sided bounded-error, the language $L_{eq}=\{a^m b^m |m \in \mathbb{N}\}$ in expected polynomial time and the language $L_{pal}=\{w \in \{a,b\}^*|w \text{ is a palindrome}\}$ in expected exponential time.  

We further demonstrate the power of 2QCFA by showing that they can recognize the word problems of a broad class of groups. In particular, we first restrict our attention to 2QCFA that: $(1)$ have a single qubit, $(2)$ recognize their language with one-sided bounded-error, and $(3)$ have transition amplitudes which are algebraic numbers. We show that such 2QCFA can recognize the word problem of any finitely-generated virtually abelian group in expected polynomial time, as well as the word problem of a large class of linear groups in expected exponential time. This latter class includes all groups whose word problem is a context-free language as well as all groups whose word problem is known to be the intersection of finitely many context-free languages. As a corollary, we obtain a direct improvement on the original Ambainis and Watrous result by showing that $L_{eq}$ can be recognized by a 2QCFA with better parameters. 

We also consider those word problems which a 2QCFA can recognize with one-sided unbounded-error, and show that this class includes the word problem of more exotic groups such as the free product of any finite collection of finitely-generated free abelian groups. As a corollary of this result, we demonstrate that a new class of group word problems are co-stochastic languages. Lastly, we exhibit analogous results for 2QCFA with any finite number of qubits or with more general transition amplitudes, as well as results for other classic QFA models.</summary>
    <updated>2019-08-18T13:27:03Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-18T13:27:03Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/106</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/106" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-106 |  Semialgebraic Proofs and Efficient Algorithm Design | 

	Noah Fleming, 

	Pravesh Kothari, 

	Toniann Pitassi</title>
    <summary>Over the last twenty years, an exciting interplay has emerged between proof systems and algorithms. Some natural families of algorithms can be viewed as a generic translation from a proof that a solution exists into an algorithm for finding the solution itself. This connection has perhaps been the most consequential in the context of semi-algebraic proof systems and basic primitives in algorithm design such as linear and semidefinite programming. The proof system perspective, in this context, has provided fundamentally new tools for both algorithm design and analysis. These news tools have helped in both designing better algorithms for well-studied problems and proving tight lower bounds on such techniques.

This monograph is aimed at expositing this interplay between proof systems and efficient algorithm design and surveying the state-of-the-art for two of the most important semi-algebraic proof systems: Sherali-Adams and Sum-of-Squares.

We rigorously develop and survey the state-of-the-art for Sherali-Adams and Sum-of-Squares both as proof systems, as well as a general family of optimization algorithms, stressing that  these perspectives are formal duals to one-another. Our treatment relies on interpreting the outputs of the Sum-of-Squares and Sherali-Adams algorithms as generalized expectation functions -- a viewpoint that has been essential in obtaining both algorithmic results and lower bounds. The emphasis is on illustrating the main ideas by presenting a small fraction of representative results with detailed intuition and commentary. The monograph is self-contained and includes a review of the necessary mathematical background including basic theory of linear and semi-definite programming.</summary>
    <updated>2019-08-18T06:14:17Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-18T06:14:17Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/?p=5432</id>
    <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/2019/08/18/abstraction-is-hard/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Abstraction is Hard</title>
    <summary>A few weeks ago I read Malcolm Gladwell’s book The Tipping Point. The book doesn’t really deal with mathematics, but it does contain one math-related anecdote. This anecdote demonstrates an interesting principle of learning mathematics, so I wanted to share it. Problem 1. We have a deck of cards, such that each card contains a […]</summary>
    <updated>2019-08-18T02:03:50Z</updated>
    <published>2019-08-18T02:03:50Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Adam Sheffer</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Discrete geometry and other typos</subtitle>
      <title>Some Plane Truths</title>
      <updated>2019-08-26T05:21:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
