<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-02-11T22:21:42Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?p=40</id>
    <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2020/02/08/icalp-and-lics-2020-relocation-and-extended-deadline/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>ICALP (and LICS) 2020 – Relocation and Extended Deadline</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the Wuhan coronavirus outbreak, the organizers of ICALP and LICS have made the difficult decision to relocate both (co-located) conferences from Beijing, China, to Saarbrücken, Germany. Speaking specifically about ICALP now (I do not have further information about LICS): As a result of previous uncertainty regarding the situation, the deadline has been extended … <a class="more-link" href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2020/02/08/icalp-and-lics-2020-relocation-and-extended-deadline/">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "ICALP (and LICS) 2020 – Relocation and Extended Deadline"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Due to the Wuhan coronavirus outbreak, the organizers of ICALP and LICS have made the difficult decision to relocate both (co-located) conferences from Beijing, China, to Saarbrücken, Germany. Speaking specifically about ICALP now (I do not have further information about LICS): As a result of previous uncertainty regarding the situation, the deadline has been extended by about six days, until Tuesday February 18, 2020, at 6 AM GMT. The dates of the conference remain (roughly) the same, July 8 – 11, 2020. <br/>The following is a more official message from ICALP Track A Chair, Artur Czumaj.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>The ICALP and the LICS steering committee have agreed together with the conference chairs in Beijing to relocate the two conferences.<br/>ICALP and LICS 2020 will take place in <strong>Saarbrücken</strong>, Germany, July 8 – 11 2020 (with satellite workshops on July 6 – 7 2020).<br/>The deadline is extended, see below.</p>



<p><strong>Call for Papers – ICALP 2020</strong><br/><strong>July 8 – 11 2020, Saarbrücken, Germany</strong></p>



<p><strong>NEW Paper submission deadline: Tuesday February 18, 2020, 6am GMT</strong><br/><a href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=icalp2020">https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=icalp2020</a></p>



<p>ICALP (International Colloquium on Automata, Languages and Programming) is the main European conference in Theoretical Computer Science and annual meeting of the European Association for Theoretical Computer Science (EATCS). ICALP 2020 will be hosted on the Saarland Informatics Campus in Saarbrücken, in co-location with LICS 2020 (ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science).</p>



<p><strong>Invited speakers:</strong><br/>Track A: Virginia Vassilevska (MIT), Robert Krauthgamer (Weizmann)<br/>Track B: Stefan Kiefer (Oxford)<br/>Joint ICALP-LICS: Andrew Yao (Tsinghua), Jérôme Leroux (Bordeaux)</p>



<p><strong>Submission Guidelines:</strong> see <a href="https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=icalp2020">https://easychair.org/conferences/?conf=icalp2020</a></p>



<p><strong>NEW Paper submission deadline: February 18</strong>, 2020, 6am GMT<br/>notifications: April 15, 2020<br/>camera ready: April 28, 2020</p>



<p>Topics: ICALP 2020 will have the two traditional tracks<br/>A (Algorithms, Complexity and Games – including Algorithmic Game Theory, Distributed Algorithms and Parallel, Distributed and External Memory Computing) and<br/>B (Automata, Logic, Semantics and Theory of Programming).<br/><strong><em>    (Notice that the old tracks A and C have been merged into a single track A.)</em></strong><br/>Papers presenting original, unpublished research on all aspects of theoretical computer science are sought.</p>



<p>Typical, but not exclusive topics are:</p>



<p>Track A — Algorithmic Aspects of Networks and Networking, Algorithms for Computational Biology, Algorithmic Game Theory, Combinatorial Optimization, Combinatorics in Computer Science, Computational Complexity, Computational Geometry, Computational Learning Theory, Cryptography, Data Structures, Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Foundations of Machine Learning, Foundations of Privacy, Trust and Reputation in Network, Network Models for Distributed Computing, Network Economics and Incentive-Based Computing Related to Networks, Network Mining and Analysis, Parallel, Distributed and External Memory Computing, Quantum Computing, Randomness in Computation, Theory of Security in Networks</p>



<p>Track B — Algebraic and Categorical Models, Automata, Games, and Formal Languages, Emerging and Non-standard Models of Computation, Databases, Semi-Structured Data and Finite Model Theory, Formal and Logical Aspects of Learning, Logic in Computer Science, Theorem Proving and Model Checking, Models of Concurrent, Distributed, and Mobile Systems, Models of Reactive, Hybrid and Stochastic Systems, Principles and Semantics of Programming Languages, Program Analysis and Transformation, Specification, Verification and Synthesis, Type Systems and Theory, Typed Calculi</p>



<p><strong>PC Track A chair: Artur Czumaj</strong> (University  of Warwick)<br/><strong>PC Track B chair: Anuj Dawar</strong> (University of Cambridge)</p>



<p>Contact<br/>All questions about submissions should be emailed to the PC Track chairs:<br/>Artur Czumaj <a href="mailto:A.Czumaj@warwick.ac.uk">A.Czumaj@warwick.ac.uk&lt;mailto:A.Czumaj@warwick.ac.uk&gt;</a><br/>Anuj Dawar <a href="mailto:Anuj.Dawar@cl.cam.ac.uk">Anuj.Dawar@cl.cam.ac.uk&lt;mailto:Anuj.Dawar@cl.cam.ac.uk&gt;</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-02-08T15:01:28Z</updated>
    <published>2020-02-08T15:01:28Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://kamathematics.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Kamathematics</title>
      <updated>2020-02-11T22:21:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?p=34</id>
    <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/20/theory-and-practice-of-differential-privacy-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy 2019</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While I’m a relative newcomer to differential privacy (my first paper on it was only in 2017), I’ve found the community to be a pleasure to interact with: paradoxically, simultaneously tight-knit yet highly welcoming to newcomers. I partially credit this culture to the number of workshops and programs which bring people together, including, but not … <a class="more-link" href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/20/theory-and-practice-of-differential-privacy-2019/">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy 2019"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>While I’m a relative newcomer to differential privacy (my <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.10127">first paper</a> on it was only in 2017), I’ve found the community to be a pleasure to interact with: paradoxically, simultaneously tight-knit yet highly welcoming to newcomers. I partially credit this culture to the number of workshops and programs which bring people together, including, but not limited to, <a href="https://www.birs.ca/events/2018/5-day-workshops/18w5189">a BIRS workshop</a>, <a href="https://privacytools.seas.harvard.edu/">the Privacy Tools project at Harvard</a>, <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/programs/privacy2019">a semester at the Simons Institute</a>, <a href="https://shonan.nii.ac.jp/seminars/164/">the forthcoming Shonan workshop</a>, and <a href="https://tpdp.cse.buffalo.edu/">the Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy (TPDP) Workshop</a>.</p>



<p>I’m writing this post to draw attention to the imminent deadline of <a href="https://tpdp.cse.buffalo.edu/2019/">TPDP 2019</a>, co-located with CCS 2019 in London. I’ll spare you the full details (click the link for more information), but most pressing is the deadline tomorrow, June 21, 2019, anywhere on Earth (let me know if this presents hardship for you, and I can pass concerns on to the chair). Essentially anything related to the theory or practice of differential privacy is welcome. Submissions are limited to four pages in length and are lightly refereed, based on originality, relevance, interest, and clarity. There are no published proceedings, and previously published results are welcome. If you’ve been looking to get to know the community, consider either submitting or attending the workshop! </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-20T18:05:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-20T18:05:19Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://kamathematics.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Kamathematics</title>
      <updated>2020-02-11T22:21:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?p=23</id>
    <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/17/hello-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hello World!</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Welcome to my blog! My name is Gautam Kamath, and I just started as an assistant professor in computer science at the University of Waterloo (for more info, see About). This blog will, broadly speaking, be about topics relevant to those interested in the the theory of computer science, statistics, and machine learning. Posts will … <a class="more-link" href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/2019/06/17/hello-world/">Continue reading<span class="screen-reader-text"> "Hello World!"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Welcome to my blog! My name is Gautam Kamath, and I just started as an assistant professor in computer science at the University of Waterloo (for more info, see <a href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/about/">About</a>).</p>



<p>This blog will, broadly speaking, be about topics relevant to those interested in the the theory of computer science, statistics, and machine learning. Posts will range from technical, to informational, to meta (read: basically whatever I want to write about, but I’ll do my best to keep it topical). Stay tuned!</p>



<p>The unofficial theme song of this blog is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8Ir-zFC9nFE">“Mathematics” by Mos Def</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-06-17T23:42:13Z</updated>
    <published>2019-06-17T23:42:13Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://kamathematics.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://kamathematics.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Kamathematics</title>
      <updated>2020-02-11T22:21:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
