<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-10-08T08:22:19Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02851</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02851" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>ER-index: a referential index for encrypted genomic databases</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Montecuollo:Ferdinando.html">Ferdinando Montecuollo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schmid:Giovannni.html">Giovannni Schmid</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02851">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Huge DBMSs storing genomic information are being created and engineerized for
doing large-scale, comprehensive and in-depth analysis of human beings and
their diseases. However, recent regulations like the GDPR require that
sensitive data are stored and elaborated thanks to privacy-by-design methods
and software. We designed and implemented ER-index, a new full-text index in
minute space which was optimized for compressing and encrypting collections of
genomic sequences, and for performing on them fast pattern-search queries. Our
new index complements the E2FM-index, which was introduced to compress and
encrypt collections of nucleotide sequences without relying on a reference
sequence. When used on collections of highly similar sequences, the ER-index
allows to obtain compression ratios which are an order of magnitude smaller
than those achieved with the E2FM-index, but maintaining its very good search
performance. Moreover, thanks to the ER-index multi-user and multiple-keys
encryption model, a single index can store the sequences related to a
population of individuals so that users may perform search operations only on
the sequences to which they were granted access. The ER-index C++ source code
plus scripts and data to assess the tool performance are available at:
https://github.com/EncryptedIndexes/erindex.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02665</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02665" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faster Minimum k-cut of a Simple Graph</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Jason.html">Jason Li</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02665">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the (exact, minimum) $k$-cut problem: given a graph and an
integer $k$, delete a minimum-weight set of edges so that the remaining graph
has at least $k$ connected components. This problem is a natural generalization
of the global minimum cut problem, where the goal is to break the graph into
$k=2$ pieces.
</p>
<p>Our main result is a (combinatorial) $k$-cut algorithm on simple graphs that
runs in $n^{(1+o(1))k}$ time for any constant $k$, improving upon the
previously best $n^{(2\omega/3+o(1))k}$ time algorithm of Gupta et
al.~[FOCS'18] and the previously best $n^{(1.981+o(1))k}$ time combinatorial
algorithm of Gupta et al.~[STOC'19]. For combinatorial algorithms, this
algorithm is optimal up to $o(1)$ factors assuming recent hardness conjectures:
we show by a straightforward reduction that $k$-cut on even a simple graph is
as hard as $(k-1)$-clique, establishing a lower bound of $n^{(1-o(1))k}$ for
$k$-cut. This settles, up to lower-order factors, the complexity of $k$-cut on
a simple graph for combinatorial algorithms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02639</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02639" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Finding Neighbors in a Forest: A b-tree for Smoothed Particle Hydrodynamics Simulations</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cavelan:Aur=eacute=lien.html">Aurélien Cavelan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cabez=oacute=n:Rub=eacute=n_M=.html">Rubén M. Cabezón</a>, Jonas H. M. Korndorfer, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Ciorba:Florina_M=.html">Florina M. Ciorba</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02639">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Finding the exact close neighbors of each fluid element in mesh-free
computational hydrodynamical methods, such as the Smoothed Particle
Hydrodynamics (SPH), often becomes a main bottleneck for scaling their
performance beyond a few million fluid elements per computing node. Tree
structures are particularly suitable for SPH simulation codes, which rely on
finding the exact close neighbors of each fluid element (or SPH particle). In
this work we present a novel tree structure, named \textit{$b$-tree}, which
features an adaptive branching factor to reduce the depth of the neighbor
search. Depending on the particle spatial distribution, finding neighbors using
\tree has an asymptotic best case complexity of $O(n)$, as opposed to $O(n \log
n)$ for other classical tree structures such as octrees and quadtrees. We also
present the proposed tree structure as well as the algorithms to build it and
to find the exact close neighbors of all particles. We assess the scalability
of the proposed tree-based algorithms through an extensive set of performance
experiments in a shared-memory system. Results show that b-tree is up to
$12\times$ faster for building the tree and up to $1.6\times$ faster for
finding the exact neighbors of all particles when compared to its octree form.
Moreover, we apply b-tree to a SPH code and show its usefulness over the
existing octree implementation, where b-tree is up to $5\times$ faster for
finding the exact close neighbors compared to the legacy code.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02611</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02611" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>RAMBO: Repeated And Merged Bloom Filter for Multiple Set Membership Testing (MSMT) in Sub-linear time</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gupta:Gaurav.html">Gaurav Gupta</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Coleman:Benjamin.html">Benjamin Coleman</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Medini:Tharun.html">Tharun Medini</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mohan:Vijai.html">Vijai Mohan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Shrivastava:Anshumali.html">Anshumali Shrivastava</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02611">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Approximate set membership is a common problem with wide applications in
databases, networking, and search. Given a set S and a query q, the task is to
determine whether q in S. The Bloom Filter (BF) is a popular data structure for
approximate membership testing due to its simplicity. In particular, a BF
consists of a bit array that can be incrementally updated. A related problem
concerning this paper is the Multiple Set Membership Testing (MSMT) problem.
Here we are given K different sets, and for any given query q the goal is the
find all of the sets containing the query element. Trivially, a multiple set
membership instance can be reduced to K membership testing instances, each with
the same q, leading to O(K) query time. A simple array of Bloom Filters can
achieve that. In this paper, we show the first non-trivial data-structure for
streaming keys, RAMBO (Repeated And Merged Bloom Filter) that achieves expected
O(sqrt(K) logK) query time with an additional worst case memory cost factor of
O(logK) than the array of Bloom Filters. The proposed data-structure is simply
a count-min sketch arrangement of Bloom Filters and retains all its favorable
properties. We replace the addition operation with a set union and the minimum
operation with a set intersection during estimation.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02598</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02598" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>BiLQ: An Iterative Method for Nonsymmetric Linear Systems with a Quasi-Minimum Error Property</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Alexis Montoison, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Orban:Dominique.html">Dominique Orban</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02598">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We introduce an iterative method named BiLQ for solving general square linear
systems Ax = b based on the Lanczos biorthogonalization process defined by
least-norm subproblems, and that is a natural companion to BiCG and QMR.
Whereas the BiCG (Fletcher, 1976), CGS (Sonneveld, 1989) and BiCGSTAB (van der
Vorst, 1992) iterates may not exist when the tridiagonal projection of A is
singular, BiLQ is reliable on compatible systems even if A is ill-conditioned
or rank deficient. As in the symmetric case, the BiCG residual is often smaller
than the BiLQ residual and, when the BiCG iterate exists, an inexpensive
transfer from the BiLQ iterate is possible. Although the Euclidean norm of the
BiLQ error is usually not monotonic, it is monotonic in a different norm that
depends on the Lanczos vectors. We establish a similar property for the QMR
(Freund and Nachtigal, 1991) residual. BiLQ combines with QMR to take advantage
of two initial vectors and solve a system and an adjoint system simultaneously
at a cost similar to that of applying either method. We derive an analogous
combination of USYMLQ and USYMQR based on the orthogonal tridiagonalization
process (Saunders, Simon, and Yip, 1988). The resulting combinations, named
BiLQR and TriLQR, may be used to estimate integral functionals involving the
solution of a primal and an adjoint system. We compare BiLQR and TriLQR with
Minres-qlp on a related augmented system, which performs a comparable amount of
work and requires comparable storage. In our experiments, BiLQR terminates
earlier than TriLQR and MINRES-QLP in terms of residual and error of the primal
and adjoint systems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02590</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02590" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>No-Signaling Proofs with $O(\sqrt{\log n})$ Provers are in PSPACE</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Holden:Dhiraj.html">Dhiraj Holden</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kalai:Yael.html">Yael Kalai</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02590">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>No-signaling proofs, motivated by quantum computation, have found
applications in cryptography and hardness of approximation. An important open
problem is characterizing the power of no-signaling proofs. It is known that
2-prover no-signaling proofs are characterized by PSPACE, and that no-signaling
proofs with $poly(n)$-provers are characterized by EXP. However, the power of
$k$-prover no-signaling proofs, for $2&lt;k&lt;poly(n)$ remained an open problem.
</p>
<p>We show that $k$-prover no-signaling proofs (with negligible soundness) for
$k=O(\sqrt{\log n})$ are contained in PSPACE. We prove this via two different
routes that are of independent interest. In both routes we consider a
relaxation of no-signaling called sub-no-signaling. Our main technical
contribution (which is used in both our proofs) is a reduction showing how to
convert any sub-no-signaling strategy with value at least $1-2^{-\Omega(k^2)}$
into a no-signaling one with value at least $2^{-O(k^2)}$.
</p>
<p>In the first route, we show that the classical prover reduction method for
converting $k$-prover games into $2$-prover games carries over to the
no-signaling setting with the following loss in soundness: if a $k$-player game
has value less than $2^{-ck^2}$ (for some constant~$c&gt;0$), then the
corresponding 2-prover game has value at most $1 - 2^{dk^2}$ (for some
constant~$d&gt;0$). In the second route we show that the value of a
sub-no-signaling game can be approximated in space that is polynomial in the
communication complexity and exponential in the number of provers.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T01:20:42Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02569</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02569" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Understanding Zadimoghaddam's Edge-weighted Online Matching Algorithm: Unweighted Case</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Huang:Zhiyi.html">Zhiyi Huang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tao:Runzhou.html">Runzhou Tao</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02569">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This article identifies a key algorithmic ingredient in the edge-weighted
online matching algorithm by Zadimoghaddam (2017) and presents a simplified
algorithm and its analysis to demonstrate how it works in the unweighted case.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02478</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02478" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Exact and/or Fast Nearest Neighbors</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Francis=Landau:Matthew.html">Matthew Francis-Landau</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Durme:Benjamin_Van.html">Benjamin Van Durme</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02478">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Prior methods for retrieval of nearest neighbors in high dimensions are fast
and approximate--providing probabilistic guarantees of returning the correct
answer--or slow and exact performing an exhaustive search. We present Certified
Cosine, a novel approach to nearest-neighbors which takes advantage of
structure present in the cosine similarity distance metric to offer
certificates. When a certificate is constructed, it guarantees that the nearest
neighbor set is correct, possibly avoiding an exhaustive search. Certified
Cosine's certificates work with high dimensional data and outperform previous
exact nearest neighbor methods on these datasets.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T01:31:08Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02470</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02470" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Approximation algorithms for maximally balanced connected graph partition</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Yong.html">Yong Chen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Zhi=Zhong.html">Zhi-Zhong Chen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lin:Guohui.html">Guohui Lin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xu:Yao.html">Yao Xu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:An.html">An Zhang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02470">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a simple connected graph $G = (V, E)$, we seek to partition the vertex
set $V$ into $k$ non-empty parts such that the subgraph induced by each part is
connected, and the partition is maximally balanced in the way that the maximum
cardinality of these $k$ parts is minimized. We refer this problem to as {\em
min-max balanced connected graph partition} into $k$ parts and denote it as
{\sc $k$-BGP}. The general vertex-weighted version of this problem on trees has
been studied since about four decades ago, which admits a linear time exact
algorithm; the vertex-weighted {\sc $2$-BGP} and {\sc $3$-BGP} admit a
$5/4$-approximation and a $3/2$-approximation, respectively; but no
approximability result exists for {\sc $k$-BGP} when $k \ge 4$, except a
trivial $k$-approximation. In this paper, we present another
$3/2$-approximation for our cardinality {\sc $3$-BGP} and then extend it to
become a $k/2$-approximation for {\sc $k$-BGP}, for any constant $k \ge 3$.
Furthermore, for {\sc $4$-BGP}, we propose an improved $24/13$-approximation.
To these purposes, we have designed several local improvement operations, which
could be useful for related graph partition problems.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T01:22:37Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02465</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02465" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the Probabilistic Degrees of Symmetric Boolean functions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Srinivasan:Srikanth.html">Srikanth Srinivasan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tripathi:Utkarsh.html">Utkarsh Tripathi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Venkitesh:S=.html">S. Venkitesh</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02465">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The probabilistic degree of a Boolean function $f:\{0,1\}^n\rightarrow
\{0,1\}$ is defined to be the smallest $d$ such that there is a random
polynomial $\mathbf{P}$ of degree at most $d$ that agrees with $f$ at each
point with high probability. Introduced by Razborov (1987), upper and lower
bounds on probabilistic degrees of Boolean functions --- specifically symmetric
Boolean functions --- have been used to prove explicit lower bounds, design
pseudorandom generators, and devise algorithms for combinatorial problems.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we characterize the probabilistic degrees of all symmetric
Boolean functions up to polylogarithmic factors over all fields of fixed
characteristic (positive or zero).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T01:21:18Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02459</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02459" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fast Detection of Outliers in Data Streams with the $Q_n$ Estimator</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cafaro:Massimo.html">Massimo Cafaro</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Melle:Catiuscia.html">Catiuscia Melle</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pulimeno:Marco.html">Marco Pulimeno</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Epicoco:Italo.html">Italo Epicoco</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02459">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present FQN (Fast $Q_n$), a novel algorithm for fast detection of outliers
in data streams. The algorithm works in the sliding window model, checking if
an item is an outlier by cleverly computing the $Q_n$ scale estimator in the
current window. We thoroughly compare our algorithm for online $Q_n$ with the
state of the art competing algorithm by Nunkesser et al, and show that FQN (i)
is faster, (ii) its computational complexity does not depend on the input
distribution and (iii) it requires less space. Extensive experimental results
on synthetic datasets confirm the validity of our approach.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02438</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02438" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Discovering Polarized Communities in Signed Networks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bonchi:Francesco.html">Francesco Bonchi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Galimberti:Edoardo.html">Edoardo Galimberti</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gionis:Aristides.html">Aristides Gionis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Ordozgoiti:Bruno.html">Bruno Ordozgoiti</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ruffo:Giancarlo.html">Giancarlo Ruffo</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02438">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Signed networks contain edge annotations to indicate whether each interaction
is friendly (positive edge) or antagonistic (negative edge). The model is
simple but powerful and it can capture novel and interesting structural
properties of real-world phenomena. The analysis of signed networks has many
applications from modeling discussions in social media, to mining user reviews,
and to recommending products in e-commerce sites. In this paper we consider the
problem of discovering polarized communities in signed networks. In particular,
we search for two communities (subsets of the network vertices) where within
communities there are mostly positive edges while across communities there are
mostly negative edges. We formulate this novel problem as a "discrete
eigenvector" problem, which we show to be NP-hard. We then develop two
intuitive spectral algorithms: one deterministic, and one randomized with
quality guarantee $\sqrt{n}$ (where $n$ is the number of vertices in the
graph), tight up to constant factors. We validate our algorithms against
non-trivial baselines on real-world signed networks. Our experiments confirm
that our algorithms produce higher quality solutions, are much faster and can
scale to much larger networks than the baselines, and are able to detect
ground-truth polarized communities.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02351</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02351" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Clustering case statements for indirect branch predictors</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Evandro Menezes, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pop:Sebastian.html">Sebastian Pop</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kumar:Aditya.html">Aditya Kumar</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02351">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present an O(nlogn) algorithm to compile a switch statement into jump
tables. To generate jump tables that can be efficiently predicted by current
hardware branch predictors, we added an upper bound on the number of entries
for each table. This modification of the previously best known algorithm
reduces the complexity from O(n^2) to O(nlogn).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02248</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02248" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A new algorithm for graph center computation and graph partitioning according to the distance to the center</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Frédéric Protin <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02248">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We propose a new algorithm for finding the center of a graph, as well as the
rank of each node in the hierarchy of distances to the center. In other words,
our algorithm allows to partition the graph according to nodes distance to the
center. Moreover, the algorithm is parallelizable. We compare the performances
of our algorithm with the ones of Floyd-Warshall algorithm, which is
traditionally used for these purposes. We show that, for a large variety of
graphs, our algorithm outperforms the Floyd-Warshall algorithm.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02179</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02179" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Template-based Minor Embedding for Adiabatic Quantum Optimization</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Serra:Thiago.html">Thiago Serra</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Huang:Teng.html">Teng Huang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Raghunathan:Arvind.html">Arvind Raghunathan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bergman:David.html">David Bergman</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02179">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Quantum Annealing (QA) can be used to quickly obtain near-optimal solutions
for Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) problems. In QA
hardware, each decision variable of a QUBO should be mapped to one or more
adjacent qubits in such a way that pairs of variables defining a quadratic term
in the objective function are mapped to some pair of adjacent qubits. However,
qubits have limited connectivity in existing QA hardware. This has spurred work
on preprocessing algorithms for embedding the graph representing problem
variables with quadratic terms in the hardware graph representing qubits
adjacencies, such as the Chimera graph in hardware produced by D-Wave
Systems.In this paper, we use integer linear programming to search for an
embedding of the problem graph into certain classes of minors of the Chimera
graph, which we call template embeddings. One of these classes corresponds to
complete bipartite graphs, for which we show the limitation of the existing
approach based on minimum Odd Cycle Transversals (OCTs). Some of the
formulations presented are exact, and thus can be used to certify the absence
of a minor embedding. On an extensive test set consisting of random graphs from
five different classes of varying size and sparsity, we can embed 38% more
graphs than a state-of-the-art OCT-based approach.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02151</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02151" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Towards a Definitive Measure of Repetitiveness</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kociumaka:Tomasz.html">Tomasz Kociumaka</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Navarro:Gonzalo.html">Gonzalo Navarro</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Prezza:Nicola.html">Nicola Prezza</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02151">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Unlike in statistical compression, where Shannon's entropy is a definitive
lower bound, no such a clear measure exists for the compressibility of
repetitive sequences other than the uncomputable Kolmogorov's complexity. Since
statistical entropy does not capture repetitiveness, ad-hoc measures like the
size $z$ of the Lempel-Ziv parse are frequently used to estimate it. Recently,
a more principled measure, the size $\gamma$ of the smallest {\em attractor} of
a string $S[1..n]$, was introduced. Measure $\gamma$ lower bounds all the
previous relevant ones (e.g., $z$), yet $S$ can be represented and indexed
within space $O(\gamma\log(n/\gamma))$, which also upper bounds most measures.
While $\gamma$ is certainly a better measure of repetitiveness, it is
NP-complete to compute, and it is not known if $S$ can always be represented in
$O(\gamma)$ space.
</p>
<p>In this paper we study a smaller measure, $\delta \le \gamma$, which can be
computed in linear time. We show that $\delta$ captures better the concept of
compressibility in repetitive strings: We prove that, for some string families,
it holds $\gamma = \Omega(\delta \log n)$. Still, we can build a representation
of $S$ of size $O(\delta\log(n/\delta))$, which supports direct access to any
$S[i]$ in time $O(\log(n/\delta))$ and finds the $occ$ occurrences of any
pattern $P[1..m]$ in time $O(m\log n + occ\log^\epsilon n)$ for any constant
$\epsilon&gt;0$. Further, such representation is worst-case optimal because, in
some families, $S$ can only be represented in $\Omega(\delta\log n)$ space. We
complete our characterization of $\delta$ by showing that $\gamma$, $z$ and
other measures of repetitiveness are always $O(\delta\log(n/\delta))$, but in
some string families, the smallest context-free grammar is of size
$g=\Omega(\delta \log^2 n / \log\log n)$. No such a lower bound is known to
hold for $\gamma$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T01:35:24Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02145</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02145" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Types for Parallel Complexity in the Pi-calculus</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Baillot:Patrick.html">Patrick Baillot</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Ghyselen:Alexis.html">Alexis Ghyselen</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02145">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Type systems as a way to control or analyze programs have been largely
studied in the context of functional programming languages. Some of those work
allow to extract from a typing derivation for a program a complexity bound on
this program. We present how to adapt this result for parallel complexity in
the pi-calculus, as a model of concurrency and parallel communication. We study
two notions of time complexity: the total computation time without parallelism
(the work) and the computation time under maximal parallelism (the span). We
define reduction relations in the pi-calculus to capture those two notions, and
we present two type systems from which one can extract a complexity bound on a
process. The type systems are inspired by input/output types and size types,
with temporal information about communications.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02123</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02123" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Maximum Matchings in Geometric Intersection Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bonnet:=Eacute=douard.html">Édouard Bonnet</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cabello:Sergio.html">Sergio Cabello</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mulzer:Wolfgang.html">Wolfgang Mulzer</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02123">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Let $G$ be an intersection graph of $n$ geometric objects in the plane. We
show that a maximum matching in $G$ can be found in
$O(\rho^{3\omega/2}n^{\omega/2})$ time with high probability, where $\rho$ is
the density of the geometric objects and $\omega&gt;2$ is a constant such that $n
\times n$ matrices can be multiplied in $O(n^\omega)$ time. The same result
holds for any subgraph of $G$, as long as a geometric representation is at
hand. For this, we combine algebraic methods, namely computing the rank of a
matrix via Gaussian elimination, with the fact that geometric intersection
graphs have small separators. We also show that in many interesting cases, the
maximum matching problem in a general geometric intersection graph can be
reduced to the case of bounded density. In particular, a maximum matching in
the intersection graph of any family of translates of a convex object in the
plane can be found in $O(n^{\omega/2})$ time with high probability, and a
maximum matching in the intersection graph of a family of planar disks with
radii in $[1, \Psi]$ can be found in $O(\Psi^6\log^{11} n + \Psi^{12 \omega}
n^{\omega/2})$ time with high probability.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01753</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01753" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On Computing a Center Persistence Diagram</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Higashikawa:Yuya.html">Yuya Higashikawa</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Katoh:Naoki.html">Naoki Katoh</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lin:Guohui.html">Guohui Lin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Miyano:Eiji.html">Eiji Miyano</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tamaki:Suguru.html">Suguru Tamaki</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Teruyama:Junichi.html">Junichi Teruyama</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhu:Binhai.html">Binhai Zhu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01753">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a set of persistence diagrams ${\cal P}_1,...,{\cal P}_m$, for the data
reduction purpose, one way to summarize their topological features is to
compute the {\em center} ${\cal C}$ of them. Let $P_i$ be the set of feature
points in ${\cal P}_i$. Here we mainly focus on the two discrete versions when
points in ${\cal C}$ could be selected with or without replacement from
$P_i$'s. (We will briefly discuss the continuous case, i.e., points in ${\cal
C}$ are arbitrary, which turns out to be closely related to the 3-dimensional
geometric assignment problem). For technical reasons, we first focus on the
case when $|P_i|$'s are all the same (i.e., all have the same size $n$), and
the problem is to compute a center point set $C$ under the bottleneck matching
distance. We show, by a non-trivial reduction from the Planar 3D-Matching
problem, that this problem is NP-hard even when $m=3$. This implies that the
general center problem for persistence diagrams, when $P_i$'s possibly have
different sizes, is also NP-hard when $m\geq 3$. On the positive side, we show
that this problem is polynomially solvable when $m=2$ and admits a factor-2
approximation for $m\geq 3$. These positive results hold for any $L_p$ metric
when $P_i$'s are point sets of the same size, and also hold for the case when
$P_i$'s have different sizes in the $L_\infty$ metric (i.e., for the center
persistence diagram problem). This is the best possible in polynomial time
unless P = NP. All these results hold for both of the discrete versions.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.03113</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1906.03113" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal algebraic Breadth-First Search for sparse graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570492800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Burkhardt:Paul.html">Paul Burkhardt</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.03113">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>There has been a rise in the popularity of algebraic methods for graph
algorithms given the development of the GraphBLAS library and other sparse
matrix methods. An exemplar for these approaches is Breadth-First Search (BFS).
The algebraic BFS algorithm is simply a recursion of matrix-vector
multiplications with the $n \times n$ adjacency matrix, but the many redundant
operations over nonzeros ultimately lead to suboptimal performance. Therefore
an optimal algebraic BFS should be of keen interest especially if it is easily
integrated with existing matrix methods.
</p>
<p>Current methods, notably in the GraphBLAS, use a Sparse Matrix Sparse Vector
(SpMSpV) multiplication in which the input vector is kept in a sparse
representation in each step of the BFS. But simply applying SpMSpV in BFS does
not lead to optimal runtime. Each nonzero in the vector must be masked in
subsequent steps. This has been an area of recent research in GraphBLAS and
other libraries. While in theory these masking methods are asymptotically
optimal on sparse graphs, many add work that leads to suboptimal runtime. We
give a new optimal, algebraic BFS for sparse graphs that is also a constant
factor faster than theoretically optimal SpMSpV methods, closing a gap in the
literature.
</p>
<p>Our method multiplies progressively smaller submatrices of the adjacency
matrix at each step, taking $O(m)$ algebraic operations on a sparse graph of
$O(m)$ edges as opposed to $O(mn)$ operations of other sparse matrix
approaches. Thus for sparse graphs it matches the bounds of the best-known
sequential algorithm and on a Parallel Random Access Machine (PRAM) it is
work-optimal. Compared to a leading GraphBLAS library our method achieves up to
24x faster sequential time and for parallel computation it can be 17x faster on
large graphs and 12x faster on large-diameter graphs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/10/07/drawing-clustered-graphs</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/10/07/drawing-clustered-graphs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Drawing clustered graphs of bounded width</title>
    <summary>In a paper from last year on clustered planarity, with Giordano Da Lozzo, Mike Goodrich, and Sid Gupta, we provided subexponential-time algorithms for arbitrary instances, and fixed-parameter tractable algorithms for instances whose embedded width and number of clusters are both bounded.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2018/03/16/drawing-clustered-graphs.html">a paper from last year</a> on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clustered_planarity">clustered planarity</a>, with Giordano Da Lozzo, Mike Goodrich, and Sid Gupta, we provided subexponential-time algorithms for arbitrary instances, and fixed-parameter tractable algorithms for instances whose embedded width and number of clusters are both bounded.</p>

<p>Now, in my newest preprint, “C-planarity testing of embedded clustered graphs with bounded dual carving-width” (with the same authors, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02057">arXiv:1910.02057</a>), we’ve eliminated the dependence on the number of clusters (using a different width parameter) and found a fixed-parameter tractable algorithm with just a single parameter.</p>

<p>It was just in time: while our paper was in submission, last July, Rado Fulek and Csaba Tóth put up their own preprint, “Atomic embeddability, clustered planarity, and thickenability” (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.13086">arXiv:1907.13086</a>) announcing a solution to the clustered planarity problem in polynomial time without dependence on parameters. I <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102537368093048271">posted about it briefly at the time</a>, and can’t find much else more recent about it, but I assume it’s in submission to somewhere good. So our results may be only of historic value…</p>

<p>Our paper was presented at IPEC 2019 (part of the <a href="http://algo2019.ak.in.tum.de/">ALGO 2019 conference in Munich</a>) last month, and won IPEC best paper award. The late timing of the preprint is because (somewhat unusually for a CS conference) IPEC makes their proceedings versions due after the conference rather than before, so they can take into account feedback from the conference.
The arXiv version is more complete than the proceedings version will be, because of page limits in the proceedings, but we prepared it at the same time.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102925193159020982">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-07T22:33:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-07T22:33:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T05:51:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3430</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/10/07/videos-from-papafest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Videos from PapaFest</title>
    <summary>Videos of all PapaFest talks and panels are here. Advertisements</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Videos of all PapaFest talks and panels are <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OX2I00QVPDI&amp;list=PLPldBy2vuDR9gp98jsowJQFn6jtpZatU0">here</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-07T21:28:05Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-07T21:28:05Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>timroughgarden</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T08:20:48Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-1096889632414067693</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/1096889632414067693/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/10/what-comes-first-theory-or-practice-its.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1096889632414067693" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1096889632414067693" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/10/what-comes-first-theory-or-practice-its.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What comes first theory or practice? Its Complicated!</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Having majored in pure math I had the impression that usually the theory comes first and then someone works out something to work in practice. While this is true sometimes it is often NOT true and this will not surprise any of my blog readers.  Even so, I want to tell you about some times it surprised me. This says more about my ignorance than about math or applications or whatnot.<br/>
<br/>
1) Quantum<br/>
<br/>
a) Factoring was proven to be in BQP way before actual quantum computers could do this in reasonable time (we're still waiting).<br/>
<br/>
b) Quantum Crypto- This really is out there. I do not know what came first, the theory or the practice. Or if they were in tandem.<br/>
<br/>
c) (this one is the inspiration for the post)  When I first heard the term <i>Quantum Supremacy</i> I thought it meant the desire for a THEOREM that problem A is in BQP but is provably not in P.  For example, if someone proved factoring is not in P (unlikely this will be proven, and hey- maybe  factoring is in P). Perhaps some contrived problem like those constructed by diagonalization (my spell checker thinks that's not a word. Having worked in computability theory, I think it is. Darn- my spellchecker thinks computability is not word.) Hence when I heard that Google had a paper proving Quantum Supremacy (I do not recall if I actually heard the word  <i>proven) </i>I assumed that there was some <i>theoretical </i>breakthrough. I was surprised and not in the slightest disappointed to find out it involved actual quantum computers.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Question</b>: When the term <i>Quantum Supremacy</i> was first coined, did they mean theoretical, or IRL, or both?<br/>
<br/>
2) Ramsey Theory<br/>
<br/>
a) For Ramsey's Theorem and Van Der waerden's theorem and Rado's theorem and others I could name, first a theorem showed a upper bound on a number, then later computers and perhaps some math got better bounds on that number.<br/>
<br/>
b) Consider the following statement:<br/>
<br/>
For all c there exists P such that for all c-colorings of {1,...,P} there exists x,y,z the same color such that x<sup>2</sup> +y<sup>2</sup> = z<sup>2</sup>.<br/>
<br/>
Ronald Graham conjectured the c=2 case and offered $100 in the 1980's. (I do not know if he had any comment on the general case.)  I assumed that it would be proven with ginormous bounds on the P(c) function, and then perhaps some reasonable bound would be found by clever programming and some math. (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boolean_Pythagorean_triples_problem">here</a> for the Wikipedia Entry about the problem, which also has pointers to other material).<br/>
<br/>
Instead the c=2 case was proven with an exact bound, P(2)=7825, by a computer program, in 2016. The proof is 200 terabytes. So my prediction was incorrect.<br/>
<br/>
As for the result<br/>
<br/>
PRO: We know the result is true for c=2 and we even know the exact bound. Wow! and for Ramsey Theory its unusual to have exact bounds!<br/>
<br/>
CON: It would be good to have a human-readable proof. This is NOT an anti-technology statement. For one thing, a human-readable proof might help us get the result for c=3 and beyond.<br/>
<br/>
3) This item is a cheat in that I knew the empirical results first. However, I will tell you what I am sure I would have thought (and been wrong) had I not know them.<br/>
<br/>
Given k, does the equation<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
x<sup>3</sup> +y<sup>3</sup> +z<sup>3</sup> = k<br/>
<br/>
have a solution in Z? I would have thought that some hard number theory would determine<br/>
for which k it has a solution (with a proof that does not give the actual solutions)  and for then a computer programs would try to find the solutions. Instead (1) some values of k are ruled out by simple mod considerations, and (2) as for the rest, computers have found solutions for some of them. Lipton-Regan (<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/09/30/writing-33-as-a-sum-of-cubes/">here</a>) and Gasarch (<a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/x-3-y-3-z-3-33-has-solution-in-z-and.html">here</a>) have blogged about the k=33 case. Lipton-Regan also comment on the more recent k=42 case.<br/>
<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-07T13:56:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-07T13:56:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T02:19:23Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/07/culty-positions-at-the-rank-of-associate-and-assistant-professor-in-machine-learning-and-data-science-at-maersk-mc-kinney-moller-institute-faculty-of-engineering-university-of-southern-denmark-appl/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/07/culty-positions-at-the-rank-of-associate-and-assistant-professor-in-machine-learning-and-data-science-at-maersk-mc-kinney-moller-institute-faculty-of-engineering-university-of-southern-denmark-appl/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>culty Positions at the rank of Associate and Assistant Professor in machine learning and data science at Maersk Mc-Kinney Moller Institute, Faculty of Engineering, University of Southern Denmark (apply by November 3, 2019)</title>
    <summary>he Group of Machine Learning and Data Science (part of Embodied Systems for Robotics and Learning) at the Maersk Mc-Kinney Moller Institute, Faculty of Engineering, University of Southern Denmark, invites applications for Faculty positions at the rank of Associate (permanent) and Assistant (3-year period) Professor. Website: https://www.sdu.dk/en/service/ledige_stillinger/1063846 Email: esi@mmmi.sdu.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>he Group of Machine Learning and Data Science (part of Embodied Systems for Robotics and Learning) at the Maersk Mc-Kinney Moller Institute, Faculty of Engineering, University of Southern Denmark, invites applications for Faculty positions at the rank of Associate (permanent) and Assistant (3-year period) Professor.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.sdu.dk/en/service/ledige_stillinger/1063846">https://www.sdu.dk/en/service/ledige_stillinger/1063846</a><br/>
Email: esi@mmmi.sdu.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-07T10:05:47Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-07T10:05:47Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T08:21:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4361</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4361" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4361#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4361" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Book Review: ‘The AI Does Not Hate You’ by Tom Chivers</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">A couple weeks ago I read The AI Does Not Hate You: Superintelligence, Rationality, and the Race to Save the World, the first-ever book-length examination of the modern rationalist community, by British journalist Tom Chivers. I was planning to review it here, before it got preempted by the news of quantum supremacy (and subsequent news […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A couple weeks ago I read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Rationalists-Artificial-Intelligence-Geeks-World/dp/1474608779/ref=tmm_hrd_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;qid=&amp;sr=">The AI Does Not Hate You: Superintelligence, Rationality, and the Race to Save the World</a>, the first-ever book-length examination of the modern <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Rationalist_movement">rationalist community</a>, by British journalist <a href="https://twitter.com/TomChivers?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor">Tom Chivers</a>.  I was planning to review it here, before it got preempted by the news of <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4317">quantum supremacy</a> (and subsequent news of <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4342">classical non-supremacy</a>).  Now I can get back to rationalists.</p>



<p>Briefly, I think the book is a triumph.  It’s based around in-person conversations with many of the notable figures in and around the rationalist community, in its Bay Area epicenter and beyond (although apparently <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eliezer_Yudkowsky">Eliezer Yudkowsky</a> only agreed to answer technical questions by Skype), together of course with the voluminous material available online.  There’s a good deal about the 1990s origins of the community that I hadn’t previously known.</p>



<p>The title is taken from Eliezer’s aphorism, “The AI does not hate you, nor does it love you, but you are made of atoms which it can use for something else.”  In other words: as soon as anyone succeeds in building a superhuman AI, if we don’t take extreme care that the AI’s values are “aligned” with human ones, the AI might be expected to obliterate humans almost instantly as a byproduct of pursuing whatever it <em>does</em> value, more-or-less as we humans did with woolly mammoths, moas, and now gorillas, rhinos, and thousands of other species.</p>



<p>Much of the book relates Chivers’s personal quest to figure out how seriously he should take this scenario.  Are the rationalists just an unusually nerdy doomsday cult?  Is there some non-negligible chance that they’re actually right about the AI thing?  If so, how much more time do we have—and is there even anything meaningful that can be done today?  Do the dramatic advances in machine learning over the past decade change the outlook?  Should Chivers be worried about his own two children?  How does this risk compare to the more “prosaic” civilizational risks, like climate change or nuclear war?  I suspect that Chivers’s exploration will be most interesting to readers who, like me, regard the answers to <em>none</em> of these questions as obvious.</p>



<p>While it sounds extremely basic, what makes <em>The AI Does Not Hate You</em> so valuable to my mind is that, as far as I know, it’s nearly the only examination of the rationalists ever written by an outsider that tries to assess the ideas on a scale from true to false, rather than from quirky to offensive.  Chivers’s own training in academic philosophy seems to have been crucial here.  He’s not put off by people who act weirdly around him, even needlessly cold or aloof, nor by utilitarian thought experiments involving death or torture or weighing the value of human lives.  He just cares, relentlessly, about the ideas—and about remaining a basically grounded and decent person while engaging them.  Most strikingly, Chivers clearly feels a need—anachronistic though it seems in 2019—actually to <em>understand</em> complicated arguments, be able to repeat them back correctly, before he attacks them.</p>



<p>Indeed, far from failing to understand the rationalists, it occurs to me that the central criticism of Chivers’s book is likely to be just the opposite: he understands the rationalists so well, extends them so much sympathy, and ends up endorsing so many aspects of their worldview, that he must simply <em>be</em> a closet rationalist himself, and therefore can’t write about them with any pretense of journalistic or anthropological detachment.  For my part, I’d say: it’s true that <em>The AI Does Not Hate You</em> is what you get if you treat rationalists as extremely smart (if unusual) people from whom you might learn something of consequence, rather than as monkeys in a zoo.  On the other hand, Chivers does perform the journalist’s task of constantly challenging the rationalists he meets, often with points that (if upheld) would be fatal to their worldview.  One of the rationalists’ best features—and this precisely matches my own experience—is that, far from clamming up or storming off when faced with such challenges (“lo! the visitor is not one of us!”), the rationalists positively relish them.</p>



<p>It occurred to me the other day that we’ll never know how the rationalists’ ideas would’ve developed, had they continued to do so in a cultural background like that of the late 20th century.  As Chivers points out, the rationalists today are effectively caught in the crossfire of a much larger cultural war—between, to their right, the recrudescent know-nothing authoritarians, and to their left, what one could variously describe as woke culture, call-out culture, or sneer culture.  On its face, it might seem laughable to conflate the rationalists with today’s resurgent fascists: many rationalists are driven by their utilitarianism to advocate open borders and massive aid to the Third World; the rationalist community is about as welcoming of alternative genders and sexualities as it’s humanly possible to be; and leading rationalists like Scott Alexander and Eliezer Yudkowsky strongly condemned Trump for the obvious reasons. </p>



<p>Chivers, however, explains how the problem started.  On rationalist Internet forums, many misogynists and white nationalists and so forth encountered nerds willing to <em>debate their ideas politely</em>, rather than immediately banning them as more mainstream venues would.  As a result, many of those forces of darkness (and they probably don’t mind being called that) predictably congregated on the rationalist forums, and their stench predictably wore off on the rationalists themselves.  Furthermore, this isn’t an easy-to-fix problem, because debating ideas on their merits, extending charity to ideological opponents, etc. is sort of the rationalists’ <em>entire shtick</em>, whereas denouncing and no-platforming anyone who can be connected to an ideological enemy (in the modern parlance, “punching Nazis”) is the entire shtick of those condemning the rationalists.</p>



<p>Compounding the problem is that, as anyone who’s ever hung out with STEM nerds might’ve guessed, the rationalist community tends to skew WASP, Asian, or Jewish, non-impoverished, and male.  Worse yet, while many rationalists live their lives in progressive enclaves and strongly support progressive values, they’ll also undergo extreme anguish if they feel forced to subordinate truth to those values.</p>



<p>Chivers writes that all of these issues “blew up in spectacular style at the end of 2014,” right here on this blog.  Oh, what the hell, I’ll just quote him:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Scott Aaronson is, I think it’s fair to say, a member of the Rationalist community.  He’s a prominent theoretical computer scientist at the University of Texas at Austin, and writes a very interesting, maths-heavy blog called Shtetl-Optimised.</p><p>People in the comments under his blog were discussing feminism and sexual harassment.  And Aaronson, in a comment in which he described himself as a fan of Andrea Dworkin, described having been terrified of speaking to women as a teenager and young man.  This fear was, he said, partly that of being thought of as a sexual abuser or creep if any woman ever became aware that he sexually desired them, a fear that he picked up from sexual-harassment-prevention workshops at his university and from reading feminist literature.  This fear became so overwhelming, he said in the comment that came to be known as Comment #171, that he had ‘constant suicidal thoughts’ and at one point ‘actually begged a psychiatrist to prescribe drugs that would chemically castrate me (I had researched which ones), because a life of mathematical asceticism was the only future that I could imagine for myself.’  So when he read feminist articles talking about the ‘male privilege’ of nerds like him, he didn’t recognise the description, and so felt himself able to declare himself ‘only’ 97 per cent on board with the programme of feminism.</p><p>It struck me as a thoughtful and rather sweet remark, in the midst of a long and courteous discussion with a female commenter.  But it got picked up, weirdly, by some feminist bloggers, including one who described it as ‘a yalp of entitlement combined with an aggressive unwillingness to accept that women are human beings just like men’ and that Aaronson was complaining that ‘having to explain my suffering to women when they should already be there, mopping my brow and offering me beers and blow jobs, is so tiresome.’</p><p>Scott Alexander (<em>not</em> Scott Aaronson) then wrote a furious 10,000-word defence of his friend… (p. 214-215)</p></blockquote>



<p>And then Chivers goes on to explain Scott Alexander’s central thesis, in <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/01/01/untitled/">Untitled</a>, that privilege is not a one-dimensional axis, so that (to take one example) society can make many women in STEM miserable while <em>also</em> making shy male nerds miserable in different ways.</p>



<p>For nerds, perhaps an alternative title for Chivers’s book could be “The Normal People Do Not Hate You (Not All of Them, Anyway).”  It’s as though Chivers is demonstrating, through understated example, that taking delight in nerds’ suffering, wanting them to be miserable and alone, mocking their weird ideas, is not simply the default, well-adjusted human reaction, with any other reaction being ‘creepy’ and ‘problematic.’  Some might even go so far as to apply the latter adjectives to the sneerers’ attitude, the one that dresses up schoolyard bullying in a social-justice wig.</p>



<p>Reading Chivers’s book prompted me to reflect on my own relationship to the rationalist community.  For years, I interacted often with the community—I’ve known Robin Hanson since ~2004 and Eliezer Yudkowsky since ~2006, and our blogs bounced off each other—but I never considered myself a member.  I never ranked <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instrumental_convergence#Paperclip_maximizer">paperclip-maximizing AIs</a> among humanity’s more urgent threats—indeed, I saw them as a distraction from an all-too-likely climate catastrophe that will leave its survivors lucky to have stone tools, let alone AIs.  I was also repelled by what I saw as the rationalists’ cultier aspects.  I even once toyed with the idea of changing the name of this blog to “More Wrong” or “Wallowing in Bias,” as a play on the rationalists’ <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/">LessWrong</a> and <a href="http://www.overcomingbias.com/">OvercomingBias</a>.</p>



<p>But I’ve drawn much closer to the community over the last few years, because of a combination of factors:</p>



<ol><li>The comment-171 affair.  This was not the sort of thing that could provide any new information about the likelihood of a dangerous AI being built, but <em>was</em> (to put it mildly) the sort of thing that can tell you who your friends are.  I learned that empathy works a lot like intelligence, in that those who boast of it most loudly are often the ones who lack it.</li><li>The astounding progress in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_learning">deep learning</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinforcement_learning">reinforcement learning</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generative_adversarial_network">GANs</a>, which caused me (like everyone else, perhaps) to update in the direction of human-level AI in our lifetimes being an actual live possibility.</li><li>The rise of <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/">Scott Alexander</a>.  To the charge that the rationalists are a cult, there’s now the reply that Scott, with his constant equivocations and doubts, his deep dives into data, his clarity and self-deprecating humor, is perhaps the least culty cult leader in human history.  Likewise, to the charge that the rationalists are basement-dwelling kibitzers who accomplish nothing of note in the real world, there’s now the reply that Scott has attracted a huge mainstream following (Steven Pinker, Paul Graham, presidential candidate Andrew Yang…), purely by offering up what’s self-evidently some of the best writing of our time.</li><li>Research.  <a href="https://intelligence.org/">MIRI</a> (the Machine Intelligence Research Institute) and <a href="https://openai.com/">OpenAI</a> are now publishing some research papers that I find interesting—some with <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1606.06565">relatively approachable problems</a> that I could see myself trying to think about if quantum computing ever got boring.  This shift seems to have happened at roughly around the same time my former student, <a href="https://paulfchristiano.com/">Paul Christiano</a>, “defected” from quantum computing to AI-risk research. </li></ol>



<p>Anyway, if you’ve spent years steeped in the rationalist blogosphere, read Eliezer’s <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Sequences">“Sequences,”</a> and so on, <em>The AI Does Not Hate You</em> will probably have little that’s new, although it might still be interesting to revisit ideas and episodes that you know through a newcomer’s eyes.  For anyone else … well, reading the book would be a lot faster than spending all those years reading blogs!  I’ve heard of some rationalists now giving out copies of the book to their relatives, by way of explaining how they’ve chosen to spend their lives.</p>



<p>I <em>still</em> don’t know whether there’s a risk worth worrying about that a misaligned AI will threaten human civilization in my lifetime, or my children’s lifetimes, or even 500 years—or whether everyone will look back and laugh at how silly some people once were to think that (except, silly in which way?).  But I do feel fairly confident that <em>The AI Does Not Hate You</em> will make a positive difference—possibly for the world, but at any rate for a little well-meaning community of sneered-at nerds obsessed with the future and with following ideas wherever they lead.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-07T02:09:05Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-07T02:09:05Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-10-07T17:01:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02063</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02063" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fully Dynamic $(\Delta+1)$-Coloring in Constant Update Time</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570406400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bhattacharya:Sayan.html">Sayan Bhattacharya</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grandoni:Fabrizio.html">Fabrizio Grandoni</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kulkarni:Janardhan.html">Janardhan Kulkarni</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Quanquan_C=.html">Quanquan C. Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Solomon:Shay.html">Shay Solomon</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02063">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The problem of (vertex) $(\Delta+1)$-coloring a graph of maximum degree
$\Delta$ has been extremely well-studied over the years in various settings and
models. Surprisingly, for the dynamic setting, almost nothing was known until
recently. In SODA'18, Bhattacharya, Chakrabarty, Henzinger and Nanongkai
devised a randomized data structure for maintaining a $(\Delta+1)$-coloring
with $O(\log \Delta)$ expected amortized update time. In this paper, we present
a $(\Delta+1)$-coloring data structure that achieves a constant amortized
update time and show that this time bound holds not only in expectation but
also with high probability.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02057</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02057" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>C-Planarity Testing of Embedded Clustered Graphs with Bounded Dual Carving-Width</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570406400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lozzo:Giordano_Da.html">Giordano Da Lozzo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Eppstein:David.html">David Eppstein</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Goodrich:Michael_T=.html">Michael T. Goodrich</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gupta:Siddharth.html">Siddharth Gupta</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02057">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>For a clustered graph, i.e, a graph whose vertex set is recursively
partitioned into clusters, the C-Planarity Testing problem asks whether it is
possible to find a planar embedding of the graph and a representation of each
cluster as a region homeomorphic to a closed disk such that 1. the subgraph
induced by each cluster is drawn in the interior of the corresponding disk, 2.
each edge intersects any disk at most once, and 3. the nesting between clusters
is reflected by the representation, i.e., child clusters are properly contained
in their parent cluster. The computational complexity of this problem, whose
study has been central to the theory of graph visualization since its
introduction in 1995 [Qing-Wen Feng, Robert F. Cohen, and Peter Eades.
Planarity for clustered graphs. ESA'95], has only been recently settled
[Radoslav Fulek and Csaba D. T\'oth. Atomic Embeddability, Clustered Planarity,
and Thickenability. To appear at SODA'20]. Before such a breakthrough, the
complexity question was still unsolved even when the graph has a prescribed
planar embedding, i.e, for embedded clustered graphs.
</p>
<p>We show that the C-Planarity Testing problem admits a single-exponential
single-parameter FPT algorithm for embedded clustered graphs, when
parameterized by the carving-width of the dual graph of the input. This is the
first FPT algorithm for this long-standing open problem with respect to a
single notable graph-width parameter. Moreover, in the general case, the
polynomial dependency of our FPT algorithm is smaller than the one of the
algorithm by Fulek and T\'oth. To further strengthen the relevance of this
result, we show that the C-Planarity Testing problem retains its computational
complexity when parameterized by several other graph-width parameters, which
may potentially lead to faster algorithms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02048</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02048" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Dichotomy for Homomorphism-Closed Queries on Probabilistic Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570406400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Amarilli:Antoine.html">Antoine Amarilli</a>, İsmail İlkan Ceylan <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.02048">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the problem of probabilistic query evaluation (PQE) over
probabilistic graphs, namely, tuple-independent probabilistic databases (TIDs)
on signatures of arity two. Our focus is the class of queries that is closed
under homomorphisms, or equivalently, the infinite unions of conjunctive
queries, denoted UCQ^\infty . Our main result states that all unbounded queries
in UCQ^\infty are #P-hard for PQE. As bounded queries in UCQ^\infty are already
classified by the dichotomy of Dalvi and Suciu [16], our results and theirs
imply a complete dichotomy on PQE for UCQ^\infty queries over arity-two
signatures. This dichotomy covers in particular all fragments in UCQ^\infty
such as negation-free (disjunctive) Datalog, regular path queries, and a large
class of ontology-mediated queries on arity-two signatures. Our result is shown
by reducing from counting the valuations of positive partitioned 2-DNF formulae
(#PP2DNF) for some queries, or from the source-to-target reliability problem in
an undirected graph (#U-ST-CON) for other queries, depending on properties of
minimal models.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01957</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01957" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Polyhedral Homotopy Algorithm For Real Zeros</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570406400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Erg=uuml=r:Alperen_A=.html">Alperen A. Ergür</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wolff:Timo_de.html">Timo de Wolff</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01957">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We design a homotopy continuation algorithm for finding real zeros of sparse
polynomial systems. Our algorithm builds on a well-known geometric deformation
process, namely Viro's patchworking method. The algorithm operates entirely
over the real numbers and tracks the optimal number of solution paths. In
exchange, the algorithm is not universally applicable: It works for polynomial
system with coefficients satisfying certain concavity conditions. More
precisely, it requires the given polynomial system to be located in the
unbounded components of the complement of the underlying $A$-discriminant
amoeba. A preliminary implementation of an example from the literature suggests
practical performance of the algorithm. We plan to work towards a vigorous
implementation including a larger scale of examples and a software paper.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01935</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01935" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Synchronization under Dynamic Constraints</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570406400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wolf:Petra.html">Petra Wolf</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01935">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Imagine an assembly line where a box with a lid and liquid in it enters in
some unknown orientation. The box should leave the line with the open lid
facing upwards with the liquid still in it. To save costs there are no complex
sensors or image recognition software available on the assembly line, so a
reset sequence needs to be computed. But how can the dependencies of the
deforming impact of a transformation of the box, such as 'do not tilt the box
over when the lid is open' or 'open the lid again each time it gets closed' be
modeled? We present three attempts to model constraints of these kinds on the
order in which the states of an automaton are transitioned by a synchronizing
word. The first two concepts relate the last visits of states and form
constraints on which states still need to be reached, whereas the third concept
concerns the first visits of states and forms constraints on which states might
still be reached. We examine the computational complexity of different variants
of the problem, whether an automaton can be synchronized with a word that
respects the constraints defined in the respective concept, and obtain nearly a
full classification. While most of the problems are PSPACE-complete we also
observe NP-complete variants and variants solvable in polynomial time. We will
also observe a drop of the complexity if we track the orders of states on
several paths simultaneously instead of tracking the set of active states.
Further, we give upper bounds on the length of a synchronizing word depending
on the size of the input relation and show that the Cerny conjecture holds for
partial weakly acyclic automata.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01934</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01934" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>FPT Inapproximability of Directed Cut and Connectivity Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570406400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chitnis:Rajesh.html">Rajesh Chitnis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Feldmann:Andreas_Emil.html">Andreas Emil Feldmann</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01934">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>(see paper for full abstract)
</p>
<p>Cut problems and connectivity problems on digraphs are two well-studied
classes of problems from the viewpoint of parameterized complexity. After a
series of papers over the last decade, we now have (almost) tight bounds for
the running time of several standard variants of these problems parameterized
by two parameters: the number $k$ of terminals and the size $p$ of the
solution. When there is evidence of FPT intractability, then the next natural
alternative is to consider FPT approximations. In this paper, we show two types
of results for several directed cut and connectivity problems, building on
existing results from the literature: first is to circumvent the hardness
results for these problems by designing FPT approximation algorithms, or
alternatively strengthen the existing hardness results by creating
"gap-instances" under stronger hypotheses such as the (Gap-)Exponential Time
Hypothesis (ETH).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01783</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01783" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Width Parameterizations for Knot-free Vertex Deletion on Digraphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570406400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bessy:St=eacute=phane.html">Stéphane Bessy</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bougeret:Marin.html">Marin Bougeret</a>, Alan D. A. Carneiro, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Protti:F=aacute=bio.html">Fábio Protti</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Souza:U=eacute=verton_S=.html">Uéverton S. Souza</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01783">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A knot in a directed graph $G$ is a strongly connected subgraph $Q$ of $G$
with at least two vertices, such that no vertex in $V(Q)$ is an in-neighbor of
a vertex in $V(G)\setminus V(Q)$. Knots are important graph structures, because
they characterize the existence of deadlocks in a classical distributed
computation model, the so-called OR-model. Deadlock detection is correlated
with the recognition of knot-free graphs as well as deadlock resolution is
closely related to the {\sc Knot-Free Vertex Deletion (KFVD)} problem, which
consists of determining whether an input graph $G$ has a subset $S \subseteq
V(G)$ of size at most $k$ such that $G[V\setminus S]$ contains no knot. In this
paper we focus on graph width measure parameterizations for {\sc KFVD}. First,
we show that: (i) {\sc KFVD} parameterized by the size of the solution $k$ is
W[1]-hard even when $p$, the length of a longest directed path of the input
graph, as well as $\kappa$, its Kenny-width, are bounded by constants, and we
remark that {\sc KFVD} is para-NP-hard even considering many directed width
measures as parameters, but in FPT when parameterized by clique-width; (ii)
{\sc KFVD} can be solved in time $2^{O(tw)}\times n$, but assuming ETH it
cannot be solved in $2^{o(tw)}\times n^{O(1)}$, where $tw$ is the treewidth of
the underlying undirected graph. Finally, since the size of a minimum directed
feedback vertex set ($dfv$) is an upper bound for the size of a minimum
knot-free vertex deletion set, we investigate parameterization by $dfv$ and we
show that (iii) {\sc KFVD} can be solved in FPT-time parameterized by either
$dfv+\kappa$ or $dfv+p$; and it admits a Turing kernel by the distance to a DAG
having an Hamiltonian path.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01749</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01749" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Finding monotone patterns in sublinear time</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570406400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Ben=Eliezer:Omri.html">Omri Ben-Eliezer</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Canonne:Cl=eacute=ment_L=.html">Clément L. Canonne</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Letzter:Shoham.html">Shoham Letzter</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Waingarten:Erik.html">Erik Waingarten</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.01749">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the problem of finding monotone subsequences in an array from the
viewpoint of sublinear algorithms. For fixed $k \in \mathbb{N}$ and
$\varepsilon &gt; 0$, we show that the non-adaptive query complexity of finding a
length-$k$ monotone subsequence of $f \colon [n] \to \mathbb{R}$, assuming that
$f$ is $\varepsilon$-far from free of such subsequences, is $\Theta((\log
n)^{\lfloor \log_2 k \rfloor})$. Prior to our work, the best algorithm for this
problem, due to Newman, Rabinovich, Rajendraprasad, and Sohler (2017), made
$(\log n)^{O(k^2)}$ non-adaptive queries; and the only lower bound known, of
$\Omega(\log n)$ queries for the case $k = 2$, followed from that on testing
monotonicity due to Erg\"un, Kannan, Kumar, Rubinfeld, and Viswanathan (2000)
and Fischer (2004).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-07T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/138</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/138" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-138 |  On the Probabilistic Degrees of Symmetric Boolean functions | 

	Srikanth Srinivasan, 

	Utkarsh Tripathi, 

	S Venkitesh</title>
    <summary>The probabilistic degree of a Boolean function $f:\{0,1\}^n\rightarrow \{0,1\}$ is defined to be the smallest $d$ such that there is a random polynomial $\mathbf{P}$ of degree at most $d$ that agrees with $f$ at each point with high probability. Introduced by Razborov (1987), upper and lower bounds on probabilistic degrees of Boolean functions --- specifically symmetric Boolean functions --- have been used to prove explicit lower bounds, design pseudorandom generators, and devise algorithms for combinatorial problems. 
		
In this paper, we characterize the probabilistic degrees of all symmetric Boolean functions up to polylogarithmic factors over all fields of fixed characteristic (positive or zero).</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-06T15:42:51Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-06T15:42:51Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T08:20:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/137</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/137" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-137 |  Decision list compression by mild random restrictions | 

	Shachar Lovett, 

	Kewen Wu, 

	Jiapeng Zhang</title>
    <summary>A decision list is an ordered list of rules. Each rule is specified by a term, which is a conjunction of literals, and a value. Given an input, the output of a decision list is the value corresponding to the first rule whole term is satisfied by the input. Decision lists generalize both CNFs and DNFs, and have been studied both in complexity theory and in learning theory.

The size of a decision list is the number of rules, and its width is the maximal number of variables in a term. We prove that decision lists of small width can always be approximated by decision lists of small size, where we obtain sharp bounds (up to constants). This in particular resolves a conjecture of Gopalan, Meka and Reingold (Computational Complexity, 2013) on DNF sparsification.

An ingredient in our proof is a new random restriction lemma, which allows to analyze how DNFs (and more generally, decision lists) simplify if a small fraction of the variables are fixed. This is in contrast to the more commonly used switching lemma, which requires most of the variables to be fixed.</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-06T11:20:34Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-06T11:20:34Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T08:20:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/136</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/136" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-136 |  Quantum Query-to-Communication Simulation Needs a Logarithmic Overhead | 

	Sourav Chakraborty, 

	Arkadev Chattopadhyay, 

	Nikhil Mande, 

	Manaswi Paraashar</title>
    <summary>Buhrman, Cleve and Wigderson (STOC'98) observed that for every Boolean function $f : \{-1, 1\}^n \to \{-1, 1\}$ and $\bullet : \{-1, 1\}^2 \to \{-1, 1\}$ the two-party bounded-error quantum communication complexity of $(f \circ \bullet)$ is $O(Q(f) \log n)$, where $Q(f)$ is the bounded-error quantum query complexity of $f$. Note that the bounded-error randomized communication complexity of $(f \circ \bullet)$ is bounded by $O(R(f))$, where $R(f)$ denotes the bounded-error randomized query complexity of $f$. Thus, the BCW simulation has an extra $O(\log n)$ factor appearing that is absent in classical simulation. A natural question is if this factor can be avoided. H{\o}yer and de Wolf (STACS'02) showed that for the Set-Disjointness function, this can be reduced to $c^{\log^* n}$ for some constant $c$, and subsequently Aaronson and Ambainis (FOCS'03) showed that this factor can be made a constant. That is, the quantum communication complexity of the Set-Disjointness function (which is $NOR_n \circ \wedge$) is $O(Q(NOR_n))$.

Perhaps somewhat surprisingly, we show that when $ \bullet = \oplus$, then the extra $\log n$ factor in the BCW simulation is unavoidable. In other words, we exhibit a total function $F : \{-1, 1\}^n \to \{-1, 1\}$ such that $Q^{cc}(F \circ \oplus) = \Theta(Q(F) \log n)$.

To the best of our knowledge, it was not even known prior to this work whether there existed a total function $F$ and 2-bit function $\bullet$, such that $Q^{cc}(F \circ \bullet) = \omega(Q(F))$.</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-06T09:03:52Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-06T09:03:52Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T08:20:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/05/future-faculty-fellow-postdoc-at-university-of-illinois-urbana-champaign-apply-by-february-1-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/05/future-faculty-fellow-postdoc-at-university-of-illinois-urbana-champaign-apply-by-february-1-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Future Faculty Fellow/Postdoc at University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign (apply by February 1, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science (CS) at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign invites applications for the “Future Faculty” program. The Future Faculty Program is a selective program offering two-year postdoctoral positions whose goal is to mentor and prepare outstanding candidates for an academic career in research and teaching. Contact a theory faculty member if […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science (CS) at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign invites applications for the “Future Faculty” program. The Future Faculty Program is a selective program offering two-year postdoctoral positions whose goal is to mentor and prepare outstanding candidates for an academic career in research and teaching. Contact a theory faculty member if interested.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://cs.illinois.edu/about-us/staff-positions#futurefaculty">https://cs.illinois.edu/about-us/staff-positions#futurefaculty</a><br/>
Email: chekuri@illinois.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-05T21:36:12Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-05T21:36:12Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T08:21:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/05/multiple-faculty-positions-at-university-of-illinois-urbana-champaign-apply-by-december-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/05/multiple-faculty-positions-at-university-of-illinois-urbana-champaign-apply-by-december-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Multiple Faculty Positions at University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign (apply by December 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science has multiple tenure track at all levels. Quantum Computing and Theory are among the priority areas. Website: https://cs.illinois.edu/about-us/faculty-positions Email: HR@cs.illinois.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science has multiple tenure track at all levels. Quantum Computing and Theory are among the priority areas.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://cs.illinois.edu/about-us/faculty-positions">https://cs.illinois.edu/about-us/faculty-positions</a><br/>
Email: HR@cs.illinois.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-05T21:23:38Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-05T21:23:38Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T08:21:16Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3427</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/10/05/blind-folks-and-the-evolving-elephant-by-vijay-vazirani/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Blind Folks and the Evolving Elephant – by Vijay Vazirani</title>
    <summary>One of my favorite parables ever since childhood was that of the four blind men and the elephant, with each man announcing the local image evoked in his mind’s eye on touching a different part of the elephant. This parable has provided an interesting metaphor even for serious scientific matters, a well-known one being wave-particle […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>One of my favorite parables ever since childhood was that of the four blind men and the elephant, with each man announcing the local image evoked in his mind’s eye on touching a different part of the elephant. This parable has provided an interesting metaphor even for serious scientific matters, a well-known one being wave-particle duality in physics.</p>
<p>But when it comes to matching markets, the parable has taken an unusual twist, with the proverbial elephant undergoing a metamorphosis of its own! The “blind men’’ in this case are entire disciplines which can lay claim to the field of matching markets. Of course, the obvious one is economics – the founders of this field, namely Gale and Shapley, were mathematical economists and <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2012/summary/">the 2012 Nobel Prize in Economics</a> was awarded to Alvin Roth and Lloyd Shapley for work on these markets.</p>
<p>A key enabler was researchers in systems and networking. Their scientific revolutions of the Internet and mobile computing put matching markets on an exciting, new journey and their systems run these centralized markets on powerful computers.</p>
<p>The discipline of algorithm design has had an umbilical connection to matching markets: At the birth of this field lies the highly sophisticated <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.4169/amer.math.monthly.120.05.386?journalCode=uamm20">Gale-Shapley</a> stable matching algorithm (1962), whose pivotal game-theoretic property of incentive compatibility follows as a free gift from polynomial time solvability — it was established <a href="http://pareto.uab.es/jmasso/pdf/DubinsFreedmanAMM1981.pdf">two decades</a> after the discovery of the algorithm! Yet most researchers, including those in theoretical computer science, are not aware that algorithm design is also a legitimate claimant to this field. Indeed, the very “engine’’ that runs almost each one of these markets is a <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/rmklectures2019-fall-1">sophisticated algorithm</a> chosen from the “gold mine’’ of matching theory! Besides stable matching, this includes maximum matching and online matching and their numerous variants.</p>
<p>Looking back at the huge expansion of matching markets over the last decade-and-a-half, one can see that all three disciplines were faced with numerous challenges: understanding the incentive structure of a new market; finding ways of dealing with terra-bytes of data, and choosing and delivering within milli-seconds the “right’’ ads to show with a user query; and designing an algorithm for the latest variant of online matching. And they all delivered!</p>
<p>The rich and diverse set of research talks given at the recent <a href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/10/02/matching-markets-simons-driven-by-theory-driving-the-economy/">Simons program</a> on matching markets is proof enough that the elephant is still evolving!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-05T20:08:09Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-05T20:08:09Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>michalfeldman</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T08:20:48Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/?p=5454</id>
    <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/2019/10/05/new-horizons-in-geometry-and-micha-sharir/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>New Horizons in Geometry and Micha Sharir</title>
    <summary>Always wanted to visit Israel? Like discrete or computational geometry, and Micha Sharir? Considering what to do with this year’s travel funds? Join us in Tel Aviv! https://geometrynyc.wixsite.com/sharir (Open on a computer – does not support mobile yet.) If you can, please help us spread the word. Partial list of speakers: Pankaj Agarwal (Duke) Noga […]</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-05T15:55:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-05T15:55:19Z</published>
    <category term="Math events"/>
    <author>
      <name>Adam Sheffer</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Discrete geometry and other typos</subtitle>
      <title>Some Plane Truths</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T08:21:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
