<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:59Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/046</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/046" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-046 |  andom walks and forbidden minors II: A $\poly(d\eps^{-1})$-query tester for minor-closed properties of bounded degree graphs | 

	Akash Kumar, 

	C. Seshadhri, 

	Andrew Stolman</title>
    <summary>Let $G$ be a graph with $n$ vertices and maximum degree $d$. Fix some minor-closed property $\mathcal{P}$ (such as planarity).
We say that $G$ is $\varepsilon$-far from $\mathcal{P}$ if one has to remove $\varepsilon dn$ edges to make it have $\mathcal{P}$.
The problem of property testing $\mathcal{P}$ was introduced in the seminal work of Benjamini-Schramm-Shapira (STOC 2008)
that gave a tester with query complexity triply exponential in $\varepsilon^{-1}$.
Levi-Ron (TALG 2015) have given the best tester to date, with a quasipolynomial (in $\varepsilon^{-1}$) query complexity.
It is an open problem to get property testers whose query complexity is $\poly(d\varepsilon^{-1})$,
even for planarity.

In this paper, we resolve this open question. For any minor-closed property,
we give a tester with query complexity $d\cdot \poly(\varepsilon^{-1})$.
The previous line of work on (independent of $n$, two-sided) testers is primarily combinatorial.
Our work, on the other hand, employs techniques from spectral graph theory. This paper
is a continuation of recent work of the authors (FOCS 2018) analyzing random walk algorithms
that find forbidden minors.</summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T08:45:13Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-01T08:45:13Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/04/01/the-sat-smt-ar-summer-school/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/04/01/the-sat-smt-ar-summer-school/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The SAT/SMT/AR Summer School</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">July 3-6, 2019 Lisbon, Portugal https://reason.di.fc.ul.pt/ssa-school-2019/ Registration deadline: May 31, 2019 Satisfiability (SAT), Satisfiability Modulo Theories (SMT), and Automated Reasoning (AR) continue to make rapid advances and find novel uses in a wide variety of applications, both in computer science and beyond. The SAT/SMT/AR Summer School aims to bring a select group of students up … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/04/01/the-sat-smt-ar-summer-school/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">The SAT/SMT/AR Summer School</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T08:39:38Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-01T08:39:38Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=15715</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/04/01/the-breakthrough-result-of-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Breakthrough Result Of 2019</title>
    <summary>Our nomination for best result of the year Cropped from source Faadosly Polir has had an incredible year of research success. A year ago we covered his research on universal information entropy in baseball. This led to uncredited co-authorship on a paper, which Quanta covered last week, about reversal of entropy in a previously-built 51-qubit […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Our nomination for best result of the year</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/carnivalfool.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-15716" height="135" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/carnivalfool.png?w=123&amp;h=135" width="123"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Cropped from <a href="https://pxhere.com/en/photo/1036632">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Faadosly Polir has had an incredible year of research success. A year ago we <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/04/01/the-entropy-of-baseball/">covered</a> his research on universal information entropy in baseball. This led to uncredited co-authorship on a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1812.05561">paper</a>, which <em>Quanta</em> <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/quantum-scarring-appears-to-defy-universes-push-for-disorder-20190320/">covered</a> last week, about reversal of entropy in a previously-built 51-qubit quantum <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nature24622">computer</a>. The paper focuses on quantum many-body scarring in a Bunimovich <a href="https://blogs.ams.org/visualinsight/2016/11/15/bunimovich-stadium/">stadium</a>, but Polir’s work on athletic body scarring in baseball stadiums was integral. </p>
<p>
Today we report on his exciting and topical new findings.</p>
<p>
Polir’s next project implemented a <a href="https://www.quora.com/How-do-random-events-of-quantum-physics-influence-the-information-content-of-the-universe">suggestion</a> by the complexity theorist Vaughan Pratt on how to research the influence of random events on the information content of the universe:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Picture inserting a giant eggbeater into the deep state cloud servers and relocating all its bits at random. How would you recover important information like the net worth of Meghan Markle or President Trump’s tax returns? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Polir began the Cloud Beater Project using spare Amazon Web Services credits from Ken. The results so far are classified, but in addition to the above objectives there is a current push to infer from web traffic the full text of the impending <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_Counsel_investigation_(2017-2019)">report</a> by Robert Mueller. The string length has been <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/28/us/politics/mueller-report-length.html">inferred</a>. Polir’s model algebraically represents the entire cloud as a finite automaton analogous to Alan Turing’s model of the Enigma machine during World War II. The inferencing process is similar and <a href="https://www.nhregister.com/technology/businessinsider/article/With-just-60-and-internet-access-researchers-13628061.php">cheap</a>. </p>
<p>
The newest work, however, will have the greatest social impact for the research community.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Problem </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The problem is one we all are familiar with: the impact of the Internet and computing technology resources on critical thinking and academic research <a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2018/03/is-technology-hurting-productivity">productivity</a>. After extensive analysis-of-variance runs on Google Scholar data, Polir’s team isolated one key adverse factor:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <i>LaTeX forces one to compile and recompile multiple times</i>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
In retrospect the effect of this should have been suspected—after all, LaTeX is the one factor common to a major part of research across all scientific disciplines. Here are examples of relevant user <a href="https://tex.stackexchange.com/questions/107967/need-to-typeset-twice-for-correct-compile">comments</a>, some paraphrased:</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet}"/> You cannot avoid it. LaTeX has to build the .aux file to store the table of contents (ToC) and such, because when typesetting the ToC it cannot know beforehand what sections will occur. </p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet}"/> Often not only two but three or more runs are necessary. Imagine a document with lots of figures and a list of figures somewhere at the first pages of the document. All pages are numbered using ascending Arabic numbers. First compilation run will typeset the document without any entry at the list of figures but collects the information at the .lof file (via .aux file). Second compilation run will typeset the list of figures with several pages and as a consequence of this the page numbers of all figures will change. So you need a third run to get the correct numbers at the list of figures.</p>
<p>
<img alt="{\bullet}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbullet%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\bullet}"/> To correctly line up the various parts of a longtable, “In the typical case the algorithm will converge after three or four passes” (manual, section 4).</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Magnitude </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The result is the observation that there now are so many uses of LaTeX that any inefficiency in using it has great consequences. The bottom line of the first findings chapter in the report led by Polir is:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> We found that over 100 million hours of productive time per year are lost to the multiple-pass issue in LaTeX. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
There are now billions of LaTeX pages being worked on each year. See <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/blog/219-youve-created-three-million-projects-and-counting-dot-dot-dot">this</a> for some data. Thus at a conservative estimate of $100 dollars per hour this means that we are losing <i>over ten billion dollars per year</i>. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Ken’s Solution </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Ken has a way of coping. He spends the time waiting for LaTeX documents to open and compile on his office PC in a productive way. He used to check fantasy baseball or football player news during these waits. But last year he acquired a Facebook friend (FBF) from the chess world who became the first—out of his several hundred FBFs—to post cat videos. Several times daily cat videos, all new. </p>
<p>
Ken had never seen a Facebook cat video before. So now he goes to the FBF’s page and clicks the next one while waiting for LaTeX to finish. This does, however, have less relevance to his statistical chess research than <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2012/07/29/benfords-law-and-baseball/">fantasy</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2015/10/12/is-the-hot-hand-fallacy-a-fallacy/">sports</a> <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/03/28/is-there-momentum-in-chess/">had</a>.</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/videocat.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-15717" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/04/videocat.png?w=600"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">The mother <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recurring_Saturday_Night_Live_characters_and_sketches_introduced_1988%E2%80%931989#Toonces_The_Driving_Cat">lode</a>?</font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p/><h2> Polir’s Solution </h2><p/>
<p>
Polir found a different solution that does not use cat videos—too bad for the cats. Polir first approached the most recently responsible party, who won the 2013 ACM Turing Award for solving the <em>broken deli number dispenser</em> problem. The prize-winning solution, as described in the <a href="https://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/lamport_1205376.cfm">citation</a>, is to have each customer choose a number higher than all the other customers’ numbers. But how to leverage this brilliant solution to solve the multi-pass problem?</p>
<p>
Polir’s insight came while consulting the original responsible party and author of the following computer <a href="https://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/programs/sat13.w">code</a> for a SAT solver. While hearing the author explain how this code emerged from his Pascal-based <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WEB">WEB</a> and C-based <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CWEB">CWEB</a> programming environments, Polir realized this in a flash:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> A LaTeX document is a <b>network</b>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This led to the realization that the quick-compilation problems could be formulated as instances of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_network_coding">network coding</a> problems upon dividing the document into <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/>-sized chunks. A helpful reader of this blog supplied the final needed piece last week in a <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/#comment-100107">comment</a>: via this new <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1902.10935">paper</a>, there is an efficient reduction from network coding to integer multiplication. The reduction is not a string mapping but rather “corporate” via direct analysis of solving circuits.</p>
<p>
Thus the solution came down to ideas in the brilliant new <a href="https://web.maths.unsw.edu.au/~davidharvey/papers/nlogn/">paper</a> on integer multiplication which we just <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/">posted</a> about. It means that we can solve the multi-pass problem essentially by multiplying pieces of the document together—or more exactly, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convolution#Discrete_convolution">convolving</a> them. We needn’t be concerned about our remarks on the algorithm in that paper being galactic—there is a clear proof of concept in that the paper’s second author is also the chief developer of the <a href="http://texmacs.org/tmweb/home/welcome.en.html">TeXmacs</a> composition environment. We thus nominate the paper plus Polir’s breakthrough consequence for result of the year.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Incidentally, that comment has tag number 100,107—which means we just passed the 100,000 milepost in whatever those tags signify. We actually have 18,694 comments over the history of the blog and have been intending to mark its passing 20K. This again gives us a “no-fooling” opportunity to thank our readers.</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-04-01T06:01:57Z</updated>
    <published>2019-04-01T06:01:57Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="April Fool"/>
    <category term="breakthrough"/>
    <category term="cat videos"/>
    <category term="entropy"/>
    <category term="Faadosly Polir"/>
    <category term="information theory"/>
    <category term="integer multiplication"/>
    <category term="internet"/>
    <category term="LaTeX"/>
    <category term="multi-pass compiling"/>
    <category term="network coding"/>
    <category term="Robert Mueller"/>
    <category term="TeX"/>
    <category term="TeXmacs"/>
    <category term="Vaughan Pratt"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:01Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12641</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12641" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Connected max cut is polynomial for graphs without $K_5\backslash e$ as a minor</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554076800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chaourar:Brahim.html">Brahim Chaourar</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12641">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a graph $G=(V, E)$, a connected cut $\delta (U)$ is the set of edges of
E linking all vertices of U to all vertices of $V\backslash U$ such that the
induced subgraphs $G[U]$ and $G[V\backslash U]$ are connected. Given a positive
weight function $w$ defined on $E$, the connected maximum cut problem (CMAX
CUT) is to find a connected cut $\Omega$ such that $w(\Omega)$ is maximum among
all connected cuts. CMAX CUT is NP-hard even for planar graphs. In this paper,
we prove that CMAX CUT is polynomial for graphs without $K_5\backslash e$ as a
minor. We deduce a quadratic time algorithm for the minimum cut problem in the
same class of graphs without computing the maximum flow.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T01:23:51Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12525</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12525" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Shed More Light on Bloom Filter's Variants</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554076800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Patgiri:Ripon.html">Ripon Patgiri</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nayak:Sabuzima.html">Sabuzima Nayak</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Borgohain:Samir_Kumar.html">Samir Kumar Borgohain</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12525">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Bloom Filter is a probabilistic membership data structure and it is
excessively used data structure for membership query. Bloom Filter becomes the
predominant data structure in approximate membership filtering. Bloom Filter
extremely enhances the query response time, and the response time is very fast.
Bloom filter (BF) is used to detect whether an element belongs to a given set
or not. The Bloom Filter returns True Positive (TP), False Positive (FP), or
True Negative (TN). The Bloom Filter is widely adapted in numerous areas to
enhance the performance of a system. In this paper, we present a) in-depth
insight on the Bloom Filter,and b) the prominent variants of the Bloom Filters.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T01:22:26Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12516</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12516" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Ham-Sandwich cuts and center transversals in subspaces</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554076800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schnider:Patrick.html">Patrick Schnider</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12516">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Ham-Sandwich theorem is a well-known result in geometry. It states that
any $d$ mass distributions in $\mathbb{R}^d$ can be simultaneously bisected by
a hyperplane. The result is tight, that is, there are examples of $d+1$ mass
distributions that cannot be simultaneously bisected by a single hyperplane. In
this abstract we will study the following question: given a continuous
assignment of mass distributions to certain subsets of $\mathbb{R}^d$, is there
a subset on which we can bisect more masses than what is guaranteed by the
Ham-Sandwich theorem?
</p>
<p>We investigate two types of subsets. The first type are linear subspaces of
$\mathbb{R}^d$, i.e., $k$-dimensional flats containing the origin. We show that
for any continuous assignment of $d$ mass distributions to the $k$-dimensional
linear subspaces of $\mathbb{R}^d$, there is always a subspace on which we can
simultaneously bisect the images of all $d$ assignments. We extend this result
to center transversals, a generalization of Ham-Sandwich cuts. As for
Ham-Sandwich cuts, we further show that for $d-k+2$ masses, we can choose $k-1$
of the vectors defining the $k$-dimensional subspace in which the solution
lies.
</p>
<p>The second type of subsets we consider are subsets that are determined by
families of $n$ hyperplanes in $\mathbb{R}^d$. Also in this case, we find a
Ham-Sandwich-type result. In an attempt to solve a conjecture by Langerman
about bisections with several cuts, we show that our underlying topological
result can be used to prove this conjecture in a relaxed setting.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T01:26:55Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12449</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12449" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Multiplication method for factoring natural numbers</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554076800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nesiolovskiy:Igor.html">Igor Nesiolovskiy</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nesiolovskiy:Artem.html">Artem Nesiolovskiy</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12449">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We offer multiplication method for factoring big natural numbers which
extends the group of the Fermat's and Lehman's factorization algorithms and has
run-time complexity $O(n^{1/3})$. This paper is argued the finiteness of
proposed algorithm depending on the value of the factorizable number n. We
provide here comparative tests results of related algorithms on a large amount
of computational checks. We describe identified advantages of the proposed
algorithm over others. The possibilities of algorithm optimization for reducing
the complexity of factorization are also shown here.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T01:22:41Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12400</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12400" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Force-Directed Approach for Offline GPS Trajectory Map Matching</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554076800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rappos:Efstratios.html">Efstratios Rappos</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Robert:Stephan.html">Stephan Robert</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cudr=eacute==Mauroux:Philippe.html">Philippe Cudré-Mauroux</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12400">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a novel algorithm to match GPS trajectories onto maps offline (in
batch mode) using techniques borrowed from the field of force-directed graph
drawing. We consider a simulated physical system where each GPS trajectory is
attracted or repelled by the underlying road network via electrical-like
forces. We let the system evolve under the action of these physical forces such
that individual trajectories are attracted towards candidate roads to obtain a
map matching path. Our approach has several advantages compared to traditional,
routing-based, algorithms for map matching, including the ability to account
for noise and to avoid large detours due to outliers in the data whilst taking
into account the underlying topological restrictions (such as one-way roads).
Our empirical evaluation using real GPS traces shows that our method produces
better map matching results compared to alternative offline map matching
algorithms on average, especially for routes in dense, urban areas.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T01:22:50Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12359</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12359" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Parallelizable global conformal parameterization of simply-connected surfaces via partial welding</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554076800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Choi:Gary_P=_T=.html">Gary P. T. Choi</a>, Yusan Leung-Liu, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gu:Xianfeng.html">Xianfeng Gu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lui:Lok_Ming.html">Lok Ming Lui</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12359">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Conformal surface parameterization is useful in graphics, imaging and
visualization, with applications to texture mapping, atlas construction,
registration, remeshing and so on. With the increasing capability in scanning
and storing data, dense 3D surface meshes are common nowadays. While meshes
with higher resolution better resemble smooth surfaces, they pose computational
difficulties for the existing parameterization algorithms. In this work, we
propose a novel parallelizable algorithm for computing the global conformal
parameterization of simply-connected surfaces via partial welding maps. A given
simply-connected surface is first partitioned into smaller subdomains. The
local conformal parameterizations of all subdomains are then computed in
parallel. The boundaries of the parameterized subdomains are subsequently
integrated consistently using a novel technique called partial welding, which
is developed based on conformal welding theory. Finally, by solving the Laplace
equation for each subdomain using the updated boundary conditions, we obtain a
global conformal parameterization of the given surface, with bijectivity
guaranteed by quasi-conformal theory. By including additional shape
constraints, our method can be easily extended to achieve disk conformal
parameterization for simply-connected open surfaces and spherical conformal
parameterization for genus-0 closed surfaces. Experimental results are
presented to demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed algorithm. When
compared to the state-of-the-art conformal parameterization methods, our method
achieves a significant improvement in both computational time and accuracy.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T01:24:17Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12312</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12312" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Data structures to represent sets of k-long DNA sequences</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554076800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chikhi:Rayan.html">Rayan Chikhi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Holub:Jan.html">Jan Holub</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Medvedev:Paul.html">Paul Medvedev</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12312">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The analysis of biological sequencing data has been one of the biggest
applications of string algorithms. The approaches used in many such
applications are based on the analysis of k-mers, which are short fixed-length
strings present in a dataset. While these approaches are rather diverse,
storing and querying k-mer sets has emerged as a shared underlying component.
Sets of k-mers have unique features and applications that, over the last ten
years, have resulted in many specialized approaches for their representation.
In this survey, we give a unified presentation and comparison of the data
structures that have been proposed to store and query k-mer sets. We hope this
survey will not only serve as a resource for researchers in the field but also
make the area more accessible to outsiders
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T01:23:56Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12243</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12243" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>DEEP-FRI: Sampling outside the box improves soundness</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1554076800</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Ben=Sasson:Eli.html">Eli Ben-Sasson</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Goldberg:Lior.html">Lior Goldberg</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kopparty:Swastik.html">Swastik Kopparty</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saraf:Shubhangi.html">Shubhangi Saraf</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12243">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Motivated by the quest for scalable and succinct zero knowledge arguments, we
revisit worst-case-to-average-case reductions for linear spaces, raised by
[Rothblum, Vadhan, Wigderson, STOC 2013]. We first show a sharp quantitative
form of a theorem which says that if an affine space $U$ is $\delta$-far in
relative Hamming distance from a linear code $V$ - this is the worst-case
assumption - then most elements of $U$ are almost $\delta$-far from $V$ - this
is the average case. This leads to an optimal analysis of the soundness of the
FRI protocol of [Ben-Sasson, et.al., eprint 2018] for proving proximity to
Reed-Solomon codes.
</p>
<p>To further improve soundness, we sample outside the box. We suggest a new
protocol which asks a prover for values of a polynomial at points outside the
domain of evaluation of the Reed-Solomon code. We call this technique Domain
Extending for Eliminating Pretenders (DEEP).
</p>
<p>We use the DEEP technique to devise two new protocols: (1) An Interactive
Oracle Proof of Proximity (IOPP) for RS codes, called DEEP-FRI. This soundness
of the protocol improves upon that of the FRI protocol while retaining linear
arithmetic proving complexity and logarithmic verifier arithmetic complexity.
(2) An Interactive Oracle Proof (IOP) for the Algebraic Linking IOP (ALI)
protocol used to construct zero knowledge scalable transparent arguments of
knowledge (ZK-STARKs) in [Ben-Sasson et al., eprint 2018]. The new protocol,
called DEEP-ALI, improves soundness of this crucial step from a small constant
$&lt; 1/8$ to a constant arbitrarily close to $1$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-04-01T01:20:35Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/03/31/summer-school-on-randomness-and-learning-in-non-linear-algebra/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/03/31/summer-school-on-randomness-and-learning-in-non-linear-algebra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Summer School on Randomness and Learning in Non-Linear Algebra</title>
    <summary>July 1-4, 2019 Leipzig, Germany https://www.mis.mpg.de/calendar/conferences/2019/ranlearn2019.html This summer school aims at bringing together researchers working on probabilistic and statistical methods and questions in nonlinear algebra. Keynote speakers will be: Peter Bürgisser (Technische Universität Berlin) Daniel Erman (University of Wisconsin-Madison) Antonio Lerario (Scuola Internazionale Superiore di Studi Avanzati)</summary>
    <updated>2019-03-31T20:03:04Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-31T20:03:04Z</published>
    <category term="school"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=17274</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/03/31/is-it-legitimate-ethical-for-google-to-close-google/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Is it Legitimate/Ethical for Google to close Google+?</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">  Google Plus is a nice social platform with tens of millions participants. I found it especially nice for scientific posts, e.g. by John Baez, Moshe Vardi, or about symplectic geometry,  about Majorana Fermions, and with a discussion about What … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/03/31/is-it-legitimate-ethical-for-google-to-close-google/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/03/google.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17276" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/03/google.png?w=640"/></a></p>
<p> </p>
<p>Google Plus is a nice social platform with tens of millions participants. I found it especially nice for scientific posts, e.g. by <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/117663015413546257905">John Baez</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/104488217075635760621">Moshe Vardi</a>, or about <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/s/symplectic%20geometry/top">symplectic geometry, </a> about <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/s/majorana%20fermions/top">Majorana Fermions</a>, and with a discussion about <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/106808239073321070854/posts/cwzYpKXSACM">What is combinatorics</a>. A few months ago Google announced  that Google+ will be closed. This is going to happen today (March 31, 2019) in a few hours. For example, I am not even sure if the above valuable links will continue to operate. (Every individual user can get his own stuff.)</p>
<p>For possible answers on why Google shut down Google Plus see this <a href="https://www.quora.com/Why-is-Google+-closed">Quora question</a>.</p>
<p>My question is different. <span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>Is it legitimate for Google to close Google+? Is it legitimate and is it ethical for Google to eliminate existing content from the public domain?</strong> </span></p>
<p> </p>
<p>(Related post: <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/06/06/what-do-firms-want/">What do firms want</a> .)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-31T17:51:53Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-31T17:51:53Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Economics"/>
    <category term="Open discussion"/>
    <category term="Rationality"/>
    <category term="Google plus"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:20:57Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/03/31/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/03/31/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>A 3-regular matchstick graph of girth 5 consisting of 54 vertices, Mike Winkler, Peter Dinkelacker, and Stefan Vogel (). The previous smallest-known graph with these properties had 180 vertices, but this one might still not be optimal, as the known lower bound is only 30. I found it difficult to understand the connectivity of the graph from its matchstick representation so I made another drawing of the same graph in a different style:</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.04304">A 3-regular matchstick graph of girth 5 consisting of 54 vertices</a>, Mike Winkler, Peter Dinkelacker, and Stefan Vogel (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101761530841835018"/>). The previous smallest-known graph with these properties had 180 vertices, but this one might still not be optimal, as the known lower bound is only 30. I found it difficult to understand the connectivity of the graph from <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Winkler_3-reg_girth5_54.svg">its matchstick representation</a> so I made another drawing of the same graph in a different style:</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="The 54-vertex 3-regular girth-5 matchstick graph of Winkler, Dinkelacker, and Vogel in Lombardi drawing style" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/girth-5-matchstick.svg"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/plexodus/comments/az285j/saving_of_public_google_content_at_the_internet/">Saving public Google+ content at the Internet Archive</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101767934776473984"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19407865">via</a>). Archive.org and the <a href="https://www.archiveteam.org/">Archive Team</a> (a separate “loose collective of rogue archivists, programmers, writers and loudmouths dedicated to saving our digital heritage”) are undertaking an organized effort to capture it all before Google takes it down at the end of the month.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@shonk/101807604452877379">Symmetric minimality</a>, Clayton Shonkwiler. An animation of a symmetric minimal-length grid realization of a trefoil knot, posted after I complained that <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@shonk/101768569662399661">his earlier animation</a> was too asymmetric, and suggested using the realization below (drawn using  <a href="http://vzome.com/home/">vZome</a>). Clayton also posted a <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@shonk/101819922406308000">bcc figure-8</a> and <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@shonk/101825678378019686">bcc </a>. Not every symmetric knot has a symmetric lattice realization (e.g. the  lattice knot doesn’t) but it may be an interesting question whether every lattice-realizable symmetry of a knot can be realized by a minimal lattice knot.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Symmetric lattice trefoil knot drawn using vZome" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/zomeknot.png"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karen_Uhlenbeck">Karen Uhlenbeck</a> becomes <a href="http://www.abelprize.no/c73996/seksjon/vis.html?tid=74011&amp;strukt_tid=73996">the first woman to win the Abel Prize</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@JordiGH/101778053801507834"/>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1073">The curse of the Euclidean metric</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101785024820380513"/>). Krzysztof Fleszar posts about a big difficulty with algorithms for problems like Euclidean shortest paths where the answer is a sum of distances: we don’t know how to compare two solutions efficiently. Fortunately in the case of <a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/10.1137/1.9781611975482.67">Krzysztof’s SODA 2019 paper on approximate TSP of hyperplanes</a> (find a short tour that touches each given hyperplane) it’s possible to use approximate numerical comparisons.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-02070778/document">Integer multiplication in time </a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@erou/101787744661719386"/>, <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/">see also</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment/arts/la-ca-cm-inksap-linda-lack-20190314-story.html">An odd couple of Los Angeles street art</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101794533654899105"/>): 20-something Inksap, a son of Vietnamese refugees, and 70-something dance teacher Linda Lack.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://archive.org/stream/BrainfillingCurves-AFractalBestiary/BrainFilling">Brain-filling curves: A fractal bestiary</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101801960587162487"/>). A 200-page compendium by Jeffrey Ventrella of space-filling curves, generated by subdivision rules that expand line segments to lattice paths whose sum of squared edge lengths equals the square of the segment.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.graphics.rwth-aachen.de/software/zometool">Automatically translate any 3d model into a zometool approximation of it</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101807397098535057"/>, <a href="http://www.zometool.com/news/amazing-app-zometool-shape-approximation/">via</a>). With obligatory Stanford bunny. See also their <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=piDPsHTLV1A">1-minute video introduction</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arstechnica.com/science/2019/03/physicists-are-decoding-math-y-secrets-of-knitting-to-make-bespoke-materials/">Physicists are decoding math-y secrets of knitting to make bespoke materials</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101813393444829450"/>). Jennifer Ouelette writes on <em>Ars Technica</em> that by varying the stitching one can control both the stretchiness and shape of the resulting knit.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathml.igalia.com/news/2019/02/12/launch-of-the-project/">The MathML people are trying again</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101820557668090856"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19344843">via</a>). Much as I think MathML has failed and that promotion by its proponents after its failure was already obvious directly caused the continued bad mathematics rendering on Wikipedia, I wish them well. A working web mathematics markup language (if it can be achieved) would be a step up from Javascripted LaTeX. Of course I’m not about to give up LaTeX in my source but that’s what markup processors are for.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@ccppurcell/101822142519831628">Chris Purcell asks “who is the mathematician/scientist who has the most Wikipedia citations without having a Wikipedia page?”</a>. <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101822690106826262">My guess</a> is Heidi Burgiel, co-author of frequently-cited book <em>The Symmetries of Things</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://jmfork.github.io/2048/">Deterministic 2048</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101830138376282978"/>). The next tile is always a 2 at the first available square. It should be possible to describe a strategy that applies to any  board and that provably achieves a score of  but apparently this is not known.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/2019/03/11/incidences-open-problem-part-1/">Adam Sheffer points out that, despite recent advances in incidence geometry, many problems remain open, and sets out on a project to catalog them</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101837928344081808"/>). His starting points are the unit distances problem and incidences with nonlinear algebraic plane curves.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://gizmodo.com/rss-is-better-than-twitter-1833624929">Why you should be keeping up with news and long-form websites using RSS rather than twitter</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101840580734668234"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19529442">via</a>). If you want to incorporate RSS feeds into your Mastodon stream, <a href="https://friend.camp/@darius/100897757870017125">Darius Kazemi’s RSS-to-Mastodon tool</a> looks useful, but I haven’t tried it, because so far I’m happy reading those feeds through NetNewsWire.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2019/03/28/scholars-complain-visa-problems-ahead-international-conference-canada">International Studies Association participants unable to get visas to go to their conference in Toronto</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/101847752696450725"/>), a repeat of an issue I posted about for <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/01/31/linkage.html">NeurIPS in January</a>. According to the story, the proportion of participants with visa issues is similar to recent years when the conference has been in the US. Which is not a great target for Canada to aspire to…</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-31T16:48:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-31T16:48:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T01:34:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12165</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12165" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faster Spectral Sparsification in Dynamic Streams</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1553990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kapralov:Michael.html">Michael Kapralov</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mousavifar:Aida.html">Aida Mousavifar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Musco:Cameron.html">Cameron Musco</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Musco:Christopher.html">Christopher Musco</a>, Navid Nouri <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12165">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Graph sketching has emerged as a powerful technique for processing massive
graphs that change over time (i.e., are presented as a dynamic stream of edge
updates) over the past few years, starting with the work of Ahn, Guha and
McGregor (SODA'12) on graph connectivity via sketching. In this paper we
consider the problem of designing spectral approximations to graphs, or
spectral sparsifiers, using a small number of linear measurements, with the
additional constraint that the sketches admit an efficient recovery scheme.
</p>
<p>Prior to our work, sketching algorithms were known with near optimal $\tilde
O(n)$ space complexity, but $\Omega(n^2)$ time decoding (brute-force over all
potential edges of the input graph), or with subquadratic time, but rather
large $\Omega(n^{5/3})$ space complexity (due to their reliance on a rather
weak relation between connectivity and effective resistances). In this paper we
first show how a simple relation between effective resistances and edge
connectivity leads to an improved $\widetilde O(n^{3/2})$ space and time
algorithm, which we show is a natural barrier for connectivity based
approaches. Our main result then gives the first algorithm that achieves
subquadratic recovery time, i.e. avoids brute-force decoding, and at the same
time nontrivially uses the effective resistance metric, achieving
$n^{1.4+o(1)}$ space and recovery time.
</p>
<p>Our main technical contribution is a novel method for `bucketing' vertices of
the input graph into clusters that allows fast recovery of edges of high
effective resistance: the buckets are formed by performing ball-carving on the
input graph using (an approximation to) its effective resistance metric. We
feel that this technique is likely to be of independent interest.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-03-31T23:22:03Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-03-29T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12150</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12150" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dynamic Streaming Spectral Sparsification in Nearly Linear Time and Space</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1553990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kapralov:Michael.html">Michael Kapralov</a>, Navid Nouri, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sidford:Aaron.html">Aaron Sidford</a>, Jakab Tardos <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12150">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper we consider the problem of computing spectral approximations to
graphs in the single pass dynamic streaming model. We provide a linear
sketching based solution that given a stream of edge insertions and deletions
to a $n$-node undirected graph, uses $\tilde O(n)$ space, processes each update
in $\tilde O(1)$ time, and with high probability recovers a spectral sparsifier
in $\tilde O(n)$ time. Prior to our work, state of the art results either used
near optimal $\tilde O(n)$ space complexity, but brute-force $\Omega(n^2)$
recovery time [Kapralov et al.'14], or with subquadratic runtime, but
polynomially suboptimal space complexity [Ahn et al.'14, Kapralov et al.'19].
</p>
<p>Our main technical contribution is a novel method for `bucketing' vertices of
the input graph into clusters that allows fast recovery of edges of
sufficiently large effective resistance. Our algorithm first buckets vertices
of the graph by performing ball-carving using (an approximation to) its
effective resistance metric, and then recovers the high effective resistance
edges from a sketched version of an electrical flow between vertices in a
bucket, taking nearly linear time in the number of vertices overall. This
process is performed at different geometric scales to recover a sample of edges
with probabilities proportional to effective resistances and obtain an actual
sparsifier of the input graph.
</p>
<p>This work provides both the first efficient $\ell_2$-sparse recovery
algorithm for graphs and new primitives for manipulating the effective
resistance embedding of a graph, both of which we hope have further
applications.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-03-31T23:22:42Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-03-29T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12146</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12146" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Improved Lower Bounds for the Restricted Isometry Property of Subsampled Fourier Matrices</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1553990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rao:Shravas.html">Shravas Rao</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12146">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Let $A$ be an $N \times N$ Fourier matrix over
$\mathbb{F}_p^{\log{N}/\log{p}}$ for some prime $p$. We improve upon known
lower bounds for the number of rows of $A$ that must be sampled so that the
resulting matrix $M$ satisfies the restricted isometry property for $k$-sparse
vectors. This property states that $\|Mv\|_2^2$ is approximately $\|v\|_2^2$
for all $k$-sparse vectors $v$. In particular, if $k = \Omega( \log^2{N})$, we
show that $\Omega(k\log{k}\log{N}/\log{p})$ rows must be sampled to satisfy the
restricted isometry property with constant probability.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-03-31T23:22:38Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-03-29T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12135</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12135" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Sparse Reconstruction from Hadamard Matrices: A Lower Bound</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1553990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Jarosław Błasiok, Patrick Lopatto, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Luh:Kyle.html">Kyle Luh</a>, Jake Marcinek <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12135">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We give a short argument that yields a new lower bound on the number of
subsampled rows from a bounded, orthonormal matrix necessary to form a matrix
with the restricted isometry property. We show that for a $N \times N$ Hadamard
matrix, one cannot recover all $k$-sparse vectors unless the number of
subsampled rows is $\Omega(k \log^2 N)$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-03-31T23:21:13Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-03-29T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12050</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.12050" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Finding a planted clique by adaptive probing</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1553990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/R=aacute=cz:Mikl=oacute=s_Z=.html">Miklós Z. Rácz</a>, Benjamin Schiffer <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.12050">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider a variant of the planted clique problem where we are allowed
unbounded computational time but can only investigate a small part of the graph
by adaptive edge queries. We determine (up to logarithmic factors) the number
of queries necessary both for detecting the presence of a planted clique and
for finding the planted clique.
</p>
<p>Specifically, let $G \sim G(n,1/2,k)$ be a random graph on $n$ vertices with
a planted clique of size $k$. We show that no algorithm that makes at most $q =
o(n^2 / k^2 + n)$ adaptive queries to the adjacency matrix of $G$ is likely to
find the planted clique. On the other hand, when $k \geq (2+\epsilon) \log_2 n$
there exists a simple algorithm (with unbounded computational power) that finds
the planted clique with high probability by making $q = O( (n^2 / k^2) \log^2 n
+ n \log n)$ adaptive queries. For detection, the additive $n$ term is not
necessary: the number of queries needed to detect the presence of a planted
clique is $n^2 / k^2$ (up to logarithmic factors).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-03-31T23:21:23Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-03-29T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.11980</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.11980" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Probabilistic Analysis of Facility Location on Random Shortest Path Metrics</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1553990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Klootwijk:Stefan.html">Stefan Klootwijk</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Manthey:Bodo.html">Bodo Manthey</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.11980">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The facility location problem is an NP-hard optimization problem. Therefore,
approximation algorithms are often used to solve large instances. Such
algorithms often perform much better than worst-case analysis suggests.
Therefore, probabilistic analysis is a widely used tool to analyze such
algorithms. Most research on probabilistic analysis of NP-hard optimization
problems involving metric spaces, such as the facility location problem, has
been focused on Euclidean instances, and also instances with independent
(random) edge lengths, which are non-metric, have been researched. We would
like to extend this knowledge to other, more general, metrics.
</p>
<p>We investigate the facility location problem using random shortest path
metrics. We analyze some probabilistic properties for a simple greedy heuristic
which gives a solution to the facility location problem: opening the $\kappa$
cheapest facilities (with $\kappa$ only depending on the facility opening
costs). If the facility opening costs are such that $\kappa$ is not too large,
then we show that this heuristic is asymptotically optimal. On the other hand,
for large values of $\kappa$, the analysis becomes more difficult, and we
provide a closed-form expression as upper bound for the expected approximation
ratio. In the special case where all facility opening costs are equal this
closed-form expression reduces to $O(\sqrt[4]{\ln(n)})$ or $O(1)$ or even
$1+o(1)$ if the opening costs are sufficiently small.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-03-31T23:21:31Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-03-29T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.11860</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.11860" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Complete Disjoint coNP-Pairs but no Complete Total Polynomial Search Problems Relative to an Oracle</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1553990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dose:Titus.html">Titus Dose</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.11860">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Consider the following conjectures:
</p>
<p>H1: the set TFNP of all total polynomial search problems has no complete
problems with respect to polynomial reductions.
</p>
<p>H2: there exists no many-one complete disjoint coNP-pair.
</p>
<p>We construct an oracle relative to which H1 holds and H2 does not hold. This
partially answers a question by Pudl\'ak [Pud17], who lists several hypotheses
and asks for oracles that show corresponding relativized hypotheses to be
different. As there exists a relativizable proof for the implication H1 -&gt; H2
[Pud17], the relativizations of the hypotheses H1 and H2 are neither
independent nor equivalent.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-03-31T23:20:35Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-03-29T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.11635</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1903.11635" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fourier Entropy-Influence Conjecture for Random Linear Threshold Functions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1553990400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chakraborty:Sourav.html">Sourav Chakraborty</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Karmalkar:Sushrut.html">Sushrut Karmalkar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kundu:Srijita.html">Srijita Kundu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lokam:Satyanarayana_V=.html">Satyanarayana V. Lokam</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saurabh:Nitin.html">Nitin Saurabh</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1903.11635">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Fourier-Entropy Influence (FEI) Conjecture states that for any Boolean
function $f:\{+1,-1\}^n \to \{+1,-1\}$, the Fourier entropy of $f$ is at most
its influence up to a universal constant factor. While the FEI conjecture has
been proved for many classes of Boolean functions, it is still not known
whether it holds for the class of Linear Threshold Functions. A natural
question is: Does the FEI conjecture hold for a `random' linear threshold
function? In this paper, we answer this question in the affirmative. We
consider two natural distributions on the weights defining a linear threshold
function, namely uniform distribution on $[-1,1]$ and Normal distribution.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-03-31T23:20:44Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-03-29T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7489</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/03/30/physics-computation-blog-post-round-up/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Physics &amp; Computation Blog Post Round-up</title>
    <summary>In the Fall, Boaz and I co-taught a grad seminar on physics and computation (see here for some of the original press coverage). We were lucky to attract an intrepid group of students from multiple fields, with representatives from computer science, physics, math and biology. As part of the course, we asked our students to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In the Fall, Boaz and I co-taught a <a href="https://www.boazbarak.org/fall18seminar/">grad seminar</a> on physics and computation (see <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/08/06/physics-envy/">here</a> for some of the original press coverage). We were lucky to attract an intrepid group of students from multiple fields, with representatives from computer science, physics, math and biology. As part of the course, we asked our students to give presentations and write expository blog posts on a number of topics at the intersection of computation and physics, including algorithms from statistical physics, quantum area laws, and the firewall paradox. The students worked hard to produce posts that make the physics concepts accessible to a computer science audience, and the result is a nice collection of posts that create a “bridge” from CS to physics.</p>
<p>Here, the aim is to give a (long overdue) table of contents for their posts. Followers of the blog may have noticed a landslide of physics &amp; computation posts around December and January; if you weren’t able to keep up with them all at the time, then here they are, rounded up and organized by topic.</p>
<h2>Statistical Physics</h2>
<h4>Background and intro to phase transitions:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/09/15/statistical-physics-an-introduction-in-two-parts/">Statistical Physics: an introduction in two parts</a> (by Tselil Schramm)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Algorithms from statistical physics: belief propagation and approximate message passing:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/10/20/belief-propagation-and-the-stochastic-block-model/">Belief Propagation and the Stochastic Block Model</a> (by Thomas Orton)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/26/introduction-to-amp-and-the-replica-trick/">Introduction to AMP and the Replica Trick</a> (by Preetum Nakkiran and <span class="qu"><span class="gD">Yueqi </span></span><span class="qu"><span class="gD">Sheng)</span></span></li>
</ul>
<h4>Informational and computational phase transitions:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/16/algorithmic-and-information-theoretic-decoding-thresholds-for-low-density-parity-check-code/">Algorithmic and Information Theoretic Decoding Thresholds for Low density Parity-Check Code</a> (by Jeremy Dohmann, Vanessa Wong, and Venkat Arun)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Proving the existence of phase transitions:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/13/ising-perceptron-under-gaussian-disorder-and-k-nae-sat/">Ising Perceptron under Gaussian Disorder, and k-NAE-SAT</a> (based on a guest lecture by <a href="https://www.stat.berkeley.edu/~nikesun/">Nike Sun</a>, as scribed by Patrick Guo, Vinh-Kha Le, Shyam Narayanan, and David Stoner)</li>
</ul>
<h4> Using convex relaxations to approximate partition functions:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/11/11/approximating-partition-functions/">Approximating Partition Functions</a> (based on a guest lecture by <a href="https://math.mit.edu/~risteski/">Andrej Risteski</a> as scribed by Alex Kelser, Alex Lin, Amil Merchant, and Suproteem Sarkar)</li>
</ul>
<h2>Quantum Computation</h2>
<h4>Background on Quantum Hamiltonians and tensor network representations:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/20/quantum-hamiltonian-complexity/">What is Quantum Hamiltonian Complexity?</a> (by Ben Edelman)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/20/tensor-networks-matrix-product-states-dmrg/">Tensor Networks, Matrix Product States and Density Matrix Renormalization Group</a> (by Fred Zhang)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Area laws:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/18/a-1d-area-law-for-gapped-local-hamiltonians/">A 1D Area Law for Gapped Local Hamiltonians</a> (by Boriana Gjura and Prayaag Venkat)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quantum algorithms:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/23/introduction-to-quantum-walks/">Introduction to Quantum Walks</a> (by Beatrice Nash)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/20/efficient-preparation-of-thermal-states-of-quantum-systems-natural-or-artificial/">Efficient preparation of thermal states of quantum systems: natural or artificial</a> (based on a guest lecture by <a href="http://web.mit.edu/aram/www/">Aram Harrow</a> as scribed by Sinho Chewi, William S. Moses, Tasha Schoenstein, Ary Swaminathan)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/22/quantum-approximate-optimization-algorithm-and-applications/">Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm and Applications</a> (by
<div class="b4">
<div class="dl">
<div class="aIj">
<div class="c5 J-J5-Ji">Amir Karamlou)</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="dp"/>
</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quantum games and quantum PCPs:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/22/towards-quantum-pcp-a-proof-of-the-nlets-theorem/">Towards Quantum PCP: A Proof of the NLETS Theorem</a> (by Abhijit Mudigonda, Richard Wang, and Lisa Yang)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/03/quantum-games/">Quantum Games</a> (by Nilin Abrahamsen, Daniel Alabi, Mitali Bafna, Emil Khabiboulline, and Juspreet Sandhu)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quantum supremacy:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/25/quantum-circuits-and-their-role-in-demonstrating-quantum-supremacy/">Quantum circuits and their role in demonstrating quantum supremacy</a> (by Hikari Sorensen)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quantum error correction:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/12/07/quantum-error-correction/">Peter Shor on Quantum Error Correction</a> (based on a guest lecture by Peter Shor as scribed by Annie Wei)</li>
</ul>
<h2>Black Holes and the Firewall Paradox</h2>
<p>(See also Boaz’s <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/08/22/black-holes-paradoxes-and-computational-complexity/">introductory post</a>)</p>
<h4>Background on black holes and the Firewall Paradox:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/20/the-firewall-paradox-in-context/">Why physicists care about the Firewall Paradox</a> (by Noah Miller)</li>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/01/30/black-hole-paradoxes-a-conservative-yet-radical-journey/">Black hole paradoxes: A conservative yet radical journey</a> (by Abhishek Anand and Noah Miller)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Firewall Paradox meets Computational Complexity:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/02/01/black-holes-a-complexity-theory-perspective/">Black Holes, a complexity theory perspective</a> (by Chi-Ning Chou and Parth Mehta)</li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-30T20:20:58Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-30T20:20:58Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>tselilschramm</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=15708</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Integer Multiplication in NlogN Time</title>
    <summary>A win for multi-variable polynomials Composite crop from src1, src2 David Harvey and Joris van der Hoeven are computational mathematicians. They have just released a paper showing how to multiply two -bit integers in time. A companion paper gives details of a simpler second algorithm that is time pending a widely-believed conjecture about primes. Today […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>A win for multi-variable polynomials</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/03/29/integer-multiplication-in-nlogn-time/harveyvanderhoeven2/" rel="attachment wp-att-15709"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-15709" height="150" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/03/harveyvanderhoeven2.png?w=201&amp;h=150" width="201"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Composite crop from <a href="https://web.maths.unsw.edu.au/~davidharvey/">src1</a>, <a href="https://www.polytechnique.edu/en/content/researchers-lx-international-congress-mathematicians-brazil">src2</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
David Harvey and Joris van der Hoeven are computational mathematicians. They have just released a <a href="https://web.maths.unsw.edu.au/~davidharvey/papers/nlogn/">paper</a> showing how to multiply two <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-bit integers in <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/> time. A companion <a href="http://www.texmacs.org/joris/ffnlogn/ffnlogn-abs.html">paper</a> gives details of a simpler second algorithm that is <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/> time pending a widely-believed conjecture about primes.</p>
<p>
Today we discuss what makes these new results possible.</p>
<p>
The first paper leads off with a nice history of algorithms that beat the <img alt="{O(n^2)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E2%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n^2)}"/>-time method all of us learned in school. Far from being <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2010/10/23/galactic-algorithms/">galactic</a>, the longtime-champion <img alt="{O(n\log n \log\!\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n+%5Clog%5C%21%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n \log\!\log n)}"/> algorithm of Arnold Schönhage and Volker Strassen is a workhorse of the GNU Multiple Precision Library (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_Multiple_Precision_Arithmetic_Library">GMP</a>). The <img alt="{\log\!\log n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog%5C%21%5Clog+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log\!\log n}"/> factor was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Furer's_algorithm">improved</a> by Martin Fürer in 2007 and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1407.3360?context=cs">further</a> in 2014 by Harvey and van der Hoeven with Grégoire Lecerf. Now it is gone altogether.</p>
<p>
Their algorithm is currently not practical, but it is also not yet tuned. At the start of section 5, they note that their estimates take effect for <img alt="{n \geq 2^{d^{12}}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn+%5Cgeq+2%5E%7Bd%5E%7B12%7D%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n \geq 2^{d^{12}}}"/> where they use <img alt="{d = 1,\!729}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd+%3D+1%2C%5C%21729%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d = 1,\!729}"/>. When they note that <img alt="{2^{d^{12}} &gt; 2^{4,\!096}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7Bd%5E%7B12%7D%7D+%3E+2%5E%7B4%2C%5C%21096%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{d^{12}} &gt; 2^{4,\!096}}"/> they don’t mean the numbers need at least <img alt="{4,\!096}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B4%2C%5C%21096%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{4,\!096}"/> bits, rather <img alt="{2^{4,\!096}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7B4%2C%5C%21096%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{4,\!096}}"/> is the number of bits. Since there are only <a href="https://www.popularmechanics.com/space/a27259/how-many-particles-are-in-the-entire-universe/">about</a> <img alt="{2^{270}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7B270%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{270}}"/> particles in the observable universe, this puts the term <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2010/10/23/galactic-algorithms/">galactic</a> to shame. </p>
<p>
The number <img alt="{1,\!729}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2C%5C%21729%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1,\!729}"/> recalls a famous <a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Hardy-RamanujanNumber.html">story</a> about Godfrey Hardy and Srinivasa Ramanujan. This is not wholly a coincidence. They get a bounding multiplier of <img alt="{36}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B36%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{36}"/> from one place, another factor of <img alt="{6}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B6%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{6}"/> from another, and finally a factor of <img alt="{8}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B8%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{8}"/> giving <img alt="{1,\!728}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2C%5C%21728%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1,\!728}"/> which equals <img alt="{12^3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B12%5E3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{12^3}"/>. Then they just make <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/> be higher by <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/>, setting up <img alt="{1,\!729 = 12^3 + 1^3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2C%5C%21729+%3D+12%5E3+%2B+1%5E3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1,\!729 = 12^3 + 1^3}"/> which happens to equal <img alt="{9^3 + 10^3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B9%5E3+%2B+10%5E3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{9^3 + 10^3}"/>. But there is much flex in the choices and they sketch how to improve the needed bound from <img alt="{1,\!728}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2C%5C%21728%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1,\!728}"/> to just <img alt="{8}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B8%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{8}"/>. They also uncover some new tricks for calculating in certain large finite rings defined via multi-variable polynomials.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Polynomials and Tricks </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
When we heard the news on Tuesday, both of us thought of the famous primality <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AKS_primality_test">test</a> of Manindra Agrawal, Neeraj Kayal, and Nitin Saxena (AKS), which placed deciding primality into deterministic polynomial time. We stated the message as the title of an old <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2011/02/26/polynomials-are-easier-than-integers/">post</a> on other joint work by Kayal: “Polynomials Are Easier Than Integers.” </p>
<p>
The crux of the AKS test is to employ the theorem that for any co-prime <img alt="{(a,N)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28a%2CN%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(a,N)}"/>, the polynomial congruence relation </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  (x + a)^N \equiv x^N + a \pmod{N} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%28x+%2B+a%29%5EN+%5Cequiv+x%5EN+%2B+a+%5Cpmod%7BN%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  (x + a)^N \equiv x^N + a \pmod{N} "/></p>
<p>holds in <img alt="{\mathbb{Z}[x]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{Z}[x]}"/> if and only if <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> is prime. This is tested in the quotient ring <img alt="{\mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^r - 1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx%5D%2F%28x%5Er+-+1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^r - 1)}"/>. The game becomes finding <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> small enough and minimizing the number of <img alt="{a}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a}"/> that need to be checked in order for the body of tests in the quotient ring to be conclusive. </p>
<p>
We take time to note that the case <img alt="{a = N-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba+%3D+N-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a = N-1}"/> is possibly sufficient while testing a small set of <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/>. Agrawal has <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agrawal's_conjecture">conjectured</a> that if <img alt="{(x - 1)^N \equiv x^N - 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x+-+1%29%5EN+%5Cequiv+x%5EN+-+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(x - 1)^N \equiv x^N - 1}"/> modulo both <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> and <img alt="{x^r - 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%5Er+-+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x^r - 1}"/> then either <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> is prime or <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> divides <img alt="{N^2 - 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%5E2+-+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N^2 - 1}"/>. This conjecture is <a href="https://aimath.org/WWN/primesinp/primesinp.pdf">doubted</a> on heuristic counting grounds but it has been verified for <img alt="{N &lt; 10^{12}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN+%3C+10%5E%7B12%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N &lt; 10^{12}}"/> and can be <a href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2009/008.pdf">modified</a> by including the case <img alt="{a = 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba+%3D+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a = 2}"/>. It would improve the polynomial time in the number <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> of bits in <img alt="{N}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BN%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{N}"/> from <img alt="{\tilde{O}(n^6)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctilde%7BO%7D%28n%5E6%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\tilde{O}(n^6)}"/> to <img alt="{\tilde{O}(n^3)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ctilde%7BO%7D%28n%5E3%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\tilde{O}(n^3)}"/> and also improve the constants. We mention this because Harvey and van der Hoeven have a number-theoretic conjecture that (as shown in their companion paper) improves both their constant on <img alt="{n\log n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5Clog+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n\log n}"/> and the simplicity of the proof.</p>
<p>
The further message of the new papers is added power from giving the polynomials more variables. They use <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/> variables: <img alt="{x_1,\dots,x_{d-1}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_%7Bd-1%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x_1,\dots,x_{d-1}}"/> plus a nominal <img alt="{x_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x_d}"/> that is later substituted by <img alt="{e^{\pi i/r} y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%5E%7B%5Cpi+i%2Fr%7D+y%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e^{\pi i/r} y}"/>. Here <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> is a certain power of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/> and combined with the <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/>-th variable <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/> to build the base ring <img alt="{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R}"/> of complex polynomials in <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y}"/> modulo <img alt="{y^r + 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%5Er+%2B+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y^r + 1}"/>. The other variables are used to mod out by <img alt="{(x_1^{t_1} - 1,\dots,x_{d-1}^{t_{d-1}} - 1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x_1%5E%7Bt_1%7D+-+1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_%7Bd-1%7D%5E%7Bt_%7Bd-1%7D%7D+-+1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(x_1^{t_1} - 1,\dots,x_{d-1}^{t_{d-1}} - 1)}"/> where the <img alt="{t_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_i}"/> are powers of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/> no higher than <img alt="{2r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2r%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2r}"/>. Operations in quotient rings of this type are especially efficient. They are used to emulate operations in <img alt="{\mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^s - 1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx%5D%2F%28x%5Es+-+1%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^s - 1)}"/> where <img alt="{s}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s}"/> is a product of primes <img alt="{s_1\cdots s_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_1%5Ccdots+s_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_1\cdots s_d}"/> that are near powers of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/>. The emulation is done via the isomorphism</p>
<p>
<a name="CRT"/></p><a name="CRT">
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^{s_1\cdots s_d} - 1) \cong \mathbb{Z}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{s_1} - 1,\dots,x_d^{s_d} - 1), \ \ \ \ \ (1)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx%5D%2F%28x%5E%7Bs_1%5Ccdots+s_d%7D+-+1%29+%5Ccong+%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5D%2F%28x_1%5E%7Bs_1%7D+-+1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5E%7Bs_d%7D+-+1%29%2C+%5C+%5C+%5C+%5C+%5C+%281%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \mathbb{Z}[x]/(x^{s_1\cdots s_d} - 1) \cong \mathbb{Z}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{s_1} - 1,\dots,x_d^{s_d} - 1), \ \ \ \ \ (1)"/></p>
</a><p><a name="CRT"/> which follows from the Chinese remainder theorem. </p>
<p>
They start with Schönhage and Strassen’s original trick of splitting the two <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-bit integers into <img alt="{\Theta(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CTheta%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Theta(\log n)}"/>-sized pieces so that the problem reduces to multiplying polynomials of degree <img alt="{\Theta(n/\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5CTheta%28n%2F%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\Theta(n/\log n)}"/> in <img alt="{\mathbb{Z}[x]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BZ%7D%5Bx%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{Z}[x]}"/> with coefficients of <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/> size. They use the <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/>-dimensional Discrete Fourier Transform over <img alt="{\mathbb{C}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BC%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{C}}"/> with complex operations that need only <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/> bits of precision individually. This setting also gives leeway for approximative methods in their final algorithm. But first we describe what was evidently their original strategy.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Recursive Strategy </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Their first task in either case is to find <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/>-many distinct primes <img alt="{s_1,\dots,s_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cs_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_1,\dots,s_d}"/> of order <img alt="{(n/\log n)^{1/d}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28n%2F%5Clog+n%29%5E%7B1%2Fd%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{(n/\log n)^{1/d}}"/> in magnitude. Now when <img alt="{d = 1,\!729}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd+%3D+1%2C%5C%21729%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d = 1,\!729}"/> the exponent <img alt="{1/d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2Fd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1/d}"/> makes the primes quite small indeed, and the need to find distinct ones already drives <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> up quite high before their algorithm can even go into effect. Moreover, for the approximation to work, the primes need to be congruent to <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/> modulo <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/>. </p>
<p>
Their original strategy—detailed in the companion paper—builds on a <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/1448407">result</a> of Charles Rader to reduce the DFT computation to multiplications in </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \mathbb{C}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{s_1 - 1} - 1,\dots,x_d^{s_d - 1} - 1), " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathbb%7BC%7D%5Bx_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5D%2F%28x_1%5E%7Bs_1+-+1%7D+-+1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5E%7Bs_d+-+1%7D+-+1%29%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \mathbb{C}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{s_1 - 1} - 1,\dots,x_d^{s_d - 1} - 1), "/></p>
<p>where compared to (<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/#CRT">1</a>) they have reduced the exponents by one. Using <img alt="{s_i \equiv 1 \pmod{r}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_i+%5Cequiv+1+%5Cpmod%7Br%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_i \equiv 1 \pmod{r}}"/>, they next reduce this to multiplications in </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \mathbb{C}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{r} - 1,\dots,x_d^{r} - 1). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathbb%7BC%7D%5Bx_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5D%2F%28x_1%5E%7Br%7D+-+1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_d%5E%7Br%7D+-+1%29.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \mathbb{C}[x_1,\dots,x_d]/(x_1^{r} - 1,\dots,x_d^{r} - 1). "/></p>
<p>Then the above-mentioned substitution of <img alt="{x_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x_d}"/> by <img alt="{e^{\pi i/r} y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%5E%7B%5Cpi+i%2Fr%7D+y%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{e^{\pi i/r} y}"/> makes them into products over </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  R[x_1,\dots,x_{d-1}]/(x_1^{t_1} - 1,\dots,x_{d-1}^{t_{d-1}} - 1) \qquad\text{with}\qquad R = \mathbb{C}[y]/(y^r + 1). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++R%5Bx_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_%7Bd-1%7D%5D%2F%28x_1%5E%7Bt_1%7D+-+1%2C%5Cdots%2Cx_%7Bd-1%7D%5E%7Bt_%7Bd-1%7D%7D+-+1%29+%5Cqquad%5Ctext%7Bwith%7D%5Cqquad+R+%3D+%5Cmathbb%7BC%7D%5By%5D%2F%28y%5Er+%2B+1%29.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  R[x_1,\dots,x_{d-1}]/(x_1^{t_1} - 1,\dots,x_{d-1}^{t_{d-1}} - 1) \qquad\text{with}\qquad R = \mathbb{C}[y]/(y^r + 1). "/></p>
<p>These last products are at last amenable to the usual Fast Fourier Transform trick of applying FFT for each <img alt="{t_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_i}"/> by pretending that <img alt="{y^{2r/t_i}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%5E%7B2r%2Ft_i%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{y^{2r/t_i}}"/> is a primitive <img alt="{t_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_i}"/>-th root of unity, multiplying pointwise in <img alt="{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R}"/>, and doing the inverse FFT. Finally the products in <img alt="{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R}"/> can be converted into <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/>-bit integer products, and this sets up the vast recursion from multiplying the original <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-bit integers to a batch of <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/>-bit ones. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Finding Good Primes </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
In order for the recursion to solve to <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/>, they need the values <img alt="{q_i = (s_i - 1)/r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq_i+%3D+%28s_i+-+1%29%2Fr%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q_i = (s_i - 1)/r}"/> to be not too large. Viewing this task from the bottom up, they want to choose a single value <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> and choose small <img alt="{q_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q_i}"/> such that <img alt="{s_i = rq_i + 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_i+%3D+rq_i+%2B+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_i = rq_i + 1}"/> is prime. Since <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> is a power of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/>, there is some resemblance to the harder task of finding Sophie Germain primes, which are also relevant to the AKS algorithm. In this case, however, all they need is a sufficiently small <img alt="{\epsilon &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon &gt; 0}"/> such that:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> For all coprime <img alt="{a,k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Ba%2Ck%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{a,k}"/> with <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k}"/> sufficiently large, there is a prime <img alt="{q &lt; k^{1+\epsilon}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq+%3C+k%5E%7B1%2B%5Cepsilon%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q &lt; k^{1+\epsilon}}"/> such that <img alt="{q \equiv a \pmod{k}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq+%5Cequiv+a+%5Cpmod%7Bk%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q \equiv a \pmod{k}}"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This is, however, only known for “<img alt="{\epsilon}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon}"/>” <img alt="{= 4.18}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3D+4.18%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{= 4.18}"/> and the Generalized Riemann Hypothesis is only known to improve the bound to <img alt="{k^{2+\delta}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%5E%7B2%2B%5Cdelta%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k^{2+\delta}}"/> for any <img alt="{\delta &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdelta+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\delta &gt; 0}"/>. The above is conjectured to hold for any <img alt="{\epsilon &gt; 0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon+%3E+0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon &gt; 0}"/> but it hasn’t been proved. They currently need it for <img alt="{\epsilon = 1/303}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon+%3D+1%2F303%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon = 1/303}"/>.</p>
<p>
The companion paper uses the conjecture to improve multiplication in the field <img alt="{\mathbb{F}_{p^\ell}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BF%7D_%7Bp%5E%5Cell%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{F}_{p^\ell}}"/> to time <img alt="{O(n\ell \log(p)(\log(n) + \log(\ell) + \log\!\log(p))}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Cell+%5Clog%28p%29%28%5Clog%28n%29+%2B+%5Clog%28%5Cell%29+%2B+%5Clog%5C%21%5Clog%28p%29%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\ell \log(p)(\log(n) + \log(\ell) + \log\!\log(p))}"/>. This uses a single algorithm over any prime <img alt="{p}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bp%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{p}"/> and power <img alt="{\ell}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cell%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\ell}"/>; of course if they are fixed, then this time likewise becomes <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/>. This currently needs <img alt="{\epsilon = 1/2^{1,\!162}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cepsilon+%3D+1%2F2%5E%7B1%2C%5C%21162%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\epsilon = 1/2^{1,\!162}}"/>. </p>
<p>
The companion <a href="http://www.texmacs.org/joris/ffnlogn/ffnlogn-abs.html">paper</a> has full details of how all this works and many more numerical tricks than we’ve mentioned—a <em>tour de force</em>. Getting the result for integer multiplication unconditionally, however, requires one more major tool in their arsenal. To use it they set up the primes <img alt="{s_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_i}"/> to be slightly below respective powers of 2 <img alt="{t_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_i}"/> (rather than be above a single power of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/> <img alt="{r}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Br%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{r}"/> by the aforementioned factors <img alt="{q_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q_i}"/>) while retaining <img alt="{t_1\cdots t_d = O(s_1 \cdots s_d)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_1%5Ccdots+t_d+%3D+O%28s_1+%5Ccdots+s_d%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_1\cdots t_d = O(s_1 \cdots s_d)}"/>. </p>
<p>
Their innovation compared to the translations in the first strategy is that one can still reduce the DFT computation in dimensions <img alt="{s_1,\dots,s_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bs_1%2C%5Cdots%2Cs_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{s_1,\dots,s_d}"/> needing <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/> precision to a complex DFT in dimensions <img alt="{t_1,\dots,t_d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt_1%2C%5Cdots%2Ct_d%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t_1,\dots,t_d}"/> by employing approximation. Their algorithm is completely deterministic but it employs weights that conform to Gaussian distributions to effect the approximation. The preservation of Gaussians under Fourier transforms enables close enough approximations to be obtained by solving relatively small and easily-specified systems of linear equations. The resulting complex DFT is then massaged in a manner similar to the first strategy. The resulting recursion is not quite as steep—it goes from <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> to <img alt="{n' = n^{1/d + o(1)}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%27+%3D+n%5E%7B1%2Fd+%2B+o%281%29%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n' = n^{1/d + o(1)}}"/>—but it gives </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  M(n) = \frac{Kn}{n'} M(n') + O(n\log n) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++M%28n%29+%3D+%5Cfrac%7BKn%7D%7Bn%27%7D+M%28n%27%29+%2B+O%28n%5Clog+n%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  M(n) = \frac{Kn}{n'} M(n') + O(n\log n) "/></p>
<p>with <img alt="{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{K}"/> and the <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/> term independent of <img alt="{d}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{d}"/> (indeed, <img alt="{K}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{K}"/> becomes the aforementioned <img alt="{1,\!729}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2C%5C%21729%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1,\!729}"/>). This gives <img alt="{M(n) = O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%28n%29+%3D+O%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{M(n) = O(n\log n)}"/>. The approximation technique does not work for multiplication in <img alt="{\mathbb{F}_{p^\ell}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathbb%7BF%7D_%7Bp%5E%5Cell%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathbb{F}_{p^\ell}}"/>, however. As usual, here is where we say to consult the papers for further details—there is a wealth of them.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Will the <img alt="{O(n\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n\log n)}"/> time be concretely improvable? Will it tell us anything about the <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2009/02/24/a-conjecture-of-hartmanis/">problem</a> of <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2012/06/15/why-the-hartmanis-stearns-conjecture-is-still-open/">proving</a> a super-linear lower bound? And short of those two goals, what new results will become possible through the multi-variable polynomial techniques they employ?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-29T13:23:44Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-29T13:23:44Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="primes"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="trick"/>
    <category term="algebra"/>
    <category term="Arnold Schonhage"/>
    <category term="asymptotics"/>
    <category term="congruence"/>
    <category term="David Harvey"/>
    <category term="finite fields"/>
    <category term="integer multiplication"/>
    <category term="Joris van der Hoeven"/>
    <category term="Manindra Agrawal"/>
    <category term="Martin Furer"/>
    <category term="Neeraj Kayal"/>
    <category term="Nitin Saxena"/>
    <category term="NlogN time"/>
    <category term="polynomials"/>
    <category term="rings"/>
    <category term="Volker Strassen"/>
    <author>
      <name>KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/045</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/045" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-045 |  On the Fine-grained Complexity of Least Weight Subsequence in Graphs | 

	Jiawei Gao</title>
    <summary>Least Weight Subsequence (LWS) is a type of highly sequential optimization problems with form $F(j) = \min_{i &lt; j} [F(i) + c_{i,j}]$. They can be solved in quadratic time using dynamic programming, but it is not known whether these problems can be solved faster than $n^{2-o(1)}$ time. Surprisingly, each such problem is subquadratic time reducible to a highly parallel, non-dynamic programming problem [KPS17]. In other words, if a "static"  problem is faster than quadratic time, so is an LWS problem. For many instances of LWS, the sequential versions are equivalent to their static versions by subquadratic time reductions. The previous result applies to LWS on linear structures, and this paper extends this result to LWS on paths in sparse graphs. When the graph is a multitree (i.e. a DAG where any pair vertices can have at most one path) or when the graph is a DAG whose underlying undirected graph has constant treewidth, we show that LWS on this graph is still subquadratically reducible to their corresponding static problems. For many instances, the graph versions are still equivalent to their static versions.

Moreover, this paper shows that on these graphs, property testing of form $\exists x \exists y (\text{TC}_E(x,y) \wedge P(x,y))$ is subquadratically reducible to property testing of form $\exists x \exists y P(x,y)$, where $P$ is a property checkable in time linear to the sizes of $x$ and $y$, and $\text{TC}_E$ is the transitive closure of relation $E$. Furthermore, when $P$ is definable by a first-order logic formula with at most one quantified variable, then the above two problems are equivalent to each other by subquadratic reductions.</summary>
    <updated>2019-03-28T20:21:13Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-28T20:21:13Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=345</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2019/03/28/tcs-talk-wednesday-april-3rd-richard-peng-georgia-tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, April 3rd — Richard Peng, Georgia Tech</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, April 3rd at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 18:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). Richard Peng from Georgia Tech will speak about “Fully Dynamic Spectral Vertex Sparsifiers and Applications” (abstract below). Please make sure you reserve a spot for your group to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, April 3rd at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 18:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC). <strong>Richard Peng</strong> from Georgia Tech will speak about “<em>Fully Dynamic Spectral Vertex Sparsifiers and Applications</em>” (abstract below).</p>
<p>Please make sure you reserve a spot for your group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk/live-seat-reservation">the online form</a>. As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/">the website</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Abstract: Problems arising from analyzing and understanding graph structures have motivated the development of many powerful tools for storing and compressing graphs and networks. Many, if not most, of these massive graphs are accumulations of updates over time. Maintaining updates and queries on dynamically changing graphs more efficiently than recomputing from scratch is a well-studied topic, with several important open problems related to global, optimization related queries.</p>
<p>We study dynamic graph algorithms for maintaining spectral vertex sparsifiers with respect to a subset of terminal vertices. Such sparsifiers preserve key structures in spectral algorithms, including effective resistances (which can be viewed as a numerical generalization of connectivity), solutions to systems of Laplacian linear equations, and energy of electrical flows between terminal vertices. We give data structures that maintain, in sublinear time, these sparsifiers under insertions/deletions of edges, as well as terminal additions.</p>
<p>This primitive in turn leads to sublinear time data structures for key primitives in spectral graph algorithms, including ones at the core of the “Laplacian paradigm” for designing graph optimization algorithms. In particular, we obtain <img alt="O(m^{4/3}\epsilon^{-4})" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=O%28m%5E%7B4%2F3%7D%5Cepsilon%5E%7B-4%7D%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0" title="O(m^{4/3}\epsilon^{-4})"/> time per query/update for effective resistances on unweighted graphs, and <img alt="O(n^{11/12}\epsilon^{-5})" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=O%28n%5E%7B11%2F12%7D%5Cepsilon%5E%7B-5%7D%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0" title="O(n^{11/12}\epsilon^{-5})"/> time per query/update for implicit access to linear system solutions, where <img alt="\epsilon" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cepsilon&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0" title="\epsilon"/> is the relative approximation accuracy.</p>
<p>The majority of the talk will focus on key components of this data structure: (1) an interpretation of vertex sparsifiers as a sum of random walks, (2) a suitable choice of terminals to keep these walks local, and (3) maintenance of local walks and numerical solutions. Potential avenues in generalizing these techniques to provide new building blocks for dynamic graph algorithms will also be discussed.</p></blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-28T17:26:49Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-28T17:26:49Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7487</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/03/28/nominate-tcs-papers-for-research-highlights/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Nominate TCS papers for research highlights</title>
    <summary>[Guest post by Aleksander Mądry] To me, one of the best things about working in theoretical computer science has always the exciting rate of progress we make as a community. On (what appears to be) a regular basis, we produce breakthroughs on problems that are absolutely fundamental to our field. Problems that often look impossible to tackle, right […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>[Guest post by Aleksander Mądry]</em></p>



<p>To me, one of the best things about working in theoretical computer <br/>science has always the exciting rate of progress we make as a community. <br/>On (what appears to be) a regular basis, we produce breakthroughs on <br/>problems that are absolutely fundamental to our field. Problems that <br/>often look impossible to tackle, right up until someone actually tackles <br/>them.</p>



<p>However, as inspiring as all these developments were to me, I also <br/>always felt that we, as a community, could do more to properly recognize <br/>and highlight them, both internally and to the outside world. This kind <br/>of outreach would make it easier for us to capitalize on the <br/>breakthroughs as well as to accelerate the impact of the underlying <br/>ideas on the other areas of computer science, and beyond.</p>



<p>Fortunately, this is about to change!</p>



<p>One of the first decisions of our newly (re-)elected <a href="https://www.sigact.org/">SIGACT committee</a> was to create a committee (as committees are wont to do <img alt="&#x1F642;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f642.png" style="height: 1em;"/> whose mission will be to help  promote top computer science theory research. This <strong>SIGACT Research Highlights Committee</strong> – consisting of <a href="https://www.boazbarak.org/">Boaz Barak</a>, <a href="https://omereingold.wordpress.com/">Omer Reingold</a>,  <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/marywootters/">Mary Wootters</a> and <a href="https://people.csail.mit.edu/madry/">myself</a> – will, in particular, work to identify results to be recommended for consideration for the <a href="http://cacm.acm.org/">CACM </a>Research Highlights section as well  as other general-audience research outlets in computer science and other  fields.</p>



<p>Of course, to do a proper job here we require your help! To this end, <br/>the committee solicits two types of nominations:</p>



<p>1) Conference nominations. Each year, the committee will ask the PC <br/>chairs of a broad set of theoretical computer science conferences to <br/>send a selection of up to three top papers from these conferences <br/>(selected based on both their technical merit and the potential <br/>significant interest to non-theory audiences) and forwarding them to the <br/>committee for consideration.</p>



<p>2) Community nominations. The committee will accept nominations from the  members of the community. Each such nomination should summarize the  contribution of the nominated (and recently published) paper and also <br/>argue why this paper particularly merits a broader outreach. The <br/>nomination should be no more than a page in length and can be submitted <br/>at any time by emailing it to <a href="mailto:sigact.cacm.nominations@gmail.com" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">sigact.cacm.nominations@gmail.com</a>. <br/>Self-nominations are discouraged.</p>



<p>To be considered in the upcoming round of our deliberations, we need to <br/>receive your nomination by <strong>April 30</strong>.</p>



<p>Looking forward to learning about all the new exciting research that you <br/>all are doing!

</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-28T15:37:01Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-28T15:37:01Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>windowsontheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4213</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/03/28/and-now-for-something-completely-different/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>And now for something completely different</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After 22 years in the United States, 19 of which spent in the San Francisco Bay Area, this Summer I will move to Milan to take a job at Bocconi University. Like a certain well-known Bay Area institution, Bocconi is … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/03/28/and-now-for-something-completely-different/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
 After 22 years in the United States, 19 of which spent in the San Francisco Bay Area, this Summer I will move to Milan to take a job at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bocconi_University">Bocconi University</a>.</p>
<p>
Like a certain well-known Bay Area institution, Bocconi is a private university that was endowed by a rich merchant in memory of his dead son. Initially characterized by an exclusive focus on law, economics and business, it has had for a while a high domestic recognition for the quality of teaching and, more recently, a good international profile both in teaching and research. Despite its small size, compared to Italy’s giant public universities, in 2017 Bocconi was the Italian university which had received the most ERC grants during the first ten years of existence of the European Research Council (in second place was my Alma Mater, the Sapienza University of Rome, which has about nine times more professors) <a href="https://milano.repubblica.it/cronaca/2017/03/07/news/in_bocconi_i_fuoriclasse_della_ricerca-159919972/">(source)</a>.</p>
<p>
About three years ago, Bocconi started planning for a move in the space of computing, in the context of their existing efforts in <a href="http://www.bidsa.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/Site/Bidsa/Home">data science</a>. As a first step, they recruited <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/riccardozecchina/home">Riccardo Zecchina</a>. You may remember Riccardo from his work providing a non-rigorous calculation of the threshold of random 3-SAT, his work on the “survey propagation” algorithm for SAT and other constraint satisfaction problems, as well as other work that brought statistical physics techniques to computer science. Currently, Riccardo and his group are doing very exciting work on the theory of deep learning.</p>
<p>
Though I knew of his work, I had never met Riccardo until I attended a 2017 workshop at the Santa Fe Institute on <a href="https://www.santafe.edu/events/thermodynamics-and-computation-towards-new-synthes">“Thermodynamics and computation,”</a> an invitation that I had accepted on whim, mostly based on the fact that I had never been to New Mexico and I had really liked Breaking Bad. Riccardo had just moved to Bocconi, he told me about their future plans, and he asked me if I was interested. I initially politely declined, but one thing led to another, and now here I am putting up my San Francisco house for sale.</p>
<p>
Last August, as I was considering this move, I applied for an <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2018/07/31/erc-vs-nsf/">ERC grant</a> from the European Union, and I just learned that the <a href="https://erc.europa.eu/news/erc-2018-advanced-grants-results">grant has been approved</a>. This grant is approximately the same amount as the total of all the grants that I have received from the NSF over the past twenty years, and it will support several postdoc positions, as well as visitors ranging from people coming for a week to give a talk and meet with my group to a full-year sabbatical visit.</p>
<p>
 Although it’s a bit late for that, I am looking for postdocs starting as early as this September: if you are interested please contact me. The postdoc positions will pay a highly competitive salary, which will be free of Italian income tax (<s>although American citizens will owe federal income tax to the IRS</s> correction: American citizens would not owe anything to IRS either). As a person from Rome, I am not allowed to say good things about Milan or else I will have to return my Roman card (it’s kind of a NY versus LA thing), but I think that the allure of the city speaks for itself.</p>
<p>
Likewise, if you are a senior researcher, and you have always wanted to visit me and work together on spectral methods, approximation algorithms, graph theory or graph algorithms, but you felt that Berkeley had insufficiently many Leonardo mural paintings and opera houses, and that it was too far from the Alps, then now you are in luck!</p>
<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-28T12:50:40Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-28T12:50:40Z</published>
    <category term="Italy"/>
    <category term="theory"/>
    <category term="Berkeley"/>
    <category term="ERC"/>
    <category term="Bocconi"/>
    <category term="Four days too soon"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:20:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-2959222585780083759</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/2959222585780083759/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/03/scooped.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2959222585780083759" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2959222585780083759" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/03/scooped.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Scooped</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At Dagstuhl I got a few ideas for future posts but then...<br/>
<br/>
We had some discussions about STOC allowing program committee members to submit papers that I planned to post about. But then Suresh wrote a <a href="http://blog.geomblog.org/2019/03/on-pc-submissions-at-soda-2020.html">fine post</a> on the same issue for SODA. My thoughts: PC members should not submit--no matter how you try to avoid the conflict of interest, there will always be a cloud on the process. Suresh suggest blind reviews that other non-theory conferences use, but I prefer the tiered PC system. It's fine to have PC members submit papers if the top of the tier, a senior PC or the PC chairs, makes the final calls.<br/>
<br/>
I was also going to post about Yann LeCun's <a href="https://www.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=10152719972317143&amp;id=722677142">Facebook rant</a> about stodgy CS departments but then Yann goes ahead and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/03/27/technology/turing-award-ai.html">wins a Turing award</a> with Geoffrey Hinton and Yoshua Bengio for their work on machine learning. I knew Yann from when we worked together at NEC Research in the early 2000's and let's just congratulate him and the others and let them bask in glory for truly transforming how we think of computing today. I'll get back to his post soon enough.</div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-28T11:26:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-28T11:26:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:02:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/044</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/044" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-044 |  DEEP-FRI: Sampling Outside the Box Improves Soundness | 

	Eli Ben-Sasson, 

	Lior Goldberg, 

	Swastik Kopparty, 

	Shubhangi Saraf</title>
    <summary>Motivated by the quest for scalable and succinct zero knowledge arguments, we revisit worst-case-to-average-case reductions for linear spaces, raised by [Rothblum, Vadhan, Wigderson, STOC 2013]. The previous state of the art by [Ben-Sasson, Kopparty, Saraf, CCC 2018] showed that if some member of an affine space $U$ is $\delta$-far in relative Hamming distance from a linear code $V$ — this is the worst-case assumption — then most elements of $U$ are almost-$\delta$-far from $V$ — this is the average case. However, this result was known to hold only below the “double Johnson” function of the relative distance $\delta_V$ of the code $V$ , i.e., only when $\delta &lt; 1 ? (1 ? \delta_V)^{1/4}$.
First, we increase the soundness-bound to the “one-and-a-half Johnson” function of $\delta_V$ and show that the average distance of $U$ from $V$ is nearly $\delta$ for any worst-case distance $\delta$ smaller than $1 ? (1 ? \delta_V)^{1/3}$. This bound is tight, which is somewhat surprising because the one-and-a-half Johnson function is unfamiliar in the literature on error correcting codes.
To improve soundness further for Reed Solomon codes we sample outside the box. We suggest a new protocol in which the verifier samples a single point $z$ outside the box $D$ on which codewords are evaluated, and asks the prover for the value at $z$ of the interpolating polynomial of a random element of $U$. Intuitively, the answer provided by the prover “forces” it to choose one codeword from a list of “pretenders” that are close to $U$. We call this technique Domain Extending for Eliminating Pretenders (DEEP).
The DEEP method improves the soundness of the worst-case-to-average-case reduction for RS codes up their list decoding radius. This radius is bounded from below by the Johnson bound, implying average distance is approximately $\delta$ for all $\delta &lt; 1 ? (1 ? \delta_V)^{1/2}$. Under a plausible conjecture about the list decoding radius of Reed-Solomon codes, average distance from $V$ is approximately $\delta$ for all $\delta$. The DEEP technique can be generalized to all linear codes, giving improved reductions for capacity-achieving list-decodable codes.
Finally, we use the DEEP technique to devise two new protocols:
• An Interactive Oracle Proof of Proximity (IOPP) for RS codes, called DEEP-FRI. This soundness of the protocol improves upon that of the FRI protocol of [Ben-Sasson et al., ICALP 2018] while retaining linear arithmetic proving complexity and logarithmic verifier arithmetic complexity.
• An Interactive Oracle Proof (IOP) for the Algebraic Linking IOP (ALI) protocol used to construct zero knowledge scalable transparent arguments of knowledge (ZK-STARKs) in [Ben-Sasson et al., eprint 2018]. The new protocol, called DEEP-ALI, improves soundness of this crucial step from a small constant $&lt; 1/8$ to a constant arbitrarily close to $1$.</summary>
    <updated>2019-03-28T07:47:29Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-28T07:47:29Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4211</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/03/27/tested-by-time/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tested by time</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I was delighted (and not at all surprised) to hear that this year’s Turing Award will go to LeCun, Hinton, and Y. Bengio for their work on deep learning. Like public-key cryptography, deep learning was ahead of its time when … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/03/27/tested-by-time/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I was delighted (and not at all surprised) to hear that this year’s Turing Award will go to <a href="https://amturing.acm.org/">LeCun, Hinton, and Y. Bengio</a> for their work on deep learning.</p>
<p>Like public-key cryptography, deep learning was ahead of its time when first studied, but, thanks to the pioneering efforts of its founders, it was ready to be used when the technology caught up. </p>
<p>Mathematical developments take a long time to mature, so it is essential that applied mathematical research be done ahead of the time of its application, that is, at a time when it is basic research. Maybe quantum computing will be the next example to teach this lesson.</p>
<p>By the way, this summer the Simons Institute will host a <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/programs/dl2019">program on the foundations of deep learning</a>, co-organized by Samy Bengio, Aleks Madry, Elchanan Mossel and Matus Telgarsky.</p>
<p>Sometimes, it is not just the practical applications of a mathematical advance that take time to develop: the same can be true even for its <i>theoretical</i> applications! Which brings me to the next announcement of this post, namely that the call for nominations for the <a href="http://focs2019.cs.jhu.edu/tota/">FOCS test of time award</a> is out. Nominations are due in about four weeks.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-27T20:32:44Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-27T20:32:44Z</published>
    <category term="politics"/>
    <category term="theory"/>
    <category term="things that are excellent"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:20:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3381</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/03/27/call-for-papers-workshop-on-behavioral-economics-and-computation-at-ec-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Call for Papers: Workshop on Behavioral Economics and Computation at EC 2019</title>
    <summary>------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- Call for Papers: Workshop on Behavioral Economics and Computation https://sites.google.com/view/behavioralec/ June 28, 2019, Phoenix, AZ In conjunction with the 20th ACM Conference on Economics and Computation (ACM EC '19) SUBMISSIONS DUE May 1, 2019, 11:59pm PDT. ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- We solicit research contributions and participants for The 1st Workshop on Behavioral Economics and Computation, to be […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><pre class="aLF-aPX-K0-aPE">-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Call for Papers:

Workshop on Behavioral Economics and Computation
<a href="https://sites.google.com/view/behavioralec/">https://sites.google.com/view/behavioralec/</a>
June 28, 2019, Phoenix, AZ
In conjunction with the 20th ACM Conference on Economics and Computation 
(ACM EC '19)

SUBMISSIONS DUE May 1, 2019, 11:59pm PDT.
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
We solicit research contributions and participants for The 1st
Workshop on Behavioral Economics and Computation, to be held in
conjunction with the 20th ACM Conference on Economics and Computation 
(ACM EC '19). The workshop will bring together researchers and
practitioners from diverse subareas of EC, who are interested in the 
intersection of human economic behavior and computation, to share new 
results and to discuss future directions for behavioral research 
related to economics and computation. It will be a full-day workshop, 
and will feature invited speakers, contributed paper presentations and 
a panel discussion.

The gap between rationality-based analysis that assumes utility-maximizing 
agents and the actual human behavior in the real world has been well 
recognized in economics, psychology and other social sciences. In recent 
years, there has been a growing interest in conducting behavioral research 
across many of the sub-areas related to economics and computation to 
address this gap. In one direction, some of these studies leverage insights 
on human decision making from behavioral economics and social psychology 
literature to study economic and computational systems with human users. 
In the other direction, computational tools are used to study and gain 
insights on human behavior and a data-driven approach is sometimes used to 
learn behavior models from user-generated data.

The Behavioral EC workshop aims to bring together researchers and 
practitioners from diverse fields, including but not limited to computer 
science, economics, psychology and sociology, to exchange ideas related to 
behavioral research in economics and computation. In addition to sharing new 
results, we hope the workshop will foster a lively discussion of future 
directions and methodologies for behavioral research related to economics 
and computation as well as fruitful cross-pollination of behavioral 
economics, cognitive psychology and computer science. 

We welcome studies at the intersection of economic behavior and computation 
from a rich set of theoretical, experimental and empirical perspectives. The 
topics of interest for the workshop are behavioral research in all settings 
covered by EC, including but not limited to:

Behavioral mechanism design and applied mechanism design
Empirical studies of economic behavior
Boundedly-rational models of economic decision making
Model evaluation and selection based on behavioral data
Online prediction markets, experiments, and crowdsourcing platforms
Hybrid human-machine systems
Models and experiments about social considerations (e.g. fairness) in 
decision making 
Methods for behavioral EC: information aggregation, probability elicitation, 
quality control


Submission Instructions
=======================

Submission deadline: May 1, 2019, 11:59pm PDT.

Notification: May 20, 2019

We will give priority to new (unpublished) research papers, but will 
also consider ongoing research and recently published papers that may 
be of interest to the workshop audience. For submissions of published 
papers, authors must clearly state the venue of publication. Papers 
will be reviewed for relevance, significance, originality, research 
contribution, and likelihood to catalyze discussion. The workshop will 
not have archival proceedings but will post accepted papers on the 
workshop website. Position papers and panel discussion proposals are also 
welcome. At least one author of each accepted paper will be expected 
to attend and present their findings at the workshop.

Submissions can be in any format and can be up to 18 pages long (plus 
a title page and excluding appendices that can be arbitrarily long). We 
recommend the format of the EC submissions. The limit of 18 pages on 
the main body is an upper bound, and papers can be significantly shorter. 

Submissions should be uploaded to the submission server no later 
than May 1, 2019, 11:59pm PDT.


Organizing Committee
====================
Yiling Chen, Harvard University
Dan Goldstein, Microsoft Research 
Kevin Leyton-Brown, University of British Columbia
Shengwu Li, Harvard University
Gali Noti, Hebrew University


More Information
================
For more information or questions, visit the workshop website:
<a href="https://sites.google.com/view/behavioralec/">https://sites.google.com/view/behavioralec/</a>
or email the organizing committee: <a href="mailto:behavioralec2019@easychair.org">behavioralec2019@easychair.org</a></pre></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-27T01:18:54Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-27T01:18:54Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Kevin Leyton-Brown</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:20:59Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947.post-3721224241252487082</id>
    <link href="http://blog.geomblog.org/feeds/3721224241252487082/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.geomblog.org/2019/03/on-pc-submissions-at-soda-2020.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/3721224241252487082" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/3721224241252487082" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/TheGeomblog/~3/PTrXNVY99dg/on-pc-submissions-at-soda-2020.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On PC submissions at SODA 2020</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SODA 2020 (in SLC!!) is experimenting with a new submission guideline: PC members will be allowed to submit papers. I had a conversation about this with Shuchi Chawla (the PC chair) and she was kind enough (thanks Shuchi!) to share the guidelines she's provided to PC members about how this will work.<br/><br/>  <br/><blockquote class="tr_bq"><span class="s1">SODA is allowing PC members (but not the PC chair) to submit papers this year. To preserve the integrity of the review process, we will handle PC member submissions as follows.</span> </blockquote><blockquote class="tr_bq"><span class="s1">1. PC members are required to declare a conflict for papers that overlap in content with their own submissions (in addition to other CoI situations). These will be treated as hard conflicts. If necessary, in particular if we don't have enough confidence in our evaluation of a paper, PC members will be asked to comment on papers they have a hard conflict with. However, they will not have a say in the final outcome for such papers. </span> </blockquote><blockquote class="tr_bq"><span class="s1">2. PC submissions will receive 4 reviews instead of just 3. This is so that we have more confidence on our evaluation and ultimate decision.</span> </blockquote><blockquote class="tr_bq"><span class="s1">3. We will make early accept/reject decisions on PC members submissions, that is, before we start considering "borderline" papers and worrying about the total number of papers accepted. This is because the later phases of discussion are when subjectivity and bias tend to creep in the most.</span> </blockquote><blockquote class="tr_bq"><span class="s1">4. In order to be accepted, PC member submissions must receive no ratings below "weak accept" and must receive at least two out of four ratings of "accept" or above.</span>  </blockquote><blockquote class="tr_bq">5. PC member submissions will not be eligible for the best paper award.</blockquote><br/>My understanding is that this was done to solve the problem of not being able to get people to agree to be on the PC - this year's PC has substantially more members than prior years.<br/><br/>And yet....<br/><br/>Given all the discussion about conflicts of interest, implicit bias, and double blind review, this appears to be a bizarrely retrograde move, and in fact one that sends a very loud message that issues of implicit bias aren't really viewed as a problem. As one of my colleagues put it sarcastically when I described the new plan:<br/><br/><blockquote class="tr_bq">"why don't they just cut out the reviews and accept all PC submissions to start with?"</blockquote>and as another colleague pointed out:<br/><br/><blockquote class="tr_bq">"It's mostly ridiculous that they seem to be tying themselves in knots trying to figure out how to resolve COIs when there's a really easy solution that they're willfully ignoring..."</blockquote><br/>Some of the arguments I've been hearing in support of this policy frankly make no sense to me.<br/><br/>First of all, the idea that a more heightened scrutiny of PC papers can alleviate the bias associated with reviewing papers of your colleagues goes against basically all of what we know about implicit bias in reviewing. The most basic tenet of human judgement is that we are very bad at filtering our own biases and this only makes it worse. The one thing that theory conferences (compared to other venues) had going for them regarding issues of bias was that PC members couldn't submit papers, but now....<br/><br/>Another claim I've heard is that the scale of SODA makes double blind review difficult. It's hard to hear this claim without bursting out into hysterical laughter (and from the reaction of the people I mentioned this to, I'm not the only one).  Conferences that manage with double blind review (and PC submissions btw) are at least an order of magnitude bigger (think of all the ML conferences). Most conference software (including easy chair) is capable of managing the conflicts of interest without too much trouble. Given that SODA (and theory conferences in general) are less familiar with this process, I’ve recommended in the past that there be a “workflow chair” whose job it is to manage the unfamiliarity associated with dealing the software. Workflow chairs are common at bigger conferences that typically deal with 1000s of reviewers and conflicts.<br/><br/>Further, as a colleague points out, what one should really be doing is "aligning nomenclature and systems with other fields: call current PC as SPC or Area Chairs, or your favorite nomenclature, and add other folks as reviewers. This way you (i) get a list of all conflicts entered into the system, and (ii) recognize the work that the reviewers are doing more officially as labeling the PC members. "<br/><br/><br/>Changes in format (and culture) take time, and I'm still hopeful that the SODA organizing team  will take a lesson from <a href="https://algo2019.ak.in.tum.de/index.php/menue-esa/esa-call">ESA 2019</a>  (and their own resolution to look at DB review more carefully that was passed a year or so ago) and consider exploring DB review. But this year's model is certainly not going to help.<br/><div><br/><b>Update: </b><a href="https://twitter.com/stevemblackburn/status/1111068299796705280?s=20">Steve Blackburn outlines how PLDI handles PC submissions</a> (in brief, double blind + external review committee)<br/><br/><b>Update: </b><a href="https://md.ekstrandom.net/blog/2019/03/anonymous-reviewing">Michael Ekstrand</a> takes on the question that Thomas Steinke asks in the comments below: "How is double blind review different from fairness-through-blindness?".<br/></div><img alt="" height="1" src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/TheGeomblog/~4/PTrXNVY99dg" width="1"/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-26T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-26T14:00:00Z</published><feedburner:origlink xmlns:feedburner="http://rssnamespace.org/feedburner/ext/1.0">http://blog.geomblog.org/2019/03/on-pc-submissions-at-soda-2020.html</feedburner:origlink>
    <author>
      <name>Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/15898357513326041822</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947</id>
      <category term="research"/>
      <category term="community"/>
      <category term="miscellaneous"/>
      <category term="soda"/>
      <category term="conferences"/>
      <category term="data-mining"/>
      <category term="socg"/>
      <category term="blogosphere"/>
      <category term="publishing"/>
      <category term="clustering"/>
      <category term="teaching"/>
      <category term="jobs"/>
      <category term="funding"/>
      <category term="humor"/>
      <category term="awards"/>
      <category term="outreach"/>
      <category term="stoc"/>
      <category term="cs.CG"/>
      <category term="focs"/>
      <category term="nsf"/>
      <category term="reviewing"/>
      <category term="socg-2010"/>
      <category term="fairness"/>
      <category term="academy"/>
      <category term="latex"/>
      <category term="stoc2017"/>
      <category term="theoryfest"/>
      <category term="workshops"/>
      <category term="acm"/>
      <category term="conf-blogs"/>
      <category term="writing"/>
      <category term="cs.DS"/>
      <category term="cs.LG"/>
      <category term="geometry"/>
      <category term="p-vs-nc"/>
      <category term="advising"/>
      <category term="sabbatical"/>
      <category term="simons foundation"/>
      <category term="announcement"/>
      <category term="big-data"/>
      <category term="deadline"/>
      <category term="jeff phillips"/>
      <category term="streaming"/>
      <category term="books"/>
      <category term="large-data"/>
      <category term="p-vs-np"/>
      <category term="cra"/>
      <category term="cstheory"/>
      <category term="focs2010"/>
      <category term="icdm"/>
      <category term="math.PR"/>
      <category term="memorial"/>
      <category term="personal"/>
      <category term="posters"/>
      <category term="potd"/>
      <category term="rajeev motwani"/>
      <category term="shonan"/>
      <category term="socg2012"/>
      <category term="software"/>
      <category term="stoc2012"/>
      <category term="GIA"/>
      <category term="SDM"/>
      <category term="alenex"/>
      <category term="alenex2011"/>
      <category term="arxiv"/>
      <category term="career"/>
      <category term="complexity"/>
      <category term="cs.CC"/>
      <category term="deolalikar"/>
      <category term="distributions"/>
      <category term="madalgo"/>
      <category term="nips"/>
      <category term="sdm2011"/>
      <category term="shape"/>
      <category term="talks"/>
      <category term="technology"/>
      <category term="theory.SE"/>
      <category term="travel"/>
      <category term="video"/>
      <category term="8f-cg"/>
      <category term="DBR"/>
      <category term="ICS"/>
      <category term="LISPI"/>
      <category term="acceptances"/>
      <category term="bibtex"/>
      <category term="bregman"/>
      <category term="cfp"/>
      <category term="clustering-book"/>
      <category term="column"/>
      <category term="combinatorial geometry"/>
      <category term="current-distance"/>
      <category term="ecml-pkdd"/>
      <category term="empirical"/>
      <category term="esa"/>
      <category term="fat*"/>
      <category term="focs2012"/>
      <category term="focs2014"/>
      <category term="fwcg"/>
      <category term="game theory"/>
      <category term="godel"/>
      <category term="graphs"/>
      <category term="implementation"/>
      <category term="journals"/>
      <category term="kernels"/>
      <category term="misc"/>
      <category term="models"/>
      <category term="obituary"/>
      <category term="productivity"/>
      <category term="programming"/>
      <category term="society"/>
      <category term="soda2011"/>
      <category term="topology"/>
      <category term="turing"/>
      <category term="tv"/>
      <category term="women-in-theory"/>
      <category term=".02"/>
      <category term="IMA"/>
      <category term="MOOC"/>
      <category term="PPAD"/>
      <category term="accountability"/>
      <category term="active-learning"/>
      <category term="aggregator"/>
      <category term="algorithms"/>
      <category term="ams"/>
      <category term="analco"/>
      <category term="barriers"/>
      <category term="beamer"/>
      <category term="blogging"/>
      <category term="candes"/>
      <category term="civil rights"/>
      <category term="classification"/>
      <category term="coding-theory"/>
      <category term="coffee"/>
      <category term="conjecture"/>
      <category term="cosmos"/>
      <category term="counting"/>
      <category term="cricket"/>
      <category term="cs.DC"/>
      <category term="dagstuhl"/>
      <category term="databuse"/>
      <category term="dimacs"/>
      <category term="dimensionality-reduction"/>
      <category term="distributed-learning"/>
      <category term="double-blind review"/>
      <category term="duality"/>
      <category term="eda"/>
      <category term="embarrassing"/>
      <category term="ethics"/>
      <category term="expanders"/>
      <category term="experiments"/>
      <category term="fake-news"/>
      <category term="fatml"/>
      <category term="fellowships"/>
      <category term="focs2013"/>
      <category term="fonts"/>
      <category term="gct"/>
      <category term="ggplot"/>
      <category term="gpu"/>
      <category term="graph minors"/>
      <category term="gt.game-theory"/>
      <category term="guest-post"/>
      <category term="guitar"/>
      <category term="hangouts"/>
      <category term="hirsch"/>
      <category term="history"/>
      <category term="ipe"/>
      <category term="ita"/>
      <category term="jmm"/>
      <category term="k-12"/>
      <category term="knuth"/>
      <category term="machine-learning"/>
      <category term="massive"/>
      <category term="math.ST"/>
      <category term="media"/>
      <category term="memes"/>
      <category term="metoo"/>
      <category term="metrics"/>
      <category term="morris"/>
      <category term="movies"/>
      <category term="multicore"/>
      <category term="music"/>
      <category term="narrative"/>
      <category term="networks"/>
      <category term="nih"/>
      <category term="parallelism"/>
      <category term="partha niyogi"/>
      <category term="polymath"/>
      <category term="polymath research"/>
      <category term="polytopes"/>
      <category term="postdocs"/>
      <category term="privacy"/>
      <category term="quant-ph"/>
      <category term="quantum"/>
      <category term="randomness"/>
      <category term="review"/>
      <category term="sampling"/>
      <category term="seminars"/>
      <category term="social-networking"/>
      <category term="soda2014"/>
      <category term="students"/>
      <category term="sublinear"/>
      <category term="submissions"/>
      <category term="summer-school"/>
      <category term="superbowl"/>
      <category term="surveys"/>
      <category term="svn"/>
      <category term="television"/>
      <category term="traffic"/>
      <category term="twitter"/>
      <category term="utah"/>
      <category term="wads"/>
      <category term="white elephant"/>
      <category term="xkcd"/>
      <author>
        <name>Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/15898357513326041822</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.geomblog.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default?alt=atom&amp;start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/TheGeomblog" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Ruminations on computational geometry, algorithms, theoretical computer science and life</subtitle>
      <title>The Geomblog</title>
      <updated>2019-03-30T23:23:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7484</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2019/03/26/news-addicts-sign-up-for-the-catcs-newsletter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News addicts: Sign up for the CATCS newsletter</title>
    <summary>If, like others following the pace of modern life, you’re the kind of person that needs to get just on time updates on the state of theoretical computer science, consider signing up for the newsletter of CATCS. You can get information about funding opportunities, advocacy efforts, and more. Sure, at the hectic rate of two […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>If, like others following <a href="https://xkcd.com/1227/">the pace of modern life</a>, you’re the kind of person that needs to get just on time updates on the state of theoretical computer science, consider signing up for the newsletter of CATCS.  You can get information about funding opportunities, advocacy efforts, and more. Sure, at the hectic rate of two messages per year, it might flood your inbox, but it is worth it.</p>



<p/>



<p>Dear Theoretical Computer Scientist,</p>



<p><br/>The <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/catcs/">Committee for the Advancement of Theoretical Computer Science </a>(CATCS) was established by SIGACT to deal with funding, outreach, and advocacy issues for our community. If you would like to receive our newsletter (no more than twice annually) we encourage you to sign up for the Google group below:<br/><a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/catcs-news" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/catcs-news</a><br/>(Navigate to the page above and click “Join group.” You can unsubscribe at any time from the same page.)<br/>Best wishes, CATCS </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-26T04:03:53Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-26T04:03:53Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>windowsontheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/03/25/postdoc-at-bar-ilan-university-apply-by-may-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/03/25/postdoc-at-bar-ilan-university-apply-by-may-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at Bar Ilan University (apply by May 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>In the our big data lab, we have several postdoctoral positions in Algorithms, Data Structures, Distributed, and Compress Sensing. Website: http://www.cs.biu.ac.il/~porately/ Email: porately@cs.biu.ac.il</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In the our big data lab, we have several postdoctoral positions in Algorithms, Data Structures, Distributed, and Compress Sensing.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://www.cs.biu.ac.il/~porately/">http://www.cs.biu.ac.il/~porately/</a><br/>
Email: porately@cs.biu.ac.il</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-25T08:20:15Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-25T08:20:15Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-2572656159267507055</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/2572656159267507055/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/03/random-thoughts-on-admissions-scandal.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2572656159267507055" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/2572656159267507055" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/03/random-thoughts-on-admissions-scandal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Random Thoughts on the admissions scandal</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In light of the recent academic scandal I am going to list ways I've heard to help get your kid into college and thoughts on how ethical they are (hint: bribing a coach to claim your kid is on the rowing team is not ethical).<br/>
<br/>
1) Your kid likes (1) helping the homeless and (2)  Ramsey Theory and (3)  helping the homeless learn Ramsey Theory. Or perhaps they like  rowing or Latin or fencing or Pig Latin or....  Great! encourage them, get them books and tutors,  and whatever they need. You have an eye towards how this will look on for college admissions; however, it is your kids choice as to what they like. Also note that these activities are in addition to doing well in school, SATs, etc, not instead of it.  Perfectly ethical, though I note that this avenue is not open to poor families and in some cases even middle class families.<br/>
<br/>
2) Item 1 is the extreme on a spectrum in terms of how much are the extra things the kid does there idea OR planned by you to GET INTO A GOOD COLLEGE. This item will be the other extreme, but realize there is a continuum (actually I doubt there are a continuum number of options here, but there are many in between. Maybe its omega + omega*.) You have heard that being on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_boxing">chess boxing</a> teams is good on a college application so you TELL YOUR KID that they  likes both Chess AND Boxing and should be on the team. You also hear this about being on the fencing team and knowing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pig_Latin">pig latin</a>, so your kid can taunt their opponents like this:<br/>
<br/>
youah, aint-kay ence-fay orth-way eans-bay<br/>
<br/>
This might not be as bad as it sounds if the kid learns to like Chess-Boxing.  But it may be worse than it sounds if the kid rebels against all of this and becomes a crack whore.<br/>
<br/>
Is this ethical? It may be bad for the kid, but it may push him into things he ends up liking. One drawback: you've HEARD that being on the chess boxing team is good for college admissions, but is it true?<br/>
<br/>
And again, not open to some families.<br/>
<br/>
3) Item 2 (or even 1) but with an addition: Hire a college adviser to help you. Someone who knows (or claims to know) what colleges look for- Trombone, Latin, Chess-boxing, whatever. Still ethical but I again worry about the kids future rehab bills.<br/>
<br/>
4) Here is where it gets murky. The college adviser helps:<br/>
<br/>
a) Polish the kids essay (my parents, who are both in English, helped polish my essay to get into graduate school (I don't recall if there was one for ugrad). They told me to use lots of `ing' words so it sounds like I am actively doing things. They also helped me figure out when recursion-theoretic is hyphenated. I got into Harvard but not MIT, so make of that what you will.) Polishing, proofreading, that could be okay. But it can slip into b or c below.<br/>
<br/>
b) The adviser (or the parents) talk to the kids to find out what to write, but then writes it. Maybe the kid proofreads and polishes. Maybe not even. The adviser is  a ghostwriter. Clearly unethical but the line between helping-to-polish and adviser-wrote-it is again a continuum.<br/>
<br/>
c) Adviser writes it and it is completely fictional. I once heard a rumor that a particular sample of an essay to get into med school was used  by several  med school applicant. Gee,they can't all have gotten inspired by watching their grandfather in his pajamas die of cancer. This is awful of course, but I wonder- what if the student writes a fictional essay all by themselves! Some combination of how much the essay is true and how much help you got on it is unethical. But some might be okay. Is it bad to polish stories that are basically true to make them flow more easily?  Prob not. But there is a 2-dim continuum based on both accuracy and how much help the student got.<br/>
<br/>
As a side note- how much does the personal statement matter for admissions? I suspect that if an elite school gets LOTS of REALLY QUALIFIED applicants, the essay may be all that distinguishes them.So it can be important. I also wonder if people on admissions can tell if an essay is not written by the applicant. Or maybe if there is an interview that can help detect it.<br/>
<br/>
5) Parents give X amount of money to the college and the kid gets in. This is talked about a lot though I don't know how common it is for someone NOT qualified to GET IN based on money. College admissions has many factors so its not quite so clear cut what NOT qualified means. Even so, if seems odd that this is not in any way shape or form illegal. It IS transparent, so I guess thats a plus. The argument I've heard is that the money is used for scholarships to fund students who get in but can't afford to go. I do not know if this is true. And this one  is only available to the top Z %, not sure what Z is, but there are people who can do 1,2,3,4 who can't do 5. I would call this unethical though colleges don't seem to think so. Or they do but they do it anyway.<br/>
<br/>
6) Before I list the current scandal I want to list another issue: having a psychologist (or whoever it is who judges these things) say your kid is Learning Disabled so they get more time on the SATs. Perhaps bribing them, or perhaps its understood what you want.  Again, I do not know how common this is.  An alternative if you can't afford some of the above options, or done in conjunction with a lot of the above options.<br/>
<br/>
7) The current scandal. Obviously unethical. A few things I wonder about:<br/>
<br/>
a) One story was that they bribed someone to say their daughter was Learning Disabled and had to take the SAT (or whatever it was) in a separate room, making it easier to change the answers to the correct ones.  So twice unethical.<br/>
<br/>
b) Some of the students  were clearly NOT qualified.<br/>
<br/>
c) A parent does unethical things to get the kid into college.<br/>
<br/>
The kid later lies to the parents about their grades or their plans<br/>
<br/>
The parents are SHOCKED that their kids lie and wonder where the learned such behaviour!<br/>
<br/>
8) Actually Item 2 --Parent has kid do things to plan to get into college-- is interesting for another reason. Are you your resume?<br/>
<br/>
Imagine that Alice helps the homeless her Sophmore year in High School NOT because she cares about the homeless but because its good for college admissions.<br/>
<br/>
Alice goes on to do other things that look good for college, NOT because she likes them or cares, but just to get into a good college.<br/>
<br/>
She gets into an elite college<br/>
<br/>
Did they take her in the hope she would KEEP doing these things or because she is the KIND OF PERSON who does these things?<br/>
<br/>
And it gets weirder- she DOES keep doing these things since she's heard its good for Business School (disclaimer- I do not know if its good for B-school)<br/>
<br/>
More generally, she keeps doing things she doesn't care about to advance. So her outward self really is doing good deeds and such, but her heart is not in it. So if her college or B-school or Job hired her because she DOES these things, that is NOT a lie. If they hired her because they want this KIND OF PERSON then... its a lie but I'm not sure what to make of that.<br/>
<br/>
9) Is there ANY reason to have legacy matter for admissions? This seems like the dumbest and most easily fixed aspect of the whole process.  I have never heard a good argument for it. Ever.<br/>
<br/>
10) College Sports--- that's an entire blog post or book all by itself, so I won't go there.<br/>
<br/>
11) One can argue whether helping the homeless, or being on the rowing team, or teaching the homeless how to row, should matter for college anyway. But lets assume that its legit to want people at your college who have lead interesting lives. So charity work or sports might be a MEASURE of that. But beware Goodhart's law:<br/>
<br/>
                         <i> When a measure becomes a target is ceases to be a measure.</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
The recent scandal is Goodhart's law on steroids.<br/>
(NOTE- I had in earlier version `Goodwin's law' but a commenter corrected me and reminded me that Goodwin's law is that if an internet discussion goes on long enough someone will be compared to Hitler. I wonder if that also applies in discussions by Nazi's.)<br/>
<br/>
12) Does getting into an Elite College really increase your income or happiness (these are two very different questions) over the course of your life? I do not know-- if you do, please comment.<br/>
<br/>
13) (ADDED LATER) A commenter pointed out that one could also go to a school outside of  the USA that values proficiency in the chosen discipline over the items above. Excellent question that raises a few more:<br/>
<br/>
Do schools outside of the USA hold Americans (or for that matter any non-citizen of their country) to a higher standard for admissions? I ask non-rhetorically.<br/>
<br/>
If you get a degree from outside of the USA will that help or hurt your job prospects in the USA? Of course this depends on the school you goto, but even with that I do not know the answer.<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-24T21:13:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-24T21:13:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:02:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/043</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/043" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-043 |  Nondeterministic and Randomized Boolean Hierarchies in Communication Complexity | 

	Toniann Pitassi, 

	Morgan Shirley, 

	Thomas Watson</title>
    <summary>We study the Boolean Hierarchy in the context of two-party communication complexity, as well as the analogous hierarchy defined with one-sided error randomness instead of nondeterminism. Our results provide a complete picture of the relationships among complexity classes within and across these two hierarchies. In particular, we prove a query-to-communication lifting theorem for all levels of the Boolean Hierarchy and use it to resolve an open problem stated in the paper by Halstenberg and Reischuk (CCC 1988) which initiated this topic.</summary>
    <updated>2019-03-24T07:12:18Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-24T07:12:18Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=17209</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/03/22/danny-nguyen-and-igor-pak-presburger-arithmetic-problem-solved/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Danny Nguyen and Igor Pak: Presburger Arithmetic Problem Solved!</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Short Presburger arithmetic is hard! This is a belated report on a remarkable breakthrough from 2017. The paper is Short Presburger arithmetic is hard, by Nguyen and Pak. Danny Nguyen Integer programming in bounded dimension: Lenstra’s Theorem Algorithmic tasks are … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/03/22/danny-nguyen-and-igor-pak-presburger-arithmetic-problem-solved/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><h2>Short Presburger arithmetic is hard!</h2>
<p>This is a belated report on a remarkable breakthrough from 2017. The paper is <a href="http://www.math.ucla.edu/~pak/papers/hard_presburger3.pdf">Short Presburger arithmetic is hard</a>, by Nguyen and Pak.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/03/ngoyen.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-17213" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/03/ngoyen.jpg?w=640"/></a></p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #ff0000;">Danny Nguyen</span></strong></p>
<h3>Integer programming in bounded dimension: Lenstra’s Theorem</h3>
<p>Algorithmic tasks are often intractable. But there are a few miracles where efficient algorithms exist: Solving systems of linear equations, linear programming, testing primality,  and solving integer programming problems when the number of variables is bounded. The last miracle is a historic 1983 theorem of Hendrik Lenstra (Here <a href="https://people.csail.mit.edu/rrw/presentations/Lenstra81.pdf">is the paper</a>) and it is the starting point of this post.</p>
<p><strong>Lensra’s theorem:</strong> Consider a system of linear inequalities</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><em>Ax ≤ b</em></h3>
<p>where <img alt="x=(x_1,x_2,\dots x_k)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x%3D%28x_1%2Cx_2%2C%5Cdots+x_k%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x=(x_1,x_2,\dots x_k)"/> is a vector of <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="k"/> variables, <em>A</em> is an integral <em>k</em> by <em>n</em> matrix and <em>b</em> is an integral vector of length <em>n</em>.</p>
<p>Let <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="k"/> be a fixed integer. There is a polynomial time algorithm to determine if the system has an integral solution.</p>
<p>Of course, the full Integer Programming problem when <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="k"/> is part of the input, is <strong>NP-complete</strong>. This problem came already (second in Karp’s list!) in<a href="https://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~luca/cs172/karp.pdf"> the Mayflower of NP-complete problems –  Karp’s paper</a>.</p>
<p>Sasha Barvinok famously showed in 1993 that even counting the number of solutions is in <strong>P</strong>. (Barvinok utilized the short generating function approach pioneered by Brion, Vergne and others.)</p>
<h3>Kannan’s theorem</h3>
<p>Next,  I want to describe an amazing 1990 theorem of Ravi Kannan,</p>
<p>Kannan’s theorem considers formulas with one quantifier alternation in the Presburger arithmetic and it asserts that when the number of variables is fixed,  there is a polynomial time algorithm to decide if the formula is satisfiable.</p>
<p>(Here is a free version of <a href="http://www.cs.yale.edu/homes/kannan/Papers/forall.pdf">Kannan’s paper</a>.) Also here the counting problems were tackled with great success. Barvinok and Kevin Woods remarkably showed <a href="http://www.ams.org/journals/jams/2003-16-04/S0894-0347-03-00428-4/S0894-0347-03-00428-4.pdf">how to count projections of integer points in a (single) polytope in polynomial time</a>, and subsequently Woods <a href="http://www2.oberlin.edu/faculty/kwoods/research/Presburger_full.pdf">extended this approach</a> to general Presburger expressions Φ with a fixed number of inequalities!</p>
<p>An important strengthening was achieved by Friedrich Eisenbrand and  Gennady Shmonin in the 2008 paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0801.4336">Parametric integer programming in fixed dimension</a>. See also the survey chapter by Barvinok <a href="https://www.csun.edu/~ctoth/Handbook/chap7.pdf">Lattice points and lattice polytopes</a>.</p>
<p>You can find the formulation of Kannan’s theorem in full generality a little further but let me present now a special case related to the famous Frobenius coin problem. (See <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2009/03/07/finite-state-automata-binary-decision-diagrams-and-presburger-arithmetic/">this post on GLL</a> for more on Presburger arithmetic)</p>
<h3>Frobenius coin problem</h3>
<p>Given <em>k</em> coins with integral values, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coin_problem">Frobinius coin problem</a> is to determine the largest integer that cannot be described as positive integer combinations of the values of the coins. (See also <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2011/04/30/congrats-ravi-kannan/">this post</a> on GLL.)</p>
<p><strong>Theorem (Kannan):</strong> There is a polynomial time algorithm to solve the Frobenius coin problem for every fixed number of coins.</p>
<p>The issue of the way theory meets practice for the problems discussed in this post is very interesting but we will not discuss it. Let me remark that Herb Scarf (who along with Kannan played a role in B-L (Before Lenstra) developments) offered another approach for the solution of the Frobenius coin problem and related IP (Integer Programming)  problems based on his theory of maximal lattice-free convex bodies. See <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2013/02/22/ann-lehmans-sculpture-based-on-herb-scarfs-maximal-lattice-free-convex-bodies/">this related post</a>.</p>
<h3>More than one quantifier</h3>
<p>Given the result of Kannan and later that of Barvinok and Woods, many people expected that also for two alternations, or even for any other fixed number of alternations, Presburger arithmetic would be in polynomial time. Nguyen and Pak proved that the problem is <strong>NP-complete</strong> already for two quantifier alternations! Here is the link to the paper <a href="http://www.math.ucla.edu/~pak/papers/hard_presburger3.pdf">Short Presburger arithmetic is hard</a>. Igor Pak’s homepage has a few other <a href="http://www.math.ucla.edu/~pak/papers/research.htm#ip">related papers</a>.</p>
<p>Let me bring here Sasha Barvinok’s <a href="http://www.math.ucla.edu/~pak/papers/PA-Barv-rev.pdf">MathSciNet featured review</a> of Nguyen and Pak’s paper which tells the story better than I could.</p>
<h2>Barvinok’s featured review to Nguyen and Pak’s paper</h2>
<p>Presburger arithmetic allows integer variables, integer constants, Boolean operations (&amp;, ∧, ¬), quantifiers (∃, ∀), equations and inequalities (=, &lt;, &gt;, ≤, ≥), addition and subtraction (+, −) and multiplication by integer constants. It does not allow multiplication of variables (if we allow multiplication of variables, we get Peano arithmetic).</p>
<p>Geometrically, a quantifier-free formula of Presburger arithmetic describes the set of integer points in a Boolean combination of rational polyhedra (that is, in the set obtained from finitely many rational polyhedra by taking unions, intersections and complements). Similarly, a formula of Presburger arithmetic with existential quantifiers only describes the set of integer points obtained from the set of integer points in a Boolean combination of polyhedra by a projection along some coordinates.</p>
<p>Unlike Peano arithmetic, Presburger arithmetic is decidable. Here the authors zoom in on the computational complexity of Presburger arithmetic, once the combinatorial complexity of the formula is bounded in advance. If we fix the number of variables, the validity of a formula with no quantifier alternations (that is, of the type ∃<img alt="x_1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_1"/> . . . ∃<img alt="x_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_k"/>Φ(<img alt="x_1, \dots , latex x_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_1%2C+%5Cdots+%2C+latex+x_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_1, \dots , latex x_k"/>) or of the type ∀<img alt="x_1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_1"/> . . . ∀<img alt="x_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_k"/>Φ(<img alt="x_1, \dots , x_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_1%2C+%5Cdots+%2C+x_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_1, \dots , x_k"/>)) can be established in polynomial time by Lenstra’s integer programming algorithm [see H. W. Lenstra Jr., Math. Oper. Res. 8 (1983), no. 4, 538–548; MR0727410].</p>
<p>For a fixed number of variables, formulas with one quantifier alternation (∃<img alt="x_1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_1"/> . . . ∃<img alt="x_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_k"/>∀<img alt="y_1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=y_1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="y_1"/> . . . ∀<img alt="y_m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=y_m&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="y_m"/>Φ(<img alt="x_1, \dots , x_k, y_1, \dots , y_m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_1%2C+%5Cdots+%2C+x_k%2C+y_1%2C+%5Cdots+%2C+y_m&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_1, \dots , x_k, y_1, \dots , y_m"/>)) can also be solved in polynomial time, as shown by R. Kannan [in Polyhedral combinatorics (Morristown, NJ, 1989), 39–47, DIMACS Ser. Discrete Math. Theoret. Comput. Sci., 1, Amer. Math. Soc., Providence, RI, 1990; MR1105115]. The decision procedure can be characterized as a polynomial time algorithm for parametric integer programming.</p>
<p>Suppose now that we fix the number of variables and the number of Boolean operations in advance (and hence get what is called a short formula of Presburger arithmetic). Thus the only parameters of the formula are the numerical values of the constants in the formula. The authors show that deciding validity becomes <strong>NP-complete</strong> if one allows<br/>
two quantifier alternations. Remarkably, they present an example of a formula</p>
<p>∃z ∈ <img alt="\mathbb Z" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\mathbb Z"/> ∀y ∈ <img alt="\mathbb Z^2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z%5E2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\mathbb Z^2"/> ∃x ∈ <img alt="\mathbb Z^2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z%5E2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\mathbb Z^2"/> Φ(x, y, z)</p>
<p>with an <strong>NP-complete</strong> decision problem, even though Φ contains at most 10 inequalities.<br/>
Another remarkable example is an <strong>NP-complete</strong> decision problem for a formula of the<br/>
type</p>
<p>∃z ∈ <img alt="\mathbb Z" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\mathbb Z"/> ∀y ∈ <img alt="\mathbb Z^2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z%5E2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\mathbb Z^2"/> ∃x ∈ <img alt="\mathbb Z^6" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z%5E6&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\mathbb Z^6"/>: <em>Ax + By + Cz ≤ b,  </em></p>
<p>with at most 24 inequalities.</p>
<p>As the number of quantifier alternations is allowed to increase, the computational complexity in the polynomial hierarchy also moves up. The authors also describe the computational complexity of corresponding counting problems.</p>
<p>The proof is very clever; it uses the continued fraction expansion of a rational number to encode a growing family of intervals, with the help of which the authors build an <strong>NP-complete</strong> problem.</p>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-22T09:47:48Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-22T09:47:48Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Convex polytopes"/>
    <category term="Danny Nguyen"/>
    <category term="Frobenius coin problem"/>
    <category term="Hendrik Lenstra"/>
    <category term="Herb Scarf"/>
    <category term="Igor Pak"/>
    <category term="Kevin Woods"/>
    <category term="Persburger Arithmetic"/>
    <category term="Ravi Kannan"/>
    <category term="Sasha Barvinok"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:20:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/03/22/workshop-on-algebraic-complexity-theory/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/03/22/workshop-on-algebraic-complexity-theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Workshop on Algebraic Complexity Theory</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">March 25-29, 2019 The International Centre for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS), Bengaluru (India) https://www.icts.res.in/discussion-meeting/wact2019 The primary objective of this workshop is to bring together experts in the field of algebraic complexity and related areas to present their research, initiate collaborations etc. The idea is to continue the tradition of having a Workshop on Algebraic Complexity Theory … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/03/22/workshop-on-algebraic-complexity-theory/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Workshop on Algebraic Complexity Theory</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-03-22T09:16:07Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-22T09:16:07Z</published>
    <category term="workshop"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-04-01T12:21:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1076</id>
    <link href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1076" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Curse of Euclidean Metric: Square Roots</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The deadline was approaching without mercy and there was, of course, still some polishing to be done for our SODA paper. But then we run into an issue. To make things worse, this issue turned out to be a hard … <a href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?p=1076">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: justify;"><a href="https://duch.mimuw.edu.pl/~tugboat/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/curseOfMetricIsland.png"><img align="right" alt="The Curse of Metric Island" class="wp-image-587 alignright" src="https://duch.mimuw.edu.pl/~tugboat/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/curseOfMetricIsland_small.png"/></a></p>
<p>The deadline was approaching without mercy and there was, of course, still some polishing to be done for <a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/1.9781611975482.67">our SODA paper</a>. But then we run into an issue. To make things worse, this issue turned out to be a hard one, a fundamental known open problem in computational geometry. The good thing is, I liked the problem so much that I decided to dedicate it this post. This is the story about the Sum of Square Roots problem and how we bypassed (ignored) it without solving it.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph {"align":"justify"} --></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Everything began in the haze of the 70's of the last millennium. It is nebulous who stumbled first upon this enigma. <a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/junkyard/small-dist.html">Some say</a> that Ron Graham has discussed the problem in public lectures, <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2321488">some others</a> say that Joseph O'Rourke has posed it as an open question in the American Mathematical Monthly, while <a href="http://cs.smith.edu/~jorourke/TOPP/P33.html">some others</a> suspect that the problem had been already hiding in older different formulations. However, it is a historical fact that one shinny/cloudy day, three computer scientists finished polishing a manuscript that became a classical paper known as "<a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/800113.803626">Some NP-complete geometric problems</a>". In this paper, Michael Garey, Ron Graham and David Johnson showed the NP-hardness of two important problems in geometric metrics: Steiner Tree and Traveling Salesman. For the Euclidean plane, they showed only NP-hardness as they did not manage to show that these problems are contained in NP. Moreover, they accentuated that we cannot even rule out that the decision version of Euclidean Minimum Spanning Tree is outside of NP. What a seeming paradox given that we can compute such a minimum tree in polynomial time! So, whom did they blame? The short answer: The Euclidean metric. Garey and his coauthors explain that all these problems have a common hidden issue: They rely on comparing Euclidean lengths, that is, they rely on comparing irrational numbers based on square roots. Whereas this task is trivial if we just want to compare two line segments (e.g. by comparing the radicands), the problem starts when we want to compare two polygonal paths. Even assuming rational (or, after scaling, integer) coordinates, this problem translates into a question that is fundamental in computational geometry: Given two lists of integers, <em>a<sub>1</sub></em> ... and <em>b<sub>1</sub></em> ..., can we decide whether "<em>∑ √a<sub>i</sub> ≥ ∑ √b<sub>i</sub></em>" in P? Put into words: <strong>Can we efficiently compare two sums of square roots over integers?</strong></p>
<p><span id="more-1076"/></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph {"align":"justify"} --></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">To emphasize the significance of this question, let me cite <a href="http://cs.smith.edu/~jorourke/TOPP/P33.html">David Eppstein</a>: "A major bottleneck in proving NP-completeness for geometric problems is a mismatch between the real-number and Turing machine models of computation: one is good for geometric algorithms but bad for reductions, and the other vice versa. Specifically, it is not known on Turing machines how to quickly compare a sum of distances (square roots of integers) with an integer or other similar sums, so even (decision versions of) easy problems such as the minimum spanning tree are not known to be in NP."</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph {"align":"justify"} --></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">"Is this problem computable at all?" - might the curious reader ask after realizing that the approach of iteratively increasing the precision until the first difference in digits will never terminate if both numbers happen to be equal. Luckily, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0747-7171(85)80013-4">Allan Borodin et al.</a> and <a href="https://refubium.fu-berlin.de/handle/fub188/18449">Johannes Blömer</a> showed that polynomial time is enough to decide whether two such sums have the same value. Therefore, it is astonishing that the problem of deciding the sign of their difference, a question that seems only slightly harder, has been only recently spotted by <a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/070697926">Eric Allender et al</a> on an island of the counting hierarchy CH (3rd level) located in the wide ocean of PSPACE. Thus, it is still far far away from the needle head of P, where <a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.44.5325">Gregorio Malajovich</a> conjectured it to live. Until this will be shown, <a href="https://cstheory.stackexchange.com/questions/4053/sum-of-square-roots-hard-problems">Jeff Erickson</a> proposes to study which problems are (<a href="https://cstheory.stackexchange.com/questions/4053/sum-of-square-roots-hard-problems">non-boringly</a>) Σ√-hard.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph {"align":"justify"} --></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">Oh, if we could only sufficiently bound the difference of the sums from below! Then we could bound from above the precision required to determine the correct sign of the difference: Just image that <em>B</em> is such a lower bound on the difference. Now, take a precision that allows us to compute an approximate difference being only <em>B/2</em> away from the real one. Then it is easy to verify that the following procedure determines the correct sign: Output the sign of the approximate difference if it is outside of <em>[-B/2,B/2]</em>, otherwise output <em>0</em>. What is the run time of this procedure? It is proportional to the precision, which corresponds to the length of <em>B</em>, that is, to <em>-log B</em>. Hence, if <em>-log B</em> is bounded from above by a polynomial in the length of the input, then we are in P! So, is there any reasonable lower bound for the worst case? That is, <strong>what is the smallest positive difference between any two sums of <em>k</em> square roots of integers of size at most <em>n</em>?</strong> Welcome to <a href="http://cs.smith.edu/~jorourke/TOPP/P33.html">Problem 33</a> of <a href="http://cs.smith.edu/~jorourke/TOPP/Welcome.html">The Open Problems Project</a>! Let <em>r(n,k)</em> denote such a minimum difference as a function of <em>n</em> and <em>k</em>. For instance, consider <em>n=20</em> and <em>k=2</em>. Then <em>r(n,k)</em> is roughly <em>0.0002</em> and it is attained by <em>√{10} + √{11} - √{5} - √{18}</em>. As being an open problem, there is no tight bound known for <em>r(n,k)</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ipl.2006.05.002">Jianbo Qian and Cao An Wang</a> as well as <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tcs.2011.06.014">Qi Cheng and Yu-Hsin Li</a> proved(*) that there are sums where <em>-log r(n,k)</em> is at least in the order of magnitude of <em>k log n</em>. However, these lower bounds constitute an exponentially gap to the best known upper bounds which are <em>O(2<sup>2k</sup> log n)</em> [<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s004530010005">Christoph Burnikel et al.</a>(**)] and <em>2<sup>O(n/log n)</sup></em> [<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tcs.2011.06.014">Qi Cheng et al.</a>]. So, maybe you, dear reader, will be the one to close the gap?</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph {"align":"justify"} --></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">In the dramatic opening of this post, I mentioned <a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/1.9781611975482.67">our paper</a>, where the problem of Sum of Square Roots appeared. There, we design a PTAS for the Traveling Salesman problem (TSP) with hyperplane neighborhoods, that is, we look for a <em>(1+ε)</em>-approximation of a minimum-length tour that, instead of points, visits a given set of hyperplanes in ℝ<sup><em>d</em></sup> with <em>d</em> being fixed. The basis of our algorithm is an integer grid of constant size (depending on <em>ε</em> and <em>d</em>). Our key observation is that there is a translation and scaling of the grid such that snapping an (adequately sparsified) optimum solution to the grid results in a <em>(1+ε</em>)-approximation. Using this insight, we let our algorithm enumerate all (reasonable) TSP tours lying in our integer grid. With a simple LP, we translate and scale each tour such that it visits all the hyperplanes of the input whilst minimizing its tour length (i.e., the scaling factor). At the end, we obtain a set of feasible TSP tours and output the shortest one. And here we were confronted with the Sum of Square Roots problem. Which of the tours is the shortest one? Was all our work devastated, all our blood, sweat and tears in vain? Just because the very last line of our algorithm had unknown complexity? Our solution was simple: We just skipped the issue and our paper got accepted. Why? Well, the issue wasn't one for the following three reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>We could be lazy and assume the real RAM computational model with constant time for square root operations (as often done in computational geometry).</li>
<li>We could be industrious and approximate the real tour lengths with a sufficiently small error since we look anyway for an approximation in overall.</li>
<li>We could think and then realize that our candidate tours consist of only constant many vertices as our integer grid has constant size. Indeed, the best known lower bound on the difference <em>r(n,k)</em> implies the following nice take-away which shall conclude this epilogue:</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>We can compare two sums of square roots in polynomial time if the number of square roots is constant!</strong></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><em><a href="https://duch.mimuw.edu.pl/~tugboat/about-us/krzysztof-fleszar/">Krzysztof Fleszar</a></em></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph {"align":"justify"} --></p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">-------------------------</p>
<p>Proof sketches for the interested reader of the lower and upper bounds on <em>r(n,k)</em>:</p>
<p>(*) <em>Ω(k log n)</em> [<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tcs.2011.06.014">Cheng et al.</a>]: The interval <em>[k, k √{n}]</em> contains so many distinct sums of square roots (over square-free integers) that, by a pigeonhole argument, there are two sums with very small distance.</p>
<p>(**) <em>O(2<sup>2k</sup> log n)</em> [<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s004530010005">Burnikel et al.</a>]: The difference is an algebraic integer and, consequently, the root of a polynomial with integer coefficients and degree at most <em>2<sup>2k</sup></em>. A simple inequality yields the bound.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-03-22T08:54:27Z</updated>
    <published>2019-03-22T08:54:27Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Renata Czarniecka</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl</id>
      <link href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://corner.mimuw.edu.pl" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>University of Warsaw</subtitle>
      <title>Banach's Algorithmic Corner</title>
      <updated>2019-03-31T23:24:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
