<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-12-03T22:21:44Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5122</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5122" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5122#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5122" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Quantum supremacy via BosonSampling</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">A group led by Jianwei Pan, based mainly in Hefei and Shanghai, announced today that it achieved BosonSampling with 40-70 detected photons—up to and beyond the limit where a classical supercomputer could feasibly verify the results. For more, see also Emily Conover’s piece in Science News, or Daniel Garisto’s in Scientific American, both of which […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A group led by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan_Jianwei">Jianwei Pan</a>, based mainly in Hefei and Shanghai, announced today that it <a href="https://science.sciencemag.org/lookup/doi/10.1126/science.abe8770">achieved BosonSampling with 40-70 detected photons</a>—up to and beyond the limit where a classical supercomputer could feasibly verify the results.  For more, see also <a href="https://www.sciencenews.org/article/new-light-based-quantum-computer-jiuzhang-supremacy">Emily Conover’s piece in <em>Science News</em></a>, or <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/light-based-quantum-computer-exceeds-fastest-classical-supercomputers/">Daniel Garisto’s in <em>Scientific American</em></a>, both of which I consulted on.  (Full disclosure: I was one of the reviewers for the Pan group’s <em>Science</em> paper, and will be writing the Perspective article to accompany it.)</p>



<p>The new result follows the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.09930">announcement</a> of 14-photon BosonSampling by the same group a year ago.  It represents the second time quantum supremacy has been reported, following Google’s celebrated <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4317">announcement</a> from last year, and the first time it’s been done using photonics rather than superconducting qubits.</p>



<p>As the co-inventor of <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/papers/optics.pdf">BosonSampling</a> (with Alex Arkhipov), obviously I’m gratified about this.</p>



<p>For anyone who regards it as boring or obvious, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=2435#comment-798278">here</a> and <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=1579#comment-92034">here</a> is Gil Kalai<a href="http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/">,</a> on this blog, telling me why BosonSampling would never scale beyond 8-10 photons.  (He wrote that, if aliens forced us to try, then much like with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramsey%27s_theorem">Ramsey number</a> R(6,6), our only hope would be to attack the aliens.)  <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oR-ufBz13Eg">Here’s </a>Kalai making a similar prediction, on the impossibility of quantum supremacy by BosonSampling or any other means, in his plenary address to the International Congress of Mathematicians two years ago.</p>



<p>Even if we set aside the quantum computing skeptics, many distinguished colleagues told me they thought experimental BosonSampling was a dead end, because of photon losses and the staggering difficulty of synchronizing 50-100 single-photon sources.  They said a convincing demonstration of quantum supremacy would have to await the arrival of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_threshold_theorem">quantum fault-tolerance</a>—or at any rate, some hardware platform more robust than photonics.  I always agreed that they might be right.  Furthermore, even if 50-photon BosonSampling <em>was</em> possible, after Google reached the supremacy milestone first with superconducting qubits, it wasn’t clear that anyone was going to bother.</p>



<p>Obviously the new result isn’t dispositive.  Maybe Gil Kalai really WON, BY A LOT, before Hugo Chávez hacked the Pan group’s computers to make it seem otherwise?  (Sorry, couldn’t resist.)  Nevertheless, as someone whose intellectual origins are close to pure math, it’s strange and exciting to find myself in a field where, once in a while, the world itself gets to weigh in on a theoretical disagreement.</p>



<p>Since excitement is best when paired with accurate understanding, please help yourself to the following FAQ, which I might add more to over the next couple days.</p>



<p><strong>What is BosonSampling?</strong>  You must be new here!  In increasing order of difficulty, <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2011/quantum-experiment-0302">here’s</a> an <em>MIT News</em> article from back in 2011, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boson_sampling">here’s</a> the Wikipedia page, <a href="http://www.scottaaronson.com/talks/bbn.ppt">here</a> are my PowerPoint slides, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=1631">here</a> are my lecture notes from Rio de Janeiro, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/papers/optics.pdf">here’s</a> my original paper with Arkhipov… </p>



<p><strong>What is quantum supremacy?</strong>  Roughly, the use of a programmable or configurable quantum computer to solve <em>some</em> well-defined computational problem much faster than we know how to solve it with any existing classical computer.  “Quantum supremacy,” a term <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1203.5813">coined</a> by John Preskill in 2012, does <em>not</em> mean useful QC, or universal QC, or scalable QC, or fault-tolerant QC, all of which remain outstanding challenges.  For more, see my <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4317">Supreme Quantum Supremacy FAQ</a>, or (e.g.) my recent <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZLhyTFk-WGs">Lytle Lecture</a> for the University of Washington.</p>



<p><strong>If Google already announced quantum supremacy a year ago, what’s the point of this new experiment?</strong>  To me, at least, quantum supremacy seems important enough to do at least twice!  Also, as I said, this represents the first demonstration that quantum supremacy is possible <em>via photonics</em>.  Finally, as the authors point out, the new experiment has one big technical advantage over Google’s: namely, many more possible output states (~10<sup>30</sup> of them, rather than a mere ~9 quadrillion).  This makes it infeasible to calculate the whole probability distribution over outputs and store it on a gigantic hard disk (after which one could easily generate as many samples as one wanted), which is what IBM proposed doing in its <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.09534">response</a> to Google’s announcement.</p>



<p><strong>Is BosonSampling a form of universal quantum computing?</strong>  No, we don’t even think it can simulate universal <em>classical</em> computing!  It’s designed for exactly one task: namely, demonstrating quantum supremacy and refuting Gil Kalai.  It <em>might</em> have some other applications besides that, but if so, they’ll be icing on the cake.  This is in contrast to Google’s Sycamore processor, which in principle <em>is</em> a universal quantum computer, just with a severe limit on the number of qubits (53) and how many layers of gates one can apply to them (about 20).</p>



<p><strong>Is BosonSampling at least a <em>step</em> toward universal quantum computing?</strong>  I think so!  In 2000, Knill, Laflamme, and Milburn (KLM) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KLM_protocol">famously showed</a> that pure, non-interacting photons, passing through a network of beamsplitters, are capable of universal QC, provided we assume one extra thing: namely, the ability to measure the photons at intermediate times, and change which beamsplitters to apply to the remaining photons depending on the outcome.  In other words, “BosonSampling plus adaptive measurements equals universality.”  Basically, KLM is the holy grail that Pan’s and other experimental optics groups around the world have been working toward for 20 years, with BosonSampling just a more achievable pit stop along the way.</p>



<p><strong>Are there any applications of BosonSampling?</strong>  We don’t know yet.  There are proposals in the literature to apply BosonSampling to quantum chemistry and other fields, but I’m not yet convinced that these proposals will yield real speedups over the best we can do with classical computers, for any task of practical interest that involves estimating specific numbers (as opposed to sampling tasks, where BosonSampling almost certainly <em>does</em> yield exponential speedups, but which are rarely the thing practitioners directly care about).</p>



<p><strong>How hard is it to simulate BosonSampling on a classical computer?</strong>  As far as we know today, the difficulty of simulating a “generic” BosonSampling experiment increases roughly like 2<sup>n</sup>, where n is the number of detected photons.  It <em>might</em> be easier than that, particularly when noise and imperfections are taken into account; and at any rate it might be easier to spoof the statistical tests that one applies to verify the outputs.  I and others managed to give some theoretical evidence against those possibilities, but just like with Google’s experiment, it’s conceivable that some future breakthrough will change the outlook and remove the case for quantum supremacy.</p>



<p><strong>Do you have any amusing stories?</strong>  When I refereed the <em>Science</em> paper, I asked why the authors directly verified the results of their experiment only for up to 26-30 photons, relying on plausible extrapolations beyond that.  While directly verifying the results of n-photon BosonSampling takes ~2<sup>n</sup> time for any known classical algorithm, I said, surely it should be possible with existing computers to go up to n=40 or n=50?  A couple weeks later, the authors responded, saying that they’d now verified their results up to n=40, but it burned $400,000 worth of supercomputer time so they decided to stop there.  This was by far the most expensive referee report I ever wrote!</p>



<p>Also: when Covid first started, and facemasks were plentiful in China but almost impossible to get in the US, Chaoyang Lu, one of the authors of the new work, decided to mail me a box of 200 masks (I didn’t ask for it).  I don’t think that influenced my later review, but was appreciated nevertheless.</p>



<p>Huge congratulations to the whole team for their accomplishment!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-03T22:19:03Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-03T22:19:03Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:19:03Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/03/postdoc-at-tel-aviv-university-at-tel-aviv-university-apply-by-december-31-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/03/postdoc-at-tel-aviv-university-at-tel-aviv-university-apply-by-december-31-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at Tel Aviv University at Tel Aviv University (apply by December 31, 2020)</title>
    <summary>I (Gil Cohen) invite applications for a postdoctoral position to start in September 2021 (the exact start date will be flexible). The position will have an initial appointment of one year, but will be extendible to two years. My main research interests right now include randomness extractors, derandomization of space bounded computation, tree codes, coding […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I (Gil Cohen) invite applications for a postdoctoral position to start in September 2021 (the exact start date will be flexible). The position will have an initial appointment of one year, but will be extendible to two years. My main research interests right now include randomness extractors, derandomization of space bounded computation, tree codes, coding theory, and spectral graph theory.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.gilcohen.org/postdoc2021">https://www.gilcohen.org/postdoc2021</a><br/>
Email: gil@tauex.tau.ac.il</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-03T18:04:18Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-03T18:04:18Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/03/postdoctoral-associate-at-dimacs-at-rutgers-university-apply-by-january-15-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/03/postdoctoral-associate-at-dimacs-at-rutgers-university-apply-by-january-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral Associate at DIMACS at Rutgers University (apply by January 15, 2021)</title>
    <summary>DIMACS, the Center for Discrete Mathematics and Theoretical Computer Science, invites applications for postdoctoral associate positions for 2021-2023. Applicants should be recent PhDs with interest in DIMACS areas, including theoretical computer science, discrete mathematics, statistics, operations research, data science, AI, machine learning, and their applications. Website: https://jobs.rutgers.edu/postings/122935 Email: postdoc@dimacs.rutgers.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>DIMACS, the Center for Discrete Mathematics and Theoretical Computer Science, invites applications for postdoctoral associate positions for 2021-2023. Applicants should be recent PhDs with interest in DIMACS areas, including theoretical computer science, discrete mathematics, statistics, operations research, data science, AI, machine learning, and their applications.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://jobs.rutgers.edu/postings/122935">https://jobs.rutgers.edu/postings/122935</a><br/>
Email: postdoc@dimacs.rutgers.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-03T18:02:31Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-03T18:02:31Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-3699673705974309715</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/3699673705974309715/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/12/chess-is-back.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3699673705974309715" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3699673705974309715" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/12/chess-is-back.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Chess is Back</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Back in 2005, I wrote a post titled <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2005/11/chess-and-poker.html">Chess and Poker</a>. Not really comparing the two but noting that Chess had lost its mojo while poker had high-stakes prime time tournaments. The inspiration was an <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/27/opinion/all-the-right-moves.html">NYT Op-Ed</a> that started "CHESS in America is having a crisis". I suggested that computers getting better than humans may have reduced interest in the game. </p><p>Now chess is <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/11/23/arts/television/chess-set-board-sales.html">booming again</a>, due to all of us being stuck at home and the Netflix limited series <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt10048342/">The Queen's Gambit</a> (highly recommended). </p><p>The fictional show takes place in the 1960's when interest in chess in the US started to pick up due to <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2008/01/bobby-fischer-guest-post-by-ken-regan.html">Bobby Fischer's exploits</a> and well before computers played a decent game. Fischer isn't mentioned in the Netflix series, the main character Beth Harmon sort of plays his role. The games themselves, created by Gary Kasparov and others, are even a joy to watch. Check out <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oIMaTKOZG-8">this analysis</a> of the final game (spoiler warning). </p><p>The New York Times <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/22/crosswords/chess/chess-50-years-of-new-york-times-columns.html">started a chess column</a> in 1962 and ran its <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/12/crosswords/chess/after-rocky-start-grand-prix-finds-a-favorite-in-the-lead.html">last column</a> in 2014, though that might be saying more about the state of newspapers than the state of chess.</p><p>What about the computers? They have just gotten so good and with <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2017/12/our-ai-future-good-and-ugly.html">AlphaZero</a> mastering the game with just machine learning on top of the rules of chess, it's not even fun to watch computer versus computer anymore. Now we're back to watching humans and getting back into the games ourselves.</p><p>Computers have opened the door to cheating. Complexity theorist Ken Regan has a <a href="http://www.buffalo.edu/news/experts/ken-regan-faculty-expert-chess.html">side gig</a> reviewing games to determine if a player punching above their weight secretly used a computer algorithm. </p><p>Microsoft just <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/blog/the-human-side-of-ai-for-chess/">announced</a> chess programs that play as a human at various levels of strength. I suppose someone could use a program like this to cheat in a way that even Ken couldn't detect. But mostly it would be like Googling in pub trivia--just takes the fun out of the game.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-03T14:48:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-03T14:48:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T16:15:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/180</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/180" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-180 |  Shrinkage under Random Projections, and Cubic Formula Lower Bounds for $\mathbf{AC}^0$ | 

	Yuval Filmus, 

	Or Meir, 

	Avishay Tal</title>
    <summary>Håstad showed that any De Morgan formula (composed of AND, OR and NOT gates) shrinks by a factor of $O(p^{2})$ under a random restriction that leaves each variable alive independently with probability $p$ [SICOMP, 1998]. Using this result, he gave an $\widetilde{\Omega}(n^{3})$ formula size lower bound for the Andreev function, which, up to lower order improvements, remains the state-of-the-art lower bound for any explicit function.

  In this work, we extend the shrinkage result of Håstad to hold under a far wider family of random restrictions and their generalization — random projections. Based on our shrinkage results, we obtain an $\widetilde{\Omega}(n^{3})$ formula size lower bound for an explicit function computed in $\mathbf{AC}^0$. This improves upon the best known formula size lower bounds for $\mathbf{AC}^0$, that were only quadratic prior to our work. In addition, we prove that the KRW conjecture [Karchmer et al., Computational Complexity 5(3/4), 1995] holds for inner functions for which the unweighted quantum adversary bound is tight. In particular, this holds for inner functions with a tight Khrapchenko bound.

  Our random projections are tailor-made to the function's structure so that the function maintains structure even under projection --- using such projections is necessary, as standard random restrictions simplify $\mathbf{AC}^0$ circuits. In contrast, we show that any De Morgan formula shrinks by a quadratic factor under our random projections, allowing us to prove the cubic lower bound.

  Our proof techniques build on the proof of Håstad for the simpler case of balanced formulas. This allows for a significantly simpler proof at the cost of slightly worse parameters. As such, when specialized to the case of $p$-random restrictions, our proof can be used as an exposition of Håstad's result.</summary>
    <updated>2020-12-03T02:53:05Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-03T02:53:05Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17821</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/12/02/too-long-didnt-read/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Too Long, Didn’t Read</title>
    <summary>How to summarize papers Top row: Cohan, Weld. Bottom: Cachola, Lo. Isabel Cachola, Kyle Lo, Arman Cohan, Daniel Weld are the authors of a recent paper on summarizing papers. They are all connected in various way to the Allen Institute for Artificial Intelligence. Today we take a moment to try out the webtool that comes […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>How to summarize papers</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/12/02/too-long-didnt-read/all-8/" rel="attachment wp-att-17825"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-17825" height="134" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/all.png?w=200&amp;h=134" width="200"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Top row: Cohan, Weld. Bottom: Cachola, Lo.</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Isabel Cachola, Kyle Lo, Arman Cohan, Daniel Weld are the authors of a recent <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.15011">paper</a> on summarizing papers. They are all connected in various way to the <a href="https://allenai.org/papers">Allen Institute</a> for Artificial Intelligence. </p>
<p>
Today we take a moment to try out the <a href="https://scitldr.apps.allenai.org/">webtool</a> that comes with their paper.  It is noted also in a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-03277-2">news item</a> last week in <i>Nature</i>.</p>
<p>
They have created a program that reads a science article and outputs a single sentence that summarizes its content. Their goal is to help researchers search through the huge number of published papers faster than looking at abstracts. The software utilizes neural networks trained on many examples. </p>
<p>
For example: Their own <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.15011">paper</a> has for its abstract:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> We introduce TLDR generation, a new form of extreme summarization, for scientific papers. TLDR generation involves high source compression and requires expert background knowledge and understanding of complex domain-specific language. To facilitate study on this task, we introduce SCITLDR, a new multi-target dataset of 5.4K TLDRs over 3.2K papers. SCITLDR contains both author-written and expert-derived TLDRs, where the latter are collected using a novel annotation protocol that produces high-quality summaries while minimizing annotation burden. We propose CATTS, a simple yet effective learning strategy for generating TLDRs that exploits titles as an auxiliary training signal. CATTS improves upon strong baselines under both automated metrics and human evaluations. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
And this becomes:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “We introduce SCITLDR, a new multi-target dataset of 5.4K TLDRs over 3.2K papers.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Not so impressive, but more on their program shortly.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Another Tryout </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Perhaps the big news this week is an advance on protein folding by Google DeepMind, the same team whose work on <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2016/03/11/stonefight-at-the-goke-corral/">AlphaGo</a> and <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2017/12/17/truth-from-zero/">AlphaZero</a> we have covered. Sure enough, their new system is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AlphaFold">AlphaFold</a>—actually, AlphaFold2. See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protein_folding">here</a> for basic information: </p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/12/02/too-long-didnt-read/fold-2/" rel="attachment wp-att-17826"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-17826" height="222" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/fold.png?w=500&amp;h=222" width="500"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
The detailed <a href="https://deepmind.com/blog/article/alphafold-a-solution-to-a-50-year-old-grand-challenge-in-biology">announcement</a> on the DeepMind <a href="https://deepmind.com/blog">blog</a> says:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Until we’ve published a paper on this work, please cite: “High Accuracy Protein Structure Prediction Using Deep Learning,” John Jumper [et al.]. In Fourteenth Critical Assessment of Techniques for Protein Structure Prediction (Abstract Book), 30 November – 4 December 2020. Retrieved from <a href="https://predictioncenter.org/casp14/doc/CASP14_Abstracts.pdf">here</a></em>.
</p></blockquote>
<p>The link under “<a href="https://predictioncenter.org/casp14/doc/CASP14_Abstracts.pdf">here</a>” goes to a long book of abstracts. Among them, there is a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-019-1923-7">paper</a> last January in <em>Nature</em> with many of the same authors, though Jumper not as first author. Using its abstract, we got:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “We train a neural network to make accurate predictions of the distances between pairs of residues, which convey more information about the structure than contact predictions.” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The abstracts book has the abstract for the current paper:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> In the CASP14 experiment, we deployed AlphaFold 2. This new system uses a different deep learning method than CASP13 AlphaFold, and it produces much more accurate protein structures and estimates of model accuracy. The training data for the system is publicly available and similar to that used for CASP13 AlphaFold. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This is already short, but with SCITLDR it becomes:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “In the CASP14 experiment, we deployed AlphaFold 2.0, a new deep learning system that produces much more accurate protein structures and” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The dangling “and” is a little mystifying. SCITLDR has optional fields for <i>Introduction</i> and <i>Conclusions</i>. The entry in the abstracts book has a body titled “Methods,” whose last subsection “T1064” reads like a conclusion, so we added them as such. We cleaned up the paste from PDF to have normal line breaks. After a few seconds, we obtained:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “In the CASP14 experiment, we deployed AlphaFold 2.0, a novel attention-based deep learning architecture that produces accurate protein structures” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The DeepMind announcement poses a further challenge: how to glean an important paper that for now exists only as a blog post. The first paragraph of their <a href="https://deepmind.com/blog/article/alphafold-a-solution-to-a-50-year-old-grand-challenge-in-biology">post</a> is boldfaced and reads like an abstract:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Proteins are essential to life, supporting practically all its functions. They are large complex molecules, made up of chains of amino acids, and what a protein does largely depends on its unique 3D structure. Figuring out what shapes proteins fold into is known as the “protein folding problem,” and has stood as a grand challenge in biology for the past 50 years. In a major scientific advance, the latest version of our AI system AlphaFold has been recognised as a solution to this grand challenge by the organisers of the biennial Critical Assessment of protein Structure Prediction (CASP). This breakthrough demonstrates the impact AI can have on scientific discovery and its potential to dramatically accelerate progress in some of the most fundamental fields that explain and shape our world. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
It becomes: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> “AlphaFold has been recognized as a solution to this grand challenge by the organizers of the Critical Assessment of protein Structure Prediction (CASP)” </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Pretty good—do you agree?</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Even Faster </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Both Ken and I are fans of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mathematical_Experience">book</a> <em>The Mathematical Experience</em> by Philip Davis and Reuben Hersch. The following passage, from the chapter “The Ideal Mathematician,” describes how one writes a paper, but Ken has always taken it to describe the swiftness needed to read a paper:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> The intended readers (all twelve of them) can decode the formal presentation, detect the new idea hidden in lemma 4, ignore the routine and uninteresting calculations of lemmas 1, 2, 3, 5, 6, 7, and see what the author is doing and why he does it. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Nowadays we pore through papers as they appear on arXiv. For most, we just scan the titles. For others, we go to the main page with the abstract. For some, we click on the PDF to read the paper. This may be the greatest exercise in freedom of intellect we have our professional lives, but it is also an exercise in speed. We who do research in time complexity need to minimize our own time. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Some CS Examples </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Another way to say this: we all need to read through the literature faster and more precisely. Here are a few examples of their one sentence abstracts for theory papers from the SCITLDR program. Rate them by seeing if you can match the summarizes with the papers.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
Here are the one sentence summaries: </p>
<ol>
<li>
“Finite automata are considered in this paper as instruments for classifying finite tapes.” <p/>
</li><li>
“The number of steps required to compute a function depends, in general, on the type of computer that is used, on the choice of computer program” <p/>
</li><li>
“In this paper, it is proven that when both randomization and interaction are allowed, the proofs that can be verified in polynomial time are” <p/>
</li><li>
“In this paper a computational complexity theory of the “knowledge” contained in a proof is developed.” <p/>
</li><li>
“It is shown that any recognition problem solved by a polynomial time-bounded nondeterministic Turing machine can be “reduced” <p/>
</li><li>
“We prove that there are arbitrarily long arithmetic progressions of primes.” <p/>
</li><li>
“Nonuniform Upper Bounds: The Converse Direction of the Nonuniform Complexity Bounds .”
</li></ol>
<p/><p><br/>
Match them to the paper titles: </p>
<ol>
<li>
The complexity of theorem-proving procedures <p/>
</li><li>
Some connections between nonuniform and uniform complexity classes <p/>
</li><li>
Finite Automata and Their Decision Problem <p/>
</li><li>
A Machine-Independent theory of the Complexity of Recursive Functions <p/>
</li><li>
Some connections between nonuniform and uniform complexity classes <p/>
</li><li>
The Knowledge Complexity Of Interactive Proof Systems <p/>
</li><li>
The primes contain arbitrarily long arithmetic progressions
</li></ol>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>The papers:</p>
<ol>
<li>
“Finite automata are considered in this paper as instruments for classifying finite tapes.” <a href="http://www.cse.chalmers.se/~coquand/AUTOMATA/rs.pdf">1</a><p/>
<p/></li><li>
“The number of steps required to compute a function depends, in general, on the type of computer that is used, on the choice of computer program” <a href="http://port70.net/~nsz/articles/classic/blum_complexity_1976.pdf">2</a><p/>
<p/></li><li>
“In this paper, it is proven that when both randomization and interaction are allowed, the proofs that can be verified in polynomial time are” <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/146585.146609">3</a><p/>
<p/></li><li>
“In this paper a computational complexity theory of the “knowledge” contained in a proof is developed.” <a href="http://crypto.cs.mcgill.ca/~crepeau/COMP647/2007/TOPIC02/GMR89.pdf">4</a><p/>
<p/></li><li>
“It is shown that any recognition problem solved by a polynomial time-bounded nondeterministic Turing machine can be “reduced” <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/800157.805047">5</a><p/>
<p/></li><li>
“We prove that there are arbitrarily long arithmetic progressions of primes.” <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/math/0404188">6</a><p/>
<p/></li><li>
“Nonuniform Upper Bounds: The Converse Direction of the Nonuniform Complexity Bounds .” <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/800141.804678">7</a>
</li></ol>
<p>
The answers in brief: <b>a-5, b-7,c-1,d-2,e-3,f-4,g-6</b>.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
[fixed blog formatting issues, fixed paper ascription in the intro]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:17:28Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-02T22:17:28Z</published>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="literature"/>
    <category term="papers"/>
    <category term="protein folding"/>
    <category term="search"/>
    <category term="summary"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/179</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/179" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-179 |  Decoding Multivariate Multiplicity Codes on Product Sets | 

	Mrinal Kumar, 

	Siddharth Bhandari, 

	Prahladh Harsha, 

	Madhu Sudan</title>
    <summary>The multiplicity Schwartz-Zippel lemma bounds the total multiplicity of zeroes of a multivariate polynomial on a product set. This lemma motivates the multiplicity codes of Kopparty, Saraf and Yekhanin [J. ACM, 2014], who showed how to use this lemma to construct high-rate locally-decodable codes. However, the algorithmic results about these codes crucially rely on the fact that the polynomials are evaluated on a vector space and not an arbitrary product set. 

In this work, we show how to decode multivariate multiplicity codes of large multiplicities in polynomial time over finite product sets (over fields of large characteristic and zero characteristic).  Previously such decoding algorithms were not known even for a positive fraction of errors. In contrast, our work goes all the way to the distance of the code and in particular exceeds both the unique decoding bound and the Johnson bound. For errors exceeding the Johnson bound, even combinatorial list-decodablity of these codes was not known.

Our algorithm is an application of the classical polynomial method directly to the multivariate setting. In particular, we do not rely on a reduction from the multivariate to the univariate case as is typical of many of the existing results on decoding codes based on multivariate polynomials.  However, a vanilla application of the polynomial method in the multivariate setting does not yield a polynomial upper bound on the list size. We obtain a polynomial bound on the list size by taking an alternative view of multivariate multiplicity codes. In this view,  we glue all the partial derivatives of the same order  together  using a fresh set $\mathbf{z}$ of variables.  We then apply the polynomial method by viewing this as a problem over the field $\mathbb{F}(\mathbf{z})$ of rational functions in $\mathbf{z}$.</summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T15:26:31Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-02T15:26:31Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/02/tenure-track-assistant-professors-at-rochester-institute-of-technology-apply-by-january-2-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/02/tenure-track-assistant-professors-at-rochester-institute-of-technology-apply-by-january-2-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure-track assistant professors at Rochester Institute of Technology (apply by January 2, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at the Rochester Institute of Technology invites applications for full-time tenure-track assistant professor positions starting in Fall 2021. We are looking to hire in all areas of computer science that strengthen our department. Website: https://sjobs.brassring.com/TGnewUI/Search/Home/Home?partnerid=25483&amp;siteid=5291#jobDetails=1534060_5291 Email: csfacsearch@cs.rit.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at the Rochester Institute of Technology invites applications for full-time tenure-track assistant professor positions starting in Fall 2021. We are looking to hire in all areas of computer science that strengthen our department.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://sjobs.brassring.com/TGnewUI/Search/Home/Home?partnerid=25483&amp;siteid=5291#jobDetails=1534060_5291">https://sjobs.brassring.com/TGnewUI/Search/Home/Home?partnerid=25483&amp;siteid=5291#jobDetails=1534060_5291</a><br/>
Email: csfacsearch@cs.rit.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-02T01:44:24Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-02T01:44:24Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00738</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00738" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Searching, Sorting, and Cake Cutting in Rounds</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Br=acirc=nzei:Simina.html">Simina Brânzei</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Paparas:Dimitris.html">Dimitris Paparas</a>, Nicholas J. Recker <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00738">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study sorting and searching in rounds, motivated by a cake cutting
problem. The search problem we consider is: we are given an array $x = (x_1,
\ldots, x_n)$ and an element $z$ promised to be in the array. We have access to
an oracle that answers comparison queries: "How is $x_i$ compared to $x_j$?",
where the answer can be "$&lt;$", "$=$", or "$&gt;$". The goal is to find the
location of $z$ with success probability at least $p \in [0,1]$ in at most $k$
rounds of interaction with the oracle. The problem is called ordered or
unordered search, depending on whether the array $x$ is sorted or unsorted,
respectively.
</p>
<p>For ordered search, we show the expected query complexity of randomized
algorithms is $\Theta\bigl(k\cdot p \cdot n^{1/k}\bigr)$ in the worst case. In
contrast, the expected query complexity of deterministic algorithms searching
for a uniformly random element is $\Theta\bigl(k\cdot p^{1/k} \cdot
n^{1/k}\bigr)$. The uniform distribution is the worst case for deterministic
algorithms.
</p>
<p>For unordered search, the expected query complexity of randomized algorithms
is $np\bigl(\frac{k+1}{2k}\bigr) \pm 1$ in the worst case, while the expected
query complexity of deterministic algorithms searching for a uniformly random
element is $np \bigl(1 - \frac{k-1}{2k}p \bigr) \pm 1$.
</p>
<p>We also discuss the connections of these search problems to the rank query
model, where the array $x$ can be accessed via queries of the form "Is
rank$(x_i) \leq k$?". Unordered search is equivalent to Select with rank
queries (given $q$, find $x_i$ with rank $q$) and ordered search to Locate with
rank queries (given $x_i$, find its rank). We show an equivalence between
sorting with rank queries and proportional cake cutting with contiguous pieces
for any number of rounds, as well as an improved lower bound for deterministic
sorting in rounds with rank queries.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:50:58Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00704</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00704" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Lower Bounds for Semialgebraic Range Searching and Stabbing Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Afshani:Peyman.html">Peyman Afshani</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cheng:Pingan.html">Pingan Cheng</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00704">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the semialgebraic range searching problem, we are to preprocess $n$ points
in $\mathbb{R}^d$ s.t. for any query range from a family of constant complexity
semialgebraic sets, all the points intersecting the range can be reported or
counted efficiently. When the ranges are composed of simplices, the problem can
be solved using $S(n)$ space and with $Q(n)$ query time with $S(n)Q^d(n) =
\tilde{O}(n^d)$ and this trade-off is almost tight. Consequently, there exists
low space structures that use $\tilde{O}(n)$ space with $O(n^{1-1/d})$ query
time and fast query structures that use $O(n^d)$ space with $O(\log^{d} n)$
query time. However, for the general semialgebraic ranges, only low space
solutions are known, but the best solutions match the same trade-off curve as
the simplex queries. It has been conjectured that the same could be done for
the fast query case but this open problem has stayed unresolved.
</p>
<p>Here, we disprove this conjecture. We give the first nontrivial lower bounds
for semilagebraic range searching and related problems. We show that any data
structure for reporting the points between two concentric circles with $Q(n)$
query time must use $S(n)=\Omega(n^{3-o(1)}/Q(n)^5)$ space, meaning, for
$Q(n)=O(\log^{O(1)}n)$, $\Omega(n^{3-o(1)})$ space must be used. We also study
the problem of reporting the points between two polynomials of form
$Y=\sum_{i=0}^\Delta a_i X^i$ where $a_0, \cdots, a_\Delta$ are given at the
query time. We show $S(n)=\Omega(n^{\Delta+1-o(1)}/Q(n)^{\Delta^2+\Delta})$. So
for $Q(n)=O(\log^{O(1)}n)$, we must use $\Omega(n^{\Delta+1-o(1)})$ space. For
the dual semialgebraic stabbing problems, we show that in linear space, any
data structure that solves 2D ring stabbing must use $\Omega(n^{2/3})$ query
time. This almost matches the linearization upper bound. For general
semialgebraic slab stabbing problems, again, we show an almost tight lower
bounds.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:56:09Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00689</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00689" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dynamic Weighted Matching with Heterogeneous Arrival and Departure Rates</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Collina:Natalie.html">Natalie Collina</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Immorlica:Nicole.html">Nicole Immorlica</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Leyton=Brown:Kevin.html">Kevin Leyton-Brown</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lucier:Brendan.html">Brendan Lucier</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Newman:Neil.html">Neil Newman</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00689">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study a dynamic non-bipartite matching problem. There is a fixed set of
agent types, and agents of a given type arrive and depart according to
type-specific Poisson processes. The value of a match is determined by the
types of the matched agents. We present an online algorithm that is
(1/6)-competitive with respect to the value of the optimal-in-hindsight policy,
for arbitrary weighted graphs. This is the first result to achieve a constant
competitive ratio when both arrivals and departures are random and unannounced.
Our algorithm treats agents heterogeneously, interpolating between immediate
and delayed matching in order to thicken the market while still matching
valuable agents opportunistically.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:46:58Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00675</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00675" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Topological Learning for Brain Networks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Songdechakraiwut:Tananun.html">Tananun Songdechakraiwut</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chung:Moo_K=.html">Moo K. Chung</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00675">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper proposes a novel topological learning framework that can integrate
networks of different sizes and topology through persistent homology. This is
possible through the introduction of a new topological loss function that
enables such challenging task. The use of the proposed loss function bypasses
the intrinsic computational bottleneck associated with matching networks. We
validate the method in extensive statistical simulations with ground truth to
assess the effectiveness of the topological loss in discriminating networks
with different topology. The method is further applied to a twin brain imaging
study in determining if the brain network is genetically heritable. The
challenge is in overlaying the topologically different functional brain
networks obtained from the resting-state functional magnetic resonance imaging
(fMRI) onto the template structural brain network obtained through the
diffusion tensor imaging (DTI).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:55:24Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00589</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00589" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Train Tracks with Gaps: Applying the Probabilistic Method to Trains</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kuszmaul:William.html">William Kuszmaul</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00589">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We identify a tradeoff curve between the number of wheels on a train car, and
the amount of track that must be installed in order to ensure that the train
car is supported by the track at all times. The goal is to build an elevated
track that covers some large distance $\ell$, but that consists primarily of
gaps, so that the total amount of feet of train track that is actually
installed is only a small fraction of $\ell$. In order so that the train track
can support the train at all points, the requirement is that as the train
drives across the track, at least one set of wheels from the rear quarter and
at least one set of wheels from the front quarter of the train must be touching
the track at all times.
</p>
<p>We show that, if a train car has $n$ sets of wheels evenly spaced apart in
its rear and $n$ sets of wheels evenly spaced apart in its front, then it is
possible to build a train track that supports the train car but uses only
$\Theta( \ell / n )$ feet of track. We then consider what happens if the wheels
on the train car are not evenly spaced (and may even be configured
adversarially). We show that for any configuration of the train car, with $n$
wheels in each of the front and rear quarters of the car, it is possible to
build a track that supports the car for distance $\ell$ and uses only
$O\left(\frac{\ell \log n}{n}\right)$ feet of track. Additionally, we show that
there exist configurations of the train car for which this tradeoff curve is
asymptotically optimal. Both the upper and lower bounds are achieved via
applications of the probabilistic method.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:42:52Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00511</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00511" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Best Fit Bin Packing with Random Order Revisited</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Albers:Susanne.html">Susanne Albers</a>, Arindam Khan, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Ladewig:Leon.html">Leon Ladewig</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00511">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Best Fit is a well known online algorithm for the bin packing problem, where
a collection of one-dimensional items has to be packed into a minimum number of
unit-sized bins. In a seminal work, Kenyon [SODA 1996] introduced the
(asymptotic) random order ratio as an alternative performance measure for
online algorithms. Here, an adversary specifies the items, but the order of
arrival is drawn uniformly at random. Kenyon's result establishes lower and
upper bounds of 1.08 and 1.5, respectively, for the random order ratio of Best
Fit. Although this type of analysis model became increasingly popular in the
field of online algorithms, no progress has been made for the Best Fit
algorithm after the result of Kenyon.
</p>
<p>We study the random order ratio of Best Fit and tighten the long-standing gap
by establishing an improved lower bound of 1.10. For the case where all items
are larger than 1/3, we show that the random order ratio converges quickly to
1.25. It is the existence of such large items that crucially determines the
performance of Best Fit in the general case. Moreover, this case is closely
related to the classical maximum-cardinality matching problem in the fully
online model. As a side product, we show that Best Fit satisfies a monotonicity
property on such instances, unlike in the general case.
</p>
<p>In addition, we initiate the study of the absolute random order ratio for
this problem. In contrast to asymptotic ratios, absolute ratios must hold even
for instances that can be packed into a small number of bins. We show that the
absolute random order ratio of Best Fit is at least 1.3. For the case where all
items are larger than 1/3, we derive upper and lower bounds of 21/16 and 1.2,
respectively.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:46:07Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00497</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00497" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Improved Online Algorithms for Knapsack and GAP in the Random Order Model</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Albers:Susanne.html">Susanne Albers</a>, Arindam Khan, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Ladewig:Leon.html">Leon Ladewig</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00497">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The knapsack problem is one of the classical problems in combinatorial
optimization: Given a set of items, each specified by its size and profit, the
goal is to find a maximum profit packing into a knapsack of bounded capacity.
In the online setting, items are revealed one by one and the decision, if the
current item is packed or discarded forever, must be done immediately and
irrevocably upon arrival. We study the online variant in the random order model
where the input sequence is a uniform random permutation of the item set.
</p>
<p>We develop a randomized (1/6.65)-competitive algorithm for this problem,
outperforming the current best algorithm of competitive ratio 1/8.06
[Kesselheim et al. SIAM J. Comp. 47(5)]. Our algorithm is based on two new
insights: We introduce a novel algorithmic approach that employs two given
algorithms, optimized for restricted item classes, sequentially on the input
sequence. In addition, we study and exploit the relationship of the knapsack
problem to the 2-secretary problem.
</p>
<p>The generalized assignment problem (GAP) includes, besides the knapsack
problem, several important problems related to scheduling and matching. We show
that in the same online setting, applying the proposed sequential approach
yields a (1/6.99)-competitive randomized algorithm for GAP. Again, our proposed
algorithm outperforms the current best result of competitive ratio 1/8.06
[Kesselheim et al. SIAM J. Comp. 47(5)].
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:50:08Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00488</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00488" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>New Results for the $k$-Secretary Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Albers:Susanne.html">Susanne Albers</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Ladewig:Leon.html">Leon Ladewig</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00488">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Suppose that $n$ items arrive online in random order and the goal is to
select $k$ of them such that the expected sum of the selected items is
maximized. The decision for any item is irrevocable and must be made on arrival
without knowing future items. This problem is known as the $k$-secretary
problem, which includes the classical secretary problem with the special case
$k=1$. It is well-known that the latter problem can be solved by a simple
algorithm of competitive ratio $1/e$ which is optimal for $n \to \infty$.
Existing algorithms beating the threshold of $1/e$ either rely on involved
selection policies already for $k=2$, or assume that $k$ is large.
</p>
<p>In this paper we present results for the $k$-secretary problem, considering
the interesting and relevant case that $k$ is small. We focus on simple
selection algorithms, accompanied by combinatorial analyses. As a main
contribution we propose a natural deterministic algorithm designed to have
competitive ratios strictly greater than $1/e$ for small $k \geq 2$. This
algorithm is hardly more complex than the elegant strategy for the classical
secretary problem, optimal for $k=1$, and works for all $k \geq 1$. We derive
its competitive ratios for $k \leq 100$, ranging from $0.41$ for $k=2$ to
$0.75$ for $k=100$.
</p>
<p>Moreover, we consider an algorithm proposed earlier in the literature, for
which no rigorous analysis is known. We show that its competitive ratio is
$0.4168$ for $k=2$, implying that the previous analysis was not tight. Our
analysis reveals a surprising combinatorial property of this algorithm, which
might be helpful to find a tight analysis for all $k$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:45:07Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00464</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00464" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>(k, l)-Medians Clustering of Trajectories Using Continuous Dynamic Time Warping</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Brankovic:Milutin.html">Milutin Brankovic</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Buchin:Kevin.html">Kevin Buchin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Klaren:Koen.html">Koen Klaren</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nusser:Andr=eacute=.html">André Nusser</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Popov:Aleksandr.html">Aleksandr Popov</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wong:Sampson.html">Sampson Wong</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00464">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Due to the massively increasing amount of available geospatial data and the
need to present it in an understandable way, clustering this data is more
important than ever. As clusters might contain a large number of objects,
having a representative for each cluster significantly facilitates
understanding a clustering. Clustering methods relying on such representatives
are called center-based. In this work we consider the problem of center-based
clustering of trajectories.
</p>
<p>In this setting, the representative of a cluster is again a trajectory. To
obtain a compact representation of the clusters and to avoid overfitting, we
restrict the complexity of the representative trajectories by a parameter l.
This restriction, however, makes discrete distance measures like dynamic time
warping (DTW) less suited.
</p>
<p>There is recent work on center-based clustering of trajectories with a
continuous distance measure, namely, the Fr\'echet distance. While the
Fr\'echet distance allows for restriction of the center complexity, it can also
be sensitive to outliers, whereas averaging-type distance measures, like DTW,
are less so. To obtain a trajectory clustering algorithm that allows
restricting center complexity and is more robust to outliers, we propose the
usage of a continuous version of DTW as distance measure, which we call
continuous dynamic time warping (CDTW). Our contribution is twofold:
</p>
<p>1. To combat the lack of practical algorithms for CDTW, we develop an
approximation algorithm that computes it.
</p>
<p>2. We develop the first clustering algorithm under this distance measure and
show a practical way to compute a center from a set of trajectories and
subsequently iteratively improve it.
</p>
<p>To obtain insights into the results of clustering under CDTW on practical
data, we conduct extensive experiments.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:51:55Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00356</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00356" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Better Fewer but Better: Community Search with Outliers</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bonchi:Francesco.html">Francesco Bonchi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Severini:Lorenzo.html">Lorenzo Severini</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sozio:Mauro.html">Mauro Sozio</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00356">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a set of vertices in a network, that we believe are of interest for the
application under analysis, community search is the problem of producing a
subgraph potentially explaining the relationships existing among the vertices
of interest. In practice this means that the solution should add some vertices
to the query ones, so to create a connected subgraph that exhibits some
"cohesiveness" property. This problem has received increasing attention in
recent years: while several cohesiveness functions have been studied, the bulk
of the literature looks for a solution subgraphs containing all the query
vertices. However, in many exploratory analyses we might only have a reasonable
belief about the vertices of interest: if only one of them is not really
related to the others, forcing the solution to include all of them might hide
the existence of much more cohesive and meaningful subgraphs, that we could
have found by allowing the solution to detect and drop the outlier vertex. In
this paper we study the problem of community search with outliers, where we are
allowed to drop up to $k$ query vertices, with $k$ being an input parameter. We
consider three of the most used measures of cohesiveness: the minimum degree,
the diameter of the subgraph and the maximum distance with a query vertex. By
optimizing one and using one of the others as a constraint we obtain three
optimization problems: we study their hardness and we propose different exact
and approximation algorithms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:40:34Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00330</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00330" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Time-Space Lower Bounds for Simulating Proof Systems with Quantum and Randomized Verifiers</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Abhijit Mudigonda, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Williams:R=_Ryan.html">R. Ryan Williams</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00330">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A line of work initiated by Fortnow in 1997 has proven model-independent
time-space lower bounds for the $\mathsf{SAT}$ problem and related problems
within the polynomial-time hierarchy. For example, for the $\mathsf{SAT}$
problem, the state-of-the-art is that the problem cannot be solved by
random-access machines in $n^c$ time and $n^{o(1)}$ space simultaneously for $c
&lt; 2\cos(\frac{\pi}{7}) \approx 1.801$.
</p>
<p>We extend this lower bound approach to the quantum and randomized domains.
Combining Grover's algorithm with components from $\mathsf{SAT}$ time-space
lower bounds, we show that there are problems verifiable in $O(n)$ time with
quantum Merlin-Arthur protocols that cannot be solved in $n^c$ time and
$n^{o(1)}$ space simultaneously for $c &lt; \frac{3+\sqrt{3}}{2} \approx 2.366$, a
super-quadratic time lower bound. This result and the prior work on
$\mathsf{SAT}$ can both be viewed as consequences of a more general formula for
time lower bounds against small-space algorithms, whose asymptotics we study in
full.
</p>
<p>We also show lower bounds against randomized algorithms: there are problems
verifiable in $O(n)$ time with (classical) Merlin-Arthur protocols that cannot
be solved in $n^c$ randomized time and $O(\log n)$ space simultaneously for $c
&lt; 1.465$, improving a result of Diehl. For quantum Merlin-Arthur protocols, the
lower bound in this setting can be improved to $c &lt; 1.5$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:39:25Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00292</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00292" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Comb inequalities for typical Euclidean TSP instances</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pegden:Wesley.html">Wesley Pegden</a>, Anish Sevekari <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00292">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We prove that even in average case, the Euclidean Traveling Salesman Problem
exhibits an integrality gap of $(1+\epsilon)$ for $\epsilon&gt;0$ when the
Held-Karp Linear Programming relaxation is augmented by all comb inequalities
of bounded size. This implies that large classes of branch-and-cut algorithms
take exponential time for the Euclidean TSP, even on random inputs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:45:57Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00193</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00193" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Lightweight Encryption for the Low Powered IoT Devices</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/u/Usman:Muhammad.html">Muhammad Usman</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00193">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The internet of things refers to the network of devices connected to the
internet and can communicate with each other. The term things is to refer
non-conventional devices that are usually not connected to the internet. The
network of such devices or things is growing at an enormous rate. The security
and privacy of the data flowing through these things is a major concern. The
devices are low powered and the conventional encryption algorithms are not
suitable to be employed on these devices. In this correspondence a survey of
the contemporary lightweight encryption algorithms suitable for use in the IoT
environment has been presented.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:37:28Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00127</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00127" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Variable-Processor Cup Game</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kuszmaul:William.html">William Kuszmaul</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Westover:Alek.html">Alek Westover</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00127">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The problem of scheduling tasks on $p$ processors so that no task ever gets
too far behind is often described as a game with cups and water. In the
$p$-processor cup game on $n$ cups, there are two players, a filler and an
emptier, that take turns adding and removing water from a set of $n$ cups. In
each turn, the filler adds $p$ units of water to the cups, placing at most $1$
unit of water in each cup, and then the emptier selects $p$ cups to remove up
to $1$ unit of water from. The emptier's goal is to minimize the backlog, which
is the height of the fullest cup.
</p>
<p>The $p$-processor cup game has been studied in many different settings,
dating back to the late 1960's. All of the past work shares one common
assumption: that $p$ is fixed. This paper initiates the study of what happens
when the number of available processors $p$ varies over time, resulting in what
we call the \emph{variable-processor cup game}.
</p>
<p>Remarkably, the optimal bounds for the variable-processor cup game differ
dramatically from its classical counterpart. Whereas the $p$-processor cup has
optimal backlog $\Theta(\log n)$, the variable-processor game has optimal
backlog $\Theta(n)$. Moreover, there is an efficient filling strategy that
yields backlog $\Omega(n^{1 - \epsilon})$ in quasi-polynomial time against any
deterministic emptying strategy.
</p>
<p>We additionally show that straightforward uses of randomization cannot be
used to help the emptier. In particular, for any positive constant $\Delta$,
and any $\Delta$-greedy-like randomized emptying algorithm $\mathcal{A}$, there
is a filling strategy that achieves backlog $\Omega(n^{1 - \epsilon})$ against
$\mathcal{A}$ in quasi-polynomial time.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:40:20Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00086</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00086" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Bridging the Gap Between Tree and Connectivity Augmentation: Unified and Stronger Approaches</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Federica Cecchetto, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Traub:Vera.html">Vera Traub</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zenklusen:Rico.html">Rico Zenklusen</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00086">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the Connectivity Augmentation Problem (CAP), a classical problem
in the area of Survivable Network Design. It is about increasing the
edge-connectivity of a graph by one unit in the cheapest possible way. More
precisely, given a $k$-edge-connected graph $G=(V,E)$ and a set of extra edges,
the task is to find a minimum cardinality subset of extra edges whose addition
to $G$ makes the graph $(k+1)$-edge-connected. If $k$ is odd, the problem is
known to reduce to the Tree Augmentation Problem (TAP) -- i.e., $G$ is a
spanning tree -- for which significant progress has been achieved recently,
leading to approximation factors below $1.5$ (the currently best factor is
$1.458$). However, advances on TAP did not carry over to CAP so far. Indeed,
only very recently, Byrka, Grandoni, and Ameli (STOC 2020) managed to obtain
the first approximation factor below $2$ for CAP by presenting a
$1.91$-approximation algorithm based on a method that is disjoint from recent
advances for TAP.
</p>
<p>We first bridge the gap between TAP and CAP, by presenting techniques that
allow for leveraging insights and methods from TAP to approach CAP. We then
introduce a new way to get approximation factors below $1.5$, based on a new
analysis technique. Through these ingredients, we obtain a
$1.393$-approximation algorithm for CAP, and therefore also TAP. This leads to
the currently best approximation result for both problems in a unified way, by
significantly improving on the above-mentioned $1.91$-approximation for CAP and
also the previously best approximation factor of $1.458$ for TAP by Grandoni,
Kalaitzis, and Zenklusen (STOC 2018). Additionally, a feature we inherit from
recent TAP advances is that our approach can deal with the weighted setting
when the ratio between the largest to smallest cost on extra links is bounded,
in which case we obtain approximation factors below $1.5$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T22:43:01Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00079</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.00079" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Integer Programming and Incidence Treedepth</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606867200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Eiben:Eduard.html">Eduard Eiben</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Ganian:Robert.html">Robert Ganian</a>, Dušan Knop, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Ordyniak:Sebastian.html">Sebastian Ordyniak</a>, Michał Pilipczuk, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wrochna:Marcin.html">Marcin Wrochna</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.00079">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Recently a strong connection has been shown between the tractability of
integer programming (IP) with bounded coefficients on the one side and the
structure of its constraint matrix on the other side. To that end, integer
linear programming is fixed-parameter tractable with respect to the primal (or
dual) treedepth of the Gaifman graph of its constraint matrix and the largest
coefficient (in absolute value). Motivated by this, Kouteck\'y, Levin, and Onn
[ICALP 2018] asked whether it is possible to extend these result to a more
broader class of integer linear programs. More formally, is integer linear
programming fixed-parameter tractable with respect to the incidence treedepth
of its constraint matrix and the largest coefficient (in absolute value)?
</p>
<p>We answer this question in negative. In particular, we prove that deciding
the feasibility of a system in the standard form, ${A\mathbf{x} = \mathbf{b}},
{\mathbf{l} \le \mathbf{x} \le \mathbf{u}}$, is $\mathsf{NP}$-hard even when
the absolute value of any coefficient in $A$ is 1 and the incidence treedepth
of $A$ is 5. Consequently, it is not possible to decide feasibility in
polynomial time even if both the assumed parameters are constant, unless
$\mathsf{P}=\mathsf{NP}$. Moreover, we complement this intractability result by
showing tractability for natural and only slightly more restrictive settings,
namely: (1) treedepth with an additional bound on either the maximum arity of
constraints or the maximum number of occurrences of variables and (2) the
vertex cover number.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-12-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-12-02T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://theorydish.blog/?p=1814</id>
    <link href="https://theorydish.blog/2020/12/01/motwani-postdoc-announced/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Motwani Postdoc Announced</title>
    <summary>After discussing postdoc opportunities with me and the opportunities as part of the Simons Collaboration on the Theory of Algorithmic Fairness, let me conclude with postdoc opportunities with Stanford theory group: The theory group at Stanford invites applications for the Motwani postdoctoral fellowship in theoretical computer science. Information and application instructions below. Applications will be accepted until the positions are filled, but review of applicants will begin after Dec 15. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17685Email: theory.stanford@gmail.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>After discussing <a href="https://theorydish.blog/2020/11/16/hiring-postdocs/">postdoc opportunities with me</a> and the <a href="https://toc4fairnesses.org/postdoc-opportunities/">opportunities as part of the Simons Collaboration on the Theory of Algorithmic Fairness</a>, let me conclude with postdoc opportunities with Stanford theory group:</p>



<p>The theory group at Stanford invites applications for the Motwani postdoctoral fellowship in theoretical computer science. Information and application instructions below. Applications will be accepted until the positions are filled, but review of applicants will begin after Dec 15.</p>



<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17685">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17685</a><br/>Email: theory.stanford@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-01T18:59:01Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-01T18:59:01Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Omer Reingold</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://theorydish.blog</id>
      <logo>https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/cropped-nightdish1.jpg?w=32</logo>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Stanford's CS Theory Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Theory Dish</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:21:19Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/01/motwani-postdoctoral-fellowship-at-stanford-computer-science-apply-by-december-15-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/12/01/motwani-postdoctoral-fellowship-at-stanford-computer-science-apply-by-december-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Motwani Postdoctoral Fellowship at Stanford Computer Science (apply by December 15, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The theory group at Stanford invites applications for the Motwani postdoctoral fellowship in theoretical computer science. Information and application instructions below. Applications will be accepted until the positions are filled, but review of applicants will begin after Dec 15. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17685 Email: theory.stanford@gmail.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The theory group at Stanford invites applications for the Motwani postdoctoral fellowship in theoretical computer science. Information and application instructions below. Applications will be accepted until the positions are filled, but review of applicants will begin after Dec 15.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17685">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17685</a><br/>
Email: theory.stanford@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-12-01T00:48:59Z</updated>
    <published>2020-12-01T00:48:59Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://theorydish.blog/?p=1809</id>
    <link href="https://theorydish.blog/2020/11/30/postdoc-opportunities-in-algorithmic-fairness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc Opportunities in Algorithmic Fairness</title>
    <summary>As promised, more postdoctoral positions now available for 2021 The Simons Collaboration on the Theory of Algorithmic Fairness seek highly qualified candidates (within five years of the award of their PhD) for a postdoctoral research position. Appointments will begin Summer or Fall 2021. This multi-year program will host several postdoctoral researchers working on modeling and theoretical work understanding (a) the sources of discriminatory behavior of algorithms, and (b) how best to mitigate such impacts. Descriptions of the scientific agendas of this research collaboration can be found at https://toc4fairnesses.org/. Fellows will be able to collaborate broadly, including with researchers at partner institutions: Stanford University, Toyota Institute of Technology at Chicago, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Harvard University, UC Berkeley, Cornell University,  Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Weizmann Institute of Science, University of Toronto,  University of Washington, and University of Pennsylvania.  The anticipated term for a fellowship is one or two years – to be decided at the time of appointment, with the possibility of extension based on mutual agreement. In addition to competitive salary and benefits, the fellowship also includes funding for independent travel to workshops, conferences and other universities and research labs. In order to apply, please email a CV, research statement, and have two [...]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://theorydish.blog/2020/11/16/hiring-postdocs/">As promised</a>, more postdoctoral positions now available for 2021</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.simonsfoundation.org/2020/06/18/foundation-announces-simons-collaboration-on-the-theory-of-algorithmic-fairness/">Simons Collaboration on the Theory of Algorithmic Fairness</a> seek highly qualified candidates (within five years of the award of their PhD) for a postdoctoral research position. Appointments will begin Summer or Fall 2021.</p>



<p>This multi-year program will host several postdoctoral researchers working on modeling and theoretical work understanding (a) the sources of discriminatory behavior of algorithms, and (b) how best to mitigate such impacts.</p>



<p>Descriptions of the scientific agendas of this research collaboration can be found at <a href="https://toc4fairnesses.org/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://toc4fairnesses.org/</a>.</p>



<p>Fellows will be able to collaborate broadly, including with researchers at partner institutions: Stanford University, Toyota Institute of Technology at Chicago, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Harvard University, UC Berkeley, Cornell University,  Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Weizmann Institute of Science, University of Toronto,  University of Washington, and University of Pennsylvania.</p>



<p> The anticipated term for a fellowship is one or two years – to be decided at the time of appointment, with the possibility of extension based on mutual agreement. In addition to competitive salary and benefits, the fellowship also includes funding for independent travel to workshops, conferences and other universities and research labs.</p>



<p>In order to apply, please email a CV, research statement, and have two reference letters sent to <a href="mailto:jamiemmt@cs.washington.edu" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">jamiemmt@cs.washington.edu</a>. Applications and reference letters are due Dec. 31, 2020, though we will consider applications which arrive after that date. Decisions will be made in February.</p>



<p>Jamie Morgenstern, chair of the postdoctoral search committee<br/>Simons Collaboration on the Foundations of Fairness in Machine Learning</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-30T21:38:08Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-30T21:38:08Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Omer Reingold</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://theorydish.blog</id>
      <logo>https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/cropped-nightdish1.jpg?w=32</logo>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Stanford's CS Theory Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Theory Dish</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:21:19Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/30/faculty-at-university-of-california-santa-cruz-apply-by-january-12-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/30/faculty-at-university-of-california-santa-cruz-apply-by-january-12-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty at University of California, Santa Cruz (apply by January 12, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Computer Science &amp; Engineering department at UC Santa Cruz is recruiting for six junior faculty positions, two in theoretical computer science, two in applied machine learning, and two in experimental systems. (The TCS position URL is given below. For the others, look at the open recruitments in Computer Science and Engineering.) Website: https://recruit.ucsc.edu/JPF00962 Email: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Computer Science &amp; Engineering department at UC Santa Cruz is recruiting for six junior faculty positions, two in theoretical computer science, two in applied machine learning, and two in experimental systems.<br/>
(The TCS position URL is given below. For the others, look at the open recruitments in Computer Science and Engineering.)</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://recruit.ucsc.edu/JPF00962">https://recruit.ucsc.edu/JPF00962</a><br/>
Email: C. Seshadhri</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-30T21:15:21Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-30T21:15:21Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/30/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/30/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>An amusing if minor repeated typo in the literature: “appiled superconductivity (\(\mathbb{M}\)). I think its 177 Google Scholar hits are the fault of IEEE, which spells Trans. on Applied Superconductivity correctly on its site but misspells it repeatedly in the doi database. So if you get your citations from doi metadata, you will get this error. You can see the metadata for an example by curl -LH "Accept: application/x-bibtex" https://doi.org/10.1109/TASC.2005.849553.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=%22Appiled+Superconductivity%22">An amusing if minor repeated typo in the literature: “appiled superconductivity</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105224219465552642">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). I think its 177 Google Scholar hits are the fault of IEEE, which spells <em>Trans. on Applied Superconductivity</em> correctly on its site but misspells it repeatedly in the doi database. So if you get your citations from doi metadata, you will get this error. You can see the metadata for an example by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">curl -LH "Accept: application/x-bibtex" https://doi.org/10.1109/TASC.2005.849553</code>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://post.lurk.org/@crickxson/105199692913412250">A map of the percentages of female researchers in Europe</a>. The numbers are highest in the Baltics and Balkans; the discussion thread suggests that there’s a negative correlation with pay.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25149206">YouTube no longer an acceptable platform for course lecture or academic talk content</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105238898515120908">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Unless, of course, you and your university are comfortable with your students or other audience members being subject to advertisements that interrupt the lectures and are beyond your control both in their placement and content.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/geometry-reveals-how-the-world-is-assembled-from-cubes-20201119/">Scientists uncover the universal geometry of geology</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105241748181882434">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). This is all a bit mystic and breathless and woo, but what <em>Quanta</em> really seems to mean to is that if you subdivide space by randomly recursively splitting by planes (sort of like a 3d <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilbert_tessellation">Gilbert tessellation</a>) then the average number of sides per bottom-level polyhedron is six.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://cameroncounts.wordpress.com/2020/11/19/a-paradox-and-where-it-led/">A paradox, and where it led</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105249285864846993">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Peter Cameron looks at the inclusion graphs of countable models of not-well-founded set theories. The well-founded ones are all the Rado graph, but without foundation the results are more varied.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://theconversation.com/curved-origami-offers-a-creative-route-to-making-robots-and-other-mechanical-devices-150253">Curved origami robot grippers with tunable stiffness</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105260956314627650">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://blog.archive.org/2020/11/23/foss-wins-again-free-and-open-source-communities-comes-through-on-19th-century-newspapers-and-books-and-periodicals/">Archive.org improves accuracy of OCR and compression of PDF on its huge collection of old scanned printed documents by switching to open-source software</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105264347147907544">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://hackers.town/@_cr0_tab/105165210380388504">Four common mathematical means of two quantities in a single compass-and-straightedge construction</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://cstaecker.fairfield.edu/~cstaecker/machines/graphsheets.html">More different kinds of graph paper than you might have even thought possible</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105275252021160077">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://renato.athaydes.com/posts/comparing-jvm-alternatives-to-js.html">Comparison of six ways to get your old Java applets running again on the modern web</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105284817164400009">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19714924">via</a>). I have a couple of old defunct ones that I’m tempted to try this on…</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@jsiehler/105288859971030412">New names for special types of hexagon: “squashogon”, “boltogon”, “extremely irregular hexagon”, and “treeah star”</a>. Boltogons are the zigzag 180-degree symmetric ones.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Wikipedia_Signpost/2020-11-29/Essay">Some tips for avoiding sexist language when writing about women</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105298265490259050">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). This is from 2015, when singular “they” was more controversial, and mostly aimed at Wikipedia editing, but it was recently reprinted in the Wikipedia <em>Signpost</em>, and I think it is still topical more generally.)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/202011/rnoti-p1780.pdf">The place of blogs in the modern math world, Katherine Thompson, <em>Notices of the AMS</em></a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105301116392488191">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). “Clearly, mathematicians are using blogs. … And yet despite all of the work that goes into blogs, the mathematical community has no idea what to make of them—even at the most basic level like citation.”</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-30T18:15:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-30T18:15:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-12-01T02:42:52Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/178</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/178" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-178 |  Reciprocal Inputs in Arithmetic and Tropical Circuits | 

	Stasys Jukna, 

	Hannes Seiwert, 

	Igor Sergeev</title>
    <summary>It is known that the size of monotone arithmetic $(+,\ast)$ circuits can be  exponentially decreased by allowing just one division  "at the very end," at the output gate. A natural question is: can the size of $(+,\ast)$ circuits be substantially  reduced if we allow divisions "at the very beginning," that is, if besides  nonnegative real constants and variables $x_1,\ldots,x_n$, the circuits can also use their reciprocals $1/x_1,\ldots,1/x_n$ as inputs. We answer this question in the negative: the gain in circuit size is  then always at most quadratic.


Over tropical $(\min,+)$ and $(\max,+)$ semirings, division turns into subtraction; so, reciprocal inputs are then $-x_1,\ldots,-x_n$.  We give the same negative answer also for tropical circuits. The question of whether reciprocal inputs can substantially speed up tropical $(\min,+,\max)$ circuits, using both $\min$ and $\max$ gates, remains open.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-30T17:48:06Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-30T17:48:06Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/30/tenure-track-assistant-professors-at-aalto-university-apply-by-january-10-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/30/tenure-track-assistant-professors-at-aalto-university-apply-by-january-10-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure Track Assistant Professors at Aalto University (apply by January 10, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at Aalto University invites applications for tenure-track positions at the Assistant Professor level. We are a diverse community welcoming applications in ALL AREAS of Computer Science. Our CS Theory group (https://research.cs.aalto.fi/theory/) has e.g. received the best paper awards in FOCS 2019 and ICALP 2017, as well as ERC starting grants […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at Aalto University invites applications for tenure-track positions at the Assistant Professor level. We are a diverse community welcoming applications in ALL AREAS of Computer Science.</p>
<p>Our CS Theory group (<a href="https://research.cs.aalto.fi/theory/">https://research.cs.aalto.fi/theory/</a>) has e.g. received the best paper awards in FOCS 2019 and ICALP 2017, as well as ERC starting grants in 2014 and 2017.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.aalto.fi/en/open-positions/tenure-track-assistant-professors-in-computer-science">https://www.aalto.fi/en/open-positions/tenure-track-assistant-professors-in-computer-science</a><br/>
Email: laura.kuusisto-noponen@aalto.fi</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-30T15:42:33Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-30T15:42:33Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/30/research-associate-postdoc-at-university-of-edinburgh-apply-by-january-6-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/30/research-associate-postdoc-at-university-of-edinburgh-apply-by-january-6-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Research Associate (Postdoc) at University of Edinburgh (apply by January 6, 2021)</title>
    <summary>Applications are invited for research associate positions in Algorithms and Complexity, funded by the European Research Council (ERC) starting grant “New Approaches to Counting and Sampling” (NACS), led by Dr. Heng Guo in the School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh. Website: https://elxw.fa.em3.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_1001/job/123/ Email: hguo@inf.ed.ac.uk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Applications are invited for research associate positions in Algorithms and Complexity, funded by the European Research Council (ERC) starting grant “New Approaches to Counting and Sampling” (NACS), led by Dr. Heng Guo in the School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://elxw.fa.em3.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_1001/job/123/">https://elxw.fa.em3.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_1001/job/123/</a><br/>
Email: hguo@inf.ed.ac.uk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-30T10:30:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-30T10:30:00Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/30/postdoc-at-technion-israel-institute-of-technology-apply-by-march-1-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/30/postdoc-at-technion-israel-institute-of-technology-apply-by-march-1-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at Technion Israel Institute of Technology (apply by March 1, 2021)</title>
    <summary>Looking for excellent post graduate researchers for a yearlong postdoc position at the Computer Science Department at Technion. Main research theme is intersection of theoretical computer science with learning, information and data. Website: https://nailon.net.technion.ac.il/openings/ Email: mayasidis@cs.technion.ac.il</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Looking for excellent post graduate researchers for a yearlong postdoc position at the Computer Science Department at Technion. Main research theme is intersection of theoretical computer science with learning, information and data.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://nailon.net.technion.ac.il/openings/">https://nailon.net.technion.ac.il/openings/</a><br/>
Email: mayasidis@cs.technion.ac.il</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-30T07:43:39Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-30T07:43:39Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-1036999202735486243</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/1036999202735486243/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/james-randi-magicians-author-skeptic.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1036999202735486243" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1036999202735486243" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/james-randi-magicians-author-skeptic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>James Randi, Magicians-Author-Skeptic, passed away at the age of 92</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><br/></p><p>James The Amazing Randi died on October 20, 2020, at the age of 92. He is survived by</p><p>his husband Jose Alvarez.  His Wikipedia page is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Randi">here</a></p><div> </div><div>A few Randi Points:</div><div><br/></div><div><div><br/></div><div>0) Wikipedia lists his careers as Magician, Author, Skeptic. I didn't know that skeptic was a career.</div><div><br/></div><div>1) Randi debunked many paranormal claims, though he did not like the term <i>debunke</i>r. He preferred <i>investigator</i>.</div><div><br/></div><div>2) Martin Gardner and James Randi founded the</div><div><br/></div><div><i>Committee for Scientific Investigation of Claims of the Paranormal.</i></div><div><br/></div><div>which publishes</div><div><br/></div><div><i>The Skeptical Inquirer</i>: see <a href="https://skepticalinquirer.org/?gclid=Cj0KCQjwuL_8BRCXARIsAGiC51AlnsnROpbKH-O1K-3WoumIXHGLAACCVDxByb2lFy0rkKunUHblUOAaAmUmEALw_wcB">here</a>  </div></div><div><br/></div><div><div><br/></div><div>3) The internet is both a place where unchecked claims of paranormal activity (and more dangerous lies) can grow faster than in an earlier time, but also a place where magazines like The Skeptical Inquirer, and fact-checking websites, can help check the unchecked claims. What is winning? I leave that as an exercise for the reader. </div><div><br/></div><div>4) I suspect most (all?) people reading this blog do not believe in astrology, UFO's, ESP, or other crank theories. Hence I was surprised to read that Alan Turing thought the evidence for  ESP was <i>overwhelming. </i>This was mentioned in passing in his paper on The Turing Test (called there <i>The</i> <i>Imitation Game</i>) as something the Turing Test will have to account for. I've tried to find out why he believed this, without success. Some websites mentioned that belief in the paranormal was more... normal in those days. One suggested that after the counter-intuitive theories of quantum mechanics and relatively were out there, other counter-intuitive theories took hold, like ESP.  Even so, what was the evidence he was referring to?</div><div><br/></div><div>5) Claims that<i>  I was abducted by a UFO</i> or <i>I saw a UFO</i> have decreased since people now have cell phones so ALWAYS have a way to take pictures. Also rumors like (I had heard this one)</div><div><br/></div><div><i>There is an alternative ending to the movie BLAH which made is way to a few DVDs by mistake.</i></div><div><br/></div><div>are no longer made since IF true you could EASILY produce evidence of such (post to you tube or elsewhere).</div><div><br/></div><div>6) The term<i> skeptic</i> just means someone who doubts something, and is not necc a positive things.</div><div><br/></div><div><i>I am a skeptic when it comes go Global Warming</i></div><div><br/></div><div>being one example.</div></div><div><br/></div><div><div>Randi largely debunked things that were obviously false and not-political. (That the very existence of Global Warming is political is  appalling. At some future point the question of whether or not we ever got to the moon will be political: Something done by big government that worked is impossible, hence it did not happen. See Scott's Blog on disbelief that we ever went to the moon <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4267">here</a>. And people like Randi will need to debunk the notion that the moon landing was faked.) </div><div><br/></div><div>7) Back to Turing- There is a large diff between believing in ESP and believing in astrology.</div><div><br/></div><div>For ESP Turing mentioned <i>overwhelming evidence. </i> While he was WRONG, he did see the need to HAVE evidence. And note that ESP CAN be tested and found to NOT be true. Also note that it is plausible (though I really doubt it) that some humans somehow have some level of ESP. Astrology has NO redeeming value or hope whatsoever. (I am reminded that in Martin Gardner's book <i>Fads and Fallacies in the name of science </i>he noted that most people would say things like `YES, I liked your debunking of A, but you are wrong about B--- B is for real!')</div><div><br/></div><div>UFO's: I do not believe that aliens have come here and abducted people or left crop circles or anything of the sort. The intelligent question of  <i>is there intelligent life in the universe  </i>is quite another matter.</div><div><br/></div><div>7) When I saw magicians as a kid (1960's) I knew that it was all tricks- though very skillful tricks which were impressive. Sometimes they would indicate that it was <i>real magic </i>but I did not know what they meant. Since then I have learned that in an earlier time it was common that magicians claimed they used  <i>real magic</i>.  I still don't quite know what that means, which is just as well since it does not exist.</div><div><br/></div><div>8) Randi has been sued by people whose tricks he has debunked. Randi seems to have always won.  I say <i>seems to </i> since legal cases are not as clear cut as mathematics.  I also looked up Uri Geller. He has sued A LOT of people, and not just people who deny his claims. Thinks like using his likeness  without permission  (he may have a point there). Very hard to tell how he is doing on balance.</div><div><br/></div><div>9) According to Wikipedia Randi dropped out of High School. I assume he learned A LOT on his own.</div><div><br/></div><div>(Trivia-- who was the last president who did not have a college degree? I will answer at the end.)</div><div><br/></div><div>10) This seems like a paradox... or something (quoted from Wikipedia):</div></div><div><br/></div><div><div>BEGIN</div><div><br/></div><div>Randi has been accused of actually using <i>psychic powers</i> to perform acts such as spoon bending. According to James Alcock, at a meeting where Randi was duplicating the performances of Uri Geller, a professor from the University at Buffalo shouted out that Randi was a fraud.  Randi said: "<i>Yes, indeed</i>, <i>I'm a trickste</i>r, <i>I'm a cheat, I'm a charlatan, that's what I do for a living. Everything I've done here was by trickery</i>. The professor shouted back:</div><div><br/></div><div><i>That's not what I mean. You're a fraud because you're pretending to do these things through trickery, but you're actually using psychic powers and misleading us by not admitting it.</i></div><div><br/></div><div>A similar event involved Senator Claiborne Pell, a confirmed believer in psychic phenomena.  When Randi personally demonstrated to Pell that he could reveal—by simple trickery—a concealed drawing that had been secretly made by the senator, Pell refused to believe that it was a trick, saying: "<i>I think</i> <i>Randi may be a </i><i>psychic and doesn't realize it</i>." Randi consistently denied having any paranormal powers or abilities.</div><div><br/></div><div>END</div><div><br/></div><div>Reminds me of <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2013/06/fraud-or-not.html">this</a> blog entry where I speculate about someone who codes up a great new classical  factoring algorithm and claims he has a quantum computer, or someone who has a working quantum computer and claims its a great new classical factoring algorithm. </div><div><br/></div><div><br/></div><div>11) The last president who did not have a college degree: Harry Truman.</div></div><div><br/></div><div><br/></div><div><br/></div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-30T04:36:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-30T04:36:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T16:15:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204.post-5616947953323689751</id>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/5616947953323689751/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=5616947953323689751" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/5616947953323689751" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/5616947953323689751" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2020/11/adapt-designing-activity-informed-viral.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>ADAPT:  Designing Activity-Informed Viral Diagnostic Assays</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><span style="font-size: small;">I wanted to give a pointer to a <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.11.28.401877v1" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">new preprint on bioRxiv</a> on developing diagnostic assays for viruses, by (first author) <a href="https://www.haydenmetsky.com/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">Hayden Metsky</a> (and others!) out of the <a href="https://www.sabetilab.org/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">Sabeti Lab</a> at the Broad Institute (that I've been a bit involved with).  Hayden, who somehow is both a computer science PhD and an expert in virology, has devised a novel software pipeline for developing diagnostics that are designed from the start to deal with genomic diversity (a virus evolves to have many somewhat different variants) and the challenge of false matches (you don't want to get false positives from matching some other different virus) -- also known as sensitivity and specificity.  Algorithmically, he uses machine learning to determine scores for possible tests for matches to small pieces of the genome, or probes, and utilizes locality-sensitive hashing, combinatorial optimization algorithms for submodular maximization, and sharding pattern matching across tries as substages in the overall design.  </span></p><div class="gmail_default" style="font-size: small;">I am always excited to see algorithmic ideas being used to solve real-world problems, and this is a deep and difficult example of the "algorithmic lens"  at work.  I am optimistically hopeful that this type of technology will help drive the development of viral diagnostic and monitoring methods forward.     </div><div class="yj6qo"/><div class="gmail_default adL" style="font-size: small;"><br style="background-color: white; color: #222222; font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"/></div><div class="gmail_default adL" style="font-size: small;">Some additional pointers:  <a href="https://github.com/broadinstitute/adapt" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">to code</a>, <a href="https://adapt.sabetilab.org/covid-19/" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">to some array designs for SARS-CoV-2</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/haydenmetsky/status/1333121522127548416" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">Hayden's twitter thread describing the work</a>.  </div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-30T03:25:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-30T03:25:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/02161161032642563814</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204</id>
      <category term="conferences"/>
      <category term="research"/>
      <category term="society"/>
      <category term="algorithms"/>
      <category term="administration"/>
      <category term="teaching"/>
      <category term="Harvard"/>
      <category term="papers"/>
      <category term="graduate students"/>
      <category term="funding"/>
      <category term="talks"/>
      <category term="blogs"/>
      <category term="codes"/>
      <category term="jobs"/>
      <category term="reviews"/>
      <category term="personal"/>
      <category term="travel"/>
      <category term="undergraduate students"/>
      <category term="books"/>
      <category term="open problems"/>
      <category term="PCs"/>
      <category term="consulting"/>
      <category term="randomness"/>
      <category term="CCC"/>
      <category term="blog book project"/>
      <category term="research labs"/>
      <category term="ISIT"/>
      <category term="tenure"/>
      <category term="comments"/>
      <category term="recommendations"/>
      <category term="outreach"/>
      <category term="students"/>
      <author>
        <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06738274256402616703</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">My take on computer science -- <br/> 
algorithms, networking, information theory -- <br/> 
and related items.</div>
      </subtitle>
      <title>My Biased Coin</title>
      <updated>2020-11-30T06:16:22Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/177</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/177" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-177 |  Counting Subgraphs in Degenerate Graphs | 

	Lior Gishboliner, 

	Asaf Shapira, 

	Yevgeny Levanzov</title>
    <summary>We consider the problem of counting the number of copies of a fixed graph $H$ within an input graph $G$. This is one of the most well-studied algorithmic graph problems, with many theoretical and practical applications. We focus on solving this problem when the input $G$ has {\em bounded degeneracy}. This is a rich family of graphs, containing all graphs without a fixed minor (e.g. planar graphs), as well as graphs generated by various random processes (e.g. preferential attachment graphs). We say that $H$ is {\em easy} if there is a linear-time algorithm for counting the number of copies of $H$ in an input $G$ of bounded degeneracy. A seminal result of Chiba and Nishizeki from '85 states that every $H$ on at most 4 vertices is easy. Bera, Pashanasangi, and Seshadhri recently extended this to all $H$ on 5 vertices, and further proved that for every $k &gt; 5$ there is a $k$-vertex $H$ which is not easy. They left open the natural problem of characterizing all easy graphs $H$. 
		
Bressan has recently introduced a framework for counting subgraphs in degenerate graphs, from which one can extract a sufficient condition for a graph $H$ to be  easy. Here we show that this sufficient condition is also necessary, thus fully answering the Bera--Pashanasangi--Seshadhri problem. We further resolve two closely related problems; namely characterizing the graphs that are easy with respect to counting induced copies, and with respect to counting homomorphisms. Our proofs rely on several novel approaches for proving hardness results in the context of subgraph-counting.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-29T16:43:59Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-29T16:43:59Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-11-29-the-lock-commit-paradigm/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-11-29-the-lock-commit-paradigm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Lock-Commit Paradigm</title>
    <summary>In this post, we explore the Lock-Commit paradigm for consensus protocols. This approach is probably the most celebrated and widely used technique for reaching consensus in a safe manner. This approach is one of the key techniques in DLS88 and Lamport’s Paxos. We exemplify this paradigm by showing a single-shot...</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-29T13:02:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-29T13:02:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T21:22:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/27/study-triangular-bottle</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/27/study-triangular-bottle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Study of a triangular bottle</title>
    <summary>We acquired this small blue glass bottle nearly 15 years ago, as a prop for a Harry Potter themed birthday party. For much of the time since then it’s been decorating our bathroom window with several other blue bottles. Like most bottles these days, it’s molded rather than blown, but a little roughly so the welding seams are more visible than they usually are on wine or liquor bottles.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We acquired this small blue glass bottle nearly 15 years ago, as a prop for a Harry Potter themed birthday party. For much of the time since then it’s been decorating our bathroom window with several other blue bottles. Like most bottles these days, it’s molded rather than blown, but a little roughly so the welding seams are more visible than they usually are on wine or liquor bottles.</p>

<div><table style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;">
<tbody><tr style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">
<td style="padding: 10px;"><img alt="Triangular blue glass bottle" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/triangularbottle/1-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="240"/></td>
<td style="padding: 10px;"><img alt="Triangular blue glass bottle" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/triangularbottle/2-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="360"/></td>
</tr><tr style="text-align: center; vertical-align: middle;">
<td style="padding: 10px;"><img alt="Triangular blue glass bottle" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/triangularbottle/3-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="280"/></td>
<td style="padding: 10px;"><img alt="Triangular blue glass bottle" src="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/triangularbottle/4-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;" width="300"/></td>
</tr></tbody></table></div>

<p>As you can see, it has an unusual triangular cross-section. The final image, with a Reuleaux triangle overlaid, shows that the curvature of this cross-section is less than a Reuleaux triangle would have. I don’t think its outline was chosen with any particular mathematics in mind, but only (as so many other curved triangles) to make an interesting shape.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105286711285736529">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-27T18:20:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-27T18:20:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-12-01T02:42:52Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=20494</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/27/recent-progress-on-high-dimensional-turan-type-problems-by-andrey-kupavskii-alexandr-polyanskii-istvan-tomon-and-dmitriy-zakharov-and-by-jason-long-bhargav-narayanan-and-corrine-yap/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Recent progress on high dimensional Turan-Type problems by Andrey Kupavskii, Alexandr Polyanskii, István Tomon, and Dmitriy Zakharov and by Jason Long, Bhargav Narayanan, and Corrine Yap.</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extremal number for surfaces Andrey Kupavskii, Alexandr Polyanskii, István Tomon, Dmitriy Zakharov: The extremal number of surfaces Abstract: In 1973, Brown, Erdős and Sós proved that if is a 3-uniform hypergraph on vertices which contains no triangulation of the sphere, then   … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/27/recent-progress-on-high-dimensional-turan-type-problems-by-andrey-kupavskii-alexandr-polyanskii-istvan-tomon-and-dmitriy-zakharov-and-by-jason-long-bhargav-narayanan-and-corrine-yap/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><h3>The extremal number for surfaces</h3>



<h3>Andrey Kupavskii, Alexandr Polyanskii, István Tomon, Dmitriy Zakharov: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.07191">The extremal number of surfaces</a></h3>



<p/><p><strong>Abstract:</strong> In 1973, Brown, Erdős and Sós proved that if <img alt="\cal H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ccal+H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\cal H"/> is a 3-uniform hypergraph on <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n"/> vertices which contains no triangulation of the sphere, then <img alt="\cal H" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ccal+H&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\cal H"/>  has at most <img alt="O(n^{5/2})" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=O%28n%5E%7B5%2F2%7D%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="O(n^{5/2})"/> edges, and this bound is the best possible up to a constant factor. Resolving a conjecture of Linial, also reiterated by Keevash, Long, Narayanan, and Scott, we show that the same result holds for triangulations of the torus. Furthermore, we extend our result to every closed orientable surface <img alt="\cal S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ccal+S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\cal S"/>.</p> <p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>Remarks:</strong> </span></p> <p><span style="color: #0000ff;">1) When <img alt="\cal S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ccal+S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\cal S"/> is fixed Nati proved that there is a simplicial complex with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n"/> vertices and <img alt="c n^{5/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=c+n%5E%7B5%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="c n^{5/2}"/> 2-faces that does not contain a triangulation of <img alt="\cal S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ccal+S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\cal S"/>. </span></p> <p><span style="color: #0000ff;">2) It is not known if there is an example with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n"/> vertices and <img alt="c n^{5/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=c+n%5E%7B5%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="c n^{5/2}"/> 2-faces which does not contain a triangulation of any orientable closed surface <img alt="\cal S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ccal+S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\cal S"/>. </span></p> <p><span style="color: #0000ff;">We can ask the same question also for pseudomanifolds. What is the number of edges that guarantees a subcomplex with the property that every 1-face is included in precisely two 2-faces.</span></p> <p><span style="color: #0000ff;">3) Nati conjectured that for every 2-dimensional simplicial complex <img alt="S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="S"/> there is a constant <img alt="C_S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=C_S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="C_S"/> such that a 2-dimensional simplicial complex with $n$ vertices and $C_Sn^{5/2}$ 2-faces always contains a homeomorph of <img alt="S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="S"/>. The paper  by Andrey, Alexandr, István, and Dmitriy asserts that proving the exponent 5/2 for the real projective space will imply the same exponent for all nonorientable closed surfaces. </span></p> <p><span style="color: #0000ff;">4) The paper also mentions an unpublished result by Friedgut and Linial that <img alt="n^{8/9}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B8%2F9%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n^{8/9}"/> 2-faces suffice for a torus. <br/></span></p> <p><span style="color: #008000;">5) Here is another problem I am curious about: How many 2-faces guarantee a subcomplex K with <img alt="H_2(K) \ne 0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H_2%28K%29+%5Cne+0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="H_2(K) \ne 0"/> and <img alt="H_1(K)=0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=H_1%28K%29%3D0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="H_1(K)=0"/>?  (You can choose the field of coefficients.)  Without the second requirement the answer is roughly <img alt="n^2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n^2"/>. </span></p> <h2>Universal exponent for homeomorphs.</h2> <h3><strong>Nati’s Problem 2:</strong> Given a <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/>-dimensional-complex <img alt="S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="S"/>, how many facets can a  <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/>-complex on <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n"/> vertices have if it contains no topological copy of <img alt="S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="S"/>? (Topological copy = homeomorphic image)</h3> <p>Jason Long, Bhargav Narayanan, and Corrine Yap:  <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2011.08167">Simplicial homeomorphs and trace-bounded hypergraphs </a></p><p/>


<p><strong>Abstract:</strong> Our first main result is a uniform bound, in every dimension <img alt="k \in \mathbb N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k+%5Cin+%5Cmathbb+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k \in \mathbb N"/>, on the topological Turán numbers of <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/>-dimensional simplicial complexes: for each <img alt="k \in \mathbb N" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k+%5Cin+%5Cmathbb+N&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k \in \mathbb N"/>, there is a <img alt="\lambda_k \ge k^{-2k^2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_k+%5Cge+k%5E%7B-2k%5E2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\lambda_k \ge k^{-2k^2}"/> such that for any <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/>-dimensional simplicial complex <img alt="S" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=S&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="S"/>, every <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/>-complex on <img alt="n \ge n_0(S)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n+%5Cge+n_0%28S%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n \ge n_0(S)"/> vertices with at least <img alt="n^{k+1-\lambda_k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7Bk%2B1-%5Clambda_k%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n^{k+1-\lambda_k}"/>  facets contains a homeomorphic copy of S.</p>
<p>This was previously known only in dimensions one and two, both by highly dimension-specific arguments: the existence of <img alt="\lambda_1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\lambda_1"/> is a result of Mader from 1967, and the existence of <img alt="\lambda_2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\lambda_2"/> was suggested by Linial in 2006 and recently proved by Keevash-Long-Narayanan-Scott.</p>
<p>Jason Long, Bhargav Narayanan, and Corrine Yap deduce this theorem  from a very interesting purely combinatorial result about trace-bounded hypergraphs.</p>
<p>Here is the link to the aforementioned paper Peter Keevash, Jason Long, Bhargav Narayanan, and Alex Scott: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.02657">A universal exponent for homeomorphs</a>. The main theorem asserts that <img alt="\lambda_2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\lambda_2"/> can be taken to be <strong>14/5</strong>.</p>
<p>Let me also mention a 2018 result by  Agelos Georgakopoulos, John Haslegrave, Richard Montgomery, and Bhargav Narayanan  in their 2018 paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.06864">Spanning surfaces in 3-graphs</a> where they prove a topological extension of Dirac’s theorem about Hamiltonian cycles in graphs proposed by Gowers in 2005.</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;">Finally, finding the correct value for <img alt="\lambda_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Clambda_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\lambda_k"/> would be very interesting.</span></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-27T12:12:04Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-27T12:12:04Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <category term="Alexandr Polyanskii"/>
    <category term="Andrey Kupavskii"/>
    <category term="Bhargav Narayanan"/>
    <category term="Corrine Yap"/>
    <category term="Dmitriy Zakharov"/>
    <category term="Istv&#xE1;n Tomon"/>
    <category term="Jason Long"/>
    <category term="Nati Linial"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:20:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=522</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2020/11/27/tcs-talk-wednesday-december-2-yang-liu-stanford-university/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, December 2 — Yang Liu, Stanford University</title>
    <summary>We hope you are all doing well and, in the case of our US audience, are slowly emerging from a comfortable Thanksgiving food-induced stupor! Our last TCS+ talk of the semester will take place this coming Wednesday, December 2nd at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). Yang […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We hope you are all doing well and, in the case of our US audience, are slowly emerging from a comfortable Thanksgiving food-induced stupor! Our last TCS+ talk of the semester will take place this coming Wednesday, December 2nd at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). <strong>Yang Liu</strong> from Stanford University will speak about “<em>Faster Algorithms for Unit Maximum Flow</em>” (abstract below). </p>



<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk/live-seat-reservation">the online form</a>. Due to security concerns, <em>registration is required</em> to attend the interactive talk. As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/">the website</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-quote">Abstract: The maximum flow problem is one of the most well-studied problems in combinatorial optimization, encompassing a broad range of cut, matching, and scheduling problems. Here we present a recent line of work obtaining provably faster algorithms for solving the maximum flow problem using interior point methods. In particular, we show how to solve the maximum flow problem in <img alt="m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="m"/>-edge unit capacity graphs in time almost <img alt="m^{4/3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m%5E%7B4%2F3%7D&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="m^{4/3}"/>, improving over the breakthrough <img alt="m^{10/7}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m%5E%7B10%2F7%7D&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="m^{10/7}"/> time algorithm of Mądry.<br/><br/>This is based on joint work with Aaron Sidford (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.14276">arxiv.org/abs/1910.14276</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.08929">arxiv.org/abs/2003.08929</a>).</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-27T09:37:25Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-27T09:37:25Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2020-12-03T22:21:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
