<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-10-10T05:22:32Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.04134</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.04134" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Importance Sample-based Approximation Algorithm for Cost-aware Targeted Viral Marketing</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570665600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pham:Canh_V=.html">Canh V. Pham</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Duong:Hieu_V=.html">Hieu V. Duong</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Thai:My_T=.html">My T. Thai</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.04134">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Cost-aware Targeted Viral Marketing (CTVM), a generalization of Influence
Maximization (IM), has received a lot of attentions recently due to its
commercial values. Previous approximation algorithms for this problem required
a large number of samples to ensure approximate guarantee. In this paper, we
propose an efficient approximation algorithm which uses fewer samples but
provides the same theoretical guarantees based on generating and using
important samples in its operation. Experiments on real social networks show
that our proposed method outperforms the state-of-the-art algorithm which
provides the same approximation ratio in terms of the number of required
samples and running time.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.04126</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.04126" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Scalable Nearest Neighbor Search for Optimal Transport</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570665600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dong:Yihe.html">Yihe Dong</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Indyk:Piotr.html">Piotr Indyk</a>, Ilya Razenshteyn, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wagner:Tal.html">Tal Wagner</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.04126">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Optimal Transport (a.k.a. Wasserstein) distance is an increasingly
popular similarity measure for rich data domains, such as images or text
documents. This raises the necessity for fast nearest neighbor search with
respect to this distance, a problem that poses a substantial computational
bottleneck for various tasks on massive datasets.
</p>
<p>In this work, we study fast tree-based approximation algorithms for searching
nearest neighbors w.r.t. the Wasserstein-1 distance. A standard tree-based
technique, known as Quadtree, has been previously shown to obtain good results.
We introduce a variant of this algorithm, called Flowtree, and formally prove
it achieves asymptotically better accuracy. Our extensive experiments, on
real-world text and image datasets, show that Flowtree improves over various
baselines and existing methods in either running time or accuracy. In
particular, its quality of approximation is in line with previous high-accuracy
methods, while its running time is much faster.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-10T01:29:04Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03950</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03950" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Impacts of Dimensionality, Diffusion, and Directedness on Intrinsic Universality in the abstract Tile Assembly Model</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570665600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hader:Daniel.html">Daniel Hader</a>, Aaron Koch, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Patitz:Matthew_J=.html">Matthew J. Patitz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sharp:Michael.html">Michael Sharp</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03950">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a series of results related to mathematical models of
self-assembling tiles and the impacts that three diverse properties have on
their dynamics. We expand upon a series of prior results which showed that (1)
the abstract Tile Assembly Model (aTAM) is intrinsically universal (IU) [FOCS
2012], and (2) the class of directed aTAM systems is not IU [FOCS 2016]. IU for
a model (or class of systems within a model) means that there is a universal
tile set which can be used to simulate an arbitrary system within that model
(or class). Furthermore, the simulation must not only produce the same
resultant structures, it must also maintain the full dynamics of the systems
being simulated modulo only a scale factor. While the FOCS 2012 result showed
the standard, two-dimensional (2D) aTAM is IU, here we show this is also the
case for the 3D version. Conversely, the FOCS 2016 result showed the class of
aTAM systems which are directed (a.k.a. deterministic, or confluent) is not IU,
implying that nondeterminism is fundamentally required for such simulations.
Here, however, we show that in 3D the class of directed aTAM systems is
actually IU, i.e. there is a universal directed simulator for them. We then
consider the influence of more rigid notions of dimensionality. Namely, we
introduce the Planar aTAM, where tiles are not only restricted to binding in
the plane, but also to traveling in the plane, and prove that the Planar aTAM
is not IU, and that the class of directed systems within the Planar aTAM also
is not IU. Finally, analogous to the Planar aTAM, we introduce the Spatial
aTAM, its 3D counterpart, and prove that it is IU.
</p>
<p>To prove our positive results we have not only designed, but also implemented
what we believe to be the first IU tile set ever implemented and simulated in
any tile assembly model. We've made it and a simulator which can demonstrate it
freely available.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03935</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03935" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On geodesic triangles with right angles in a dually flat space</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570665600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nielsen:Frank.html">Frank Nielsen</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03935">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The dualistic structure of statistical manifolds yields eight types of
geodesic triangles defining overall eighteen interior angles. In general, the
interior angles of geodesic triangles can sum up to $\pi$ like in
Euclidean/Mahalanobis geometry, or exhibit either angle excesses or angle
defects. In this paper, we initiate the study of geodesic triangles in dually
flat spaces where a generalized Pythagorean theorem holds. First, we show when
it is possible how to construct geodesic triangles which either have one, two,
or three interior right angles. Then we report a construction of triples of
points for which the dual Pythagorean theorems hold simultaneously at a point,
yielding two dual pairs of dual geodesic triangles with doubly right angles.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03798</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03798" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Prophets, Secretaries, and Maximizing the Probability of Choosing the Best</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570665600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Esfandiari:Hossein.html">Hossein Esfandiari</a>, MohammadTaghi HajiAghayi, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lucier:Brendan.html">Brendan Lucier</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mitzenmacher:Michael.html">Michael Mitzenmacher</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03798">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Suppose a customer is faced with a sequence of fluctuating prices, such as
for airfare or a product sold by a large online retailer. Given distributional
information about what price they might face each day, how should they choose
when to purchase in order to maximize the likelihood of getting the best price
in retrospect? This is related to the classical secretary problem, but with
values drawn from known distributions. In their pioneering work, Gilbert and
Mosteller [\textit{J. Amer. Statist. Assoc. 1966}] showed that when the values
are drawn i.i.d., there is a thresholding algorithm that selects the best value
with probability approximately $0.5801$. However, the more general problem with
non-identical distributions has remained unsolved.
</p>
<p>In this paper we provide an algorithm for the case of non-identical
distributions that selects the maximum element with probability $1/e$, and we
show that this is tight. We further show that if the observations arrive in a
random order, this barrier of $1/e$ can be broken using a static threshold
algorithm, and we show that our success probability is the best possible for
any single-threshold algorithm under random observation order. Moreover, we
prove that one can achieve a strictly better success probability using more
general multi-threshold algorithms, unlike the non-random-order case. Along the
way, we show that the best achievable success probability for the random-order
case matches that of the i.i.d.\ case, which is approximately $0.5801$, under a
"no-superstars" condition that no single distribution is very likely ex ante to
generate the maximum value. We also extend our results to the problem of
selecting one of the $k$ best values.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-10T01:24:08Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03651</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03651" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Improved Bounds for Two Query Adaptive Bitprobe Schemes Storing Five Elements</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570665600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Baig:Mirza_Galib_Anwarul_Husain.html">Mirza Galib Anwarul Husain Baig</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kesh:Deepanjan.html">Deepanjan Kesh</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03651">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we study two-bitprobe adaptive schemes storing five elements.
For these class of schemes, the best known lower bound is m^{1/2} due to Alon
and Feige [SODA 2009]. Recently, it was proved by Kesh [FSTTCS 2018] that
two-bitprobe adaptive schemes storing three elements will take at least m^{2/3}
space, which also puts a lower bound on schemes storing five elements. In this
work, we have improved the lower bound to m^{3/4}. We also present a scheme for
the same that takes O(m^{5/6}) space. This improves upon the
O(m^{18/19})-scheme due to Garg [Ph.D. Thesis] and the O(m^{10/11})-scheme due
to Baig et al. [WALCOM 2019].
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03645</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03645" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Span-core Decomposition for Temporal Networks: Algorithms and Applications</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570665600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Galimberti:Edoardo.html">Edoardo Galimberti</a>, Martino Ciaperoni, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Barrat:Alain.html">Alain Barrat</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bonchi:Francesco.html">Francesco Bonchi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cattuto:Ciro.html">Ciro Cattuto</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gullo:Francesco.html">Francesco Gullo</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03645">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>When analyzing temporal networks, a fundamental task is the identification of
dense structures (i.e., groups of vertices that exhibit a large number of
links), together with their temporal span (i.e., the period of time for which
the high density holds). In this paper we tackle this task by introducing a
notion of temporal core decomposition where each core is associated with two
quantities, its coreness, which quantifies how densely it is connected, and its
span, which is a temporal interval: we call such cores span-cores. For a
temporal network defined on a discrete temporal domain $T$, the total number of
time intervals included in $T$ is quadratic in $|T|$, so that the total number
of span-cores is potentially quadratic in $|T|$ as well. Our first main
contribution is an algorithm that, by exploiting containment properties among
span-cores, computes all the span-cores efficiently. Then, we focus on the
problem of finding only the maximal span-cores, i.e., span-cores that are not
dominated by any other span-core by both their coreness property and their
span. We devise a very efficient algorithm that exploits theoretical findings
on the maximality condition to directly extract the maximal ones without
computing all span-cores. Finally, we introduce the problem of temporal
community search, where a set of query vertices is given as input, and the goal
is to find a set of densely-connected subgraphs containing the query vertices
and covering the whole underlying temporal domain $T$. We derive a connection
between this problem and the problem of finding (maximal) span-cores. Based on
this connection, we show how temporal community search can be solved in
polynomial-time via dynamic programming, and how the maximal span-cores can be
profitably exploited to significantly speed-up the basic algorithm.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-10T01:20:32Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03640</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03640" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>MAMS-A*: Multi-Agent Multi-Scale A*</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570665600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Jaein Lim, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tsiotras:Panagiotis.html">Panagiotis Tsiotras</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03640">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a multi-scale forward search algorithm for distributed agents to
solve single-query shortest path planning problems. Each agent first builds a
representation of its own search space of the common environment as a
multi-resolution graph, it communicates with the other agents the result of its
local search, and it uses received information from other agents to refine its
own graph and update the local inconsistency conditions. As a result, all
agents attain a common subgraph that includes a provably optimal path in the
most informative graph available among all agents, if one exists, without
necessarily communicating the entire graph. We prove the completeness and
optimality of the proposed algorithm, and present numerical results supporting
the advantages of the proposed approach.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03578</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03578" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Stack Sorting with Increasing and Decreasing Stacks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570665600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cerbai:Giulio.html">Giulio Cerbai</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cioni:Lapo.html">Lapo Cioni</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Ferrari:Luca.html">Luca Ferrari</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03578">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We introduce a sorting machine consisting of $k+1$ stacks in series: the
first $k$ stacks can only contain elements in decreasing order from top to
bottom, while the last one has the opposite restriction. This device
generalizes \cite{SM}, which studies the case $k=1$. Here we show that, for
$k=2$, the set of sortable permutations is a class with infinite basis, by
explicitly finding an antichain of minimal nonsortable permutations. This
construction can easily be adapted to each $k \ge 3$. Next we describe an
optimal sorting algorithm, again for the case $k=2$. We then analyze two types
of left-greedy sorting procedures, obtaining complete results in one case and
only some partial results in the other one. We close the paper by discussing a
few open questions.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03553</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03553" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Differentially private anonymized histograms</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570579200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Suresh:Ananda_Theertha.html">Ananda Theertha Suresh</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03553">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>For a dataset of label-count pairs, an anonymized histogram is the multiset
of counts. Anonymized histograms appear in various potentially sensitive
contexts such as password-frequency lists, degree distribution in social
networks, and estimation of symmetric properties of discrete distributions.
Motivated by these applications, we propose the first differentially private
mechanism to release anonymized histograms that achieves near-optimal privacy
utility trade-off both in terms of number of items and the privacy parameter.
Further, if the underlying histogram is given in a compact format, the proposed
algorithm runs in time sub-linear in the number of items. For anonymized
histograms generated from unknown discrete distributions, we show that the
released histogram can be directly used for estimating symmetric properties of
the underlying distribution.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03438</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03438" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fast Diameter Computation within Split Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570579200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Ducoffe:Guillaume.html">Guillaume Ducoffe</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Habib:Michel.html">Michel Habib</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Viennot:Laurent.html">Laurent Viennot</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03438">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>When can we compute the diameter of a graph in quasi linear time? We address
this question for the class of split graphs, that we observe to be the hardest
instances for deciding whether the diameter is at most two. We stress that
although the diameter of a non-complete split graph can only be either 2 or 3,
under the Strong Exponential-Time Hypothesis (SETH) we cannot compute the
diameter of a split graph in less than quadratic time. Therefore it is worth to
study the complexity of diameter computation on subclasses of split graphs, in
order to better understand the complexity border. Specifically, we consider the
split graphs with bounded clique-interval number and their complements, with
the former being a natural variation of the concept of interval number for
split graphs that we introduce in this paper. We first discuss the relations
between the clique-interval number and other graph invariants such as the
classic interval number of graphs, the treewidth, the VC-dimension and the
stabbing number of a related hypergraph. Then, in part based on these above
relations, we almost completely settle the complexity of diameter computation
on these subclasses of split graphs: $\bullet$ For the k-clique-interval split
graphs, we can compute their diameter in truly subquadratic time if k = O(1),
and even in quasi linear time if k = o(log n) and in addition a corresponding
ordering is given. However, under SETH this cannot be done in truly
subquadratic time for any k = $\omega$(log n). $\bullet$ For the complements of
k-clique-interval split graphs, we can compute their diameter in truly
subquadratic time if k = O(1), and even in time O(km) if a corresponding
ordering is given. Again this latter result is optimal under SETH up to
polylogarithmic factors. Our findings raise the question whether a k-clique
interval ordering can always be computed in quasi linear time. We prove that it
is the case for k = 1 and for some subclasses such as bounded-treewidth split
graphs, threshold graphs and comparability split graphs. Finally, we prove that
some important subclasses of split graphs-including the ones mentioned
above-have a bounded clique-interval number.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03409</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03409" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Length-Bounded Cuts: Proper Interval Graphs and Structural Parameters</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570579200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bentert:Matthias.html">Matthias Bentert</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Heeger:Klaus.html">Klaus Heeger</a>, Dušan Knop <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03409">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the presented paper we study the Length-Bounded Cut problem for special
graph classes as well as from a parameterized-complexity viewpoint. Here, we
are given a graph $G$, two vertices $s$ and $t$, and positive integers $\beta$
and $\lambda$. The task is to find a set of edges $F$ of size at most $\beta$
such that every $s$-$t$-path of length at most $\lambda$ in $G$ contains some
edge in $F$.
</p>
<p>Bazgan et al. conjectured that Length-Bounded Cut admits a polynomial-time
algorithm if the input graph $G$ is a~proper interval graph. We confirm this
conjecture by showing a dynamic-programming based polynomial-time algorithm. We
strengthen the W[1]-hardness result of Dvo\v{r}\'ak and Knop. Our reduction is
shorter, seems simpler to describe, and the target of the reduction has
stronger structural properties. Consequently, we give W[1]-hardness for the
combined parameter pathwidth and maximum degree of the input graph. Finally, we
prove that Length-Bounded Cut is W[1]-hard for the feedback vertex number. Both
our hardness results complement known XP algorithms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03332</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03332" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Upper and Lower Bounds for Fully Retroactive Graph Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570579200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Henzinger:Monika.html">Monika Henzinger</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wu:Xiaowei.html">Xiaowei Wu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03332">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Classic dynamic data structure problems maintain a data structure subject to
a sequence S of updates and they answer queries using the latest version of the
data structure, i.e., the data structure after processing the whole sequence.
To handle operations that change the sequence S of updates, Demaine et al.
(TALG 2007) introduced retroactive data structures. A retroactive operation
modifies the update sequence S in a given position t, called time, and either
creates or cancels an update in S at time t. A partially retroactive data
structure restricts queries to be executed exclusively in the latest version of
the data structure. A fully retroactive data structure supports queries at any
time t: a query at time t is answered using only the updates of S up to time t.
If the sequence S only consists of insertions, the resulting data structure is
an incremental retroactive data structure. While efficient retroactive data
structures have been proposed for classic data structures, e.g., stack,
priority queue and binary search tree, the retroactive version of graph
problems are rarely studied.
</p>
<p>In this paper we study retroactive graph problems including connectivity,
minimum spanning forest (MSF), maximum degree, etc. We provide fully
retroactive data structures for maintaining the maximum degree, connectivity
and MSF in $\tilde{O}(n)$ time per operation. We also give an algorithm for the
incremental fully retroactive connectivity with $\tilde{O}(1)$ time per
operation. We compliment our algorithms with almost tight hardness results. We
show that under the OMv conjecture (proposed by Henzinger et al. (STOC 2015)),
there does not exist fully retroactive data structures maintaining connectivity
or MSF, or incremental fully retroactive data structure maintaining the maximum
degree with $O(n^{1-\epsilon})$ time per operation, for any constant $\epsilon
&gt; 0$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-09T23:25:58Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03287</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03287" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Understanding Zadimoghaddam's Edge-weighted Online Matching Algorithm: Weighted Case</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570579200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Huang:Zhiyi.html">Zhiyi Huang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03287">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This article presents a simplification of Zadimoghaddam's algorithm for the
edge-weighted online bipartite matching problem, under the online primal dual
framework. In doing so, we obtain an improved competitive ratio of $0.514$. We
first combine the online correlated selection (OCS), an ingredient distilled
from Zadimoghaddam (2017) by Huang and Tao (2019), and an interpretation of the
edge-weighted online bipartite matching problem by Devanur et al. (2016) which
we will refer to as the complementary cumulative distribution function (CCDF)
viewpoint, to derive an online primal dual algorithm that is
$0.505$-competitive. Then, we design an improved OCS which gives the $0.514$
ratio.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03249</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03249" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Parallel Online Algorithms for the Bin Packing Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570579200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fekete:S=aacute=ndor_P=.html">Sándor P. Fekete</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grosse=Holz:Jonas.html">Jonas Grosse-Holz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Keldenich:Phillip.html">Phillip Keldenich</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schmidt:Arne.html">Arne Schmidt</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03249">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study \emph{parallel} online algorithms:
</p>
<p>For some fixed integer $k$, a collective of $k$ parallel processes that
perform online decisions on the same sequence of events forms a $k$-\emph{copy
algorithm}.
</p>
<p>For any given time and input sequence, the overall performance is determined
by the best of the $k$ individual total results.
</p>
<p>Problems of this type have been considered for online makespan minimization;
they are also related to optimization with \emph{advice} on future events,
i.e., a number of bits available in advance.
</p>
<p>We develop \textsc{Predictive Harmonic}$_3$ (PH3), a relatively simple family
of $k$-copy algorithms for the online Bin Packing Problem, whose joint
competitive factor converges to 1.5 for increasing $k$. In particular, we show
that $k=6$ suffices to guarantee a factor of $1.5714$ for PH3, which is better
than $1.57829$, the performance of the best known 1-copy algorithm
\textsc{Advanced Harmonic}, while $k=11$ suffices to achieve a factor of
$1.5406$, beating the known lower bound of $1.54278$ for a single online
algorithm.
</p>
<p>In the context of online optimization with advice, our approach implies that
4 bits suffice to achieve a factor better than this bound of $1.54278$, which
is considerably less than the previous bound of 15 bits.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-09T23:21:02Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03241</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1910.03241" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Fast Exact Algorithm for Airplane Refueling Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1570579200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Jianshu.html">Jianshu Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hu:Xiaoyin.html">Xiaoyin Hu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Luo:Junjie.html">Junjie Luo</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cui:Jinchuan.html">Jinchuan Cui</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.03241">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the airplane refueling problem, where we have a fleet of
airplanes that can refuel each other. Each airplane is characterized by
specific fuel tank volume and fuel consumption rate, and the goal is to find a
drop out order of airplanes that last airplane in the air can reach as far as
possible. This problem is equivalent to the scheduling problem $1||\sum w_j (-
\frac{1}{C_j})$. Based on the dominance properties among jobs, we reveal some
structural properties of the problem and propose a recursive algorithm to solve
the problem exactly. The running time of our algorithm is directly related to
the number of schedules that do not violate the dominance properties. An
experimental study shows our algorithm outperforms state of the art exact
algorithms and is efficient on larger instances.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2019-10-09T23:20:35Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2019-10-09T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/08/tenure-track-tenured-professors-in-theoretical-computer-science-at-purdue-university-apply-by-december-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/08/tenure-track-tenured-professors-in-theoretical-computer-science-at-purdue-university-apply-by-december-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TENURE-TRACK/TENURED PROFESSORS IN THEORETICAL COMPUTER SCIENCE at Purdue University (apply by December 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science in the College of Science at Purdue University invites applications for two or more tenure-track or tenured positions in theoretical computer science. These appointments will be at the level of Assistant or Associate Professor. Review of applications and interviews will begin in November 2019, and will continue until positions are […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science in the College of Science at Purdue University invites applications for two or more tenure-track or tenured positions in theoretical computer science. These appointments will be at the level of Assistant or Associate Professor. Review of applications and interviews will begin in November 2019, and will continue until positions are filled.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.cs.purdue.edu/hiring/faculty2019-theory.html">https://www.cs.purdue.edu/hiring/faculty2019-theory.html</a><br/>
Email: TA-search@cs.purdue.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-08T21:09:56Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-08T21:09:56Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:21:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/139</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/139" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-139 |  Direct sum testing - the general case | 

	Irit Dinur, 

	Konstantin Golubev</title>
    <summary>A function f:[n_1] x ... x [n_d]--&gt;F  is a direct sum if it is of the form f(a_1,...,a_d) = f_1(a_1) + ... + f_d (a_d)  (mod 2) for some d functions f_i:[n_i]--&gt;F_i for all i=1,...,d. We present a 4-query test which distinguishes between direct sums and functions that are far from them. The test relies on the BLR linearity test (Blum, Luby, Rubinfeld, 1993) and on an agreement test which slightly generalizes the direct product test.

In multiplicative {+1,-1} notation, our result reads as follows. A d-dimensional tensor with {+1,-1} entries is called a tensor product if it is a tensor product of d vectors with {+1,-1} entries, or equivalently, if it is of rank 1. The presented tests can be read as tests for distinguishing between tensor products and tensors that are far from being tensor products.

We also present a different test, which queries the function at most (d+2) times, but is easier to analyze.</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-08T18:27:56Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-08T18:27:56Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:20:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/10/07/drawing-clustered-graphs</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/10/07/drawing-clustered-graphs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Drawing clustered graphs of bounded width</title>
    <summary>In a paper from last year on clustered planarity, with Giordano Da Lozzo, Mike Goodrich, and Sid Gupta, we provided subexponential-time algorithms for arbitrary instances, and fixed-parameter tractable algorithms for instances whose embedded width and number of clusters are both bounded.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2018/03/16/drawing-clustered-graphs.html">a paper from last year</a> on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clustered_planarity">clustered planarity</a>, with Giordano Da Lozzo, Mike Goodrich, and Sid Gupta, we provided subexponential-time algorithms for arbitrary instances, and fixed-parameter tractable algorithms for instances whose embedded width and number of clusters are both bounded.</p>

<p>Now, in my newest preprint, “C-planarity testing of embedded clustered graphs with bounded dual carving-width” (with the same authors, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02057">arXiv:1910.02057</a>), we’ve eliminated the dependence on the number of clusters (using a different width parameter) and found a fixed-parameter tractable algorithm with just a single parameter.</p>

<p>It was just in time: while our paper was in submission, last July, Rado Fulek and Csaba Tóth put up their own preprint, “Atomic embeddability, clustered planarity, and thickenability” (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.13086">arXiv:1907.13086</a>) announcing a solution to the clustered planarity problem in polynomial time without dependence on parameters. I <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102537368093048271">posted about it briefly at the time</a>, and can’t find much else more recent about it, but I assume it’s in submission to somewhere good. So our results may be only of historic value…</p>

<p>Our paper was presented at IPEC 2019 (part of the <a href="http://algo2019.ak.in.tum.de/">ALGO 2019 conference in Munich</a>) last month, and won IPEC best paper award. The late timing of the preprint is because (somewhat unusually for a CS conference) IPEC makes their proceedings versions due after the conference rather than before, so they can take into account feedback from the conference.
The arXiv version is more complete than the proceedings version will be, because of page limits in the proceedings, but we prepared it at the same time.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/102925193159020982">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-07T22:33:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-07T22:33:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T05:51:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3430</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/10/07/videos-from-papafest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Videos from PapaFest</title>
    <summary>Videos of all PapaFest talks and panels are here. Advertisements</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Videos of all PapaFest talks and panels are <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OX2I00QVPDI&amp;list=PLPldBy2vuDR9gp98jsowJQFn6jtpZatU0">here</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-07T21:28:05Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-07T21:28:05Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>timroughgarden</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:20:44Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-1096889632414067693</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/1096889632414067693/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/10/what-comes-first-theory-or-practice-its.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1096889632414067693" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1096889632414067693" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/10/what-comes-first-theory-or-practice-its.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What comes first theory or practice? Its Complicated!</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Having majored in pure math I had the impression that usually the theory comes first and then someone works out something to work in practice. While this is true sometimes it is often NOT true and this will not surprise any of my blog readers.  Even so, I want to tell you about some times it surprised me. This says more about my ignorance than about math or applications or whatnot.<br/>
<br/>
1) Quantum<br/>
<br/>
a) Factoring was proven to be in BQP way before actual quantum computers could do this in reasonable time (we're still waiting).<br/>
<br/>
b) Quantum Crypto- This really is out there. I do not know what came first, the theory or the practice. Or if they were in tandem.<br/>
<br/>
c) (this one is the inspiration for the post)  When I first heard the term <i>Quantum Supremacy</i> I thought it meant the desire for a THEOREM that problem A is in BQP but is provably not in P.  For example, if someone proved factoring is not in P (unlikely this will be proven, and hey- maybe  factoring is in P). Perhaps some contrived problem like those constructed by diagonalization (my spell checker thinks that's not a word. Having worked in computability theory, I think it is. Darn- my spellchecker thinks computability is not word.) Hence when I heard that Google had a paper proving Quantum Supremacy (I do not recall if I actually heard the word  <i>proven) </i>I assumed that there was some <i>theoretical </i>breakthrough. I was surprised and not in the slightest disappointed to find out it involved actual quantum computers.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Question</b>: When the term <i>Quantum Supremacy</i> was first coined, did they mean theoretical, or IRL, or both?<br/>
<br/>
2) Ramsey Theory<br/>
<br/>
a) For Ramsey's Theorem and Van Der waerden's theorem and Rado's theorem and others I could name, first a theorem showed a upper bound on a number, then later computers and perhaps some math got better bounds on that number.<br/>
<br/>
b) Consider the following statement:<br/>
<br/>
For all c there exists P such that for all c-colorings of {1,...,P} there exists x,y,z the same color such that x<sup>2</sup> +y<sup>2</sup> = z<sup>2</sup>.<br/>
<br/>
Ronald Graham conjectured the c=2 case and offered $100 in the 1980's. (I do not know if he had any comment on the general case.)  I assumed that it would be proven with ginormous bounds on the P(c) function, and then perhaps some reasonable bound would be found by clever programming and some math. (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boolean_Pythagorean_triples_problem">here</a> for the Wikipedia Entry about the problem, which also has pointers to other material).<br/>
<br/>
Instead the c=2 case was proven with an exact bound, P(2)=7825, by a computer program, in 2016. The proof is 200 terabytes. So my prediction was incorrect.<br/>
<br/>
As for the result<br/>
<br/>
PRO: We know the result is true for c=2 and we even know the exact bound. Wow! and for Ramsey Theory its unusual to have exact bounds!<br/>
<br/>
CON: It would be good to have a human-readable proof. This is NOT an anti-technology statement. For one thing, a human-readable proof might help us get the result for c=3 and beyond.<br/>
<br/>
3) This item is a cheat in that I knew the empirical results first. However, I will tell you what I am sure I would have thought (and been wrong) had I not know them.<br/>
<br/>
Given k, does the equation<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
x<sup>3</sup> +y<sup>3</sup> +z<sup>3</sup> = k<br/>
<br/>
have a solution in Z? I would have thought that some hard number theory would determine<br/>
for which k it has a solution (with a proof that does not give the actual solutions)  and for then a computer programs would try to find the solutions. Instead (1) some values of k are ruled out by simple mod considerations, and (2) as for the rest, computers have found solutions for some of them. Lipton-Regan (<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/09/30/writing-33-as-a-sum-of-cubes/">here</a>) and Gasarch (<a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/04/x-3-y-3-z-3-33-has-solution-in-z-and.html">here</a>) have blogged about the k=33 case. Lipton-Regan also comment on the more recent k=42 case.<br/>
<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-07T13:56:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-07T13:56:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-10-09T16:57:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/07/culty-positions-at-the-rank-of-associate-and-assistant-professor-in-machine-learning-and-data-science-at-maersk-mc-kinney-moller-institute-faculty-of-engineering-university-of-southern-denmark-appl/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/07/culty-positions-at-the-rank-of-associate-and-assistant-professor-in-machine-learning-and-data-science-at-maersk-mc-kinney-moller-institute-faculty-of-engineering-university-of-southern-denmark-appl/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>culty Positions at the rank of Associate and Assistant Professor in machine learning and data science at Maersk Mc-Kinney Moller Institute, Faculty of Engineering, University of Southern Denmark (apply by November 3, 2019)</title>
    <summary>he Group of Machine Learning and Data Science (part of Embodied Systems for Robotics and Learning) at the Maersk Mc-Kinney Moller Institute, Faculty of Engineering, University of Southern Denmark, invites applications for Faculty positions at the rank of Associate (permanent) and Assistant (3-year period) Professor. Website: https://www.sdu.dk/en/service/ledige_stillinger/1063846 Email: esi@mmmi.sdu.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>he Group of Machine Learning and Data Science (part of Embodied Systems for Robotics and Learning) at the Maersk Mc-Kinney Moller Institute, Faculty of Engineering, University of Southern Denmark, invites applications for Faculty positions at the rank of Associate (permanent) and Assistant (3-year period) Professor.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.sdu.dk/en/service/ledige_stillinger/1063846">https://www.sdu.dk/en/service/ledige_stillinger/1063846</a><br/>
Email: esi@mmmi.sdu.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-07T10:05:47Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-07T10:05:47Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:21:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4361</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4361" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4361#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4361" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Book Review: ‘The AI Does Not Hate You’ by Tom Chivers</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">A couple weeks ago I read The AI Does Not Hate You: Superintelligence, Rationality, and the Race to Save the World, the first-ever book-length examination of the modern rationalist community, by British journalist Tom Chivers. I was planning to review it here, before it got preempted by the news of quantum supremacy (and subsequent news […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A couple weeks ago I read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Rationalists-Artificial-Intelligence-Geeks-World/dp/1474608779/ref=tmm_hrd_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;qid=&amp;sr=">The AI Does Not Hate You: Superintelligence, Rationality, and the Race to Save the World</a>, the first-ever book-length examination of the modern <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Rationalist_movement">rationalist community</a>, by British journalist <a href="https://twitter.com/TomChivers?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor">Tom Chivers</a>.  I was planning to review it here, before it got preempted by the news of <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4317">quantum supremacy</a> (and subsequent news of <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4342">classical non-supremacy</a>).  Now I can get back to rationalists.</p>



<p>Briefly, I think the book is a triumph.  It’s based around in-person conversations with many of the notable figures in and around the rationalist community, in its Bay Area epicenter and beyond (although apparently <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eliezer_Yudkowsky">Eliezer Yudkowsky</a> only agreed to answer technical questions by Skype), together of course with the voluminous material available online.  There’s a good deal about the 1990s origins of the community that I hadn’t previously known.</p>



<p>The title is taken from Eliezer’s aphorism, “The AI does not hate you, nor does it love you, but you are made of atoms which it can use for something else.”  In other words: as soon as anyone succeeds in building a superhuman AI, if we don’t take extreme care that the AI’s values are “aligned” with human ones, the AI might be expected to obliterate humans almost instantly as a byproduct of pursuing whatever it <em>does</em> value, more-or-less as we humans did with woolly mammoths, moas, and now gorillas, rhinos, and thousands of other species.</p>



<p>Much of the book relates Chivers’s personal quest to figure out how seriously he should take this scenario.  Are the rationalists just an unusually nerdy doomsday cult?  Is there some non-negligible chance that they’re actually right about the AI thing?  If so, how much more time do we have—and is there even anything meaningful that can be done today?  Do the dramatic advances in machine learning over the past decade change the outlook?  Should Chivers be worried about his own two children?  How does this risk compare to the more “prosaic” civilizational risks, like climate change or nuclear war?  I suspect that Chivers’s exploration will be most interesting to readers who, like me, regard the answers to <em>none</em> of these questions as obvious.</p>



<p>While it sounds extremely basic, what makes <em>The AI Does Not Hate You</em> so valuable to my mind is that, as far as I know, it’s nearly the only examination of the rationalists ever written by an outsider that tries to assess the ideas on a scale from true to false, rather than from quirky to offensive.  Chivers’s own training in academic philosophy seems to have been crucial here.  He’s not put off by people who act weirdly around him, even needlessly cold or aloof, nor by utilitarian thought experiments involving death or torture or weighing the value of human lives.  He just cares, relentlessly, about the ideas—and about remaining a basically grounded and decent person while engaging them.  Most strikingly, Chivers clearly feels a need—anachronistic though it seems in 2019—actually to <em>understand</em> complicated arguments, be able to repeat them back correctly, before he attacks them.</p>



<p>Indeed, far from failing to understand the rationalists, it occurs to me that the central criticism of Chivers’s book is likely to be just the opposite: he understands the rationalists so well, extends them so much sympathy, and ends up endorsing so many aspects of their worldview, that he must simply <em>be</em> a closet rationalist himself, and therefore can’t write about them with any pretense of journalistic or anthropological detachment.  For my part, I’d say: it’s true that <em>The AI Does Not Hate You</em> is what you get if you treat rationalists as extremely smart (if unusual) people from whom you might learn something of consequence, rather than as monkeys in a zoo.  On the other hand, Chivers does perform the journalist’s task of constantly challenging the rationalists he meets, often with points that (if upheld) would be fatal to their worldview.  One of the rationalists’ best features—and this precisely matches my own experience—is that, far from clamming up or storming off when faced with such challenges (“lo! the visitor is not one of us!”), the rationalists positively relish them.</p>



<p>It occurred to me the other day that we’ll never know how the rationalists’ ideas would’ve developed, had they continued to do so in a cultural background like that of the late 20th century.  As Chivers points out, the rationalists today are effectively caught in the crossfire of a much larger cultural war—between, to their right, the recrudescent know-nothing authoritarians, and to their left, what one could variously describe as woke culture, call-out culture, or sneer culture.  On its face, it might seem laughable to conflate the rationalists with today’s resurgent fascists: many rationalists are driven by their utilitarianism to advocate open borders and massive aid to the Third World; the rationalist community is about as welcoming of alternative genders and sexualities as it’s humanly possible to be; and leading rationalists like Scott Alexander and Eliezer Yudkowsky strongly condemned Trump for the obvious reasons. </p>



<p>Chivers, however, explains how the problem started.  On rationalist Internet forums, many misogynists and white nationalists and so forth encountered nerds willing to <em>debate their ideas politely</em>, rather than immediately banning them as more mainstream venues would.  As a result, many of those forces of darkness (and they probably don’t mind being called that) predictably congregated on the rationalist forums, and their stench predictably wore off on the rationalists themselves.  Furthermore, this isn’t an easy-to-fix problem, because debating ideas on their merits, extending charity to ideological opponents, etc. is sort of the rationalists’ <em>entire shtick</em>, whereas denouncing and no-platforming anyone who can be connected to an ideological enemy (in the modern parlance, “punching Nazis”) is the entire shtick of those condemning the rationalists.</p>



<p>Compounding the problem is that, as anyone who’s ever hung out with STEM nerds might’ve guessed, the rationalist community tends to skew WASP, Asian, or Jewish, non-impoverished, and male.  Worse yet, while many rationalists live their lives in progressive enclaves and strongly support progressive values, they’ll also undergo extreme anguish if they feel forced to subordinate truth to those values.</p>



<p>Chivers writes that all of these issues “blew up in spectacular style at the end of 2014,” right here on this blog.  Oh, what the hell, I’ll just quote him:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Scott Aaronson is, I think it’s fair to say, a member of the Rationalist community.  He’s a prominent theoretical computer scientist at the University of Texas at Austin, and writes a very interesting, maths-heavy blog called Shtetl-Optimised.</p><p>People in the comments under his blog were discussing feminism and sexual harassment.  And Aaronson, in a comment in which he described himself as a fan of Andrea Dworkin, described having been terrified of speaking to women as a teenager and young man.  This fear was, he said, partly that of being thought of as a sexual abuser or creep if any woman ever became aware that he sexually desired them, a fear that he picked up from sexual-harassment-prevention workshops at his university and from reading feminist literature.  This fear became so overwhelming, he said in the comment that came to be known as Comment #171, that he had ‘constant suicidal thoughts’ and at one point ‘actually begged a psychiatrist to prescribe drugs that would chemically castrate me (I had researched which ones), because a life of mathematical asceticism was the only future that I could imagine for myself.’  So when he read feminist articles talking about the ‘male privilege’ of nerds like him, he didn’t recognise the description, and so felt himself able to declare himself ‘only’ 97 per cent on board with the programme of feminism.</p><p>It struck me as a thoughtful and rather sweet remark, in the midst of a long and courteous discussion with a female commenter.  But it got picked up, weirdly, by some feminist bloggers, including one who described it as ‘a yalp of entitlement combined with an aggressive unwillingness to accept that women are human beings just like men’ and that Aaronson was complaining that ‘having to explain my suffering to women when they should already be there, mopping my brow and offering me beers and blow jobs, is so tiresome.’</p><p>Scott Alexander (<em>not</em> Scott Aaronson) then wrote a furious 10,000-word defence of his friend… (p. 214-215)</p></blockquote>



<p>And then Chivers goes on to explain Scott Alexander’s central thesis, in <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/01/01/untitled/">Untitled</a>, that privilege is not a one-dimensional axis, so that (to take one example) society can make many women in STEM miserable while <em>also</em> making shy male nerds miserable in different ways.</p>



<p>For nerds, perhaps an alternative title for Chivers’s book could be “The Normal People Do Not Hate You (Not All of Them, Anyway).”  It’s as though Chivers is demonstrating, through understated example, that taking delight in nerds’ suffering, wanting them to be miserable and alone, mocking their weird ideas, is not simply the default, well-adjusted human reaction, with any other reaction being ‘creepy’ and ‘problematic.’  Some might even go so far as to apply the latter adjectives to the sneerers’ attitude, the one that dresses up schoolyard bullying in a social-justice wig.</p>



<p>Reading Chivers’s book prompted me to reflect on my own relationship to the rationalist community.  For years, I interacted often with the community—I’ve known Robin Hanson since ~2004 and Eliezer Yudkowsky since ~2006, and our blogs bounced off each other—but I never considered myself a member.  I never ranked <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instrumental_convergence#Paperclip_maximizer">paperclip-maximizing AIs</a> among humanity’s more urgent threats—indeed, I saw them as a distraction from an all-too-likely climate catastrophe that will leave its survivors lucky to have stone tools, let alone AIs.  I was also repelled by what I saw as the rationalists’ cultier aspects.  I even once toyed with the idea of changing the name of this blog to “More Wrong” or “Wallowing in Bias,” as a play on the rationalists’ <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/">LessWrong</a> and <a href="http://www.overcomingbias.com/">OvercomingBias</a>.</p>



<p>But I’ve drawn much closer to the community over the last few years, because of a combination of factors:</p>



<ol><li>The comment-171 affair.  This was not the sort of thing that could provide any new information about the likelihood of a dangerous AI being built, but <em>was</em> (to put it mildly) the sort of thing that can tell you who your friends are.  I learned that empathy works a lot like intelligence, in that those who boast of it most loudly are often the ones who lack it.</li><li>The astounding progress in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_learning">deep learning</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinforcement_learning">reinforcement learning</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generative_adversarial_network">GANs</a>, which caused me (like everyone else, perhaps) to update in the direction of human-level AI in our lifetimes being an actual live possibility,</li><li>The rise of <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/">Scott Alexander</a>.  To the charge that the rationalists are a cult, there’s now the reply that Scott, with his constant equivocations and doubts, his deep dives into data, his clarity and self-deprecating humor, is perhaps the least culty cult leader in human history.  Likewise, to the charge that the rationalists are basement-dwelling kibitzers who accomplish nothing of note in the real world, there’s now the reply that Scott has attracted a huge mainstream following (Steven Pinker, Paul Graham, presidential candidate Andrew Yang…), purely by offering up what’s self-evidently some of the best writing of our time.</li><li>Research.  The AI-risk folks started publishing some research papers that I found interesting—some with <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1606.06565">relatively approachable problems</a> that I could see myself trying to think about if quantum computing ever got boring.  This shift seems to have happened at roughly around the same time my former student, <a href="https://paulfchristiano.com/">Paul Christiano</a>, “defected” from quantum computing to AI-risk research. </li></ol>



<p>Anyway, if you’ve spent years steeped in the rationalist blogosphere, read Eliezer’s <a href="https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Sequences">“Sequences,”</a> and so on, <em>The AI Does Not Hate You</em> will probably have little that’s new, although it might still be interesting to revisit ideas and episodes that you know through a newcomer’s eyes.  To anyone else … well, reading the book would be a lot faster than spending all those years reading blogs!  I’ve heard of some rationalists now giving out copies of the book to their relatives, by way of explaining how they’ve chosen to spend their lives.</p>



<p>I <em>still</em> don’t know whether there’s a risk worth worrying about that a misaligned AI will threaten human civilization in my lifetime, or my children’s lifetimes, or even 500 years—or whether everyone will look back and laugh at how silly some people once were to think that (except, silly in which way?).  But I do feel fairly confident that <em>The AI Does Not Hate You</em> will make a positive difference—possibly for the world, but at any rate for a little well-meaning community of sneered-at nerds obsessed with the future and with following ideas wherever they lead.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-07T02:09:05Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-07T02:09:05Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-10-08T10:08:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/138</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/138" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-138 |  On the Probabilistic Degrees of Symmetric Boolean functions | 

	Srikanth Srinivasan, 

	Utkarsh Tripathi, 

	S Venkitesh</title>
    <summary>The probabilistic degree of a Boolean function $f:\{0,1\}^n\rightarrow \{0,1\}$ is defined to be the smallest $d$ such that there is a random polynomial $\mathbf{P}$ of degree at most $d$ that agrees with $f$ at each point with high probability. Introduced by Razborov (1987), upper and lower bounds on probabilistic degrees of Boolean functions --- specifically symmetric Boolean functions --- have been used to prove explicit lower bounds, design pseudorandom generators, and devise algorithms for combinatorial problems. 
		
In this paper, we characterize the probabilistic degrees of all symmetric Boolean functions up to polylogarithmic factors over all fields of fixed characteristic (positive or zero).</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-06T15:42:51Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-06T15:42:51Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:20:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/137</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/137" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-137 |  Decision list compression by mild random restrictions | 

	Shachar Lovett, 

	Kewen Wu, 

	Jiapeng Zhang</title>
    <summary>A decision list is an ordered list of rules. Each rule is specified by a term, which is a conjunction of literals, and a value. Given an input, the output of a decision list is the value corresponding to the first rule whole term is satisfied by the input. Decision lists generalize both CNFs and DNFs, and have been studied both in complexity theory and in learning theory.

The size of a decision list is the number of rules, and its width is the maximal number of variables in a term. We prove that decision lists of small width can always be approximated by decision lists of small size, where we obtain sharp bounds (up to constants). This in particular resolves a conjecture of Gopalan, Meka and Reingold (Computational Complexity, 2013) on DNF sparsification.

An ingredient in our proof is a new random restriction lemma, which allows to analyze how DNFs (and more generally, decision lists) simplify if a small fraction of the variables are fixed. This is in contrast to the more commonly used switching lemma, which requires most of the variables to be fixed.</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-06T11:20:34Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-06T11:20:34Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:20:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/136</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/136" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-136 |  Quantum Query-to-Communication Simulation Needs a Logarithmic Overhead | 

	Sourav Chakraborty, 

	Arkadev Chattopadhyay, 

	Nikhil Mande, 

	Manaswi Paraashar</title>
    <summary>Buhrman, Cleve and Wigderson (STOC'98) observed that for every Boolean function $f : \{-1, 1\}^n \to \{-1, 1\}$ and $\bullet : \{-1, 1\}^2 \to \{-1, 1\}$ the two-party bounded-error quantum communication complexity of $(f \circ \bullet)$ is $O(Q(f) \log n)$, where $Q(f)$ is the bounded-error quantum query complexity of $f$. Note that the bounded-error randomized communication complexity of $(f \circ \bullet)$ is bounded by $O(R(f))$, where $R(f)$ denotes the bounded-error randomized query complexity of $f$. Thus, the BCW simulation has an extra $O(\log n)$ factor appearing that is absent in classical simulation. A natural question is if this factor can be avoided. H{\o}yer and de Wolf (STACS'02) showed that for the Set-Disjointness function, this can be reduced to $c^{\log^* n}$ for some constant $c$, and subsequently Aaronson and Ambainis (FOCS'03) showed that this factor can be made a constant. That is, the quantum communication complexity of the Set-Disjointness function (which is $NOR_n \circ \wedge$) is $O(Q(NOR_n))$.

Perhaps somewhat surprisingly, we show that when $ \bullet = \oplus$, then the extra $\log n$ factor in the BCW simulation is unavoidable. In other words, we exhibit a total function $F : \{-1, 1\}^n \to \{-1, 1\}$ such that $Q^{cc}(F \circ \oplus) = \Theta(Q(F) \log n)$.

To the best of our knowledge, it was not even known prior to this work whether there existed a total function $F$ and 2-bit function $\bullet$, such that $Q^{cc}(F \circ \bullet) = \omega(Q(F))$.</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-06T09:03:52Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-06T09:03:52Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:20:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/05/future-faculty-fellow-postdoc-at-university-of-illinois-urbana-champaign-apply-by-february-1-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/05/future-faculty-fellow-postdoc-at-university-of-illinois-urbana-champaign-apply-by-february-1-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Future Faculty Fellow/Postdoc at University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign (apply by February 1, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science (CS) at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign invites applications for the “Future Faculty” program. The Future Faculty Program is a selective program offering two-year postdoctoral positions whose goal is to mentor and prepare outstanding candidates for an academic career in research and teaching. Contact a theory faculty member if […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science (CS) at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign invites applications for the “Future Faculty” program. The Future Faculty Program is a selective program offering two-year postdoctoral positions whose goal is to mentor and prepare outstanding candidates for an academic career in research and teaching. Contact a theory faculty member if interested.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://cs.illinois.edu/about-us/staff-positions#futurefaculty">https://cs.illinois.edu/about-us/staff-positions#futurefaculty</a><br/>
Email: chekuri@illinois.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-05T21:36:12Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-05T21:36:12Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:21:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/05/multiple-faculty-positions-at-university-of-illinois-urbana-champaign-apply-by-december-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/05/multiple-faculty-positions-at-university-of-illinois-urbana-champaign-apply-by-december-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Multiple Faculty Positions at University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign (apply by December 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science has multiple tenure track at all levels. Quantum Computing and Theory are among the priority areas. Website: https://cs.illinois.edu/about-us/faculty-positions Email: HR@cs.illinois.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science has multiple tenure track at all levels. Quantum Computing and Theory are among the priority areas.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://cs.illinois.edu/about-us/faculty-positions">https://cs.illinois.edu/about-us/faculty-positions</a><br/>
Email: HR@cs.illinois.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-05T21:23:38Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-05T21:23:38Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:21:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3427</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/10/05/blind-folks-and-the-evolving-elephant-by-vijay-vazirani/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Blind Folks and the Evolving Elephant – by Vijay Vazirani</title>
    <summary>One of my favorite parables ever since childhood was that of the four blind men and the elephant, with each man announcing the local image evoked in his mind’s eye on touching a different part of the elephant. This parable has provided an interesting metaphor even for serious scientific matters, a well-known one being wave-particle […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>One of my favorite parables ever since childhood was that of the four blind men and the elephant, with each man announcing the local image evoked in his mind’s eye on touching a different part of the elephant. This parable has provided an interesting metaphor even for serious scientific matters, a well-known one being wave-particle duality in physics.</p>
<p>But when it comes to matching markets, the parable has taken an unusual twist, with the proverbial elephant undergoing a metamorphosis of its own! The “blind men’’ in this case are entire disciplines which can lay claim to the field of matching markets. Of course, the obvious one is economics – the founders of this field, namely Gale and Shapley, were mathematical economists and <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2012/summary/">the 2012 Nobel Prize in Economics</a> was awarded to Alvin Roth and Lloyd Shapley for work on these markets.</p>
<p>A key enabler was researchers in systems and networking. Their scientific revolutions of the Internet and mobile computing put matching markets on an exciting, new journey and their systems run these centralized markets on powerful computers.</p>
<p>The discipline of algorithm design has had an umbilical connection to matching markets: At the birth of this field lies the highly sophisticated <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.4169/amer.math.monthly.120.05.386?journalCode=uamm20">Gale-Shapley</a> stable matching algorithm (1962), whose pivotal game-theoretic property of incentive compatibility follows as a free gift from polynomial time solvability — it was established <a href="http://pareto.uab.es/jmasso/pdf/DubinsFreedmanAMM1981.pdf">two decades</a> after the discovery of the algorithm! Yet most researchers, including those in theoretical computer science, are not aware that algorithm design is also a legitimate claimant to this field. Indeed, the very “engine’’ that runs almost each one of these markets is a <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/rmklectures2019-fall-1">sophisticated algorithm</a> chosen from the “gold mine’’ of matching theory! Besides stable matching, this includes maximum matching and online matching and their numerous variants.</p>
<p>Looking back at the huge expansion of matching markets over the last decade-and-a-half, one can see that all three disciplines were faced with numerous challenges: understanding the incentive structure of a new market; finding ways of dealing with terra-bytes of data, and choosing and delivering within milli-seconds the “right’’ ads to show with a user query; and designing an algorithm for the latest variant of online matching. And they all delivered!</p>
<p>The rich and diverse set of research talks given at the recent <a href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/10/02/matching-markets-simons-driven-by-theory-driving-the-economy/">Simons program</a> on matching markets is proof enough that the elephant is still evolving!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-05T20:08:09Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-05T20:08:09Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>michalfeldman</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:20:44Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/?p=5454</id>
    <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/2019/10/05/new-horizons-in-geometry-and-micha-sharir/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>New Horizons in Geometry and Micha Sharir</title>
    <summary>Always wanted to visit Israel? Like discrete or computational geometry, and Micha Sharir? Considering what to do with this year’s travel funds? Join us in Tel Aviv! https://geometrynyc.wixsite.com/sharir (Open on a computer – does not support mobile yet.) If you can, please help us spread the word. Partial list of speakers: Pankaj Agarwal (Duke) Noga […]</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-05T15:55:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-05T15:55:19Z</published>
    <category term="Math events"/>
    <author>
      <name>Adam Sheffer</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Discrete geometry and other typos</subtitle>
      <title>Some Plane Truths</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:21:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/05/faculty-at-universidad-catolica-de-chile-apply-by-november-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/05/faculty-at-universidad-catolica-de-chile-apply-by-november-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty at Universidad Católica de Chile (apply by November 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>OPEN POSITION AT THE INSTITUTE FOR MATHEMATICAL AND COMPUTATIONAL ENGINEERING (IMC) ,PONTIFICIA UNIVERSIDAD CATÓLICA DE CHILE We are offering a full-time position at the assistant or associate level. We invite highly qualified candidates in all areas of applied mathematics, including data science and machine learning. Website: http://imc.uc.cl/index.php/noticias/135-open-position-at-the-institute-for-mathematical-and-computational-engineering Email: pbarcelo@ing.puc.cl</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>OPEN POSITION AT THE<br/>
INSTITUTE FOR MATHEMATICAL AND COMPUTATIONAL<br/>
ENGINEERING (IMC) ,PONTIFICIA UNIVERSIDAD CATÓLICA DE CHILE</p>
<p>We are offering a full-time position at the assistant or associate level. We invite highly qualified candidates in all areas of applied mathematics, including data science and machine learning.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://imc.uc.cl/index.php/noticias/135-open-position-at-the-institute-for-mathematical-and-computational-engineering">http://imc.uc.cl/index.php/noticias/135-open-position-at-the-institute-for-mathematical-and-computational-engineering</a><br/>
Email: pbarcelo@ing.puc.cl</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-05T12:04:39Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-05T12:04:39Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:21:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://grigory.github.io/blog/how-i-spent-last-summer</id>
    <link href="http://grigory.github.io/blog/how-i-spent-last-summer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title xml:lang="en">How I Spent Last Summer FAQ</title>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><!--
<div align="center"><img alt="CAML" src="http://grigory.github.io/blog/pics/summer.png" width="400"></div>
-->

<p>I get a lot of questions about how I spent last summer. Normally I just take off to the Bay Area the day my last Spring class is over and fly back the day before my Fall class begins.
However, last summer I decided I’ve been in the US long enough to learn everything it has to offer and it was time to explore life across the pond and spend three months at the Alan Turing Institute in London. Then I had two interns coming over to Bloomington so I spent my first ever summer month here. 
Since it is that time of year, a quick reminder to <a href="https://cs.indiana.edu/apply/graduate-application.html">apply by Dec 15</a> if you are interested in doing a Ph.D. and stay tuned for the internship call announcement (probably similar deadline).</p>

<h1 id="summer-interns-in-bloomington">Summer Interns in Bloomington</h1>

<p>IU has started a <a href="https://sice.indiana.edu/research/student-research/fellowship.html">Global Talent Attraction Program (GTAP)</a> – fantastic program for international summer interns. The program gives you a $4000 stipend and you spend 2 months here at IU. There were a lot of strong applicants so it took me a while to interview all candidates. In the end, the two interns I got were <a href="https://codeforces.com/profile/Chameleon2460">Jakub Boguta</a> (U. Warsaw, ACM ICPC gold this year, must be tough to be in the lead for 4 hours and not win) and <a href="https://codeforces.com/profile/josdas">Stanislav Naumov</a> (SPb ITMO, ACM ICPC finalist, who spent summer at Google and just arrived on campus). Also, <a href="https://www.eleves.ens.fr/home/farthaud/">Farid Arthaud</a> joined us from ENS Paris, Ulm with a short recommendation of being “probably the best third-year CS student in France”. If you think you are the best in your country, have U.S. citizenship and don’t need to get paid, shoot me an email ;) Despite it being hot and humid here in Bloomington during the summer, we had a great time.</p>

<div align="center"><img alt="interns" src="http://grigory.github.io/blog/pics/interns.jpg" width="400"/></div>
<p><br/></p>

<p>We decided to dive into deep learning for image classification and figured out how to get more mileage out of standard pretrained neural nets by using them to produce hierarchical clusterings (with guarantees). If this sounds fun, you can apply for GTAP next year (picture by Farid).</p>

<div align="center"><img alt="hc" src="http://grigory.github.io/blog/pics/hc.png" width="400"/></div>

<h1 id="london-and-the-alan-turing-institute">London and the Alan Turing Institute</h1>

<p>Overall, this was a great experience as it quickly became clear that my neural net is overfit to the US lifestyle. I think of UK as throwing in some perturbations to your visual and verbal input (some may seem adversarial, but mostly just random) which, as we know, is good for robustness, generalization and what not.</p>

<ul>
  <li><b>Q</b>: Is grass greener there? <b>A</b>: Yes, of course. Especially, if you live next to the Regent’s Park.</li>
  <li><b>Q</b>: Is it your cup of tea? <b>A</b>: No, I still only function on Redbull, but the afternoon teas are a great experience. Proximity to cutting-edge tech, CS research and startups still matters most to me. However, if you are into math or finance, your mileage will almost certainly vary. Also, London seems perfect for a short-term visit/sabbatical, especially if you want to take a break from the tech hype, write a book, explore Europe, etc.</li>
  <li><b>Q</b>: What’s up with the <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/">Alan Turing Institute</a> and DeepMind? <b>A</b>: These two are probably the most happening places in the UK right now in academia and industry respectively. They are within a 5-minute walk from each other in King’s Cross. I was staying right across the road and it was perfect except for no AC. ATI serves as a meeting hub for researchers from all of the top UK schools (Cambridge, Oxford, Warwick, UCL, Edinburgh, etc.).
ATI is based inside the British library, which was the largest public building constructed in the UK in the 20th century. ATI has its own space inside the library which is equipped similarly to Google/FB offices. Except no free food, only drinks – would you want to have free British food anyway?</li>
</ul>

<div align="center"><img alt="ati" src="http://grigory.github.io/blog/pics/ati.jpg" width="400"/></div>
<p><br/></p>
<div align="center"><img alt="bl" src="http://grigory.github.io/blog/pics/bl.jpg" width="400"/></div>

<ul>
  <li><b>Q</b>: Is Shoreditch the most hip neighborhood? <b>A</b>: I think so, best Sci-Fi graffiti ever.</li>
</ul>

<div align="center"><img alt="murals" src="http://grigory.github.io/blog/pics/mural.jpg" width="400"/></div>

<ul>
  <li><b>Q</b>: Did you meet the King? <b>A</b>: Yes, in Heathrow I ran into a 250-pound dude from Atlanta who made it quite clear that’s him by wearing one of these (except in a larger font and in dirty red color).</li>
</ul>

<div align="center"><img alt="king" src="http://grigory.github.io/blog/pics/king.jpg" width="400"/></div>

<ul>
  <li><b>Q</b>: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ViHsfeXNgjY">Is Paris still Paris?</a> <b>A</b>: I think so (my third time). K and I took a 2-hour train down there directly from King’s Cross (St. Pancras station, another reason to stay in King’s Cross). We’ve enjoyed our time greatly, especially in Versailles and ENS Paris, Ulm. The Salvador Dali Museum in Montmartre was another highlight of this trip.</li>
</ul>

<div align="center"><img alt="versailles" src="http://grigory.github.io/blog/pics/versailles.jpg" width="400"/></div>

<ul>
  <li><b>Q</b>: Brexit, Boris Johnson? <b>A</b>: Locals made fun of me for having never heard of Boris Johnson. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dXyO_MC9g3k">Is there much to know anyway</a>?</li>
</ul>


  <p><a href="http://grigory.github.io/blog/how-i-spent-last-summer/">How I Spent Last Summer FAQ</a> was originally published by Grigory Yaroslavtsev at <a href="http://grigory.github.io/blog">The Big Data Theory</a> on October 05, 2019.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Grigory Yaroslavtsev</name>
      <email>grigory@grigory.us</email>
      <uri>http://grigory.github.io/blog</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://grigory.github.io/blog/</id>
      <author>
        <name>Grigory Yaroslavtsev</name>
        <email>grigory@grigory.us</email>
        <uri>http://grigory.github.io/blog/</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://grigory.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://grigory.github.io/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <title xml:lang="en">The Big Data Theory</title>
      <updated>2019-10-05T20:27:22Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/135</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/135" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-135 |  Doubly-Efficient Pseudo-Deterministic Proofs | 

	Dhiraj Holden, 

	Shafi Goldwasser, 

	Michel Goemans</title>
    <summary>In [20] Goldwasser, Grossman and Holden  introduced pseudo-deterministic interactive proofs for search problems where a powerful prover can convince a probabilistic polynomial time verifier that a solution to a search problem is canonical.  They studied  search problems for which polynomial time algorithms are not known and for which many solutions are possible. They showed that whereas there exists a constant round pseudo deterministic proof for graph isomorphism where the canonical solution is the lexicographically smallest isomorphism, the existence of pseudo-deterministic interactive proofs for NP-hard problems would imply the collapse of the polynomial time hierarchy.

In this paper, we turn our attention to studying  doubly-efficient pseudo-deterministic proofs for polynomial time search problems:  pseudo-deterministic proofs with the extra requirement that the prover runtime is polynomial  and the verifier runtime to verify that a solution is canonical is significantly lower  than the complexity of finding any solution, canonical or otherwise. Naturally this question is particularly interesting for search problems for which a lower bound on its worst case complexity  is known or has been widely conjectured. 

We show doubly-efficient pseudo-deterministic algorithms for a host of natural problems whose complexity has long been conjectured. In particular:

We show a doubly efficient pseudo-deterministic proof for linear programming where the canonical solution which the prover will provide is  the lexicographically greatest optimal solution for the LP. To this end, we show how through perturbing the linear program and strong duality this solution can be both  computed efficiently by the prover, and verified by the verifier.  
The time of the verifier is $O(d^2 )$ for a linear program with integer data and at most $d$ variables and constraints, whereas the time to solve such linear program is $\tilde{O}(d^{\omega} )$ by randomized algorithms [11] for $\omega$  the exponent for fast matrix multiplication .


We show a doubly efficient pseudo-deterministic proof for 3-SUM and problems reducible to 3-SUM where the prover is a $O(n^2)$ time algorithm and the verifier takes time $\tilde{O}(n^{1.5})$. 


We show a doubly-efficient pseudo-deterministic proof for the hitting set problem} where the verifier runs in time $\tilde{O}(m)$ and the prover runs in time $\tilde{O}(m^2)$ where $ m = \sum_{S \in \mathcal{S}} |S| + \sum_{T \in \mathcal{T}} |T|$ for inputs  collections of sets $\mathcal{S}, \mathcal{T}$.

We show a doubly-efficient pseudo-deterministic proof for the Zero Weight Triangle problem where the verifier runs in time $\tilde{O}(n^{2 + \omega/3})$ and the prover runs in randomized time $\tilde{O}(n^3)$. The Zero Weight Triangle problem is equivalent to the All-Pairs Shortest Path problem, a well-studied problem that is the foundation of many hardness results in graph algorithms [39,38], under sub-cubic reductions.</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-04T15:50:06Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-04T15:50:06Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:20:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/134</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/134" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-134 |  Finding monotone patterns in sublinear time | 

	Omri Ben-Eliezer, 

	Clement Canonne, 

	Shoham Letzter, 

	Erik Waingarten</title>
    <summary>We study the problem of finding monotone subsequences in an array from the viewpoint of sublinear algorithms. For fixed $k \in \mathbb{N}$ and $\varepsilon &gt; 0$, we show that the non-adaptive query complexity of finding a length-$k$ monotone subsequence of $f \colon [n] \to \mathbb{R}$, assuming that $f$ is $\varepsilon$-far from free of such subsequences, is $\Theta((\log n)^{\lfloor \log_2 k \rfloor})$. Prior to our work, the best algorithm for this problem, due to Newman, Rabinovich, Rajendraprasad, and Sohler (2017), made $(\log n)^{O(k^2)}$ non-adaptive queries; and the only lower bound known, of $\Omega(\log n)$ queries for the case $k = 2$, followed from that on testing monotonicity due to Erg\"un, Kannan, Kumar, Rubinfeld, and Viswanathan (2000) and Fischer (2004).</summary>
    <updated>2019-10-04T15:42:39Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-04T15:42:39Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:20:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/04/postdoc-at-university-of-warwick-uk-apply-by-december-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/04/postdoc-at-university-of-warwick-uk-apply-by-december-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at University of Warwick, UK (apply by December 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>We invite applications for a postdoc position hosted by Tom Gur at the University of Warwick, United Kingdom, in the fields of sublinear-time algorithms, coding theory, interactive and probabilistically checkable proofs, and complexity theory. Please contact Tom Gur directly with your CV. The start date is flexible. Website: https://www.dcs.warwick.ac.uk/~tomgur/ Email: tom.gur@warwick.ac.uk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We invite applications for a postdoc position hosted by Tom Gur at the University of Warwick, United Kingdom, in the fields of sublinear-time algorithms, coding theory, interactive and probabilistically checkable proofs, and complexity theory.</p>
<p>Please contact Tom Gur directly with your CV. The start date is flexible.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.dcs.warwick.ac.uk/~tomgur/">https://www.dcs.warwick.ac.uk/~tomgur/</a><br/>
Email: tom.gur@warwick.ac.uk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-04T13:10:04Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-04T13:10:04Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:21:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://agtb.wordpress.com/?p=3425</id>
    <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/2019/10/04/highlights-beyond-ec-call-for-nominations/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Highlights Beyond EC – Call for Nominations</title>
    <summary>The 21st ACM Conference on Economics and Computation (EC’20) will host a special plenary session highlighting some of the best work in economics and computation that appears in conferences and journals other than EC, or mature working papers. The intention of this session is to expose EC attendees to related work just beyond the boundary of their […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The <a href="http://ec20.sigecom.org/">21st ACM Conference on Economics and Computation</a> (EC’20) will host a special <strong>plenary session</strong> highlighting some of the best work in economics and computation that appears in conferences and journals other than EC, or mature working papers. The intention of this session is to expose EC attendees to related work just beyond the boundary of their current awareness. We seek nominations for papers in Economics and Computation that have made breakthrough advances, opened up new horizons for research, made interesting connections between different scientific areas, or had significant impact on practice. Examples of relevant conferences and journals include STOC/FOCS/SODA/ITCS, AAAI/IJCAI/AAMAS, NIPS/ICML/COLT, WWW/KDD, AER/Econometrica/JPE/QJE/RESTUD/TE/AEJ Micro/JET/GEB, and Math of OR/Management Science/Operations Research.</p>
<p><strong>Who can nominate? </strong>This call is open to everyone (self-nominations are also allowed), but we particularly encourage members of PCs or editorial boards in various venues to submit nominations.</p>
<p><strong>Deadline:</strong> December 23, 2019.</p>
<p><strong>Nomination format:</strong> Nominations should be emailed to <a href="mailto:HighlightsBeyondEC@gmail.com">HighlightsBeyondEC2020@gmail.com</a>, and should include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Paper title and author names.</li>
<li>Publication venue or online working version. Preference will be given to papers that have appeared in a related conference or journal within the past two years, or have a working version circulated within the past two years.</li>
<li>A short (2-3 paragraph) justification letter, explaining the significance of the paper.</li>
<li>Names of 1-3 experts on the area of the paper.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Committee members:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Michal Feldman </strong>(Tel Aviv University)</li>
<li><strong>Hervé Moulin</strong> (University of Glasgow)</li>
<li><strong>Michael Wellman </strong>(University of Michigan)</li>
<li><strong>Adam Wierman </strong>(California Institute of Technology)</li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-04T06:05:58Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-04T06:05:58Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>michalfeldman</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://agtb.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://secure.gravatar.com/blavatar/52ef314e11e379febf97d1a97547f4cd?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fs0.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://agtb.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Computation, Economics, and Game Theory</subtitle>
      <title>Turing's Invisible Hand</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:20:44Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1192</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1192" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for Sept 2019</title>
    <summary>Five Six papers this month: results on testing separations, linearity testing in \(\mathbb{R}^n\), testing for regular languages, graph property testing, topological property testing, and Boolean rank. Hard properties with (very) short PCPPs and their applications, by Omri Ben-Eliezer, Eldar Fischer, Amit Levi, and Ron D. Rothblum (arXiv). Probably, the most significant takeaway from this work is a (largest […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><s>Five</s> Six papers this month: results on testing separations, linearity testing in \(\mathbb{R}^n\), testing for regular languages, graph property testing, topological property testing, and Boolean rank. </p>



<p><strong>Hard properties with (very) short PCPPs and their applications</strong>, by Omri Ben-Eliezer, Eldar Fischer, Amit Levi, and Ron D. Rothblum (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/088/">arXiv</a>). Probably, the most significant takeaway from this work is a (largest possible) separation between standard and tolerant property testing. PCPPs (Probabilistically Checkable Proofs of Proximity) are the “NP” variant of property testing, where the tester is aided by a proof string. Consider property \(\mathcal{P}\). If \(x \in \mathcal{P}\), there must be a proof string that makes the tester accept (with probability 1). If \(x\) is far from \(\mathcal{P}\) (in the usual property testing sense), for any proof string, the tester must reject with sufficiently high probability. PCPPs have played a role in the classical constructions of PCPs, but have also found uses in getting a better understanding of property testing itself. And this paper shows how PCPP constructions can be used to get property testing separations. The main result in this paper is a property \(\mathcal{P}\) that (basically) requires \(\Omega(n)\) queries to “property test”, but has a PCPP system where the proof length is \(\widetilde{O}(n)\). (\(n\) is the input length.) The main construction uses collections of random linear codes. Significantly, these constructions show a strong separation between standard vs tolerant property testing, and standard vs erasure-resilient property testing. (The latter is a recent variant by <a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/abs/10.1137/16M1075661?journalCode=smjcat">Dixit et al</a>, where certain parts of the input are hidden from the tester.) There is a property that is testable in a constant number of queries, but requires \(\widetilde{\Omega}(n)\) queries to test tolerantly (for any non-trivial choice of parameters). An analogous result holds for erasure-resilient testing.</p>



<p><strong>Distribution-Free Testing of Linear Functions on R^n</strong>, by Noah Fleming and Yuichi Yoshida (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.03391">arXiv</a>). Linearity testing is arguably <em>the</em> canonical problem in property testing, yet there is still much to be learned about it. This paper considers functions \(f: \mathbb{R}^n \to \mathbb{R}\), and the <em>distribution-free setting</em>. (In this setting, distance is measured according is an unknown distribution \(\mathcal{D}\) over the input, and the tester can access samples from this distribution. For \(\mathbb{R}^n\), the “standard” distribution would the \(n\)-dimensional Gaussian.) The main result is that linearity testing can be done in the distribution-free setting with \(\widetilde{O}(1/\varepsilon)\) queries, assuming that the distribution is continuous. The primary technical tool, an interesting result in its own right, is that additivity \((f(x+y) = f(x) + f(y))\) can be tested in \(\widetilde{O}(1/\varepsilon)\) queries. The significance of the testing result is cemented by an \(\Omega(n)\) lower bound for sample-based testers.</p>



<p><strong>Sliding window property testing for regular languages</strong> by Moses Ganardi, Danny Hucke, Markus Lohrey, Tatiana Starikovskaya (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.10261">arXiv</a>). Fix a regular language \(\mathcal{R}\). Consider the streaming model, and the basic question of recognizing whether the string (being streamed) is in \(\mathcal{R}\). Simple, you will say! Run the DFA recognizing \(\mathcal{R}\) in constant space. Now, suppose there is a sliding window length of \(n\). The aim is to determine if the past \(n\) symbols (the “active window”) form a string in \(\mathcal{R}\). Suprisingly (at least to me), there is a full characterization of the space required for randomized algorithms, and (depending on \(\mathcal{R}\)), it is either \(\Theta(1)\), \(\Theta(\log\log n)\), \(\Theta(\log n)\), or \(\Theta(n)\).  In the interest of beating these lower bounds, suppose we wish to property test on the active window. It turns out the answer is quite nuanced. There are deterministic \(O(\log n)\)-space testers and randomized two-sided \(O(1/\varepsilon)\)-space testers for all regular languages. For randomized one-sided testers, there are multiple possibilities for the optimal space complexity, and there is a full characterization of these regular languages.</p>



<p><strong>A characterization of graph properties testable for general planar graphs with one-sided error (It’s all about forbidden subgraphs)</strong> by Artur Czumaj and Christian Sohler (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1909.10647.pdf">arXiv</a>). Property testing of sparse graphs has been receiving more attention, but most results focus on the bounded degree setting. Unfortunately, many of these results break quite dramatically on sparse graphs with unbounded degrees. This paper focuses on property testing, within the class of unbounded degree planar graphs. (Meaning, the input is always assumed to be planar.) The results achieve a significant goal: as the title suggests, there is a complete characterization of properties that are constant-query testable with one-sided error. The easier part is in showing that all such properties can be reduced to testing \(H\)-freeness. The harder (remarkable) result is \(H\)-freeness can be tested in general planar queries with constant queries. (This is non-trivial even for triangle-freeness.) And, as is easy to conjecture but hard to prove, these results carry over for all minor-closed families.  As a small indication of the challenge, most testers for bounded-degree graphs work by doing constant depth BFSes. When high degree vertices are present, this method fails, and we really need new ideas to deal with such graphs.</p>



<p><strong>Near Coverings and Cosystolic Expansion – an example of topological property testing</strong> by Irit Dinur and Roy Meshulam (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/126/">ECCC</a>). In most algebraic settings, property testing results can be seen as local to global theorems. When do local constraints on a large object imply a global condition? This paper gives a topological instantiation of this phenomenon. We need to define the <em>cover</em> of a simplicial complex \(X\). For concreteness, think of a 2D simplicial complex \(X\), which is a hypergraph with hyperedges of size at most 3, where subsets of hyperedges are also present. A 2-cover is a simplicial complex \(X’\) with the following property. It has two copies of each vertex of \(X\). Each hyperedge of \(X\) must have two “corresponding” disjoint copies in \(X’\). Let the copies of vertex \(v\) be \(v_0, v_1\). Then, for every hyperedge (say) \((u,v,w)\) of \(X\), there must be two disjoint hyperedges in \(X’\) involving copies of the corresponding vertices. One can consider the property testing twist: if the neighborhoods of “most” vertices \(v\) in \(X\) satisfy these condition (with respect to the neighborhoods of the copies of \(v\) in \(X’\)), then is \(X’\) close to being a cover of \(X\)? Indeed, this paper proves that such a “property testing condition” holds iff \(X\) is a high-dimensional expander.</p>



<p><strong>Property testing of the Boolean and binary rank</strong> by Michal Parnas, Dana Ron, and Adi Shraibman (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.11632">arXiv</a>). The Boolean rank of a matrix \(M\) is a fundamental quantity that appears in many lower bound constructions. (Recall that an \(n \times m\) Boolean matrix \(M\) has a rank \(r\) if \(M\) can be expressed as \(X \cdot Y\), where \(X \in \mathbb{F}_2^{n \times d}\) and \(Y \in \mathbb{F}_2^{d \times m}\).) In the real-valued setting, results show that one can property test rank in \(poly(d/\varepsilon)\) queries. This paper proves an analogous result for the Boolean rank. There is a surprise element here: over reals, the rank can be computed in polynomial time, and many of the geometric intuitions can be brought over to the property testing problem. On the other hand, the Boolean rank is NP-hard to compute exactly, yet we can still get a tester with \(poly(d)\) query complexity. The paper also gives results for <em>binary rank</em>. For the binary rank, we require the component matrices \(X, Y\) to be Boolean, but algebraic operations are over the reals. In the case, the tester has query complexity \(2^{2d}\) (with varying dependencies on \(\varepsilon\) for adaptive/non-adaptive testers). The intriguing open problem is whether \(poly(d)\)-query testers exist for binary rank.</p>



<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-04T05:54:43Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-04T05:54:43Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Seshadhri</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2019-10-09T23:32:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-3615744836127152440</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/3615744836127152440/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/10/quantum-supremacy-guest-post-by-abhinav.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3615744836127152440" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3615744836127152440" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/10/quantum-supremacy-guest-post-by-abhinav.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum Supremacy: A Guest Post by Abhinav Deshpande</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to introduce you to Abhinav Deshpande, who is a graduate student at the University of Maryland, studying Quantum Computing. This will be a guest post on the rumors of the recent Google breakthrough on Quantum Supremacy. For other blog posts on this exciting rumor, see <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4317">Scott Aaronson's post</a>, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4342">Scott Aaronson's second post on it</a>, <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/john-preskill-explains-quantum-supremacy-20191002/">John Preskill's quanta article</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/09/quantum-supremacy.html">Fortnow's post</a>,<br/>
and there may be others.<br/>
<br/>
Guest post by Abhinav:<br/>
<br/>
I (Abhinav) thank Bill Fefferman for help with this post, and Bill Gasarch for inviting me to do a guest post.<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<b>The quest towards quantum computational supremacy</b><br/>
<br/>
September saw some huge news in the area of quantum computing, with rumours that the Google AI Lab has achieved a milestone known as 'quantum computational supremacy', also termed 'quantum supremacy' or 'quantum advantage' by some authors. Today, we examine what this term means, the most promising approach towards achieving this milestone, and the best complexity-theoretic evidence we have so far against classical simulability of quantum mechanics. We will not be commenting on details of the purported paper since there is no official announcement or claim from the authors so far.<br/>
<br/>
<b>What it means</b><br/>
<br/>
First off, the field of quantum computational supremacy arose from trying to formally understand the differences in the power of classical and quantum computers. A complexity theorist would view this goal as trying to give evidence to separate the complexity classes BPP and BQP. However, it turns out that one can gain more traction from considering the sampling analogues of these classes, SampBPP and SampBQP.  These are classes of distributions that can be efficiently sampled on classical and quantum computers, respectively. Given a quantum circuit U on n qubits, one may define an associated probability distribution over 2^n outcomes as follows: apply U to the fiducial initial state |000...0&gt; and measure the resulting state in the computational basis. This produces a distribution D_U.<br/>
<br/>
A suitable way to define the task of simulating the quantum circuit is as follows<b style="font-style: italic;">:</b><br/>
<br/>
Input: Description of a quantum circuit U acting on n qubits.<br/>
<br/>
Output: A sample from the probability distribution D_U obtained by measuring U|000...0&gt; in the computational basis.<br/>
<br/>
One of the early works in this field was that of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0205133">Terhal and DiVincenzo</a>, which first considered the complexity of sampling from a distribution (weak simulation) as opposed to that of calculating the exact probability of a certain outcome (strong simulation). Weak simulation is arguably the more natural notion of simulating a quantum system, since in general, we cannot feasibly compute the probability of a certain outcome even if we can simulate the quantum circuit. Subsequent works by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1011.3245">Aaronson and Arkhipov</a>, and by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1005.1407">Bremner, Jozsa, and Shepherd</a> established that if there is a classically efficient weak simulator for different classes of quantum circuits, the polynomial hierarchy collapses to the third level.<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
So far, we have only considered the question of exactly sampling from the distribution D_U. However, any realistic experiment is necessarily noisy, and a more natural problem is to sample from a distribution that is not exactly D_U but from any distribution D_O that is ε-close in a suitable distance measure, say the variation distance.<br/>
<br/>
The aforementioned work by Aaronson and Arkhipov was the first to consider this problem, and they made progress towards showing that a special class of quantum circuits (linear optical circuits) is classically hard to approximately simulate in the sense above. The task of sampling from the output of linear optical circuits is known as boson sampling. At the   time, it was the best available way to show that quantum computers  may solve some problems that are far beyond the reach of classical computers.<br/>
<br/>
Even granting that the PH doesn't collapse, one still needs to make an additional conjecture to establish that boson sampling is not classically simulable.  The conjecture is that additively approximating the output probabilities of a random linear optical quantum circuit is #P-hard.  The reason this may be true is that output probabilities of random linear optical quantum circuits are Permanents of a Gaussian random matrix, and the Permanent is as hard to compute on a random matrix as it is on a worst-case matrix. Therefore, the only missing link is to go from average-case hardness of exact computation to average-case hardness of an additive estimation. In addition, if we make a second conjecture known as the "anti-concentration" conjecture, we can show that this additive estimation is non-trivial: it suffices to give us a good multiplicative estimation with high probability.<br/>
<br/>
So that's what quantum computational supremacy is about: we have a computational task that is efficiently solvable with quantum computers, but which would collapse the polynomial hierarchy if done by a classical computer (assuming certain other conjectures are true). One may substitute "collapse of the polynomial hierarchy" with stronger conjectures and incur a corresponding tradeoff in the likelihood of the conjecture being true.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Random circuit sampling</b><br/>
<br/>
In 2016,<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1608.00263"> Boixo et al</a>. proposed to replace the class of quantum circuits for which some hardness results were known (commuting circuits and boson sampling) by random circuits of sufficient depth on a 2D grid of qubits having nearest-neighbour interactions. Concretely, the proposed experiment would be to apply random unitaries from a specified set on n qubits arranged on a 2D grid for sufficient depth, and then sample from the resulting distribution. The two-qubit unitaries in the set are restricted to act between nearest neighbours, respecting the geometric This task is called random circuit sampling (RCS).<br/>
<br/>
At the time, the level of evidence for the hardness of this scheme was not yet the same as the linear optical scheme. However, given the theoretical and experimental interest in the idea of demonstrating a quantum speedup over classical computers, subsequent works by<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.04402"> Bouland, Fefferman, Nirkhe and Vazirani</a>, and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1809.06957">Harrow and Mehraban</a> bridged this gap (the relevant work by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.05903">Aaronson and Chen</a> will be discussed in the following section). Harrow and Mehraban proved anticoncentration for random circuits. In particular, they showed that a 2-dimensional grid of n qubits achieve anticoncentration in depth O(\sqrt{n}), improving upon earlier results with higher depth due to <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1208.0692">Brandao, Harrow and Horodeck</a>i. Bouland et al. proved the same supporting evidence for RCS as that for boson sampling, namely a worst-to-average-case reduction for exactly computing most output probabilities, even without the permanent structure possessed by linear optical quantum circuits.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Verification</b><br/>
<br/>
So far, we have not discussed the elephant in the room: of verifying that the output distribution supported on 2^n outcomes. It turns out that there are concrete lower bounds such as those due to Valiant and Valiant, showing that verifying whether an empirical distribution is close to a target distribution is impossible if one has few samples.<br/>
<br/>
Boixo et al. proposed a way of certifying the fidelity of the purported simulation. Their key observation was to note that if their experimental system is well modelled by a noise model called global depolarising noise, estimating the output fidelity is possible with relatively few outcomes. Under global depolarising noise with fidelity f, the noisy distribution takes the form D_N = f D_U + (1-f) I, where I is the uniform distribution over the 2^n outcomes. Together with another empirical observation about the statistics of output probabilities of the ideal distribution D_U, they argued that computing the following cross-entropy score would serve as a good estimator of the fidelity:<br/>
<br/>
f ~ H(I, D_U) - H(D_exp, D_U), where H(D_A,D_B) is the cross-entropy between the two distributions: H(D_A, D_B) = -\sum_i p_A log (p_B).<br/>
<br/>
The proposal here was to experimentally collect several samples from D_exp, classically compute using brute-force the probabilities of these outcomes in the distribution D_U, and estimate the cross-entropy using this information. If the test outputs a high score for a computation on sufficiently many qubits and depth, the claim is that quantum supremacy has been achieved.<br/>
<br/>
Aaronson and Chen gave alternative form of evidence for the hardness of scoring well on a test that aims to certify quantum supremacy similar to the manner above. This sidesteps the issue of whether a test similar to the one above does indeed certify the fidelity. The specific problem considered was "Heavy Output Generation" (HOG), the problem of outputting strings that have higher than median probability in the output distribution. Aaronson and Chen linked the hardness of HOG to a closely related problem called "QUATH", and conjectured that QUATH is hard for classical computers.<br/>
<br/>
<b>Open questions</b><br/>
<br/>
Assuming the Google team has performed the impressive feat of both running the experiment outlined before and classically computing the probabilities of the relevant outcomes to see a high score on their cross-entropy test, I discuss the remaining positions a skeptic might take regarding the claim about quantum supremacy.<br/>
<br/>
"The current evidence of classical hardness of random circuit sampling is not sufficient to conclude that the task is hard". Assuming that the skeptic believes that the polynomial hierarchy does not collapse, a remaining possibility is that there is no worst-to-average-case reduction for the problem of *approximating* most output probabilities, which kills the proof technique of Aaronson and Arkhipov to show hardness of approximate sampling.<br/>
<br/>
"The cross-entropy proposal does not certify the fidelity." Boixo et al. gave numerical evidence and other arguments for this statement, based on the observation that the noise is of the global depolarising form. A skeptic may argue that the assumption of global depolarising noise is a strong one.<br/>
<br/>
"The QUATH problem is not classically hard." In order to give evidence for the hardness of QUATH, Aaronson and Chen examined the best existing algorithms for this problem and also gave a new algorithm that nevertheless do not solve QUATH with the required parameters.<br/>
<br/>
It would be great if the community could work towards strengthening the evidence we already have for this task to be hard, either phrased as a sampling experiment or together with the verification test.<br/>
<br/>
Finally, I think this is an exciting time for quantum computing and to witness this landmark event. It may not be the first probe of an experiment that is "hard" to classically simulate, since there are many quantum experiments that are beyond the reach of current classical simulations, but the inherent programmability and control present in the experimental system is what enables the tools of complexity theory to be applied to the problem. A thought that fascinates me is the idea that we may be exploring quantum mechanics in a regime never probed this carefully before, the "high complexity regime" of quantum mechanics. One imagines there are important lessons in physics here.<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-03T19:41:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-03T19:41:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-10-09T16:57:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=18199</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/10/03/noisy-quantum-circuits-how-do-we-know-that-we-have-robust-experimental-outcomes-at-all-and-do-we-care/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Noisy quantum circuits: how do we know that we have robust experimental outcomes at all? (And do we care?)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a recent post we discussed Google’s claim of achieving “quantum supremacy” and my reasons to think that these claims will not stand. (See also this comment for necessary requirements from a quantum supremacy experiment.) This debate gives a good … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/10/03/noisy-quantum-circuits-how-do-we-know-that-we-have-robust-experimental-outcomes-at-all-and-do-we-care/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/09/23/quantum-computers-amazing-progress-google-ibm-and-extraordinary-but-probably-false-supremacy-claims-google/">a recent post we discussed Google’s claim of achieving “quantum supremacy” and my reasons to think that these claims will not stand.</a> (See also <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/09/23/quantum-computers-amazing-progress-google-ibm-and-extraordinary-but-probably-false-supremacy-claims-google/#comment-61043">this comment</a> for necessary requirements from a quantum supremacy experiment.) This debate gives a good opportunity to discuss some conceptual issues regarding sampling, probability distributions, statistics, and computational complexity. This time we will discuss <span style="color: #ff0000;">chaotic behavior vs. robust experimental outcomes.</span></p>
<p>On unrelated matter, I just heard Shachar Lovett’s very beautiful TCS+ lecture on the sunflower conjecture (<a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/23/amazing-ryan-alweiss-shachar-lovett-kewen-wu-jiapeng-zhang-made-dramatic-progress-on-the-sunflower-conjecture/">see this post</a> on the Alweiss, Lovett, Wu, and Zhang’s breakthrough). You can see the lecture and many others on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/TCSplusSeminars/videos">TCS+ you tube channel</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/10/cern-slide-30c.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18240" height="449" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/10/cern-slide-30c.png?w=640&amp;h=449" width="640"/></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;"><span style="color: #993366;">Slide 30 from my August, ’19 CERN lecture: predictions of near-term experiments. (Here is the</span> <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/09/cern.pptx">full powerpoint presentation</a><span style="color: #993366;">.) In this post we mainly</span> <strong>discuss</strong> <strong>point b) about chaotic behavior. </strong><span style="color: #800080;">See also <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02499">my paper: The argument against quantum computers</a>.</span></span></p>
<p>Consider an experiment aimed for establishing quantum supremacy: your quantum computer produced a sample <img alt="x_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_i"/> which is a 0-1 string of length <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="n"/> from a certain distribution <img alt="D_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="D_i"/>. The research assumption is that <img alt="D_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="D_i"/>  is close enough to a fixed distribution <img alt="D" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="D"/> (<img alt="D" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="D"/> accounts for the computing process and the noise) which is very hard to be demonstrated on a classical computer. By looking at a large number of samples you can perform a statistical test on the samples to verify that they were (approximately) sampled from <img alt="D" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="D"/>, or at least that they were sampled from a probability distribution that is very hard to be computed on a classical computer!</p>
<p>But, is it possible that all the distributions <img alt="D_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="D_i"/>‘s are very different? Namely that each sample is taken from a completely different distribution? More formally, is it possible  that under a correct modeling of the device for two different samples <img alt="x_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_i"/> and <img alt="x_j" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_j&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="x_j"/>, <img alt="D_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=D_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="D_i"/> has a very small correlation with <img alt="D_j" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=D_j&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="D_j"/>? In this case we say that the experiment outcomes are <strong>not robust</strong> and that the situation is <strong>chaotic</strong>.</p>
<p>Here are a couple of questions that I propose to think about:</p>
<ul>
<li>How do we test robustness?</li>
<li>Do the supremacy experiments require that the experiment is robust?</li>
<li>If, after many samples, you reach a probability distribution that require exponential time on a classical computer should you worry about the question whether the experiment is robust?</li>
<li><span style="color: #0000ff;">Do the 10,000,000 samples for the Google 53-qubit experiment represent a robust sampling experiment?</span></li>
</ul>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-03T19:23:25Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-03T19:23:25Z</published>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Quantum"/>
    <category term="chaos"/>
    <category term="chaos and computation"/>
    <category term="quantum supremacy"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/03/faculty-position-at-university-of-minnesota-twin-cities-apply-by-november-1-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/10/03/faculty-position-at-university-of-minnesota-twin-cities-apply-by-november-1-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty position at University of Minnesota-Twin Cities (apply by November 1, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science &amp; Engineering at the University of Minnesota-Twin Cities is hiring to fill multiple tenure-track positions at the assistant professor level, although higher levels of appointments may be considered when commensurate with experience and accomplishments. One of the areas of interest is theoretical computer science. Website: https://www.cs.umn.edu/news/cse-now-hiring-new-faculty Email: csciadmin@umn.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science &amp; Engineering at the University of Minnesota-Twin Cities is hiring to fill multiple tenure-track positions at the assistant professor level, although higher levels of appointments may be considered when commensurate with experience and accomplishments. One of the areas of interest is theoretical computer science.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.cs.umn.edu/news/cse-now-hiring-new-faculty">https://www.cs.umn.edu/news/cse-now-hiring-new-faculty</a><br/>
Email: csciadmin@umn.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-10-03T18:02:59Z</updated>
    <published>2019-10-03T18:02:59Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-10-10T05:21:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
