<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2022-01-22T07:39:01Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/21/postdoc-at-faculty-of-computer-science-of-hse-university-apply-by-january-31-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/21/postdoc-at-faculty-of-computer-science-of-hse-university-apply-by-january-31-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at Faculty of Computer Science of HSE University (apply by January 31, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Faculty of Computer Science of HSE University (Moscow, Russia) accepts applications for postdoctoral positions in the following research areas: theoretical computer science, theoretical foundation of ML, interpretable knowledge discovery and explainable AI, complex systems and applied mathematics, formal concept analysis, process mining. The application deadline is January 31, 2022. Website: https://cs.hse.ru/en/news/554897133.html Email: fellowship@hse.ru</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Faculty of Computer Science of HSE University (Moscow, Russia) accepts applications for postdoctoral positions in the following research areas: theoretical computer science, theoretical foundation of ML, interpretable knowledge discovery and explainable AI, complex systems and applied mathematics, formal concept analysis, process mining. The application deadline is January 31, 2022.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://cs.hse.ru/en/news/554897133.html">https://cs.hse.ru/en/news/554897133.html</a><br/>
Email: fellowship@hse.ru</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-21T10:06:35Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-21T10:06:35Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08288</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08288" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Scalable $k$-d trees for distributed data</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1642723200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chakravorty:Aritra.html">Aritra Chakravorty</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cleveland:William_S=.html">William S. Cleveland</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wolfe:Patrick_J=.html">Patrick J. Wolfe</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08288">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Data structures known as $k$-d trees have numerous applications in scientific
computing, particularly in areas of modern statistics and data science such as
range search in decision trees, clustering, nearest neighbors search, local
regression, and so forth. In this article we present a scalable mechanism to
construct $k$-d trees for distributed data, based on approximating medians for
each recursive subdivision of the data. We provide theoretical guarantees of
the quality of approximation using this approach, along with a simulation study
quantifying the accuracy and scalability of our proposed approach in practice.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-21T22:42:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08279</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08279" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Modeling and hexahedral meshing of arterial networks from centerlines</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1642723200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Decroocq:M=eacute=ghane.html">Méghane Decroocq</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Frindel:Carole.html">Carole Frindel</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Ohta:Makoto.html">Makoto Ohta</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lavou=eacute=:Guillaume.html">Guillaume Lavoué</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08279">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Computational fluid dynamics (CFD) simulation provides valuable information
on blood flow from the vascular geometry. However, it requires to extract
accurate models of arteries from low resolution medical images, which remains
challenging. Centerline-based representation is widely used to model large
vascular networks with small vessels, as it enables manual editing and encodes
the topological information. In this work, we propose an automatic method to
generate an hexahedral mesh suitable for CFD directly from centerlines. The
proposed method is an improvement of the state-of-the-art in terms of
robustness, mesh quality and reproductibility.
</p>
<p>Both the modeling and meshing tasks are addressed. A new vessel model based
on penalized splines is proposed to overcome the limitations inherent to the
centerline representation, such as noise and sparsity. Bifurcations are
reconstructed using a physiologically accurate parametric model that we
extended to planar n-furcations. Finally, a volume mesh with structured,
hexahedral and flow oriented cells is produced from the proposed vascular
network model.
</p>
<p>The proposed method offers a better robustness and mesh quality than the
state-of-the-art methods. As it combines both modeling and meshing techniques,
it can be applied to edit the geometry and topology of vascular models
effortlessly to study the impact on hemodynamics. We demonstrate the efficiency
of our method by entirely meshing a dataset of 60 cerebral vascular networks.
92\% of the vessels and 83\% of the bifurcations where mesh without defects
needing manual intervention, despite the challenging aspect of the input data.
The source code will be released publicly.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-21T22:50:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08225</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08225" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Exact learning for infinite families of concepts</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1642723200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Moshkov:Mikhail.html">Mikhail Moshkov</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08225">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, based on results of exact learning, test theory, and rough set
theory, we study arbitrary infinite families of concepts each of which consists
of an infinite set of elements and an infinite set of subsets of this set
called concepts. We consider the notion of a problem over a family of concepts
that is described by a finite number of elements: for a given concept, we
should recognize which of the elements under consideration belong to this
concept. As algorithms for problem solving, we consider decision trees of five
types: (i) using membership queries, (ii) using equivalence queries, (iii)
using both membership and equivalence queries, (iv) using proper equivalence
queries, and (v) using both membership and proper equivalence queries. As time
complexity, we study the depth of decision trees. In the worst case, with the
growth of the number of elements in the problem description, the minimum depth
of decision trees of the first type either grows as a logarithm or linearly,
and the minimum depth of decision trees of each of the other types either is
bounded from above by a constant or grows as a logarithm, or linearly. The
obtained results allow us to distinguish seven complexity classes of infinite
families of concepts.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-21T22:38:16Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08207</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08207" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Invasion Dynamics in the Biased Voter Process</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1642723200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Loke Durocher, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Karras:Panagiotis.html">Panagiotis Karras</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pavlogiannis:Andreas.html">Andreas Pavlogiannis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tkadlec:Josef.html">Josef Tkadlec</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08207">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The voter process is a classic stochastic process that models the invasion of
a mutant trait $A$ (e.g., a new opinion, belief, legend, genetic mutation,
magnetic spin) in a population of agents (e.g., people, genes, particles) who
share a resident trait $B$, spread over the nodes of a graph. An agent may
adopt the trait of one of its neighbors at any time, while the invasion bias
$r\in(0,\infty)$ quantifies the stochastic preference towards ($r&gt;1$) or
against ($r&lt;1$) adopting $A$ over $B$. Success is measured in terms of the
fixation probability, i.e., the probability that eventually all agents have
adopted the mutant trait $A$. In this paper we study the problem of fixation
probability maximization under this model: given a budget $k$, find a set of
$k$ agents to initiate the invasion that maximizes the fixation probability. We
show that the problem is NP-hard for both $r&gt;1$ and $r&lt;1$, while the latter
case is also inapproximable within any multiplicative factor. On the positive
side, we show that when $r&gt;1$, the optimization function is submodular and thus
can be greedily approximated within a factor $1-1/e$. An experimental
evaluation of some proposed heuristics corroborates our results.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08118</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08118" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Interval-Memoized Backtracking on ZDDs for Fast Enumeration of All Lower Cost Solutions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1642723200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Minato:Shin=ichi.html">Shin-ichi Minato</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Banbara:Mutsunori.html">Mutsunori Banbara</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Horiyama:Takashi.html">Takashi Horiyama</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kawahara:Jun.html">Jun Kawahara</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Takigawa:Ichigaku.html">Ichigaku Takigawa</a>, Yutaro Yamaguchi <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08118">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In many real-life situations, we are often faced with combinatorial problems
under linear cost functions. In this paper, we propose a fast method for
exactly enumerating a very large number of all lower cost solutions for various
combinatorial problems. Our method is based on backtracking for a given
decision diagram which represents the feasible solutions of a problem. The main
idea is to memoize the intervals of cost bounds to avoid duplicate search in
the backtracking process. Although existing state-of-the-art methods with
dynamic programming requires a pseudo-polynomial time with the total cost
values, it may take an exponential time when the cost values become large. In
contrast, the computation time of the proposed method does not directly depend
on the total cost values, but is bounded by the input and output size of the
decision diagrams. Therefore, it can be much faster than the existing methods
if the cost values are large but the output of the decision diagrams are
well-compressed. Our experimental results show that, for some practical
instances of the Hamiltonian path problem, we succeeded in exactly enumerating
billions of all lower cost solutions in a few seconds, which is hundred or more
times faster than existing methods. Our method can be regarded as a novel
search algorithm which integrates the two classical techniques,
branch-and-bound and dynamic programming. This method would have many
applications in various fields, including operations research, data mining,
statistical testing, hardware/software system design, etc.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-21T22:49:08Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08005</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.08005" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>FreSCo: Mining Frequent Patterns in Simplicial Complexes</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1642723200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Preti:Giulia.html">Giulia Preti</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Morales:Gianmarco_De_Francisci.html">Gianmarco De Francisci Morales</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bonchi:Francesco.html">Francesco Bonchi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.08005">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Simplicial complexes are a generalization of graphs that model higher-order
relations. In this paper, we introduce simplicial patterns -- that we call
simplets -- and generalize the task of frequent pattern mining from the realm
of graphs to that of simplicial complexes. Our task is particularly challenging
due to the enormous search space and the need for higher-order isomorphism. We
show that finding the occurrences of simplets in a complex can be reduced to a
bipartite graph isomorphism problem, in linear time and at most quadratic
space. We then propose an anti-monotonic frequency measure that allows us to
start the exploration from small simplets and stop expanding a simplet as soon
as its frequency falls below the minimum frequency threshold. Equipped with
these ideas and a clever data structure, we develop a memory-conscious
algorithm that, by carefully exploiting the relationships among the simplices
in the complex and among the simplets, achieves efficiency and scalability for
our complex mining task. Our algorithm, FreSCo, comes in two flavors: it can
compute the exact frequency of the simplets or, more quickly, it can determine
whether a simplet is frequent, without having to compute the exact frequency.
Experimental results prove the ability of FreSCo to mine frequent simplets in
complexes of various size and dimension, and the significance of the simplets
with respect to the traditional graph patterns.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-21T22:39:09Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.07834</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.07834" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Adaptive B\'ezier Degree Reduction and Splitting for Computationally Efficient Motion Planning</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1642723200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Arslan:=Ouml=m=uuml=r.html">Ömür Arslan</a>, Aron Tiemessen <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07834">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>As a parametric polynomial curve family, B\'ezier curves are widely used in
safe and smooth motion design of intelligent robotic systems from flying drones
to autonomous vehicles to robotic manipulators. In such motion planning
settings, the critical features of high-order B\'ezier curves such as curve
length, distance-to-collision, maximum curvature/velocity/acceleration are
either numerically computed at a high computational cost or inexactly
approximated by discrete samples. To address these issues, in this paper we
present a novel computationally efficient approach for adaptive approximation
of high-order B\'ezier curves by multiple low-order B\'ezier segments at any
desired level of accuracy that is specified in terms of a B\'ezier metric.
Accordingly, we introduce a new B\'ezier degree reduction method, called
parameterwise matching reduction, that approximates B\'ezier curves more
accurately compared to the standard least squares and Taylor reduction methods.
We also propose a new B\'ezier metric, called the maximum control-point
distance, that can be computed analytically, has a strong equivalence relation
with other existing B\'ezier metrics, and defines a geometric relative bound
between B\'ezier curves. We provide extensive numerical evidence to demonstrate
the effectiveness of our proposed B\'ezier approximation approach. As a rule of
thumb, based on the degree-one matching reduction error, we conclude that an
$n^\text{th}$-order B\'ezier curve can be accurately approximated by $3(n-1)$
quadratic and $6(n-1)$ linear B\'ezier segments, which is fundamental for
B\'ezier discretization.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-21T22:51:12Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.07204</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.07204" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dynamical Dorfman Testing with Quarantine</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1642723200</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Doger:Mustafa.html">Mustafa Doger</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/u/Ulukus:Sennur.html">Sennur Ulukus</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.07204">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider dynamical group testing problem with a community structure. With
a discrete-time SIR (susceptible, infectious, recovered) model, we use
Dorfman's two-step group testing approach to identify infections, and step in
whenever necessary to inhibit infection spread via quarantines. We analyze the
trade-off between quarantine and test costs as well as disease spread. For the
special dynamical i.i.d. model, we show that the optimal first stage Dorfman
group size differs in dynamic and static cases. We compare the performance of
the proposed dynamic two-stage Dorfman testing with state-of-the-art
non-adaptive group testing method in dynamic settings.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-21T22:42:32Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19548</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/20/dinner-drinks-denominators/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dinner! Drinks! Denominators!</title>
    <summary>Mathematics is only a systematic effort of solving puzzles posed by nature—Shakuntala Devi. source—note MoMath cap Peter Winkler is featured in the current issue of the New Yorker magazine. Peter is a famous Dartmouth mathematics professor. He is an expert on math puzzles, both for making them and solving them—see his book, simply titled Mathematical […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Mathematics is only a systematic effort of solving puzzles posed by nature—Shakuntala Devi.</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/20/dinner-drinks-denominators/peter/" rel="attachment wp-att-19550"><img alt="" class="alignright size-full wp-image-19550" height="208" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/peter.png?resize=147%2C208&amp;ssl=1" width="147"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2"><a href="https://art19.com/shows/the-sydcast/episodes/18162392-6c05-4727-a8e9-57df23b28e30">source</a>—note MoMath cap</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Peter Winkler is featured in the current issue of the <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2022/01/17/dinner-drinks-denominators">New Yorker</a> magazine. Peter is a famous Dartmouth mathematics professor. He is an expert on math puzzles, both for making them and solving them—see his <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Mathematical_Puzzles/XWwNEAAAQBAJ?hl=en">book</a>, simply titled <em>Mathematical Puzzles</em>.</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/20/dinner-drinks-denominators/mathpuzzlescover/" rel="attachment wp-att-19552"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19552" height="162" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/MathPuzzlesCover.jpg?resize=105%2C162&amp;ssl=1" width="105"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p/><p><br/>
A recent evening of mathematical dinner theater hosted by Peter is the subject of the article, which is by <a href="https://faculty-directory.dartmouth.edu/daniel-rockmore">Dan Rockmore</a>, also of the Dartmouth math department. This event was co-coordinated by <a href="https://momath.org/cindy-lawrence/">Cindy Lawrence</a>, who is executive director of the National Museum of Mathematics:</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/20/dinner-drinks-denominators/cl/" rel="attachment wp-att-19554"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19554" height="241" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/cl.jpg?resize=315%2C241&amp;ssl=1" width="315"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2"><a href="https://www.6sqft.com/spotlight-momaths-executive-director-cindy-lawrence-makes-math-fun-and-interactive/">source</a> (malfunctioned for us)</font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p/><p><br/>
The event was attended by a group of investors, economists. and teachers in a suitable alcove of a restaurant in Manhattan.  Quoting Rockmore’s article:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Winkler began the evening’s program. The first course of math, delivered during the first course of dinner (a scattering of salads), was a statistics starter called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simpson's_paradox">Simpson’s paradox</a>. The paradox explains how apparent biases in large samples can disappear in smaller ones. A famous example: For the University of California at Berkeley’s graduate programs in 1975, over all, men were admitted at a higher rate than women, but, program by program, women were admitted at a higher rate. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
About Berkeley, see <a href="https://www.refsmmat.com/posts/2016-05-08-simpsons-paradox-berkeley.html">this</a> first. We covered Simpson’s paradox <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2014/01/30/global-warming/">here</a>. The article goes on the mention the famous trick of how a biased coin can be made to simulate a fair coin by tossing it twice, and continues:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Winkler let loose with the last official mind bender, a gambling thought experiment involving a fictitious couple named Alice and Bob, who are famous in math circles. Each of them has a biased coin—fifty-one-per-cent chance of heads, forty-nine-per-cent chance of tails. They each start with a hundred dollars, flipping the coin and betting against the bank on the outcome. Alice calls heads every time; Bob calls tails. The puzzle: Given that they both go broke, which one is more likely to have gone broke first? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The article relates that most diners guessed Bob, but the correct answer is Alice. Former Times math and science columnist John Tierney, a serious enough math fan to have remarked once that the term “recreational mathematics” is a self-contradiction, reasoned it out: “The longer Alice plays, the less likely she is to go broke.” We finish Tierney’s intent by contraposing: hence given that she too went broke, the more likely it was she that played less time.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Old Friend </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Peter is a long time friend of mine. See him in action <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jg6XZcNAgrw">here</a>. He is a delight to talk to about many things—just about any part of math. </p>
<p>
Peter has a <a href="https://math.dartmouth.edu/~pw/solutions.pdf">paper</a> with the title, “Seven Puzzles You Think You Must Not Have Heard Correctly.” I had already started writing this post when I looked up this paper to get a few more puzzle examples. I found this one:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> #4 <b>Unwanted Expansion:</b> <br/>
Suppose you have an algebraic expression involving variables, addition, multiplication, and parentheses. You repeatedly attempt to expand it using the distributive law. How do you know that the expression doesn’t continue to expand forever? Comment: Note that applying the distributive law to, say, the outer product in <img alt="{(x + y)(s(u + v) + t)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x+%2B+y%29%28s%28u+%2B+v%29+%2B+t%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, yields <img alt="{x(s(u + v) + t) + y(s(u + v) + t)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%28s%28u+%2B+v%29+%2B+t%29+%2B+y%28s%28u+%2B+v%29+%2B+t%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> which has more parentheses than before. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>I thought about this for a little. Then I looked up the answer. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> One can analyze the expression in terms of depth of trees, but there’s an easier way: set all the variables equal to 2. The point of the distributive law is that its application doesn’t change the value of the expression. The value of the initial expression limits the size of anything you can get from it by expansion. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Peter then says: <i>This proof of stopping is due to Dick Lipton.</i> I must say that surprised me. I am getting old. Oops.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Let’s end with a fun puzzle about the dictionary that is also mentioned in the <em>New Yorker</em> article.</p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/20/dinner-drinks-denominators/dictionary/" rel="attachment wp-att-19556"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19556" height="156" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/dictionary.jpg?resize=240%2C156&amp;ssl=1" width="240"/></a></p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> If each number between one and ten billion was written down in English, which odd number would appear first alphabetically? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Given that spaces do not count, here is the <a href="https://puzzleaday.wordpress.com/2018/10/05/what-is-the-first-odd-number-in-the-dictionary/">answer</a>. The last part changes because the number must be odd. If spaces do count—as in many dictionaries of phrases—then what is the answer?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-20T17:30:07Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-20T17:30:07Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Teaching"/>
    <category term="trick"/>
    <category term="Cindy Lawrence"/>
    <category term="coin puzzles"/>
    <category term="Dan Rockmore"/>
    <category term="Museum of Mathematics"/>
    <category term="New Yorker"/>
    <category term="Peter Winkler"/>
    <category term="puzzles"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:44Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/20/research-associate-postdoc-at-the-university-of-edinburgh-apply-by-february-18-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/20/research-associate-postdoc-at-the-university-of-edinburgh-apply-by-february-18-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Research Associate (postdoc) at the University of Edinburgh (apply by February 18, 2022)</title>
    <summary>Applications are invited for research associate positions in Algorithms and Complexity, funded by the European Research Council (ERC) starting grant “New Approaches to Counting and Sampling” (NACS), led by Dr. Heng Guo in the School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh. Website: https://elxw.fa.em3.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_1001/job/3010/ Email: hguo at inf.ed.ac.uk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Applications are invited for research associate positions in Algorithms and Complexity, funded by the European Research Council (ERC) starting grant “New Approaches to Counting and Sampling” (NACS), led by Dr. Heng Guo in the School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://elxw.fa.em3.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_1001/job/3010/">https://elxw.fa.em3.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_1001/job/3010/</a><br/>
Email: hguo at inf.ed.ac.uk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-20T15:21:25Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-20T15:21:25Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6232</id>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6232" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6232#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=6232" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Win a Scott Aaronson Speculation Grant!</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Exciting news, everyone! Jaan Tallinn, who many of you might recognize as a co-creator of Skype, tech enthusiast, and philanthropist, graciously invited me, along with a bunch of other nerds, to join the new Speculation Grants program of the Survival and Flourishing Fund (SFF). In plain language, that means that Jaan is giving me $200,000 […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Exciting news, everyone!  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaan_Tallinn">Jaan Tallinn</a>, who many of you might recognize as a co-creator of Skype, tech enthusiast, and philanthropist, graciously invited me, along with a bunch of other nerds, to join the new <a href="https://survivalandflourishing.fund/speculation-grants">Speculation Grants</a> program of the <a href="https://survivalandflourishing.fund/">Survival and Flourishing Fund (SFF)</a>.  In plain language, that means that Jaan is <strong>giving me $200,000 to distribute to charitable organizations in any way I see fit</strong>—though ideally, my choices will have <em>something</em> to do with the survival and flourishing of our planet and civilization.</p>



<p>(If all goes well, this blog post will actually lead to a lot <em>more</em> than just $200,000 in donations, because it will inspire applications to SFF that can then be funded by other “Speculators” or by SFF’s usual process.)</p>



<p>Thinking about how to handle the responsibility of this amazing and unexpected gift, I decided that I couldn’t possibly improve on what Scott Alexander did with his <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/acx-grants-results">personal grants program</a> on <em>Astral Codex Ten</em>.  Thus: I hereby invite the readers of <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em> to pitch registered charities (which might or might not be their own)—especially, charities that are relatively small, unknown, and unappreciated, yet that would resonate strongly with someone who thinks the way I do.  Feel free to renominate (i.e., bring back to my attention) charities that were mentioned when I <a href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=5448">asked a similar question</a> after winning $250,000 from the ACM Prize in Computing.</p>



<p>If you’re interested, there’s a two-step process this time:</p>



<p><strong>Step 1</strong> is to make your pitch to me, either by a comment on this post or by email to me, depending on whether you’d prefer the pitch to be public or private.  Let’s set a deadline for this step of <strong>Thursday, January 27, 2022</strong> (i.e., one week from now).  Your pitch can be extremely short, like 1 paragraph, although I might ask you followup questions.  After January 27, I’ll then take one of two actions in response: I’ll either</p>



<p>(a) commit a specified portion of my $200,000 to your charity, <em>if</em> the charity formally applies to SFF, and <em>if</em> the charity isn’t excluded for some unexpected reason (5 sexual harassment lawsuits against its founders or whatever), and <em>if</em> one of my fellow “Speculators” doesn’t fund your charity before I do … or else I’ll</p>



<p>(b) not commit, in which case your charity <strong>can still apply</strong> for funding from SFF!  One of the other Speculators might fund it, or it might be funded by the “ordinary” SFF process.</p>



<p><strong>Step 2</strong>, which <strong>cannot</strong> be skipped, is then to have your charity <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSc4PRBIP8CNCviFiNkSSMKy6Ms3sUJBOi_ykE8IDvTeB5Nr_A/viewform">submit a formal application</a> to SFF.  The application form isn’t too bad.  But if the charity isn’t your own, it would help enormously if you at least <em>knew</em> someone at the charity, so you could tell them to apply to SFF.  Again, Step 2 can be taken regardless of the outcome of Step 1.</p>



<p>The one big rule is that anything you suggest has to be a registered, tax-exempt charity in either the US or the UK.  I won’t be distributing funds myself, but only advising SFF how to do so, and this is SFF’s rule, not mine.  So alas, no political advocacy groups and no individuals.  Donating to groups outside the US and UK is apparently possible but difficult.</p>



<p>While I’m not putting any restrictions on the scope, let me list a few examples of areas of interest to me.</p>



<ul><li>Advanced math and science education at the precollege level: gifted programs, summer camps, online resources, or anything, really, that aims to ensure that the next Ramanujan or von Neumann isn’t lost to the world.</li><li>Conservation of endangered species.</li><li>Undervalued approaches to dealing with the climate catastrophe (including new approaches to nuclear energy, geoengineering, and carbon capture and storage … or even, e.g., studies of the effects of rising CO<sub>2</sub> on cognition and how to mitigate them).</li><li>Undervalued approaches to preventing or mitigating future pandemics—basically, anything dirt-cheap that we <em>wish</em> had been done before covid.</li><li>Almost anything that <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/acx-grants-results">Scott Alexander might have funded</a> if he’d had more money.</li><li>Anything that would enrage the SneerClubbers or those who attack me on Twitter, by doing stuff that even <em>they</em> would have to acknowledge makes the world better, but that does so via people, organizations, and means that they despise.</li></ul>



<p>Two examples of areas that I <em>don’t</em> plan to focus on are:</p>



<ul><li>AI-risk and other “strongly rationalist-flavored” organizations (these are already well-covered by others at SFF, so that I don’t expect to have an advantage), and</li><li>quantum computing research (this is already funded by a zillion government agencies, companies, and venture capitalists).</li></ul>



<p>Anyway, thanks so much to Jaan and to SFF for giving me this incredible opportunity, and I look forward to seeing what y’all come up with!</p>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Note:</span></strong> Any other philanthropists who read this blog, and who’d like to add to the amount, are more than welcome to do so!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-20T14:42:16Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-20T14:42:16Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Contests"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <icon>https://scottaaronson.blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-Jacket-32x32.gif</icon>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T01:15:09Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/19/tenure-track-assistant-professor-in-algorithms-at-university-of-vienna-apply-by-january-24-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/19/tenure-track-assistant-professor-in-algorithms-at-university-of-vienna-apply-by-january-24-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure-track assistant professor in algorithms at University of Vienna (apply by January 24, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The department of Computer Science at the University of Vienna invites applications for a tenure-track assistant professor position in algorithms. The starting date is negotiable. Website: https://univis.univie.ac.at/ausschreibungstellensuche/flow/bew_ausschreibung-flow?_flowExecutionKey=_c0BC6DB4A-6047-8758-BA4B-005110088D19_k7DD77CC1-13FE-009B-5AB9-3185BE466C0D&amp;tid=88323.28 Email: monika.henzinger@univie.ac.at</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The department of Computer Science at the University of Vienna invites applications for a tenure-track assistant professor position in algorithms. The starting date is negotiable.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://univis.univie.ac.at/ausschreibungstellensuche/flow/bew_ausschreibung-flow?_flowExecutionKey=_c0BC6DB4A-6047-8758-BA4B-005110088D19_k7DD77CC1-13FE-009B-5AB9-3185BE466C0D&amp;tid=88323.28">https://univis.univie.ac.at/ausschreibungstellensuche/flow/bew_ausschreibung-flow?_flowExecutionKey=_c0BC6DB4A-6047-8758-BA4B-005110088D19_k7DD77CC1-13FE-009B-5AB9-3185BE466C0D&amp;tid=88323.28</a><br/>
Email: monika.henzinger@univie.ac.at</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-19T12:45:26Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-19T12:45:26Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/19/postdoctoral-researcher-at-george-mason-university-apply-by-january-31-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/19/postdoctoral-researcher-at-george-mason-university-apply-by-january-31-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral Researcher at George Mason University (apply by January 31, 2022)</title>
    <summary>Postdoctoral position available starting Fall’22. Want to do bold cutting-edge research on the foundations of Algorithms/AI/ML? Interested in living in the Washington, DC area? Shoot me your CV. Soft deadline: Jan 31. Website: https://www.linkedin.com/jobs/view/2879807616/ Email: grigory@grigory.us</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Postdoctoral position available starting Fall’22. Want to do bold cutting-edge research on the foundations of Algorithms/AI/ML? Interested in living in the Washington, DC area? Shoot me your CV. Soft deadline: Jan 31.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/jobs/view/2879807616/">https://www.linkedin.com/jobs/view/2879807616/</a><br/>
Email: grigory@grigory.us</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-19T00:20:35Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-19T00:20:35Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/009</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/009" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-009 |  On Finer Separations between Subclasses of Read-once Oblivious ABPs | 

	C. Ramya, 

	Anamay Tengse</title>
    <summary>Read-once Oblivious Algebraic Branching Programs (ROABPs) compute polynomials as products of univariate polynomials that have matrices as coefficients. In an attempt to understand the landscape of algebraic complexity classes surrounding ROABPs, we study classes of ROABPs based on the algebraic structure of these coefficient matrices. We study connections between polynomials computed by these structured variants of ROABPs and other well-known classes of polynomials (such as depth-three powering circuits, tensor-rank and Waring rank of polynomials).

Our main result concerns commutative ROABPs, where all coefficient matrices commute with each other, and diagonal ROABPs, where all the coefficient matrices are just diagonal matrices. In particular, we show a somewhat surprising connection between these models and the model of depth-three powering circuits that is related to the Waring rank of polynomials. We show that if the dimension of partial derivatives captures Waring rank up to polynomial factors, then the model of diagonal ROABPs efficiently simulates the seemingly more expressive model of commutative ROABPs. Further, a commutative ROABP that cannot be efficiently simulated by a diagonal ROABP will give an explicit polynomial that gives a super-polynomial separation between dimension of partial derivatives and Waring rank.

Our proof of the above result builds on the results of Marinari, Möller and Mora (1993), and Möller and Stetter (1995), that characterise rings of commuting matrices in terms of polynomials that have small dimension of partial derivatives. The algebraic structure of the coefficient matrices of these ROABPs plays a crucial role in our proofs.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-18T09:42:14Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-18T09:42:14Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19527</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/17/zoom-workshop-e-minder-4pm-et-today/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Zoom Workshop E-Minder: 4pm ET Today</title>
    <summary>And a place to look for fallback info in case things go wrong This is a deviation from the “blog invariants” that were maintained for 1,000 posts. We’ll be happy to have suggestions for style changes and general ideas going forward. Here were the open links for the workshop. Rewritten afterward: Things went smoothly, despite […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>And a place to look for fallback info in case things go wrong</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p>
This is a deviation from the “blog invariants” that were maintained for 1,000 posts.  We’ll be happy to have suggestions for style changes and general ideas going forward. </p>
<p>
Here <i>were</i> the open links for the workshop.  <b>Rewritten afterward:</b> Things went smoothly, despite even my “Heisenberg” feeling of uncertainty about whether I had altered the setup by testing the links beforehand.  Dick’s talk for Princeton’s 2012 Turing <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2012/05/17/turings-tiger-birthday-party/">centennial</a> included among “Grand Challenges” getting AV equipment for lectures to work—well Zoom etc. are a decade-later evolution of that.</p>
<p>
Again we thank all who spoke—note the enlarged list of speakers in the original <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/14/happy-1000th-post-and-75th-birthday-dick/">post</a>.  We will do some combination of a curated video and followup blog post(s).</p>
<p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>
This is post <b>7*11*13</b> = <b>1001</b>.  The passcode—which should not be needed—remains 111317.  Looking forward to a fun session, and thanks again to all speakers and other visitors.</p>
<p>
[added update]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-17T17:44:29Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-17T17:44:29Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="1001st post"/>
    <category term="4pmET today"/>
    <category term="anniversary"/>
    <category term="GLL"/>
    <category term="Richard Lipton"/>
    <category term="workshop"/>
    <author>
      <name>KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/01/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/01/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>You can find plenty of online stories celebrating the release into the public domain of Winnie the Pooh (text, not film), Hemingway’s The Sun Also Rises, etc. But the situation for Ludwig Wittgenstein is more complicated. All his own writing is now public domain in life+70 countries, but the work of later editors might not be. Michele Lavazza explains (\(\mathbb{M}\), via).</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p>You can find <a href="https://boingboing.net/2022/01/01/winnie-the-pooh-is-now-officially-public-domain.html">plenty of online stories</a> celebrating the release into the public domain of Winnie the Pooh (text, not film), Hemingway’s The Sun Also Rises, etc. But the situation for Ludwig Wittgenstein is more complicated. All his own writing is now public domain in life+70 countries, but the work of later editors might not be. <a href="https://www.wittgensteinproject.org/w/index.php?title=Project:Why_are_some_of_Wittgenstein%E2%80%99s_texts_missing_from_this_website%3F">Michele Lavazza explains</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107549495811533662">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=29760747">via</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CW0z3zZAlZU/">Math rock</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107554494911062896">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://boingboing.net/2022/01/02/the-breathtakingly-gorgeous-work-of-french-comic-artist-jordi-lafebre.html">via</a>), Jordi Lefebre.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_abelian_group">Free abelian group</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107557410158230373">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> now a Good Article at Wikipedia. This concept may seem trivial at first, wrapped in unnecessary formalism. But these things come up in a lot of seemingly-unrelated contexts: multiplication of rational numbers, addition of integer polynomials, lattices in the geometry of numbers, chains in homology theory, and divisors in algebraic geometry. I worried that its technicality might make it hard to pass GA but fortunately I got a sympathetic reviewer.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/05/quantum-graph-theory/">Quantum graph theory</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107571090684894770">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span> what happens when qubits have pairwise entanglements described by some graph? And which graphs can be transformed into each other by local quantum operations? Ken Regan explains.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.atlasobscura.com/places/gomboc">Giant weeble in a Budapest plaza</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107574673412832258">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2022/01/gomboc.html">via</a>): it wobbles but it won’t fall down. But unlike the childhood toy, it does it despite being of uniform density, because of its special shape, rather than by having a much denser weight near one end. It’s theorized that tortoises have evolved a similar shape so that they can automatically right themselves. For more mathematical details, see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6mb%C3%B6c">Gömböc on Wikipedia</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.flyingcoloursmaths.co.uk/the-dictionary-of-mathematical-eponymy-the-laves-graph/">Dictionary of mathematical eponymy: The Laves Graph</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107580283699756452">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> I did a lot of work in 2014 on this topic in Wikipedia, but it evidently needs more editing for accessibility. I did not know the part about Laves being sent to the army because the Nazis viewed him as sympathetic to Jews, and then pulled into a secret project to develop unobtanium for Göring, guarded by an alchemist who helpfully insisted on adding lizard bones to the alloys and dangling crystal spheres over them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Our quarter started this week, online through Zoom, accessed in Canvas <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107585920689338985">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> To set it up I have to:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Find and navigate to another site in which I can request a Canvas site, but get redirected to the campus login page, where I have to hand-type my name and password, then get to a page to choose my two-factor authentication, select the phone option on that page, find and unlock my phone, and find and approve the two-factor authentication request on my phone</li>
      <li>Back at the site to request a Canvas site, use it to actually request a Canvas site; this does not actually create the site, but rather puts it into a queue to be processed one or two hours later</li>
      <li>Once the site is created, navigate to Canvas, going through all the same campus login steps first.</li>
      <li>Search the web for the <a href="https://sites.uci.edu/teachanywhere/home/tools/zoom/">campus page on how to enable Zoom</a>, because the steps to do so are not simple or obvious enough to remember, and neither is the location of the campus page.</li>
      <li>Follow the five non-obvious steps on that page for adding Zoom to a Canvas site.</li>
      <li>Go to the new Zoom tab of my new Canvas site where I still have to go through all of the usual Zoom things to schedule a meeting that repeats weekly but only for some of the weekdays (many more steps).</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Someone else in the discussion said that to manage their online classes they have to go through seven different web sites; my count is not nearly that high. Whatever happened to the science of user-friendly interfaces?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2021/04/14/guest-post-an-early-look-at-the-impact-of-the-chinese-academy-of-sciences-journals-warning-list/">An early look at the impact of the Chinese Academy of Sciences journals warning list</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107591437363977756">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> The CAS list does not seem helpful as a tool for identifying specific journals as predatory, because it lists so few, and one has to filter for  political motivation, but maybe it can still find patterns of bad publishing practices. I wasn’t particularly surprised to see MDPI and Hindawi high on their hit list, but the presence of a major IEEE journal (IEEE Access) was more interesting.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.combinatoire.ca/ArsCombinatoria/index.html">The new web site of the journal <em>Ars Combinatoria</em></a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107593800163410461">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> after the old site got taken over by gambling spammers. Thanks to Jannis Harder for finding it for me by tracing through DNS history and trying its old IP address; it wasn’t coming up on searches and I wouldn’t have thought of doing that. Despite being found again, the journal may be in trouble: MathSciNet doesn’t list anything from them in 2021 and the new site says that as of December 2021 the entire editorial board has resigned (with no explanation other than “ask the publisher”).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CslIgQvbx0U">Short video of curve-folded squishable paper helix by Richard Sweeney</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107602947906293833">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/2022/01/richard-sweeney-paper-sculpture/">via</a>). <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2015/01/31/linkage.html">Sweeney, previously</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://igorpak.wordpress.com/2022/01/09/the-insidious-corruption-of-open-access-publishers/">The insidious corruption of open access publishers</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107608628939783540">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span> Igor Pak looks at predatory publishing and MDPI through a deep examination of MDPI’s journal <em>Mathematics</em>. Ultimately he concludes that it is not actually a predatory journal, but that doesn’t mean that he thinks it is doing good work. Instead, he favors diamond open-access and in particular arXiv-overlay journals.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/2022/01/david-rivillo-pasta/">Colorful geometric designs for pasta interact interestingly with the pasta’s intricate shapes</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107613972021621156">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> by David Rivillo.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematicians-clear-hurdle-in-quest-to-decode-prime-numbers-20220113/">Typical incoherence from <em>Quanta</em>’s attempts at making mathematics accessible</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107616481712855051">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span> “the Riemann hypothesis says that the Riemann zeta function equals zero whenever the real part of \(s\) equals \(\tfrac12\)”. No. No, it doesn’t.  Fortunately they fixed it quickly. The actual result in question concerns proving better-than-trivial growth rate on the critical line of \(L\)-functions; see “Bounds for standard \(L\)-functions”, Paul D. Nelson, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.15230">arXiv:2109.15230</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://cp4space.hatsya.com/2022/01/14/conway-conjecture-settled/">An unconstructable still life in Conway’s Game of Life</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107621849707591699">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> The configuration shown in the link is stable (if its boundary is stabilized appropriately) but, if it appears in any pattern, it must always have been that way, in all predecessors of the pattern. As such, it answers the question “can every still life be constructed by gliders?” negatively.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="http://www.science.smith.edu/~jorourke/PopUps/">Pop-Up Geometry: The Mathematics behind Pop-Up Cards</a></em> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107629200040843502">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> new book by Joe O’Rourke, to appear this year. The link goes to Joe’s web site for the book. I haven’t yet seen the actual book, but it looks likely to be very interesting.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-15T23:02:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-15T23:02:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2022-01-16T07:04:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19500</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/14/happy-1000th-post-and-75th-birthday-dick/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Happy 1,000th Post and 75th Birthday, Dick</title>
    <summary>Plus an open Zoom mini-workshop Monday 1/17, 4–5:30pm ET From Rich DeMillo Richard Lipton founded this blog 1,000 posts ago. He was not quite as young as in the photo. This blog is almost 13 years old but measures time by the count of posts. Time itself occurs only between posts. Unlike what we said […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Plus an open Zoom mini-workshop Monday 1/17, 4–5:30pm ET</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/14/happy-1000th-post-and-75th-birthday-dick/rjl1980scropped/" rel="attachment wp-att-19502"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-19502" height="160" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/RJL1980scropped.png?resize=200%2C160&amp;ssl=1" width="200"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">From Rich DeMillo</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Richard Lipton founded this blog 1,000 posts ago. He was not quite as young as in the photo. This blog is almost 13 years old but measures time by the count of posts. Time itself occurs only between posts. Unlike what we said <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2018/03/14/happy-0x50th-birthday-donald-knuth/">here</a> about counting birthdays, we are counting “1,000 posts ago” correctly—because the blog was created before the first post with the <em>pages</em> one can click on above.</p>
<p>
Today we—including many from the community—also salute Dick’s 75th birthday.</p>
<p>
The birthday was last September 6. A year ago, I thought the anniversaries could be made to coincide, but the time between posts flowed heavily. Much as a ship captain’s personal attributes become vested in the ship, I felt the birthday could best be hailed at the blog milestone. In this we take after the Queen of England. Elizabeth Windsor was born on April 21 (1926), but follows the centuries-old royal custom of celebrating the birthday in late spring. </p>
<p>
It has been my great pleasure to know Dick for 35 years in-person and several years before that through his papers. His STOC 1980 <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/221590666_The_Consistency_of_P_NP_and_Related_Problems_with_Fragments_of_Number_Theory">paper</a> with Rich DeMillo on the possible independence of P versus NP influenced me to focus on systems of logic as a graduate student. We talked most at STACS 1994 in Caen, France, and this led to a <a href="https://miami.pure.elsevier.com/en/publications/communication-complexity-of-key-agreement-on-small-ranges">paper</a> with four others in the next STACS. I gave an invited talk at Dick’s 2008 birthday celebration workshop—of which more below—and this began our closer association the next year. Dick and the blog are a fount of ideas, and if I say I wish I had time to develop them all, the answer is that our readers are always freely welcome to do so.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Elevator Workshop </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
It is also my delight to have a slate of volunteer speakers for a <b>mini-workshop</b> this coming <b>Monday</b> (Martin Luther King Day, <b>January 17</b>) starting at <b>4pm Eastern Time</b> (US). It will have the theme “Open Problems”—what else?—actually there is “else” as some of the brief talks will be personal notes or nuggets of work that influenced careers. It is open to the public—all readers are invited to attend on Monday via the following Zoom link.  <b>Update:</b> things worked fine, and I have removed the link…</p>
<p>
…except to note that the passcode I made was 111317.  I intended the passcode to be the three primes that multiply to <b>1,001</b>, thinking of what comes next, but those three multiply to 2,431—way far ahead, but see Lance Fortnow’s comment below.  There is no “Waiting Room” and no restriction on when to come or go.</p>
<p>
Here are speakers who have volunteered so far—alphabetical except those in overseas time zones beginning with India will go first:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Subruk Kalyanasundaram <p/>
</li><li>
Ravi Kannan <p/>
</li><li>
Gil Kalai <p/>
</li><li>
Joel Ouaknine<p/>
</li><li>
Harry Buhrman <p/>
</li><li>
Jin-Yi Cai<p/>
</li><li>
Zvi Galil <p/>
</li><li>
Bill Gasarch <p/>
</li><li>
Mitsunori Ogihara <p/>
</li><li>
Rafail Ostrovsky<p/>
</li><li>
Atri Rudra <p/>
</li><li>
Santosh Vempala <p/>
</li><li>
Michael Wehar <p/>
</li><li>
Ryan Williams
</li></ul>
<p>
And possibly a few more. Among the open problems, some may be “Favorite Problems” and some “Formative Problems.” The latter means ones that can shape the field during the coming decade. They should be both important and <em>pliable</em>. The latter word is a pun: it means flexible, but we also mean something a beginning researcher can <em>ply</em> into a dissertation and early career. Computational complexity has many problems that seem to have become rigid, but its sideways growth shows pliable ones are out there. </p>
<p>
One of this blog’s first posts in February, 2009, was on conveying the key idea to solve a problem in the time of an <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/02/16/proofs-and-elevator-rides/">elevator pitch</a>. The same goes for the time to state a good problem. The talks, including pauses and time for questions, will aim to fit within an hour, or 90 minutes at most. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Some Well-Wishes </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I am also thankful to have the following well-wishes thus far from around the community, including several more fellow bloggers. </p>
<ul>
<li>
<b>Scott Aaronson</b>: Happy birthday Dick! Your results have been an inspiration to me, from DeMillo-Lipton in 1979 on the independence of P vs NP to self-testing of the permanent (which played a central role in my work on BosonSampling). I hear some of your students, like Avi Wigderson, have done OK stuff as well. I look forward to checking your blog for many years to come! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Andrew Appel</b>: I have <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/1676454">Massive Memories</a> of the decade and a half that we overlapped at Princeton, in which you were one of my mentors, explaining to me the ways of the world. When I arrived there from from my PhD it seemed like all the really senior professors (you among them) were celebrating their 40th birthdays. Very best wishes for your 75th. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Boaz Barak</b>: Congratulations to GLL for its 1,000th post and to Dick for his 75th birthday! Dick has done so much for computer science, including many works that have become part of our canon and shaped our “conventional wisdom.” And then with GLL both Ken and Dick have managed to inject fun and humanity into our technical field and also question some of that conventional wisdom itself. Looking forward to the next 1,000 posts! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Paul Beame</b>: Double congratulations, Dick! and congratulations to Ken, too. Through GLL you have helped foster a closer sense of community in our field. Your thought-provoking and informative posts and depth of engagement are inspirational.<p/>
</li><li>
<b>Avrim Blum</b>: Very happy 75th birthday, Dick! We are fortunate to have you in our field! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Harry Buhrman</b>: Congratulations to Dick on his birthday and edition 1,000 of this blog. For me it is also the 42nd birthday of the beautiful Karp-Lipton theorem which is one of my favourite theorems. Its quantum variants are still very relevant and are currently of importance in the quantum computing community. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Jin-Yi Cai</b>: My most sincere well wishes to Dick’s 75th birthday! You have been an inspiration to so many of us over many decades! And warm congratulations to your successful 1,000th post! Your blog GLL, now with Ken, has become a most important landmark in our community. (And will speak, as above.)<p/>
</li><li>
<b>Rich DeMillo</b>—see below. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>David Dobkin</b>—see below. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>David Eppstein</b>: Happy birthday, and congratulations on the 1,000th post! I always look forward to your posts, both for their clear explanations of difficult topics and for the way you lighten them up with the biographical parts. May you have many more excellent birthdays and posts.<p/>
</li><li>
<b>Ron Fagin</b>: I have always enjoyed the Gödel’s Lost Letter blog. In fact, I view it as an important part of my computer science experience! Congratulations, Dick and Ken, on the 1,000th post! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Lance Fortnow</b>: Congrats to Dick and Ken for their millenary post. Learned much about chess, leprechauns, and even some theory. Best wishes for the next 1,000. BTW, Bill Gasarch and I are at 2895 posts so you have some catching up to do. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Merrick Furst</b>: Dick, it’s been an incredible pleasure to work with you and play with you and be allies with you since we first met and became fast friends in the late 70’s.  What a long, strange, wonderfully complex trip it’s been.  Wishing you all the best and hope to find a way to see you sometime soon.<p/>
</li><li>
<b>Bill Gasarch</b>—will speak, as above. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Gil Kalai</b>—will speak, as above. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Subruk Kalyanasundaram</b>: I am delighted to see GLL complete 1,000 posts! Since its inception in February 2009, GLL has created and continues to exist in its own unique space. After putting up a handful of posts, Dick sent a few of us students an understated email that went something like “started a new blog. see if you like it.” At that time, I had no idea that Dick could keep it going for 1,000 posts. I was actively involved in proofreading posts in the first couple of years, but am still a regular reader. It was a privilege to see the posts a day or two before the rest of the world. GLL has been such a successful and popular blog, and wishing many many more exciting posts! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Richard Karp</b>: Dear Dick, It has been my good fortune to be your friend and collaborate with you over many years, especially during your Berkeley period. Gödel’s Last Letter has been a major source of information and insight for me, consistently demonstrating your virtuosity and the depth of your knowledge. Congratulations also to Kathryn for her support of your efforts, and to Ken for his fruitful partnership with you. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Andrea LaPaugh</b>: Dick, congratulations and the best of wishes as you celebrate your 1,000th GLL post and your 75th birthday! The great energy, insight and joy you bring to computational theory has been an inspiration to me and many others. May you enjoy your passion for theory, and life, for many years to come. (And more below.) <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Jonathan Lenchner</b>: Congratulations on the 1,000th posting to the GLL blog—an incredible go-to reference for the computational complexity community! It has been great to reconnect with Ken, who I first met through chess, over logic. Sending belated well wishes also to Dick on the occasion of his 75th birthday! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Harry Lewis</b>: Dick—Thank you for being the guy who always made TCS fun! There is no one who better exemplifies the principle that irreverence is key to the creative process. You have always had the gift of showing how seriously you took the questions of the field by taking their canonical answers so lightly. Your milestone sounds better in French, so I’ll paraphrase: Happy sixty-somethingth! And may you be forever young. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Daniel Lopresti</b>: Dick, I want to wish you a happy (belated) 75th birthday. Your deep and broad insights have had a tremendous impact on me and many of our colleagues in the field of computer science over the years. With warm regards, Dan Lopresti.<p/>
</li><li>
<b>Danupon Nanongkai</b>: About a decade ago, I had the privilege to learn about many exciting problems and insights from many meetings with Dick while I was his PhD student. That was when the Gödel’s Lost Letter blog started, and I am grateful that I can continue to learn by reading this blog. Congratulations on the 1,000th post and Dick’s 75th birthday! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Mitsunori Ogihara</b>—will speak, as above. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Rafail Ostrovsky</b>: My warmest congratulations to Dick and Kathryn on Dick’s birthday wishing Dick many more equally productive and healthy years to come and enjoy. GLL is a truly an inspiration to us all—big thank you to Dick and Ken for an amazing and always inspiring content. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Joel Ouaknine</b>: Thanks for the many many inspirational and insightful posts! I’ve learned more computer science and mathematics on GLL than in any other single source I can think of! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Vijaya Ramachandran</b>: As one of the Dick’s earlier Ph.D. students (graduating in 1983), I would like to offer Dick my best wishes for a very happy 75th birthday, and for many more years to come. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Atri Rudra</b>: I have always been and continue to be amazed by the frequency of posts on GLL especially given the mathematical depth of the exposition, which somehow still manages to be accessible to a wide audience. Here’s wishing to many more years of GLL posts being prolific!  <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Terence Tao</b>: Happy 1,000th post Dick! I very much appreciate the personal and inclusive style of mathematical storytelling that you bring to the mathematical blogging community. Look forward to the next 1,000. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Santosh Vempala</b>: My best wishes to Dick and many thanks to Dick and Ken for a 1,000 interesting posts! Here’s to the next 1,000. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Suresh Venkatasubramanian</b>: On the internet, last week is like 2 years ago. Or so it feels that way. While some of us are frantically trying to tweet our papers and TikTok our talks, it’s a testimonial to persistence and steadiness that GLL has reached its 1,000th <em>blog</em> post (although I would subscribe to a TikTok live feed of Ken and Dick composing their latest post). GLL is an oasis of depth and substance in the desert of social media, and I for one am glad it’s going strong. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Avi Wigderson</b>: I had the good fortune to be Dick Lipton’s PhD student in the years 1980-83. Being with a researcher so knowledgeable, curious, original and passionate in these formative years has shaped my own research path. Happy 75th, Dick, and many happy returns! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Ryan Williams</b>—will speak, as above. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Virginia Vassilevska Williams</b>: Happy 1,000th post, Dick! Your blog posts are always so fun to read, highly informative and polished, a treasured gift to our community. Thank you for working on them all this time. I’m looking forward to many more!
</li></ul>
<p>
More may be added, and our readers are welcome to add more in the comments.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Some Words From Princeton—and Yale </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Andrea LaPaugh <a href="https://dof.princeton.edu/about/clerk-faculty/emeritus/andrea-s-lapaugh">became</a> Dean of the Faculty at Princeton and served until her recent retirement. She has some further words from that perspective going back to the beginning of her 38 years at Princeton.</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Dick was a major force in the development of the CS department at Princeton. His work was instrumental in the creation of the department as separate from Electrical Engineering, in recruiting faculty to grow the department, and in acquiring resources. He arrived in 1980 and immediately recruited David Dobkin as a full professor and me as an assistant professor. He continued to have major involvement in recruiting, not only in theoretical computer science, but across the CS disciplines. He was never chair, but worked first with Bruce Arden, chair of the Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, and then with Bob Sedgewick, the first chair of the Department of Computer Science (after Dick recruited him) to implement a vision of a strong and well-rounded CS department. Of course Dick was not alone in this mission. David Dobkin in particular was an important partner. But from my perspective, Dick was the spark. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
David Dobkin, also writing from Princeton, goes back a few years further still to Yale:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> In 1973 when I arrived at Yale as a new faculty member with a fresh PhD, Dick Lipton was the person in the next office who had arrived perhaps a week earlier. He came by to introduce himself. After a bit of formalities, we began to discuss research problems and he asked me about NP-complete problems which were all the rage at the time. The only problem I knew about was the knapsack problem and so I described it.</em></p><em>
<p>
This led to a discussion about integer programming (which neither of us had a good handle on) and then to a discussion about determining in which region of a subdivision of <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-space (by a set of hyperplanes) a new point was in. Here again, neither Dick nor I had much background and so we invented things as we went. I had this idea that we could understand things with visual help and so we took one of my moving boxes as our universe and the back of some tablets as planes and began to simulate how regions would be determined in 3d.</p>
<p>
From this work emerged our first paper together which was presented at STOC ’74. This on planar subdivision searching opened up a field and led to a long and enjoyable collaboration that followed.</p>
</em><p><em>
So, congratulations Dick on having escaped the world of cardboard planes in a moving box and headed on to a remarkable career in the field. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> More Words From Georgia Tech </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Rich DeMillo sent the following from summer sunshine and open water:</p>
<p>
The last time I missed Dick’s birthday was 2008. In 2007, Dan Boneh, Merrick Furst, Santosh Vempala, and I sent the following 60th birthday symposium invitation to twenty of Lipton’s closest friends and collaborators:</p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/14/happy-1000th-post-and-75th-birthday-dick/rjl2008invite/" rel="attachment wp-att-19503"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19503" height="215" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/RJL2008invite.jpg?resize=327%2C215&amp;ssl=1" width="327"/></a></p>
<p>
The <a href="http://denseoutliers.blogspot.com/2008/03/lipton-theory-symposium.html">Lipton-60</a> <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2008/05/report-on-sym-for-liptons-60th-bday.html">Symposium</a> was finally held in April 2008. It was less the retrospective I had imagined than a mile marker in a career that continued to accelerate in unexpected ways. A few years later, he was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. A few months after that, he was announced as winner of the 2014 Knuth Prize. Even more memorable was the other thing that draws us together here today: the launch in 2009 of the GLL blog that he now writes with Ken. </p>
<p>
I have long since strayed from the mainstream of theory and algorithms, but most of the work we did together has found its way into GLL essays that illuminate in startling new ways material I thought I understood thoroughly. Our paper on the nature of proof that now appears in Harry Lewis’s <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/ideas-created-future">collection</a> of 46 of the most important (in his view) papers in computer science made its first <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/02/16/proofs-and-elevator-rides/">appearance</a> on the blog in 2009 and has been a recurring character in the “GLL universe” ever since. Our probabilistic <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/11/30/the-curious-history-of-the-schwartz-zippel-lemma/">algorithm</a> for polynomial zero testing also entered GLL in 2009. For years I harbored vague resentment that Jack Schwartz was often cited in the Schwartz-Zippel Lemma for a result that Dick and I had published two years before in 1979, but the <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/11/30/the-curious-history-of-the-schwartz-zippel-lemma/">exposition</a> in GLL, Ken’s subsequent <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/11/30/the-curious-history-of-the-schwartz-zippel-lemma/#comment-1993">commentary</a>, and <em>years later</em>, a reader’s <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/11/30/the-curious-history-of-the-schwartz-zippel-lemma/#comment-64661">comment</a> showing that Daniel Erickson’s 1974 Caltech dissertation had scooped us all, laid that to rest. </p>
<p>
We both had a fascination with the idea of algorithm correctness—incorrectness, actually—that turned into entire fields in software engineering and cryptography. Those were documented in an “Un-Birthday” <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/01/29/happy-un-birthday-rich/">post</a> a year ago:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Rich and I started our work together over four decades ago. A central theme of our work was correctness. We were concerned That programs might not work as planned. At the time it was not obvious that this was a major theme of our joint work. But looking back now I can see that it was. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Also recently, I managed to coax Dick into the fraught waters of election security. I stood back to watch how flustered researchers would respond to his (brilliant but unworkable) <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/05/10/making-elections-safe/">reconstructions</a> of what it means to vote in a public election. </p>
<p>
I have been delaying my plans to remove myself from day-to-day management duties to found a new department of cybersecurity at Georgia Tech, and I have missed Dick at my side since his retirement. There was always the possibility when Dick was in the room that someone’s long-held (but wrong) assumption would fall apart under a trademarked but understated Lipton assault. Michael Rabin (who also contributed to the Lipton-60 symposium) was fond of telling Dick on such occasions, “You are a very dangerous person.” </p>
<p>
With this intimate gathering on January 17 to commemorate GLL 1,000 and Dick Lipton’s 75th Birthday, Ken Regan has slyly kept alive the tradition of meetings that take place months after the anniversary of Dick’s birth. Times are different. Virtual meetings have replaced the casual travel and camaraderie of 2008. I cannot attend in any form on January 17 since I am at present on a ship bound for the Drake Passage and Patagonia, and I will lose Internet connectivity soon. I hope that explanation excuses this longer-than-asked-for expression of affection and admiration for Dick, my friend and collaborator for nearly 50 years. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
A meta open-problem: Which was the most <em>pliable</em> problem at the time this blog was founded? The Unique Games <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unique_games_conjecture">conjecture</a> strikes us as a perfect example, but you readers may have other examples from then and now.</p>
<p>
[fixed product 11*13*17, added more greetings and speakers, removed workshop link afterward]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-14T21:14:32Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-14T21:14:32Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="1000th post"/>
    <category term="anniversary"/>
    <category term="birthday"/>
    <category term="GLL blog"/>
    <category term="Richard Lipton"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:44Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/14/empire-innovation-professor-quantum-information-science-and-engineering-at-stony-brook-university-apply-by-june-30-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/14/empire-innovation-professor-quantum-information-science-and-engineering-at-stony-brook-university-apply-by-june-30-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Empire Innovation Professor – Quantum Information Science and Engineering at Stony Brook University (apply by  June 30, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Computer Science (CS) Department and the Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) Department at Stony Brook University invite applications for a tenure-track/tenured faculty position in Quantum Information Science and Engineering with an expected start date of Fall 2022. Exceptionally qualified candidates at any rank are invited to apply. Website: https://www.cs.stonybrook.edu/about-us/career/empire Email: recruit@cs.stonybrook.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Computer Science (CS) Department and the Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) Department at Stony Brook University invite applications for a tenure-track/tenured faculty position in Quantum Information Science and Engineering with an expected start date of Fall 2022. Exceptionally qualified candidates at any rank are invited to apply.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.cs.stonybrook.edu/about-us/career/empire">https://www.cs.stonybrook.edu/about-us/career/empire</a><br/>
Email: recruit@cs.stonybrook.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-14T16:36:58Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-14T16:36:58Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/008</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/008" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-008 |  Approximating Large Powers of Stochastic Matrices in Small Space | 

	Gil Cohen, 

	Dean Doron, 

	Ori Sberlo</title>
    <summary>We give a deterministic space-efficient algorithm for approximating powers of stochastic matrices. On input a $w \times w$ stochastic matrix $A$, our algorithm approximates $A^{n}$ in space $\widetilde{O}(\log n + \sqrt{\log n}\cdot \log w)$ to within high accuracy. This improves upon the seminal work by Saks and Zhou (FOCS'95), that requires $O(\log^{3/2}n + \sqrt{\log n} \cdot \log w)$ space, in the regime $n \gg w$.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-14T09:34:37Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-14T09:34:37Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/007</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/007" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-007 |  A Simpler Proof of the Worst-Case to Average-Case Reduction for Polynomial Hierarchy via Symmetry of Information | 

	Valentine Kabanets, 

	Halley Goldberg</title>
    <summary>We give a simplified proof of Hirahara's STOC'21 result showing that $DistPH \subseteq AvgP$ would imply $PH \subseteq DTIME[2^{O(n/\log n)}]$. The argument relies on a proof of the new result: Symmetry of Information for time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity under the assumption that $NP$ is easy on average, which is interesting in its own right and generalizes the ``weak'' Symmetry of Information theorem from the original paper by Hirahara.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-14T02:52:14Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-14T02:52:14Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/13/faculty-positions-in-quantum-science-and-information-at-university-of-maryland-apply-by-february-1-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/13/faculty-positions-in-quantum-science-and-information-at-university-of-maryland-apply-by-february-1-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty Positions in Quantum Science and Information at University of Maryland (apply by February 1, 2022)</title>
    <summary>UMD invites applications for faculty positions in quantum science and information. Areas to be considered include quantum computation, quantum simulation, quantum information processing, quantum sensing, and quantum networking. Research can be experimental, theoretical or computational in nature. Successful applicants will be expected to maintain active research programs and teach. Website: https://ejobs.umd.edu/postings/91259 Email: gene@umd.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>UMD invites applications for faculty positions in quantum science and information. Areas to be considered include quantum computation, quantum simulation, quantum information processing, quantum sensing, and quantum networking. Research can be experimental, theoretical or computational in nature. Successful applicants will be expected to maintain active research programs and teach.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://ejobs.umd.edu/postings/91259">https://ejobs.umd.edu/postings/91259</a><br/>
Email: gene@umd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-13T20:29:53Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-13T20:29:53Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8286</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/01/13/call-for-godel-prize-nominations-guest-post-by-david-zuckerman-and-samson-abramsky/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Call for Gödel prize nominations (guest post by David Zuckerman and Samson Abramsky)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We’d like to encourage everyone to nominate outstanding papers in any area of theoretical computer science for the 2022 Gödel Prize. In short, papers that first appeared since 2009 (in any form) and appeared in a refereed journal by 2021 are eligible. If you wish to nominate a paper, or might wish to do so, or … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/01/13/call-for-godel-prize-nominations-guest-post-by-david-zuckerman-and-samson-abramsky/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Call for Gödel prize nominations (guest post by David Zuckerman and Samson Abramsky)</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We’d like to encourage everyone to nominate outstanding papers in any area of theoretical computer science for the 2022 Gödel Prize. </p>



<p>In short, papers that first appeared since 2009 (in any form) and appeared in a refereed journal by 2021 are eligible. If you wish to nominate a paper, or might wish to do so, or if you want to suggest a paper informally, please contact the award committee chair, Samson Abramsky (<a href="mailto:s.abramsky@ucl.ac.uk" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">s.abramsky@ucl.ac.uk</a>). The deadline is February 28, 2022, but please contact the chair well in advance to coordinate efforts. For details, see <a href="https://sigact.org/prizes/g%C3%B6del.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://sigact.org/prizes/g%C3%B6del.html</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-13T18:33:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-13T18:33:00Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:59Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/006</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/006" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-006 |  Secret Sharing, Slice Formulas, and Monotone Real Circuits | 

	Benny Applebaum, 

	Amos Beimel, 

	Oded Nir, 

	Naty Peter, 

	Toniann Pitassi</title>
    <summary>A secret-sharing scheme allows to distribute a secret $s$ among $n$ parties such that only some predefined ``authorized'' sets of parties can reconstruct the secret, and all other ``unauthorized'' sets learn nothing about $s$. For over 30 years, it was known that any (monotone) collection of authorized sets can be realized by a secret-sharing scheme whose shares are of size $2^{n-o(n)}$ and until recently no better scheme was known. In a recent breakthrough, Liu and Vaikuntanathan (STOC 2018) have reduced the share size to $2^{0.994n+o(n)}$, and this was further improved by several follow-ups accumulating in an upper bound of $1.5^{n+o(n)}$ (Applebaum and Nir, CRYPTO 2021). Following these advances, it is natural to ask whether these new approaches can lead to a truly sub-exponential upper-bound of $2^{n^{1-\epsilon}}$ for some constant $\epsilon&gt;0$, or even all the way down to polynomial upper-bounds.

In this paper, we relate this question to the complexity of computing monotone Boolean functions by monotone real circuits (MRCs)  -- a computational model that was introduced by Pudl\'{a}k  (J. Symb. Log., 1997) in the context of proof complexity. We introduce a new notion of ``separable'' MRCs that lies between monotone real circuits and monotone real formulas (MRFs). As our main results, we show that recent constructions of general secret-sharing schemes implicitly give rise to separable MRCs for general monotone functions of similar complexity, and that some monotone functions (in monotone NP) cannot be computed by sub-exponential size separable MRCs. Interestingly, it seems that proving similar lower-bounds for general MRCs is beyond the reach of current techniques.

We use this connection to obtain lower-bounds against a natural family of secret-sharing schemes, as well as new non-trivial upper-bounds for MRCs. Specifically, we conclude that recent approaches for secret-sharing schemes cannot achieve sub-exponential share size and that every monotone function can be realized by an MRC (or even MRF) of complexity $1.5^{n+o(n)}$. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first improvement over the trivial $2^{n-o(n)}$ upper-bound. Along the way, we show that the recent constructions of general secret-sharing schemes implicitly give rise to Boolean formulas over slice functions and prove that such formulas can be simulated by separable MRCs of similar size. On a conceptual level, our paper continues the rich line of study that relates the share size of secret-sharing schemes to monotone complexity measures.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-12T15:39:53Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-12T15:39:53Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7334971011736548221</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7334971011736548221/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/on-california-math-framework.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7334971011736548221" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7334971011736548221" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/on-california-math-framework.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the California Math Framework</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><i>Guest post by Boaz Barak
and Jelani Nelson</i></p><p class="MsoNormal"/>

<p class="MsoNormal">In a <a href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/12/defending-status-quo.html">recent
post</a>, Lance Fortnow critiqued our <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/k12mathmatters/home">open letter</a> on the
proposed revisions for the <a href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ma/cf/">California Mathematics Framework</a> (CMF). We disagree
with Lance’s critique, and he has kindly allowed us to post our rebuttal here
(thank you Lance!).</p><p class="MsoNormal">First, let us point out the aspects where we agree with both
Lance and the authors of the CMF. Inequality in mathematical education, and in
particular the obstacles faced by low-income students and students of color, is
a huge problem in the US at large and California in particular. As a Black
mathematician, this portion of the CMF’s <a href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ma/cf/documents/mathfwchapter1.docx">introduction</a> particularly resonated
with me (Jelani):</p><blockquote><p class="MsoNormal">Girls and Black and Brown children, notably, represent
groups that more often receive messages that they are not capable of high-level
mathematics, compared to their White and male counterparts (Shah &amp;
Leonardo, 2017). As early as preschool and kindergarten, research and policy
documents use deficit-oriented labels to describe Black and Latinx and
low-income children’s mathematical learning and position them as already behind
their white and middle-class peers (NCSM &amp; TODOS, 2016).</p></blockquote><p class="MsoNormal"/>

<p class="MsoNormal">We agree with the observation that bias in the public
education system can have a negative impact on students from underrepresented
groups. Where we strongly oppose the CMF though is regarding their conclusions
on how to address this concern. </p><p class="MsoNormal"/>

<p class="MsoNormal">The CMF may state that they are motivated by increasing
equity in mathematics. However, if we read past the introduction to the actual
details of the CMF revisions, then we see they suffer from fundamental flaws,
which we believe if implemented, would <b>exacerbate</b> educational gaps, and
in particular make it <b>harder</b> for low-income students and students of
color to reach and be successful in college STEM.</p><p class="MsoNormal"/>

<p class="MsoNormal">You can read our <a href="https://gdoc.pub/doc/e/2PACX-1vQvuzlJ8MWthsqOhRLxQc5akGS0JkgThz3umqO3K-WQiXFhWiq9qw-9iYdTyC652Ftjvv5nHvgGYTEv">detailed
critique</a> of the CMF, but the revisions we take issue with are:</p><p class="MsoNormal"/>

<ol start="1" style="margin-top: 0in;" type="1"><li class="MsoNormal">Recommendation
     to drop the option of Algebra I in the 8th grade<br/>
     <!--[endif]--></li><li class="MsoNormal">Recommendation
     to offer (and in fact push and elevate above others) a “data science”
     pathway for high school education as an alternative to the traditional
     Algebra and Geometry curriculum. While data science can be a deep and
     important field, teaching it for students without a math background will
     be necessarily shallow. Indeed, the proposed data science courses focus on
     tools such as using spreadsheets etc., and do not provide mathematical
     foundations.</li>
</ol>

<p class="MsoNormal">1 and 2 make it all but impossible for students that follow
the recommended path to reach calculus (perhaps even pre-calculus)  in the
12th grade.  This means that such students will be at a disadvantage if
they want to pursue STEM majors in college. And who will be these students?
Since the CMF is only recommended, wealthier school districts are free to
reject it, and some already <a href="https://calmatters.org/education/k-12-education/2021/11/california-math/">signalled
that they will do so</a>. Within districts that do adopt the recommendations,
students with means are likely to take private Algebra I courses outside the
curriculum (as <a href="https://calmatters.org/education/k-12-education/2021/12/san-francisco-math/">already
</a><a href="https://edsource.org/2021/one-districts-faulty-data-shouldnt-drive-californias-math-policy/663374">happened</a>
in San Francisco), and reject the calculus-free “data science” pathway. Hence
this pathway will amount to a lower-tier track by another name, and worse than
now, students will be tracked based on whether their family has the financial
means to supplement the child’s public education with private coursework.</p><p class="MsoNormal">Notably, though the CMF aims to elevate data science, we’ve
had several data science faculty at the university level express disapproval of
the proposal by signing our opposition letter, including a founding faculty
member of the Data Science Institute at UCSD, and several others who are
directors of various undergraduate programs at their respective universities,
including four who direct their universities' undergraduate data science
programs (at Indiana University, Loyola University in Chicago, MIT, and the
University of Wisconsin)! </p>

<p class="MsoNormal">One could say that while the framework may hurt low-income
or students of color who want to pursue STEM in college, it might help other
students who are not interested in STEM. However, interest in STEM majors is <a href="https://www.ppic.org/blog/more-students-are-earning-stem-degrees/">rapidly
rising</a>, and with good reasons: employment in math occupations is projected
to <a href="https://www.bls.gov/ooh/math/mobile/home.htm">grow much faster </a>than
other occupations. With the increasing centrality of technology and STEM to our
society, we urgently need reforms that will diversify these professions rather
than the other way around.</p><p class="MsoNormal">As a final note, Lance claimed that by rejecting the CMF, we
are “defending the status quo”. This is not true. The CMF revisions are far
from the “only game in town” for improving the status quo in mathematics
education. In fact, unlike these largely untested proposals, there is a history
of approaches that do work for teaching mathematics for under-served
populations. We do not need to change the math itself, just invest in more
support (including extracurricular support) for students from under-resourced
communities. For example, Bob Moses’ <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2013/08/02/206813091/to-60s-civil-rights-hero-math-is-kids-formula-for-success">Algebra
Project</a> has time and again taken the least successful students according to
standardized exams, and turned them into a cohort that <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/07/education/algebra-project-bob-moses-empowers-students.html">outperformed</a>
state averages in math. One of our letter’s contact people is Adrian Mims, an
educator with 27 years of experience, whose dissertation was on 
"Improving African American Achievement in Geometry Honors" and who
went on to found <a href="https://thecalculusproject.org/">The Calculus
Project</a>, a non-profit organization creating a pathway for low-income
students and students of color to succeed in advanced mathematics. </p><p class="MsoNormal">To close, a critique of the proposed CMF revision is not a
defense of the status quo. Even if change is needed, not all change is good
change, and our letter does make some recommendations on the front, one of
which is a matter of process: if a goal is to best prepare Californian youth
for majors in data science and STEM more broadly, and ultimately careers in
these spaces, then involve college-level STEM educators and STEM professionals
in the <a href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ma/cf/mathcfccapplicants.asp">Curriculum
Framework and Evaluation Criteria Committee</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-12T15:32:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-12T15:32:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T02:55:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/005</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/005" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-005 |  Sunflowers: from soil to oil | 

	Anup Rao</title>
    <summary>A \emph{sunflower} is a collection of sets whose pairwise intersections are identical. In this article, we shall go sunflower-picking. We find sunflowers in several seemingly unrelated fields, before turning to discuss recent progress on the famous sunflower conjecture of Erd\H{o}s and Rado, made by Alweiss, Lovett, Wu and Zhang.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-11T19:30:19Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-11T19:30:19Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6215</id>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6215" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6215#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=6215" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">On tardigrades, superdeterminism, and the struggle for sanity</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">(Hopefully no one has taken taken that title yet!) I waste a large fraction of my existence just reading about what’s happening in the world, or discussion and analysis thereof, in an unending scroll of paralysis and depression. On the first anniversary of the January 6 attack, I read the recent revelations about just how […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>(Hopefully no one has taken taken that title yet!)</em></p>



<p>I waste a large fraction of my existence just reading about what’s happening in the world, or discussion and analysis thereof, in an unending scroll of paralysis and depression.  On the first anniversary of the January 6 attack, I read the <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2022/01/january-6-insurrection-trump-coup-2024-election/620843/n">recent revelations</a> about just how close the seditionists actually came to overturning the election outcome (e.g., by pressuring just one Republican state legislature to “decertify” its electors, after which the others would likely follow in a domino effect), and how hard it now is to see a path by which democracy in the United States will survive beyond 2024.  Or I read <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2022/01/10/manchin-bbb-coal-miners-vs-owners/">about</a> Joe Manchin, who’s already entered the annals of history as the man who could’ve halted the slide to the abyss and decided not to.  Of course, I also read about the wokeists, who correctly see the swing of civilization getting pushed terrifyingly far out of equilibrium to the right, so their solution is to push the swing terrifyingly far out of equilibrium to the <em>left</em>, and then they act shocked when their own action, having added all this potential energy to the swing, causes it to swing back <em>even further</em> to the right, as swings tend to do.  (And <em>also</em> there’s a global pandemic killing millions, and the correct response to it—to authorize and distribute new vaccines as quickly as the virus mutates—is completely outside the Overton Window between Obey the Experts and Disobey the Experts, advocated by no one but a few nerds.  When I first wrote this post, I forgot all about the global pandemic.)  And I see all this and I am powerless to stop it.</p>



<p>In such a dark time, it’s easy to forget that I’m a theoretical computer scientist, mainly focused on quantum computing.  It’s easy to forget that people come to this blog because they want to read about quantum computing.  It’s like, who gives a crap about that anymore?  What doth it profit a man, if he gaineth a few thousand fault-tolerant qubits with which to calculateth chemical reaction rates or discrete logarithms, and he loseth civilization?</p>



<p>Nevertheless, in the rest of this post I’m going to share some quantum-related debunking updates—not because that’s what’s at the top of my mind, but in an attempt to find my way back to sanity.  Picture that: quantum mechanics (and specifically, the refutation of outlandish claims related to quantum mechanics) as the part of one’s life that’s comforting, normal, and sane.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>There’s been lots of online debate about the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.07978">claim</a> to have entangled a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tardigrade">tardigrade</a> (i.e., water bear) with a superconducting qubit; see also <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.15166">this paper</a> by Vlatko Vedral, <a href="https://www.cnet.com/news/no-tardigrades-have-not-been-quantum-entangled-with-a-qubit/">this</a> from CNET, <a href="https://twitter.com/benbenbrubaker/status/1472287582654455817?s=20">this</a> from Ben Brubaker on Twitter.  So, do we now have Schrödinger’s Tardigrade: a living, “macroscopic” organism maintained coherently in a quantum superposition of two states?  How could such a thing be possible with the technology of the early 21<sup>st</sup> century?  Hasn’t it been a huge challenge to demonstrate even Schrödinger’s Virus or Schrödinger’s Bacterium?  So then how did this experiment leapfrog (or leaptardigrade) over those vastly easier goals?</p>



<p>Short answer: it didn’t.  The experimenters couldn’t directly measure the degree of freedom in the tardigrade that’s claimed to be entangled with the qubit.  But it’s consistent with everything they report that whatever entanglement is there, it’s between the superconducting qubit and a microscopic <em>part</em> of the tardigrade.  It’s <em>also</em> consistent with everything they report that there’s no entanglement at all between the qubit and <em>any</em> part of the tardigrade, just boring classical correlation.  (Or rather that, if there’s “entanglement,” then it’s the Everett kind, involving not merely the qubit and the tardigrade but the whole environment—the same as we’d get by just measuring the qubit!)  Further work would be needed to distinguish these possibilities.  In any case, it’s of course cool that they were able to cool a tardigrade to near absolute zero and then revive it afterwards.</p>



<p>I thank the authors of the tardigrade paper, who clarified a few of these points in correspondence with me.  Obviously the comments section is open for whatever I’ve misunderstood.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>People also asked me to respond to Sabine Hossenfelder’s recent <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ytyjgIyegDI">video</a> about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superdeterminism">superdeterminism</a>, a theory that holds that quantum entanglement doesn’t actually exist, but the universe’s initial conditions were fine-tuned to stop us from choosing to measure qubits in ways that would make its nonexistence apparent: even when we <em>think</em> we’re applying the right measurements, we’re not, because the initial conditions messed with our brains or our computers’ random number generators.  (See, I tried to be as non-prejudicial as possible in that summary, and it still came out sounding like a parody.  Sorry!)</p>



<p>Sabine sets up the usual dichotomy that people argue against superdeterminism only because they’re attached to a belief in free will.  She rejects Bell’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bell%27s_theorem#Statistical_independence">statistical independence</a> assumption, which she sees as a mere dogma rather than a prerequisite for doing science.  Toward the end of the video, Sabine mentions the objection that, without statistical independence, a demon could destroy any randomized controlled trial, by tampering with the random number generator that decides who’s in the control group and who isn’t.  But she then reassures the viewer that it’s no problem: superdeterministic conspiracies will only appear when quantum mechanics would’ve predicted a Bell inequality violation or the like.  Crucially, she never explains the mechanism by which superdeterminism, once allowed into the universe (<em>including</em> into macroscopic devices like computers and random number generators), will stay confined to reproducing the specific predictions that quantum mechanics already told us were true, rather than enabling ESP or telepathy or other mischief.  This is <em>stipulated</em>, never explained or derived.</p>



<p>To say I’m not a fan of superdeterminism would be a super-understatement.  And yet, nothing I’ve written previously on this blog—about superdeterminism’s gobsmacking lack of explanatory power, or about how trivial it would be to cook up a superdeterministic “mechanism” for, e.g., faster-than-light signaling—none of it seems to have made a dent.  It’s all come across as obvious to the majority of physicists and computer scientists who think as I do, and it’s all fallen on deaf ears to superdeterminism’s fans.</p>



<p>So in desperation, let me now try another tack: going meta.  It strikes me that no one who saw quantum mechanics as a profound clue about the nature of reality could ever, in a trillion years, think that superdeterminism looked like a promising route forward given our current knowledge.  The only way you could think that, it seems to me, is if you saw quantum mechanics as an <strong>anti-clue</strong>: a red herring, actively misleading us about how the world really is.  To be a superdeterminist is to say:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>OK, fine, there’s the Bell experiment, which <em>looks like</em> Nature screaming the reality of ‘genuine indeterminism, as predicted by QM,’ louder than you might’ve thought it even <em>logically possible</em> for that to be screamed.  But don’t listen to Nature, listen to us!  If you just drop what you thought were foundational assumptions of science, we can explain this away!  Not <em>explain</em> it, of course, but explain it <em>away</em>.  What more could you ask from us?</p></blockquote>



<p>Here’s my challenge to the superdeterminists: when, in 400 years from Galileo to the present, has such a gambit <em>ever</em> worked?  Maxwell’s equations were a clue to special relativity.  The Hamiltonian and Lagrangian formulations of classical mechanics were clues to quantum mechanics.  When has a great theory in physics ever been <em>grudgingly accommodated</em> by its successor theory in a horrifyingly ad-hoc way, rather than gloriously explained and derived?</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update:</span></strong> Oh right, and the <a href="https://custom.cvent.com/9563374D7DF84F27BC7A463F7B7B5F5F/files/b7f46addeac74520affde9abb00c17ca.pdf">QIP’2022 list of accepted talks</a> is out!  And I was on the program committee!  And <s>they’re still planning to hold QIP in person, in March at Caltech, will you fancy that!</s>  actually I have no idea—but if they’re going to move to virtual, I’m awaiting an announcement just like everyone else.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-11T02:14:38Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-11T02:14:38Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <icon>https://scottaaronson.blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-Jacket-32x32.gif</icon>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T01:15:09Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://differentialprivacy.org/synth-data-0/</id>
    <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/synth-data-0/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What is Synthetic Data?</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The concept of synthetic data seems to be having “a moment” in the privacy world as a promising approach to sharing data while protecting privacy.  Strictly speaking, any time you make up data, you have produced a synthetic dataset, but more specifically</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>a <strong>synthetic dataset</strong> is a stand-in for some original dataset that has the same format, and accurately reflects the statistical properties of the original dataset, but contains only “fake” records.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Intuitively, a synthetic dataset can be used as if it were the real data—we can stare at it, compute summary statistics from it, train models from it, and do everything we normally do with data—but because the records do not correspond to “real” people, we don’t have to worry about protecting privacy.</p>

<p>To be sure, synthetic data is a very appealing concept, but</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>simply making data “synthetic” does not guarantee privacy in any meaningful sense of the word,</p>
</blockquote>

<p>and we need to be careful about what it actually means to generate <strong>private synthetic data.</strong></p>

<p>In this post I will briefly describe <strong>differentially private synthetic data</strong>, why we need it, and what we know about producing it.  The post will serve as a warmup to some more technical posts that will follow later, describing general approaches and state-of-the-art algorithms for producing synthetic data.</p>

<h3 id="what-is-synthetic-data">What is synthetic data?</h3>

<p>Given a dataset \(X\), a synthetic dataset \(Y\) is a new dataset that has the same <em>structure</em> as \(X\), but whose elements are “fake.”  For example, if \(X\) is a highly stylized version of the data collected in the US decennial census, then each element of \(X\) would be a tuple of the form (age, census_block, sex, race, ethnicity) corresponding to the data of a real person who filled out a census card.  A synthetic dataset should also contain such tuples, but they no longer need to correspond to real people.</p>

<p>An example of a synthetic dataset for the census would be a dataset consisting of 300,000,000 individuals, all living at one location in rural Mississippi, and all of whom are white, non-hispanic females aged 81.  And therein lies the challenge.  Of course we want a synthetic dataset not to merely have the same <em>structure</em> as the original data, but also to preserve the <em>statistical properties</em> of the original data.  A synthetic dataset for the census should put roughly the right number of individuals of the right types in the right places to reflect the actual population of the US.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thus, to generate synthetic data, we have to know something about the original data, which creates opportunities to leak sensitive information.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="synthetic-data-from-generative-modeling">Synthetic data from generative modeling</h4>

<p>Ensuring that a synthetic dataset really only reflects the statistical properties of the real data, and doesn’t encode sensitive information about the individuals in the real dataset, is quite difficult.  I could go on forever about strawman proposals that would generate records that appear to be “fake” but really just encode the original dataset in obvious ways.  Just so you believe I could do it, suppose for every real record, we get a fake record by adding 10 years to that individual’s age.  But what people typically mean when they talk about generating synthetic data, and what the synthetic data products being sold by companies typically do, is train a generative model for the dataset \(X\) and obtain the synthetic dataset \(Y\) by sampling from that model.  The hope is that samples from the generative model look like the original dataset in aggregate, but the actual people in the sample have nothing to do with the real people in the original dataset.  For example, a generative model from the US population will lead to more people living in California than in Montana, but ideally wouldn’t simply spit out the data of the actual residents of California.</p>

<h4 id="generative-models-dont-magically-protect-privacy">Generative models don’t magically protect privacy</h4>

<p>Simply training a generative model on \(X\) doesn’t actually mean we’ve hidden anything about \(X\) or the people in it.  For an extreme example, suppose the records in \(X\) are \(x_1,\dots,x_n\) and our generative model is arbitrarily expressive and determines that the best model for the data is just the uniform distribution on the set \(x_1,\dots,x_n\).  Then if our synthetic dataset consists of \(n\) iid samples from the generative model, our synthetic dataset will simply contain one or more copies of the real data for a large fraction (about 70%) of the people in the original dataset.</p>

<h4 id="reconstruction-attacks-say-hello">Reconstruction attacks say hello</h4>

<p>My example was admittedly a strawman, and when we train a generative model we typically expect it to produce new examples that aren’t in the original training dataset.  Maybe by training generative models in the right way, we can ensure that the generative model only captures statistics about the dataset, without revealing information about the individuals in the dataset?  Let’s not forget that</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>a synthetic dataset is just one of many possible ways to release statistical information about a dataset, and we know from the theory of reconstruction attacks that <strong>any</strong> mechanism that accurately preserves too many statistics inevitably destroys privacy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Specifically, there is a rich and fairly comprehensive theory of <strong>reconstruction attacks</strong>, whose <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/reconstruction-theory/">theory</a> and <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/diffix-attack/">practice</a> we detailed in earlier posts.  This theory says that any synthetic dataset that preserves answers to every statistic of the form “How many elements of the dataset satisfies property P?” with any meaningful notion of accuracy, is spectacularly non-private, in the sense that an attacker can reconstruct nearly all of the private information in the original dataset.  Viewed through this lens, synthetic data becomes something of a red herring.  The important question is which subset of statistics we want to preserve and how to preserve them without compromising privacy.</p>

<h3 id="differentially-private-synthetic-data">Differentially private synthetic data</h3>

<p>Making a dataset “synthetic” may not be a magic bullet, but it’s still a useful goal.  Fortunately, we already have a good working definition of what it means for an algorithm to protect the privacy of the individuals in the dataset—<strong>differential privacy</strong>.  So perhaps we can design a differentially private algorithm that takes the original dataset \(X\) and outputs a synthetic dataset \(Y\) that preserves many of the properties of \(X\) accurately (but still within the limits imposed by reconstruction attacks)?  In fact, the answer turns out to be a resounding yes!</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>There is a differentially private algorithm that takes a dataset \(X\) and outputs a synthetic dataset \(Y\) that preserves an <strong>exponential</strong> number of statistical properties of \(X\) <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1109.2229">[BLR08]</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This statement is intentionally quite informal, but intutively this result says that we can hope to do amazing things, like generate a synthetic dataset that satisfies the strong guarantee of differential privacy while still approximately preserving impressively complex statistics of the dataset, such as the marginal distribution of every set of three attributes, or the prediction error of every linear classifier.</p>

<p>So what’s the problem?  Well, primarily it’s computational complexity. This algorithm, and the many beautiful algorithms it inspired, all have exponential worst-case running time.  Specifically, if each element of the dataset contains \(d\) bits, then the worst-case running time is at least as large as \(2^d\).  Unfortunately, this turns out to be an inherent bottleneck for any algorithm that generates synthetic data.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Any private algorithm that takes a dataset \(X\) and outputs a synthetic dataset \(Y\) that preserves even just the correlations between each pair of features must have worst-case running time that grows exponentially in the number of features, under widely believed complexity assumptions. <a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2010/017/">[UV11]</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>While there are inherent limits of the accuracy of all differentially private algorithms (see <a href="https://privacytools.seas.harvard.edu/publications/exposed-survey-attacks-private-data">[DSSU17]</a>), and there are significant barriers to making differentially private algorithms practical,</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>computational complexity is the main barrier that is specific to differentially private algorithms for generating synthetic data.<sup id="fnref:1"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="where-do-we-go-from-here">Where do we go from here?</h4>

<p>Despite the computational bottlenecks, there has stll been a lot of amazing progress on differentially private synthetic data.  And, despite my criticism of generative modeling in isolation as a means of generating synthetic data, most of these approaches are indeed based on <em>differentially private generative models</em> such as sparse graphical models or GANs, and leverage the fact that these types of models can typically be fit efficiently to realistic data, despite their worst-case hardness.  In the next few posts, we will try to describe the landscape of the most promising approaches that we currently have available.</p>

<hr/>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>See <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.13239">[AACGKLSSTZ21]</a> for an interesting example of a <em>statistical</em> limitation that is specific to differentially private algorithms that generate synthetic data. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:1">↩</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-10T23:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-10T23:00:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Jonathan Ullman</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://differentialprivacy.org</id>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Website for the differential privacy research community</subtitle>
      <title>Differential Privacy</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T22:53:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/10/faculty-at-national-university-of-singapore-apply-by-february-28-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/10/faculty-at-national-university-of-singapore-apply-by-february-28-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty at National University of Singapore (apply by February 28, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science (CS) at the National University of Singapore (NUS) invites applications for a faculty position in quantum computing with joint appointment in the Centre for Quantum Technologies (CQT). Website: https://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/about/depts/cs/recruitment/faculty/ Email: rahul@comp.nus.edu.sg</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science (CS) at the National University of Singapore (NUS) invites applications for a faculty position in quantum computing with joint appointment in the Centre for Quantum Technologies (CQT).</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/about/depts/cs/recruitment/faculty/">https://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/about/depts/cs/recruitment/faculty/</a><br/>
Email: rahul@comp.nus.edu.sg</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-10T03:08:31Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-10T03:08:31Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-3357688667258653719</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/3357688667258653719/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/math-problems-involving-food.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3357688667258653719" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3357688667258653719" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/math-problems-involving-food.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Math problems involving Food</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> A few people emailed me an Math article on arxiv about cutting a pizza, and since I wrote the book (literally) on cutting muffins, they thought it might interest me. It did, though perhaps not in the way they intended. I got curious about math problems that involve food. Here are some</p><p>The Muffin Problem. See my book (<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mathematical-Muffin-Morsels-Problem-Mathematics/dp/9811215170">here</a>), or my website (<a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/MUFFINS/muffins.html">here</a>)</p><p>The Candy Sharing Game. See this paper  (<a href="https://msuweb.montclair.edu/~bald/files/candy-sharing.pdf">here</a>).</p><p>Sharing a pizza. See this paper (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.06752">here</a>)</p><p>Cake Cutting. See  this book (<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Cake-Cutting-Algorithms-Fair-You-Can/dp/1568810768">here</a>) or google  <i>Fair Division </i> on amazon</p><p>Chicken McNugget Problem. See this paper (<a href="https://mikebeneschan.medium.com/the-chicken-mcnugget-theorem-explained-2daca6fbbe1e">here</a>)</p><p>The Ham Sandwich  Theorem. See this paper (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ham_sandwich_theorem">here</a>)</p><p>Spaghetti Breaking Theorem. See this paper (<a href="https://news.mit.edu/2018/mit-mathematicians-solve-age-old-spaghetti-mystery-0813">here</a>)</p><p>Perfect Head on a Beer. See this paper (<a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/mathematics-point-the-w/">here)</a></p><p>A smorgasbord of math-food connections, see this pinterest posting <a href="https://www.pinterest.com/mrelementarymath/food-and-math/">(here)</a></p><p>And of course the question that has plagued mankind since the time of Stonehenge: </p><p>                     <i>Why do Hot Dogs come in packs of 10 and Hot Dog buns in Packs of 8 (<a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/the-secret-math-of-hot-dogs-and-buns-20211118/">here</a>)</i></p><p><br/></p><p>All of these problems could have been stated without food (The Chicken McNugget Problem is also Frobenius's Problem) but they are easier to understand with food.</p><p>I am sure I missed some. If you now of any other food-based math problems, leave a comment.</p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-10T01:33:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-10T01:33:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T02:55:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=22386</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2022/01/10/reflections-on-the-occasion-of-ron-adins-and-yuval-roichmans-birthdays-and-fpsac-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Reflections: On the Occasion of Ron Adin’s and Yuval Roichman’s Birthdays, and FPSAC 2021</title>
    <summary>Two hybrid conferences, Bar-Ilan University:Monday, January 10,2022 10:00-16:00 (Israel time) Reflections: On the occasion of Ron Adin’s and Yuval Roichman’s 60th Birthdays. FPSAC 2021 Starting  Monday, January 10,2022 16:30 (Israel time). Ending Thursday, January 20, 2022.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><h3>Two hybrid conferences, Bar-Ilan University:<br/>Monday, January 10,2022 10:00-16:00 (Israel time) <br/><a href="https://u.math.biu.ac.il/~vishneu/Conferences/Yuval-Ron-2021/index.html"><strong>Reflections: On the occasion of Ron Adin’s and Yuval Roichman’s 60th Birthdays.</strong></a><br/><br/><a href="https://fpsac2021.math.biu.ac.il/?page_id=100"><strong>FPSAC 2021</strong></a> Starting  Monday, January 10,2022 16:30 (Israel time). Ending Thursday, January 20, 2022. </h3>


<p/>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-09T21:42:15Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-09T21:42:15Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Updates"/>
    <category term="Ron Adin"/>
    <category term="Yuval Roichman"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/004</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/004" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-004 |  Analyzing Ta-Shma’s Code via the Expander Mixing Lemma | 

	Silas Richelson, 

	Sourya Roy</title>
    <summary>Random walks in expander graphs and their various derandomizations (e.g., replacement/zigzag product) are invaluable tools from pseudorandomness. Recently, Ta-Shma used s-wide replacement walks in his breakthrough construction of a binary linear code almost matching the Gilbert-Varshamov bound (STOC 2017). Ta-Shma’s original analysis was entirely linear algebraic, and subsequent developments have inherited this viewpoint. In this work, we rederive Ta-Shma’s analysis from a combinatorial point of view using repeated application of the expander mixing lemma. We hope that this alternate perspective will yield a better understanding of Ta-Shma’s construction. As an additional application of our techniques, we give an alternate proof of the expander hitting set lemma.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-09T04:39:36Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-09T04:39:36Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:33Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://dstheory.wordpress.com/?p=112</id>
    <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2022/01/08/thursday-jan-13th-2022-piotr-indyk-from-mit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Thursday Jan 13th 2022 — Piotr Indyk from MIT</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first Foundations of Data Science virtual talk of this year will take place on Thursday, Jan 13th at 10:00 AM Pacific Time (13:00 Eastern Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). Piotr Indyk from MIT will speak about “Learning-Based Sampling and Streaming”. Please register here to join the virtual talk. Abstract: Classical algorithms typically provide<a class="more-link" href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2022/01/08/thursday-jan-13th-2022-piotr-indyk-from-mit/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">"Thursday Jan 13th 2022 — Piotr Indyk from MIT"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="has-text-align-justify">The first <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory/home" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Foundations of Data Science</a> virtual talk of this year will take place on <strong>Thursday, Jan 13</strong>th at <strong>10:00 AM Pacific Time</strong> (13:00 Eastern Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). <strong><a href="https://people.csail.mit.edu/indyk/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Piotr Indyk</a> </strong>from<strong> MIT</strong> will speak about “Learning-Based Sampling and Streaming”.</p>



<p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Please register here to join the virtual talk.</a></p>



<p class="has-text-align-justify"><strong>Abstract</strong>:  Classical algorithms typically provide “one size fits all” performance, and do not leverage properties or patterns in their inputs. A recent line of work aims to address this issue by developing algorithms that use machine learning predictions to improve their performance. In this talk I will present two examples of this type, in the context of streaming and sampling algorithms. In particular, I will show how to use machine learning predictions to improve the performance of (a) low-memory streaming algorithms for frequency estimation (ICLR’19), and (b) sampling algorithms for estimating the support size of a distribution (ICLR’21).   Both algorithms use an ML-based predictor that, given a data item, estimates the number of times the item occurs in the input data set.  </p>



<p>The talk will cover material from papers co-authored with  T Eden, CY Hsu, D Katabi, S Narayanan, R Rubinfeld, S Silwal, T Wagner and A Vakilian.</p>



<p>The series is supported by the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1934846&amp;HistoricalAwards=false">NSF HDR TRIPODS Grant 1934846</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-08T04:33:15Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-08T04:33:15Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>dstheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://dstheory.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Foundation of Data Science – Virtual Talk Series</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:38:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/07/postdoc-at-new-york-university-apply-by-february-1-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/07/postdoc-at-new-york-university-apply-by-february-1-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at New York University (apply by February 1, 2022)</title>
    <summary>We have a postdoc position open jointly between the Algorithms and Foundations and VIDA groups at NYU Tandon’s Computer Science and Engineering Department. The position is for a joint project between Prof. Christopher Musco and Prof. Juliana Freire, and we are looking for candidates broadly interested in algorithms for sketching, streaming, and high-dimensional search. Website: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We have a postdoc position open jointly between the Algorithms and Foundations and VIDA groups at NYU Tandon’s Computer Science and Engineering Department. The position is for a joint project between Prof. Christopher Musco and Prof. Juliana Freire, and we are looking for candidates broadly interested in algorithms for sketching, streaming, and high-dimensional search.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://apply.interfolio.com/101044">https://apply.interfolio.com/101044</a><br/>
Email: cmusco@nyu.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-07T16:36:42Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-07T16:36:42Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>http://offconvex.github.io/2022/01/06/gf-gd/</id>
    <link href="http://offconvex.github.io/2022/01/06/gf-gd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Does Gradient Flow Over Neural Networks Really Represent Gradient Descent?</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><h2 id="tldr">TL;DR</h2>

<p>A lot was said in this blog (cf. <a href="http://www.offconvex.org/2019/06/03/trajectories/">post by Sanjeev</a>) about the importance of studying trajectories of gradient descent (<strong><em>GD</em></strong>) for understanding deep learning.
Researchers often conduct such studies by considering <em>gradient flow</em> (<strong><em>GF</em></strong>), equivalent to GD with infinitesimally small step size.
Much was learned from analyzing GF over neural networks (<strong><em>NNs</em></strong>), but to what extent <strong><em>do results for GF apply to GD with practical step size?</em></strong>
This is an open question in deep learning theory.
My student Omer Elkabetz and I investigated it in a recent NeurIPS 2021 spotlight <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=iX0TSH45eOd">paper</a>.
In a nutshell, we found that, although in general an exponentially small step size is required for guaranteeing that GD is well represented by GF, specifically over NNs, a much larger step size can suffice.
This allows <strong><em>immediate translation of analyses for GF over NNs to results for GD</em></strong>.
The translation bears potential to shed light on both optimization and generalization (implicit regularization) in deep learning, and indeed, we exemplify its use for proving what is, to our knowledge, the <strong><em>first guarantee of random near-zero initialization almost surely leading GD over a deep (three or more layer) NN of fixed size to efficiently converge to global minimum</em></strong>.
The remainder of this post provides more details; for the full story see our <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=iX0TSH45eOd">paper</a>.</p>

<h2 id="gf-a-continuous-surrogate-for-gd">GF: a continuous surrogate for GD</h2>

<p>Let $f : \mathbb{R}^d \to \mathbb{R}$ be an objective function (e.g. training loss of deep NN) that we would like to minimize via GD with step size $\eta &gt; 0$: 
[
\boldsymbol\theta_{k + 1} = \boldsymbol\theta_k - \eta \nabla f ( \boldsymbol\theta_k ) ~ ~ ~ \text{for} ~ k = 0 , 1 , 2 , …
\qquad \color{green}{\text{(GD)}}
]
We may imagine a continuous curve $\boldsymbol\theta : [ 0 , \infty ) \to \mathbb{R}^d$ that passes through the $k$’th GD iterate at time $t = k \eta$.
This would imply $\boldsymbol\theta ( t + \eta ) = \boldsymbol\theta ( t ) - \eta \nabla f ( \boldsymbol\theta ( t ) )$, which we can write as $\frac{1}{\eta} ( \boldsymbol\theta ( t + \eta ) - \boldsymbol\theta ( t ) ) = - \nabla f ( \boldsymbol\theta ( t ) )$.
In the limit of infinitesimally small step size ($\eta \to 0$), we obtain the following characterization for $\boldsymbol\theta ( \cdot )$:
[
\frac{d}{dt} \boldsymbol\theta ( t ) = - \nabla f ( \boldsymbol\theta ( t ) ) ~ ~ ~ \text{for} ~ t \geq 0 
.
\qquad \color{blue}{\text{(GF)}}
]
This differential equation is known as GF, and represents a continuous surrogate for GD.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<img src="http://www.offconvex.org/assets/gf-gd-illustration.png" style="width: 540px;"/>
<br/>
<i><b>Figure 1:</b> 
Illustration of GD and its continuous surrogate GF.
</i>
</div>
<p><br/></p>

<p>GF brings forth the possibility of employing a vast array of continuous mathematical machinery for studying GD.
It is for this reason that GF has become a popular model in deep learning theory (see our <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=iX0TSH45eOd">paper</a> for a long list of works analyzing GF over NNs).
There is only one problem: GF assumes infinitesimal step size for GD!
This is of course impractical, leading to the following open question $-$ the topic of our <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=iX0TSH45eOd">work</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Open Question:</strong>
Does GF over NNs represent GD with practical step size?</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="gd-as-numerical-integrator-for-gf">GD as numerical integrator for GF</h2>

<p>The question of proximity between GF and GD (with positive step size) is closely related to an area of numerical analysis known as <em>numerical integration</em>.
There, the motivation is the other way around $-$ given a differential equation $\frac{d}{dt} \boldsymbol\theta ( t ) = \boldsymbol g ( \boldsymbol\theta ( t ) )$ induced by some vector field $\boldsymbol g : \mathbb{R}^d \to \mathbb{R}^d$, the interest lies on a continuous solution $\boldsymbol\theta : [ 0 , \infty ) \to \mathbb{R}^d$, and numerical (discrete) integration algorithms are used for obtaining approximations.
A classic numerical integrator, known as <em>Euler’s method</em>, is given by $\boldsymbol\theta_{k + 1} = \boldsymbol\theta_k + \eta \boldsymbol g ( \boldsymbol\theta_k )$ for $k = 0 , 1 , 2 , …$, where $\eta &gt; 0$ is a predetermined step size.
With Euler’s method, the goal is for the $k$’th iterate to approximate the sought-after continuous solution at time $k \eta$, meaning $\boldsymbol\theta_k \approx \boldsymbol\theta ( k \eta )$.
Notice that when the vector field $\boldsymbol g ( \cdot )$ is chosen to be minus the gradient of an objective function $f : \mathbb{R}^d \to \mathbb{R}$, i.e. $\boldsymbol g ( \cdot ) = - \nabla f ( \cdot )$, the given differential equation is no other than GF, and its numerical integration via Euler’s method yields no other than GD!
We can therefore employ known results from numerical integration to bound the distance between GF and GD!</p>

<h2 id="gf-matches-gd-if-its-trajectory-is-roughly-convex">GF matches GD if its trajectory is roughly convex</h2>

<p>There exist classic results bounding the approximation error of Euler’s method, but these are too coarse for our purposes.
Instead, we invoke a modern result known as “Fundamental Theorem” (cf. <a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-540-78862-1">Hairer et al. 1993</a>), which implies the following:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem 1:</strong>
The distance between the GF trajectory $\boldsymbol\theta ( \cdot )$ at time $t$, and iterate $k = t / \eta$ of GD, is upper bounded as:</p>

  <p>[ 
|| \boldsymbol\theta ( t ) - \boldsymbol\theta_{k = t / \eta} || \leq \mathcal{O} \Big( e^{- \smallint_0^{~ t} \lambda_- ( t’ ) dt’} t \eta \Big)
, 
]
where $\lambda_- ( t’ ) := \min \left( \lambda_{min} \left( \nabla^2 f ( \boldsymbol\theta ( t’ ) ) \right) , 0 \right)$, i.e. $\lambda_- ( t’ )$ is defined to be the negative part of the minimal eigenvalue of the Hessian on the GF trajectory at time $t’$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As expected, by using a sufficiently small step size $\eta$, we may ensure that GD is arbitrarily close to GF for arbitrarily long.
How small does $\eta$ need to be?
For the theorem to guarantee that GD follows GF up to time $t$, we must have $\eta \in \mathcal{O} \big( e^{\smallint_0^{~ t} \lambda_- ( t’ ) dt’} / t \big)$.
In particular, $\eta$ must be exponential in $\smallint_0^{~ t} \lambda_- ( t’ ) dt’$, i.e. in the integral of (the negative part of) the minimal Hessian eigenvalue along the GF trajectory (up to time $t$).
If the optimized objective $f ( \cdot )$ is convex then Hessian eigenvalues are everywhere non-negative, and therefore $\lambda_- ( \cdot ) \equiv 0$, which means that a moderately small $\eta$ (namely, $\eta \in \mathcal{O} ( 1 / t )$) suffices.
If on the other hand $f ( \cdot )$ is non-convex then Hessian eigenvalues may be negative, meaning $\lambda_- ( \cdot )$ may be negative, which in turn implies that $\eta$ may have to be exponentially small.
We prove in our <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=iX0TSH45eOd">paper</a> that there indeed exist cases where an exponentially small step size is unavoidable:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Proposition 1:</strong>
For any $m &gt; 0$, there exist (non-convex) objectives on which the GF trajectory at time $t$ is <strong>not</strong> approximated by GD if $\eta \notin \mathcal{O} ( e^{- m t} )$.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Despite this negative result, not all hope is lost.
It might be that even though a given objective function is non-convex, specifically over GF trajectories it is “roughly convex,” in the sense that along these trajectories the minimal eigenvalue of the Hessian is “almost non-negative.”
This would mean that $\lambda_- ( \cdot )$ is almost non-negative, in which case (by Theorem 1) a moderately small step size suffices in order for GD to track GF!</p>

<h2 id="trajectories-of-gf-over-nns-are-roughly-convex">Trajectories of GF over NNs are roughly convex</h2>

<p>Being interested in the match between GF and GD over NNs, we analyzed the geometry of GF trajectories on training losses of NNs with homogeneous activations (e.g. linear, ReLU, leaky ReLU).
The following theorem (informally stated) was proven:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem 2:</strong>
For a training loss of a NN with homogeneous activations, the minimal Hessian eigenvalue is arbitrarily negative across space, but along GF trajectories initialized near zero it is almost non-negative.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Combined with Theorem 1, this theorem suggests that over NNs (with homogeneous activations), in the common regime of near-zero initialization, a moderately small step size for GD suffices in order for it to be well represented by GF!
We verify this prospect empirically, demonstrating that in basic deep learning settings, reducing the step size for GD often leads to only slight changes in its trajectory.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<img src="http://www.offconvex.org/assets/gf-gd-experiment.png" style="width: 600px;"/>
<br/>
<i><b>Figure 2:</b> 
Experiment with NN comparing every iteration of GD with step size $\eta_0 := 0.001$, to every $r$'th iteration of GD with step size $\eta_0 / r$, where $r = 2 , 5 , 10 , 20$.
Left plot shows training loss values; right one shows distance (in weight space) of GD with step size $\eta_0$ from initialization, against its distance from runs with smaller step size.
Takeaway: reducing step size barely made a difference, suggesting GD was already close to the continuous (GF) limit.
</i>
</div>

<h2 id="translating-analyses-of-gf-to-results-for-gd">Translating analyses of GF to results for GD</h2>

<p>Theorems 1 and 2 together form a tool for automatically translating analyses of GF over NNs to results for GD with practical step size.
This means that a vast array of continuous mathematical machinery available for analyzing GF can now be leveraged for formally studying practical NN training!
Since analyses of GF over NNs often establish convergence to global minimum and/or characterize the solution found (again, see our <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=iX0TSH45eOd">paper</a> for long list of examples), the translation we developed bears potential to shed new light on both optimization and generalization (implicit regularization) in deep learning.
To demonstrate this point, we analyze GF over arbitrarily deep linear NNs with scalar output, and prove the following result:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Proposition 2:</strong>
GF over an arbitrarily deep linear NN with scalar output converges to global minimum almost surely (i.e. with probability one) under a random near-zero initialization.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Applying our translation yields an analogous result for GD with practical step size:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Theorem 3:</strong>
GD over an arbitrarily deep linear NN with scalar output efficiently converges to global minimum almost surely under a random near-zero initialization.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first guarantee of random near-zero initialization <strong><em>almost surely</em></strong> leading GD over a deep (three or more layer) NN of fixed size to efficiently converge to global minimum!</p>

<h2 id="what-about-large-step-size-momentum-stochasticity">What about large step size, momentum, stochasticity?</h2>

<p>An emerging belief (see our <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=iX0TSH45eOd">paper</a> for several supporting references) is that for GD over NNs, large step size can be beneficial in terms of generalization.
While the large step size regime isn’t necessarily captured by standard GF, recent works (e.g. <a href="https://openreview.net/pdf?id=3q5IqUrkcF">Barrett &amp; Dherin 2021</a>, <a href="https://openreview.net/pdf?id=q8qLAbQBupm">Kunin et al. 2021</a>) argue that it is captured by certain modifications of GF.
Modifications were also proposed for capturing other aspects of NN training, for example momentum (cf. <a href="https://jmlr.org/papers/volume17/15-084/15-084.pdf">Su et al. 2016</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1603.04245.pdf">Wibisono et al. 2016</a>, <a href="http://proceedings.mlr.press/v80/franca18a/franca18a.pdf">Franca et al. 2018</a>, <a href="https://jmlr.org/papers/volume22/20-195/20-195.pdf">Wilson et al. 2021</a>) and stochasticity (see, e.g., <a href="https://jmlr.org/papers/volume20/17-526/17-526.pdf">Li et al. 2017</a>, <a href="https://openreview.net/pdf?id=rq_Qr0c1Hyo">Smith et al. 2021</a>, <a href="https://openreview.net/pdf?id=goEdyJ_nVQI">Li et al. 2021</a>).
Extending our GF-to-GD translation machinery to account for modifications as above would be very interesting in my opinion.
All in all, I believe that in the years to come, the vast knowledge on continuous dynamical systems, and GF in particular, will unravel many mysteries behind deep learning.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.cohennadav.com/"><strong><em>Nadav Cohen</em></strong></a></p>

<p><br/>
<strong><em>Thanks:</em></strong>
<em>I’d like to thank many people with whom I’ve had illuminating discussions on GF vs. GD over NNs.
These include <a href="https://noahgol.github.io/">Noah Golowich</a>, <a href="https://weihu.me/">Wei Hu</a>, <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~zl4/">Zhiyuan Li</a> and Kaifeng Lyu.
Special thanks to <a href="https://www.dam.brown.edu/people/menon/">Govind Menon</a>, who drew my attention to the connection to numerical integration, and of course to <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~arora/">Sanjeev</a>, who has been a companion and guide in promoting the “trajectory approach” to deep learning.</em></p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-06T12:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-06T12:00:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>http://offconvex.github.io/</id>
      <author>
        <name>Off the Convex Path</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://offconvex.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://offconvex.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Algorithms off the convex path.</subtitle>
      <title>Off the convex path</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T22:52:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=981</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2022/01/06/the-story-of-stuff-and-installing-linux-on-a-32-bit-computer-from-15-years-ago/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The story of stuff,  and installing Linux on a 32-bit computer from 15 years ago</title>
    <summary>If you haven’t seen it, now is the time to drop everything you are doing and watch The story of stuff. Computer scientists like myself will latch onto the scene where the old computer which looks like a washing machine is thrashed because a tiny component doesn’t fit anymore. In this spirit, I am happy […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>If you haven’t seen it, now is the time to drop everything you are doing and watch <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9GorqroigqM">The story of stuff</a></em>. Computer scientists like myself will latch onto the scene where the old computer which looks like a washing machine is thrashed because a tiny component doesn’t fit anymore.  In this spirit, I am happy to announce that after substantial challenges I was able to install Linux on a 32-bit laptop from about 15 years ago.  First I tried Ubuntu, but I was saddened to learn that they dropped support for 32-bit platforms.  Luckily, Debian still supports it for a number of years, and I went for it.  The incidents I had during the installation include missing non-free firmware for the wifi which I had to fetch and stick in random places in the USB stick, and an inexplicable failure of the base installation which can be fixed by mounting the USB stick during it.</p>



<p>When you say these things, you get the familiar shrug which means “In the same time you spent doing this I can write a grant proposal and make enough money to buy two new machines.”  While this is true, it does not mean it is the right thing to do.  We should strive to prolong the life of computers and their components indefinitely, instead of taking pride in showing off the latest gadget purchase.  I am writing this post from an Ubuntu system installed on a 2008 desktop.</p>



<p>Uncharacteristically, I see a bright future in this domain.  We can store drivers for every hardware configuration ever assembled, and create easy-to-use installation packages.  Moreover, all of this can be automated, while we still are at the stage where human intervention is required.  And one thing that gives me a lot of hope and continues to impress me is the amazing network of people that are willing to help each other to get computers to work, especially when they run free software.  You can have the most technical question and quickly get — for free — the most caring and expert advice, say by posting on <a href="https://stackexchange.com/">stackexachange</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-06T11:16:27Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-06T11:16:27Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="HES: health, environment, and sustainability"/>
    <category term="Utopia"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:38:07Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4602</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2022/01/05/bocconi-is-hiring-assistant-professors-of-computer-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Bocconi is hiring Assistant Professors of Computer Science</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bocconi University is recruiting for tenure-track positions in computer science. Some details are here. Candidates must apply online by January 15 (end of day Central Europe time) for the application to be considered. To apply online, go to https://jobmarket.unibocconi.eu/ and … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2022/01/05/bocconi-is-hiring-assistant-professors-of-computer-science/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Bocconi University is recruiting for tenure-track positions in computer science.</p>



<p>Some <a href="https://academicpositions.com/ad/bocconi-university/2021/assistant-professor-of-computer-science/172733">details are here</a>. Candidates must apply online by January 15 (end of day Central Europe time) for the application to be considered. To apply online, go to <a href="https://jobmarket.unibocconi.eu/">https://jobmarket.unibocconi.eu/</a> and look at the only opening that has a Jan 15 expiration (currently it is at the top of the list). The negotiable start date is September, 2022. By that time the new Computing Sciences department will be fully operational.</p>



<p>We are interested in all areas of computer science. <a href="https://www.alonrosen.net/">Alon Rosen</a>, <a href="http://www.dirkhovy.com/index.php">Dirk Hovy</a> and I are very happy to talk to prospective candidates about what the university is like and what are its plans for developing computer science.</p>



<p>The university pays internationally competitive salary and provides relocation assistance. The language of instructions of all computer science courses at both undergraduate and graduate levels is English.</p>



<p>Scholars of any nationality who have not lived in Italy for the past two years and who move to Italy to take a university tenure-track or tenured position pay almost no income tax for six years, or more if they buy a home in Italy and/or have children under the age of 18.</p>



<p>For Italians working in Italy: this position is governed by a private-law contract with Bocconi, which is not the same as a RDTA or RDTB position, although the terms are similar. </p>



<p>Subject to a successful mid-term review (which usually happens after three years), and a successful tenure review (which happens within five years from the mid-term review, or possibly earlier depending on the background of the candidate), assistant professors are promoted to associate professors with tenure. (For those familiar with the Italian system, the latter positions are fully recognized as professore associato by the ministry of university.)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-05T15:52:40Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-05T15:52:40Z</published>
    <category term="Bocconi"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19459</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/05/quantum-graph-theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum Graph Theory</title>
    <summary>More ways quantum can invigorate “classical” research Composite crop of src1, src2, src3 Axel Dahlberg, Jonas Helsen, and Stephanie Wehner are researchers from QuTech associated to Delft Technological University. They have produced five wonderful and elegant recent papers that update the theory of quantum graph states. Today we introduce some of what their papers are […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>More ways quantum can invigorate “classical” research</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/05/quantum-graph-theory/dahlberghelsenwehner/" rel="attachment wp-att-19461"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-19461" height="90" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/DahlbergHelsenWehner.png?resize=200%2C90&amp;ssl=1" width="200"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Composite crop of <a href="https://qutechacademy.nl/about-us/meet-our-students/axel-dahlberg/">src1</a>, <a href="https://qutech.nl/academy/about/meet-our-students/jonas-helsen/">src2</a>, <a href="https://www.tudelft.nl/en/2019/tnw/stephanie-wehner-wins-ammodo-science-award">src3</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Axel Dahlberg, Jonas Helsen, and Stephanie Wehner are researchers from <a href="https://qutech.nl/">QuTech</a> associated to Delft Technological University. They have produced <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/2058-9565/aba763">five</a> <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S002001902100137X">wonderful</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1805.05305.pdf">elegant</a> <a href="https://quantum-journal.org/papers/q-2020-10-22-348/">recent</a> <a href="https://aip.scitation.org/doi/10.1063/1.5120591">papers</a> that update the theory of quantum graph states.</p>
<p>
Today we introduce some of what their papers are about.<br/>
<span id="more-19459"/></p>
<p>
We covered material <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/06/04/a-quantum-connection-for-matrix-rank/">related</a> to <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/06/10/net-zero-graphs/">graph</a> states a few times before the pandemic, <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/06/17/contraction-and-explosion/">going</a> in the <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/08/26/a-matroid-quantum-connection/">direction</a> of <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2020/02/11/using-negative-nodes-to-count/">matroid</a> theory. The work by Dahlberg, Helsen, and Wehner stays with ordinary simple undirected graphs. </p>
<p>
Wehner was the advisor of Dahlberg and Helsen, and she was in turn a student of Harry Buhrman at CWI Amsterdam, where Helsen is now. Wehner’s <a href="https://qutech.nl/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/CV-Wehner-June-2021.pdf">CV</a> lists one of her jobs prior to graduate study as “Hacker” for ITSX BV in Amsterdam, a fact used in the lead sentence in a 2018 <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-01835-3">news feature</a> in <em>Nature</em> on work toward a quantum Internet. Both that and her Wikipedia <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephanie_Wehner">page</a> call her a theoretical physicist. We would claim her for theoretical computer science. </p>
<p>
Amid the entanglement of fields, a key point is that simple problems about simple graphs govern blueprints for vast networking technology that we can now only conceive. Is all this simple enough to introduce in a short post? We’ll see.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Graph States </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The quantum gates most commonly used to define and operate on <b>graph states</b> are the one-qubit Hadamard and Pauli gates </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \mathsf{H} = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; -1 \end{bmatrix},\quad \mathsf{X} = \begin{bmatrix} 0 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; 0 \end{bmatrix},\quad \mathsf{Y} = \begin{bmatrix} 0 &amp; -i \\ i &amp; 0 \end{bmatrix},\quad \mathsf{Z} = \begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; -1 \end{bmatrix}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathsf%7BH%7D+%3D+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B%5Csqrt%7B2%7D%7D%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7D+1+%26+1+%5C%5C+1+%26+-1+%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D%2C%5Cquad+%5Cmathsf%7BX%7D+%3D+%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7D+0+%26+1+%5C%5C+1+%26+0+%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D%2C%5Cquad+%5Cmathsf%7BY%7D+%3D+%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7D+0+%26+-i+%5C%5C+i+%26+0+%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D%2C%5Cquad+%5Cmathsf%7BZ%7D+%3D+%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7D+1+%26+0+%5C%5C+0+%26+-1+%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>together with the controlled-<img alt="{\mathsf{Z}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BZ%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and controlled-NOT gates, which are shown together with their usual quantum circuit notation:</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/05/quantum-graph-theory/czcnot/" rel="attachment wp-att-19462"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19462" height="64" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/CZCNOT.png?resize=400%2C64&amp;ssl=1" width="400"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Just because we like to be different, we will represent edges of undirected graphs by the following two-qubit gate instead: </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \mathsf{E} = \frac{1}{2}\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; -1\\ 1 &amp; 1 &amp; -1 &amp; 1\\ 1 &amp; -1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1\\ -1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \end{bmatrix}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathsf%7BE%7D+%3D+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7D+1+%26+1+%26+1+%26+-1%5C%5C+1+%26+1+%26+-1+%26+1%5C%5C+1+%26+-1+%26+1+%26+1%5C%5C+-1+%26+1+%26+1+%26+1+%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>
We don’t know a common name, but the gate is provided by Craig Gidney’s popular <a href="https://algassert.com/">Quirk</a> quantum circuit simulator with the following logical notation and enjoys the identities shown here: </p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/05/quantum-graph-theory/eidentities/" rel="attachment wp-att-19464"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19464" height="72" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Eidentities.jpg?resize=500%2C72&amp;ssl=1" width="500"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
The third identity means that <img alt="{\mathsf{E}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BE%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is the same as <img alt="{\mathsf{CZ}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BCZ%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> under the change of basis by the Hadamard transform. Graph states are usually defined by an initial <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-qubit Hadamard transform of all-zero input followed by placing a <img alt="{\mathsf{CZ}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BCZ%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> gate between qubits <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for each edge <img alt="{(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> in the graph; the order does not matter because <img alt="{\mathsf{CZ}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BCZ%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> gates commute no matter how placed. Instead, we have dispensed with the initial transform and simply place an <img alt="{\mathsf{E}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BE%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for each edge. Here are our circuits for the star graph <img alt="{S_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> on <img alt="{4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> nodes, the <img alt="{4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-cycle graph <img alt="{C_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, and the complete graph <img alt="{K_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, respectively: </p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/05/quantum-graph-theory/s4c4k4/" rel="attachment wp-att-19465"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19465" height="90" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/S4C4K4.jpg?resize=500%2C90&amp;ssl=1" width="500"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Putting an <img alt="{\mathsf{X}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BX%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> gate anywhere on line <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is the same as flipping the input bit <img alt="{x_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and adds a self-loop to node <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> in the graph. A double edge between two nodes is the same as a non-edge; only the parity matters. The gates <img alt="{\mathsf{E}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BE%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, <img alt="{\mathsf{X}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BX%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, and <img alt="{\mathsf{CNOT}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BCNOT%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> all commute. Both <img alt="{\mathsf{E}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BE%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and <img alt="{\mathsf{CZ}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BCZ%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> can be represented as <img alt="{e^{\pi i A}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Be%5E%7B%5Cpi+i+A%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for some Hermitian matrix <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> of rank <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> whose diagonal form <img alt="{D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BD%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is all-zero except for a single <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> entry. The matrix <img alt="{D}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BD%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> eloquently speaks “one unit of interaction.” </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Entanglement Examples </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
If we start with the graph <img alt="{K_2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK_2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> with just one edge on <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> nodes, then the quantum graph state is given by the first column of the matrix <img alt="{\mathsf{E}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BE%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> above: <img alt="{|K_2\rangle = \frac{1}{2}[1,1,1,-1]^T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CK_2%5Crangle+%3D+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%5B1%2C1%2C1%2C-1%5D%5ET%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. If we follow with a single Hadamard gate on line <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, then the state becomes </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}[1,0,0,1]^T = \frac{|00\rangle + |11\rangle}{\sqrt{2}}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B%5Csqrt%7B2%7D%7D%5B1%2C0%2C0%2C1%5D%5ET+%3D+%5Cfrac%7B%7C00%5Crangle+%2B+%7C11%5Crangle%7D%7B%5Csqrt%7B2%7D%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>This is the <em>Bell pair</em>. Named after John Bell, which is the simplest entangled state. If we say that the first qubit is held by “Alice” and the second by “Bob,” then Alice and Bob are entangled. For any <img alt="{n \geq 2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn+%5Cgeq+2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, the state <img alt="{\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}(|0^n\rangle + |1^n\rangle)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B%5Csqrt%7B2%7D%7D%28%7C0%5En%5Crangle+%2B+%7C1%5En%5Crangle%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, which is called the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger_state">GHZ state</a> after Daniel Greenberger, Michael Horne, and Anton Zeilinger, has the maximum possible entanglement among <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> qubits by several quantitative measures. </p>
<p>
Now let us add interactions with two more qubits held by “Charlie” and “Donna” in the form of the cycle graph <img alt="{C_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>:</p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/05/quantum-graph-theory/abcd/" rel="attachment wp-att-19467"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19467" height="130" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ABCD.png?resize=168%2C130&amp;ssl=1" width="168"/></a></p>
<p>
Questions that we can ask include:</p>
<ol>
<li>
Are Alice and Bob entangled? Or Alice and Charlie? <p/>
</li><li>
Do they have less entanglement than a Bell pair? <p/>
</li><li>
Do the four parties together have as much entanglement as the <img alt="{4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-qubit GHZ state?
</li></ol>
<p>
The answers to the first two questions are, “it depends.” Absent any knowledge of what Charlie and Donna do with their qubits, the status of Alice and Bob is conveyed by the <img alt="{4 \times 4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B4+%5Ctimes+4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> <em>density matrix</em> resulting from the <em>partial trace-out</em> of Charlie and Donna. Here is a direct <a href="https://tinyurl.com/2p8dj2pd">shortlink</a> to view it on <em>Quirk</em> under its native “little-endian” qubit order (Donna uppermost), or <a href="https://tinyurl.com/4yd323pt">this</a> to view with Alice uppermost. This gives the <img alt="{4 \times 4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B4+%5Ctimes+4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> identity matrix, which represents the <em>completely mixed state</em> of two qubits, by which Alice and Bob have two independent classical coins with no entanglement. Regardless of what unitary operations Charlie and Donna do unto themselves, the trace-out remains the same.</p>
<p>
However, if Charlie and Donna <em>measure</em> their qubits, different effects can occur to Alice and Bob depending primarily on <em>how</em> they measure, and secondarily on the measurement results they get. If they both immediately measure in the standard basis, then Alice and Bob “collapse” to one of the four two-qubit basis states, as can be viewed on <em>Quirk</em> using the <em>post-selection</em> widgets “<img alt="{|0 \rangle\langle 0|}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7C0+%5Crangle%5Clangle+0%7C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>” and “<img alt="{|1 \rangle\langle 1|}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7C1+%5Crangle%5Clangle+1%7C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.” </p>
<p>
Yet if Charlie and Donna each apply one Hadamard gate before their measurement, then Alice and Bob get <img alt="{|K_2\rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CK_2%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, or something they can make equal to <img alt="{|K_2\rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CK_2%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> by applying one of the Pauli matrices on being told Charlie’s and Donna’s outcomes. A further Hadamard by Alice or Bob then creates the Bell pair, as viewable <a href="https://tinyurl.com/bddz37zj">here</a> (or <a href="https://tinyurl.com/2p8dm9bm">here</a> for a big-endian view).</p>
<p>
To ask about Alice and Charlie, it is most convenient to re-order <img alt="{C_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> so that Donna and Bob are consecutive: </p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/05/quantum-graph-theory/acbd/" rel="attachment wp-att-19468"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19468" height="153" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/ACBD.png?resize=397%2C153&amp;ssl=1" width="397"/></a></p>
<p>
Tracing out Donna and Bob now <a href="https://tinyurl.com/26b52vtd">leaves</a> <a href="https://tinyurl.com/5bksjwau">the</a> density matrix <font size="-2"><img alt="{\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 \end{bmatrix}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7D+1+%26+0+%26+0+%26+0+%5C%5C+0+%26+0+%26+0+%26+0+%5C%5C+0+%26+0+%26+0+%26+0+%5C%5C+0+%26+0+%26+0+%26+1+%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></font>. This means that Alice and Charlie have classical coins that are fully correlated, but not quantum entanglement. However, if <em>just one</em> of Bob or Donna applies one Hadamard gate before measuring, Alice and Charlie <a href="https://tinyurl.com/4v3h9brv">become</a> a Bell pair (perhaps after a local tweak like the <img alt="{\mathsf{Z}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BZ%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-gate <a href="https://tinyurl.com/524praur">here</a>). </p>
<p>
We can pose the same questions for other graphs. On the third, given the star <img alt="{S_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> with Alice at the center, let her apply one Hadamard gate to her qubit. The <a href="https://tinyurl.com/2cmmdp4r">result</a> is the GHZ state. </p>
<p>
Given <img alt="{K_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, we can do the same by involving two more gates: </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \mathsf{S} = \begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; i \end{bmatrix},\qquad \mathsf{V} = \frac{1}{2}\begin{bmatrix} 1+i &amp; 1-i \\ 1-i &amp; 1+i \end{bmatrix}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathsf%7BS%7D+%3D+%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7D+1+%26+0+%5C%5C+0+%26+i+%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D%2C%5Cqquad+%5Cmathsf%7BV%7D+%3D+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%5Cbegin%7Bbmatrix%7D+1%2Bi+%26+1-i+%5C%5C+1-i+%26+1%2Bi+%5Cend%7Bbmatrix%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>
These obey the identities <img alt="{\mathsf{S}^2 = \mathsf{Z}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BS%7D%5E2+%3D+%5Cmathsf%7BZ%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, <img alt="{\mathsf{V} = \mathsf{HSH}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BV%7D+%3D+%5Cmathsf%7BHSH%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, and so </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \mathsf{V}^2 = \mathsf{HSHHSH} = \mathsf{HSSH} = \mathsf{HZH} = \mathsf{X}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cmathsf%7BV%7D%5E2+%3D+%5Cmathsf%7BHSHHSH%7D+%3D+%5Cmathsf%7BHSSH%7D+%3D+%5Cmathsf%7BHZH%7D+%3D+%5Cmathsf%7BX%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>
Thus <img alt="{\mathsf{V}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BV%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is also written <img alt="{\mathsf{X^{1/2}}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BX%5E%7B1%2F2%7D%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> as by <em>Quirk</em>. Applications of these along with Hadamard and the Pauli matrices on any one qubit generate the <em>local Clifford group</em>. Now let three of the qubits do <img alt="{\mathsf{V}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BV%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> while the fourth does <img alt="{\mathsf{S}^*}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BS%7D%5E%2A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> followed by <img alt="{\mathsf{H}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BH%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. The <a href="https://tinyurl.com/yrjrr57r">result</a> is again the GHZ state. The same tricks work with <img alt="{S_n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS_n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and <img alt="{K_n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK_n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for any <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.</p>
<p>
Can we get the GHZ state from the cycle <img alt="{C_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>? The answer is <em>no</em>. This leads into the basic quantum connection to graphs.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Neighborhood Flip </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The upshot is that because the graph states of <img alt="{K_n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK_n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and the star <img alt="{S_n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS_n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> can each produce the GHZ state, they can produce each other. The graph operation that does this is to choose one node <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, and for every pair <img alt="{j,k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%2Ck%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> of neighbors of <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>:</p>
<ul>
<li>
if <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> are not connected, connect them by an edge; <p/>
</li><li>
if <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> are connected, delete the edge between them.
</li></ul>
<p>
Here are pictures for <img alt="{n = 4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn+%3D+4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, the second showing how Donna could connect Alice and Charlie in the cycle graph. This <em>neighborhood flip</em> operation <img alt="{F_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is self-inverse. It cannot disconnect a node, and so defines an equivalence relation <img alt="{\sim_{F}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csim_%7BF%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> on connected graphs.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/05/quantum-graph-theory/flips/" rel="attachment wp-att-19469"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19469" height="120" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/Flips.png?resize=550%2C120&amp;ssl=1" width="550"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
If Alice is chosen in the graph at right after Donna’s flip, then Charlie is disconnected from Bob and Donna but Bob and Donna are connected. The edges to Alice do not change, so we get a triangle of Alice-Bob-Donna plus the edge Alice-Charlie. </p>
<p>
The quantum circuit rule for <img alt="{F_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is simple:</p>
<ul>
<li>
add an inverse-<img alt="{\mathsf{S}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BS%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> gate on qubit line <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>; <p/>
</li><li>
for each neighbor <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> of <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, add a <img alt="{\mathsf{V}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BV%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> gate on line <img alt="{j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.
</li></ul>
<p>
What gives this power is that <em>every</em> local quantum transformation of graph states arises this way. This was proved in a 2004 <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0308151">paper</a> by Maarten Van den Nest, Jeroen Dehaene, and Bart De Moor, among <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/quant-ph/0307130.pdf">several</a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0004051">related</a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0301052">papers</a> leading to a long 2006 <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/quant-ph/0602096.pdf">synthesis</a>. </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 1</b> <em><a name="flip"/> A graph state <img alt="{|G\rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> can be converted to a graph state <img alt="{|G'\rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%27%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> by local Clifford operations if and only if <img alt="{G \sim_{F} G'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%5Csim_%7BF%7D+G%27%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The star and complete graphs go only to each other, though the center of the star can be moved to any vertex. This answers the last section’s question about <img alt="{C_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Proposition 2</b> <em> <img alt="{C_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_4%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and <img alt="{K_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK_4%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> are in different equivalence classes, and these are the only two classes among connected graphs on four nodes.</em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Hence the entanglement in <img alt="{C_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_4%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is different from that of the four-qubit GHZ state from the standpoint of local Clifford conversions.  It is further known that no local unitary operations can convert them.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Measurement and Vertex Deletion </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
With our version of graph states <img alt="{|G\rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, applying one Hadamard to qubit <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, measuring in the standard basis, and post-selecting on <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> yields <img alt="{|G'\rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%27%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for the graph <img alt="{G'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> obtained by deleting vertex <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. If the outcome is <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, then <img alt="{|G'\rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%27%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is obtained by further applying <img alt="{\mathsf{X}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BX%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> to every neighbor of <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. (Measuring in the <img alt="{\{|+\rangle,|-\rangle\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%7B%7C%2B%5Crangle%2C%7C-%5Crangle%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> basis and then applying <img alt="{\mathsf{H}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BH%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> on line <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> has similar result. With the original version of graph states, use <img alt="{\mathsf{H}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BH%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> on neighbors of <img alt="{i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> instead.) </p>
<p>
The new papers, in particular <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1805.05305.pdf">this</a> by Dahlberg and Wehner, complete the above-mentioned earlier work to prove the following extension of Theorem <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/#flip">1</a>. Write <img alt="{G' \leq_F G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%27+%5Cleq_F+G%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and call <img alt="{G'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> a <em>vertex minor</em> of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> if <img alt="{G'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> can be obtained from <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> by neighborhood flips and vertex deletions. The deletions can without loss of generality be done last. </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 3</b> <em><a name="delete"/> An <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-qubit graph state <img alt="{|G\rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> can be converted to a graph state <img alt="{|G'\rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%27%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> by local Clifford operations, standard-basis measurements, and classical communication of measurement results, if and only if <img alt="{G' \leq_F G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%27+%5Cleq_F+G%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
In our example of entangling Alice and Charlie in <img alt="{C_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, Donna’s applying <img alt="{\mathsf{H}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BH%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and then measuring left Alice and Charlie connected only to Bob. Bob’s <em>not</em> applying <img alt="{\mathsf{H}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BH%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> before measuring was the same as applying it twice, first to flip Alice and Charlie into being connected, and then to drop himself out. Donna and Bob still needed to communicate their measurement results in order for Alice and Charlie to choose exactly the operations that produce the state <img alt="{|K_2\rangle}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CK_2%5Crangle%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. </p>
<p>
This opens the possibility of creating new entanglements by adding a node, flipping some neighborhoods, then deleting it. For example, neither <img alt="{C_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> nor <img alt="{K_4}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BK_4%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> can work itself into two entangled pairs by local means, because <img alt="{\sim_{F}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csim_%7BF%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> cannot disconnect a graph. Suppose we invite Eve not to eavesdrop but to slot between Bob and Charlie in the path graph shown at left below.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?attachment_id=19470" rel="attachment wp-att-19470"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19470" height="113" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/CongaLine.png?resize=500%2C113&amp;ssl=1" width="500"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Bob and Charlie do neighborhood flips that connect Eve to Alice and Donna as well. This yields the bowtie graph in the middle. Then Eve can measure and step away, leaving Alice-Bob and Charlie-Donna as separate couples.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The New Hardness Results </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
In 1991, before the quantum connection was visible, André Bouchet <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF01275668">showed</a> that whether two <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-vertex graphs are equivalent under <img alt="{\sim_F}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csim_F%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is polynomial-time decidable. The corresponding quantum problem about graph states is part-and-parcel with simulation questions for the larger class of <em>stabilizer states</em>, which we have also covered <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/06/04/a-quantum-connection-for-matrix-rank/">here</a> and <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/06/10/net-zero-graphs/">here</a>. </p>
<p>
But once deletion is allowed, Dahlberg, Helsen, and Wehner show that the feasible picture changes—at least when the target graph is on a fixed set of vertices.</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 4</b> <em> Given <img alt="{G = (V,E)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG+%3D+%28V%2CE%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> and <img alt="{G' = (V',E')}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%27+%3D+%28V%27%2CE%27%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> with <img alt="{V' \subset V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%27+%5Csubset+V%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> (but not necessarily <img alt="{E' \subset E}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BE%27+%5Csubset+E%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>), the problem of whether <img alt="{G' \leq_F G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%27+%5Cleq_F+G%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is <img alt="{\mathsf{NP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BNP%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-complete. It remains complete when <img alt="{G'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%27%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is a star or consists of multiple disjoint edges. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The disjoint edges are on prescribed pairs of vertices. They also show hardness when both graphs are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circle_graph">circle graphs</a>, a subclass on which many other <img alt="{\mathsf{NP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BNP%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-complete problems become polynomial-time decidable. In consequence:</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 5</b> <em> It is <img alt="{\mathsf{NP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BNP%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-hard to decide whether an <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-qubit graph state can be converted into a GHZ state on a given subset of the qubits, or into Bell pairs on designated pairs of qubits, by local unitary operations, measurements, and classical communication. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The fifth paper contains a further surprise. Even though the decision problem of <img alt="{\sim_F}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csim_F%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> belongs to <img alt="{\mathsf{P}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BP%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> (indeed, to a subclass defined by parity and linear algebra), the associated counting problem is hard.</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 6</b> <em> Given a graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, counting the number of labeled graphs equivalent to <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> under <img alt="{\sim_F}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csim_F%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is <img alt="{\mathsf{\#P}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7B%5C%23P%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-complete. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Again the completeness holds under restriction to circle graphs, which furnish machinery for the proof that connects to other linear- and group-algebraic constructs important to quantum mechanics.</p>
<p>
What does the hardness mean? One takeaway is that shortcuts with multi-variable polynomials that suffice to simulate quantum graph-state and stabilizer circuits may not extend nicely to describe entanglement and how it is affected by measurement. Another is that various other problems about quantifying and channeling quantum entanglement are likely to be hard as well. To pick up one theme we took from Lance Fortnow in our previous <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/12/31/make-a-trillion-dollars/">post</a>, the decision hardness channels questions about approximate optimization and heuristic most-case solving. Can entanglement be moved around a network and delivered to clients on demand, at what practical cost and loss of quantum coherence? I’ve tried to hint at such wider quantitative problems in the third section.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
What other areas of graph theory may be enriched by the quantum connection? The role of vertex deletion makes us think of the graph <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reconstruction_conjecture">reconstruction</a> conjecture in particular. Can results on minors in this 2019 <a href="http://publications.rwth-aachen.de/record/771369/files/771369.pdf">dissertation</a> extend to show that the <img alt="{\sim_F}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csim_F%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> relation is <em>reconstructible</em>? There are other uses of graphs in quantum mechanics, even a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schild's_Ladder">novel</a> about them.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
For a footnote, the double-<img alt="{\oplus}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Coplus%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> construction can be added to the <a href="http://physics.unm.edu/CQuIC/Qcircuit/">Qcircuit.tex</a> macro package by including the two lines</p>
<p><code>\newcommand{\controlplus}{{\xy ="i","i"-&lt;.39em,0em&gt;;"i"+&lt;.39em,0em&gt; **\dir{-}, "i"-&lt;0em,.39em&gt;;"i"+&lt;0em,.39em&gt; **\dir{-},"i"*\xycircle&lt;.4em&gt;{} \endxy}}<br/>
\newcommand{\ctrlp}[1]{\controlplus \qwx[#1] \qw}<br/>
</code></p>
<p>
and using <font size="+1"><tt>\ctrlp</tt></font> the same way as <font size="+1"><tt>\ctrl</tt></font> with <font size="+1"><tt>\targ</tt></font> and a numerical argument.</p>
<p>
[a couple of minor word changes; clarified the scope of proposition 2 and added a note afterwards in view of comment by GK below]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-05T08:17:04Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-05T08:17:04Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="graph isomorphism"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="Axel Dahlberg"/>
    <category term="entanglement"/>
    <category term="graph states"/>
    <category term="graph theory"/>
    <category term="Jonas Helsen"/>
    <category term="NP-completeness"/>
    <category term="quantum"/>
    <category term="quantum circuits"/>
    <category term="quantum networking"/>
    <category term="Quirk"/>
    <category term="Stephanie Wehner"/>
    <category term="vertex minors"/>
    <author>
      <name>KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1612</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2022/01/news-for-december-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for December 2021</title>
    <summary>Happy 2022 everyone! We now cover the last papers of 2021. Our readers have pointed out a number of papers from previous months that we missed (sorry). To adequately cover (and publicize) these papers, we’ve decided to just incorporate those papers on this post rather than update previous posts. We have a breakthrough on Locally […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Happy 2022 everyone! We now cover the last papers of 2021. Our readers have pointed out a number of papers from previous months that we missed (sorry). To adequately cover (and publicize) these papers, we’ve decided to just incorporate those papers on this post rather than update previous posts. </p>



<p>We have a breakthrough on Locally Testable Codes, sublinear algorithms for testing pattern freeness, new thoughts on convexity testing, and a perspective on sampling community structure. And here’s the final list for 2021.</p>



<p><strong>Locally Testable Codes with constant rate, distance, and locality</strong> by Irit Dinur, Shai Evra, Ron Livne, Alexander Lubotzky, and Shahar Mozes (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/151/">ECCC</a>, posted Nov 2021). A Locally Testable Code (LTC) is one where the set of codewords has a property tester. The study of LTCs started with the PCP theorem, but blossomed into a deep research agenda. The holy grail is a \(c^3\)-LTC: one with constant rate, constant distance, and constant query property tester. Just to recall, the rate \(r \in (0,1)\) is the ratio of the message length to the encoding length. The distance \(\delta \in (0,1)\) is the (normalized) Hamming distance between codewords (we typically expect this to be constant for an error correcting code). And, most familiar to us, \(q\) is the number of queries required to property test codewords. The aim is to get all these parameters to be constants independent of the message length. The classic linearity test of BLR basically proves that the Hadamard code is 3-query testable. But the Hadamard code has poor (exponentially small) rate. Low-degree tests prove that Reed-Muller codes are constant-query testable, but they have inverse polynomial rate. Further work constructed LTCs with inverse polylogarithmic rate, meaning that the encoding has length \(n\cdot poly(\log n)\) for message length \(n\). There was even some belief that any LTC must have a rate going to zero. This paper invalidates that belief, and gives a truly \(c^3\)-construction. The construction is based on a 2-dimensional simplicial complex based on Cayley graphs. This is basically a graph with hyperedges corresponding to “squares” of vertices. Concurrent and independent work of <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.09271.pdf">Breuckmann-Ebedhardt</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03654">Panteleev-Kalachev</a> also have similar constructions, though their perspective is of quantum codes.</p>



<p><strong>On the Locally Testable Code of Dinur et al. (2021)</strong> by Oded Goldreich (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/175/">ECCC</a>). As the title says, this short paper gives a high level discussion of the previous result. It abstracts out some of the graph theoretic aspects, to explain connections to more combinatorial constructions. The construction and analysis is based on expander codes. These codes (e.g. low-density parity check, LDPC codes) have constant rate and distance, but we do not know how to test them. A string far from a codeword might only fail on (say) one parity check constraint. Interpreting the Dinur et al as an expander code, we essentially get a collection of correlated parity constraints. Hence, a string that is far from a codeword violates many constraints, leading to a tester. (Of course, this is an extremely watered down version of the analysis idea.) The construction takes two Cayley graphs on a non-Abelian group (which form the vertices). Specific 4-cycles in this graph (together with a constant sized tensor code) are used to make the final codewords.</p>



<p><strong>Strongly Sublinear Algorithms for Testing Pattern Freeness</strong> by Ilan Newman and Nithin Varma (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.04856">arXiv</a>, posted Jun 2021). Pattern freeness is a major generalization of monotonicity testing. The input is (query access to) a function \(f: [n] \mapsto \mathbb{R}\). Let \(\pi: [k] \mapsto [k]\) be a permutation. The input is \(pi\)-free if no restriction of \(f\) to \(k\) elements induces the permutation \(pi\). <a href="http://cs.haifa.ac.il/~ilan/online-papers/permutations.pdf">Newman-Rabinovich-Rajendraprasad-Sohler</a> introduced this problem. When \(k=2\), this property is precisely monotonicity, for which (many) \(O(\varepsilon^{-1} \log n)\) property testers are known. Is such a bound achievable for \(k \geq 3\)? Interestingly, for non-adaptive algorithms, an optimal bound of \(\Theta(n^{1-1/(k-1)})\) (ignoring, \(\varepsilon, k\) dependencies) was achieved by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.10660">Ben-Eliezer and Canonne</a>. This papers shows that there is an adaptive algorithm that makes \(n^{o(1)}\) queries, thereby proving a separation between adaptive and non-adaptive algorithms. A key idea is to visualize the input as a set of points in the plane, and construct a coarse grid that partitions the points. There is a highly non-trivial case analysis on top of this that leads to a \(O(\sqrt{n})\)-query algorithm (this already beats the non-adaptive lower bound).</p>



<p><strong>Parameterized Convexity Testing</strong> by Abhiruk Lahiri, Ilan Newman, and Nithin Varma (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.13012">arXiv</a>, posted Oct 2021). Given a function \(f:[n] \mapsto \mathbb{R}\), the property of interest is (discrete) convexity. The discrete derivatives should be monotonically non-decreasing. It is known that there is a \(O(\varepsilon^{-1}\log n)\) query non-adaptive tester for this property. This paper studies this problem from the perspective of parameterized property testing, where the range is restricted. The main result is that if the number of distinct discrete derivates is at most \(s\), there is a \(O(\varepsilon^{-1} \log s)\) query non-adaptive tester. Moreover, this bound is optimal even for adaptive algorithms. This picture parallels that of monotonicity. Interestingly, when there are only two distinct discrete derivatives, the tester can be made deterministic.</p>



<p><strong>Modularity and edge sampling</strong> by Colin McDiarmid and Fiona Skerman (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.13190">arXiv</a>). Not your typical sublinear algorithms paper, but certainly of interest to us. The main problem is to understand when a random samples of edges in a graph can reveal information about the “community structure”. The modularity of a graph is a measure of this structure. Essentially, a partition has low modularity if the number of edges crossing the partition is close to that of a random graph with the same degree distribution. A partition of high modularity has significant fewer edges, and is thus a valid “clustering” of the graph. The modularity of the graph is obtained by maximizing over partitions. (The normalization of modularity is chosen so that the partition generally has a constant number of sets.) This paper proves a concentration inequality for the modularity of a constant sample of uniform random edges. The modularity of a sample of \(\Theta(\varepsilon^{-5})\) edges is an additive \(\varepsilon\)-approximation of the overall modularity, whp.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-04T23:42:02Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-04T23:42:02Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Seshadhri</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2022-01-21T22:52:56Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/04/faculty-positions-in-human-centered-design-at-the-uc-san-diego-design-lab-assistant-and-associate-professor-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-18-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/04/faculty-positions-in-human-centered-design-at-the-uc-san-diego-design-lab-assistant-and-associate-professor-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-18-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty Positions in Human-Centered Design at the UC San Diego Design Lab (Assistant and Associate Professor) at University of California – San Diego (apply by January 18, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Design Lab at UC San Diego seeks candidates for tenure-track Assistant Professor and tenured Associate Professor faculty positions across multiple disciplines to begin July 1, 2022. We especially seek scholars who engage major societal issues at the intersections of Blackness, Indigeneity, race, migration, gender, sexuality, disability, class and other manifestations of power and difference. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Design Lab at UC San Diego seeks candidates for tenure-track Assistant Professor and tenured Associate Professor faculty positions across multiple disciplines to begin July 1, 2022. We especially seek scholars who engage major societal issues at the intersections of Blackness, Indigeneity, race, migration, gender, sexuality, disability, class and other manifestations of power and difference.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://cse.ucsd.edu/index.php/administration/human-resources/recruitment/faculty-position/assistant-and-associate-professor">https://cse.ucsd.edu/index.php/administration/human-resources/recruitment/faculty-position/assistant-and-associate-professor</a><br/>
Email: nherrera@eng.ucsd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-04T19:58:43Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-04T19:58:43Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-22T07:37:46Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
