<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2021-11-20T15:39:20Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09787</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09787" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Near-Optimal Quantum Algorithms for Multivariate Mean Estimation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637366400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cornelissen:Arjan.html">Arjan Cornelissen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hamoudi:Yassine.html">Yassine Hamoudi</a>, Sofiene Jerbi <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09787">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We propose the first near-optimal quantum algorithm for estimating in
Euclidean norm the mean of a vector-valued random variable with finite mean and
covariance. Our result aims at extending the theory of multivariate
sub-Gaussian estimators to the quantum setting. Unlike classically, where any
univariate estimator can be turned into a multivariate estimator with at most a
logarithmic overhead in the dimension, no similar result can be proved in the
quantum setting. Indeed, Heinrich ruled out the existence of a quantum
advantage for the mean estimation problem when the sample complexity is smaller
than the dimension. Our main result is to show that, outside this low-precision
regime, there is a quantum estimator that outperforms any classical estimator.
Our approach is substantially more involved than in the univariate setting,
where most quantum estimators rely only on phase estimation. We exploit a
variety of additional algorithmic techniques such as amplitude amplification,
the Bernstein-Vazirani algorithm, and quantum singular value transformation.
Our analysis also uses concentration inequalities for multivariate truncated
statistics.
</p>
<p>We develop our quantum estimators in two different input models that showed
up in the literature before. The first one provides coherent access to the
binary representation of the random variable and it encompasses the classical
setting. In the second model, the random variable is directly encoded into the
phases of quantum registers. This model arises naturally in many quantum
algorithms but it is often incomparable to having classical samples. We adapt
our techniques to these two settings and we show that the second model is
strictly weaker for solving the mean estimation problem. Finally, we describe
several applications of our algorithms, notably in measuring the expectation
values of commuting observables and in the field of machine learning.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09766</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09766" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Untangling Circular Drawings: Algorithms and Complexity</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637366400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bhore:Sujoy.html">Sujoy Bhore</a>, Guangping Li, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/N=ouml=llenburg:Martin.html">Martin Nöllenburg</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rutter:Ignaz.html">Ignaz Rutter</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wu:Hsiang=Yun.html">Hsiang-Yun Wu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09766">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the problem of untangling a given (non-planar) straight-line
circular drawing $\delta_G$ of an outerplanar graph $G=(V, E)$ into a planar
straight-line circular drawing by shifting a minimum number of vertices to a
new position on the circle. For an outerplanar graph $G$, it is clear that such
a crossing-free circular drawing always exists and we define the circular
shifting number shift$(\delta_G)$ as the minimum number of vertices that are
required to be shifted in order to resolve all crossings of $\delta_G$. We show
that the problem Circular Untangling, asking whether shift$(\delta_G) \le K$
for a given integer $K$, is NP-complete. For $n$-vertex outerplanar graphs, we
obtain a tight upper bound of shift$(\delta_G) \le n - \lfloor\sqrt{n-2}\rfloor
-2$. Based on these results we study Circular Untangling for almost-planar
circular drawings, in which a single edge is involved in all the crossings. In
this case, we provide a tight upper bound shift$(\delta_G) \le \lfloor
\frac{n}{2} \rfloor-1$ and present a constructive polynomial-time algorithm to
compute the circular shifting number of almost-planar drawings.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09505</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09505" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On Clustering with Discounts</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637366400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Deng:Shichuan.html">Shichuan Deng</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09505">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the $k$-median with discounts problem, wherein we are given clients
with non-negative discounts and seek to open at most $k$ facilities. The goal
is to minimize the sum of distances from each client to its nearest open
facility which is discounted by its own discount value, with minimum
contribution being zero. $k$-median with discounts unifies many classic
clustering problems, e.g., $k$-center, $k$-median, $k$-facility $l$-centrum,
etc. We obtain a bi-criteria constant-factor approximation using an iterative
LP rounding algorithm. Our result improves the previously best approximation
guarantee for $k$-median with discounts [Ganesh et al., ICALP'21]. We also
devise bi-criteria constant-factor approximation algorithms for the matroid and
knapsack versions of median clustering with discounts.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09387</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09387" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Submodular Optimization for Coupled Task Allocation and Intermittent Deployment Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637366400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Jun.html">Jun Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Williams:Ryan_K=.html">Ryan K. Williams</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09387">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we demonstrate a formulation for optimizing coupled submodular
maximization problems with provable sub-optimality bounds. In robotics
applications, it is quite common that optimization problems are coupled with
one another and therefore cannot be solved independently. Specifically, we
consider two problems coupled if the outcome of the first problem affects the
solution of a second problem that operates over a longer time scale. For
example, in our motivating problem of environmental monitoring, we posit that
multi-robot task allocation will potentially impact environmental dynamics and
thus influence the quality of future monitoring, here modeled as a multi-robot
intermittent deployment problem. The general theoretical approach for solving
this type of coupled problem is demonstrated through this motivating example.
Specifically, we propose a method for solving coupled problems modeled by
submodular set functions with matroid constraints. A greedy algorithm for
solving this class of problem is presented, along with sub-optimality
guarantees. Finally, practical optimality ratios are shown through Monte Carlo
simulations to demonstrate that the proposed algorithm can generate
near-optimal solutions with high efficiency.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09386</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09386" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Monitoring Over the Long Term: Intermittent Deployment and Sensing Strategies for Multi-Robot Teams</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637366400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Jun.html">Jun Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Williams:Ryan_K=.html">Ryan K. Williams</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09386">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we formulate and solve the intermittent deployment problem,
which yields strategies that couple \emph{when} heterogeneous robots should
sense an environmental process, with where a deployed team should sense in the
environment. As a motivation, suppose that a spatiotemporal process is slowly
evolving and must be monitored by a multi-robot team, e.g., unmanned aerial
vehicles monitoring pasturelands in a precision agriculture context. In such a
case, an intermittent deployment strategy is necessary as persistent deployment
or monitoring is not cost-efficient for a slowly evolving process. At the same
time, the problem of where to sense once deployed must be solved as process
observations yield useful feedback for determining effective future deployment
and monitoring decisions. In this context, we model the environmental process
to be monitored as a spatiotemporal Gaussian process with mutual information as
a criterion to measure our understanding of the environment. To make the
sensing resource-efficient, we demonstrate how to use matroid constraints to
impose a diverse set of homogeneous and heterogeneous constraints. In addition,
to reflect the cost-sensitive nature of real-world applications, we apply
budgets on the cost of deployed heterogeneous robot teams. To solve the
resulting problem, we exploit the theories of submodular optimization and
matroids and present a greedy algorithm with bounds on sub-optimality. Finally,
Monte Carlo simulations demonstrate the correctness of the proposed method.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09376</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09376" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal Decremental Connectivity in Non-Sparse Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637366400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Anders Aaman, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Karczmarz:Adam.html">Adam Karczmarz</a>, Jakub Łącki, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Parotsidis:Nikos.html">Nikos Parotsidis</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rasmussen:Peter_M=_R=.html">Peter M. R. Rasmussen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Thorup:Mikkel.html">Mikkel Thorup</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09376">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a dynamic algorithm for maintaining the connected and
2-edge-connected components in an undirected graph subject to edge deletions.
The algorithm is Monte-Carlo randomized and processes any sequence of edge
deletions in $O(m + n \operatorname{polylog} n)$ total time. Interspersed with
the deletions, it can answer queries to whether any two given vertices
currently belong to the same (2-edge-)connected component in constant time. Our
result is based on a general Monte-Carlo randomized reduction from decremental
$c$-edge-connectivity to a variant of fully-dynamic $c$-edge-connectivity on a
sparse graph.
</p>
<p>For non-sparse graphs with $\Omega(n \operatorname{polylog} n)$ edges, our
connectivity and $2$-edge-connectivity algorithms handle all deletions in
optimal linear total time, using existing algorithms for the respective
fully-dynamic problems. This improves upon an $O(m \log (n^2 / m) + n
\operatorname{polylog} n)$-time algorithm of Thorup [J.Alg. 1999], which runs
in linear time only for graphs with $\Omega(n^2)$ edges.
</p>
<p>Our constant amortized cost for edge deletions in decremental connectivity in
non-sparse graphs should be contrasted with an $\Omega(\log n/\log\log n)$
worst-case time lower bound in the decremental setting [Alstrup, Thore
Husfeldt, FOCS'98] as well as an $\Omega(\log n)$ amortized time lower-bound in
the fully-dynamic setting [Patrascu and Demaine STOC'04].
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09309</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09309" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Stream Sampling with Immediate Decision</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637366400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Panahbehagh:Bardia.html">Bardia Panahbehagh</a>, Raphaël Jauslin, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Till=eacute=:Yves.html">Yves Tillé</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09309">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The manuscript introduces a method to select a random sample from a stream by
deciding on each sampling unit immediately after observing it. The process
could be applied to unequal as well as equal probability sampling. The
implementation is straightforward. Algorithm selects a unit in the sample based
on a single condition. It is particularly effective to make direct decisions on
stream data, despite the data arriving in groups or the stream being linear.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/19/simons-berkeley-fellowships-for-fall-2022-and-spring-2023-at-simons-institute-for-the-theory-of-computing-apply-by-december-15-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/19/simons-berkeley-fellowships-for-fall-2022-and-spring-2023-at-simons-institute-for-the-theory-of-computing-apply-by-december-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Simons-Berkeley Fellowships for Fall 2022 and Spring 2023 at Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing (apply by December 15, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing invites applications for Simons-Berkeley Research Fellowships for the Fall 2022 and Spring 2023 semesters. The Institute will host programs on “Data-Driven Decision Processes” and “Graph Limits and Processes on Networks: From Epidemics to Misinformation” in Fall 2022 and “Meta-Complexity in Spring 2023. Website: https://simons.berkeley.edu/simons-berkeley-research-fellowship-call-applications Email: simonsvisitorservices@berkeley.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing invites applications for Simons-Berkeley Research Fellowships for the Fall 2022 and Spring 2023 semesters. The Institute will host programs on “Data-Driven Decision Processes” and “Graph Limits and Processes on Networks: From Epidemics to Misinformation” in Fall 2022 and “Meta-Complexity in Spring 2023.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/simons-berkeley-research-fellowship-call-applications">https://simons.berkeley.edu/simons-berkeley-research-fellowship-call-applications</a><br/>
Email: simonsvisitorservices@berkeley.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-19T22:07:32Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-19T22:07:32Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6129</id>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6129" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6129#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=6129" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">The Acrobatics of BQP</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Just in case anyone is depressed this afternoon and needs something to cheer them up, students William Kretschmer, DeVon Ingram, and I have finally put out a new paper: The Acrobatics of BQP Abstract: We show that, in the black-box setting, the behavior of quantum polynomial-time (BQP) can be remarkably decoupled from that of classical […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Just in case anyone is depressed this afternoon and needs something to cheer them up, students <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~kretsch/">William Kretschmer</a>, <a href="https://www.quantitativebiology.northwestern.edu/2021/02/23/three-students-awarded-prizes-in-the-great-math-challenge-in-biology-contest/">DeVon Ingram</a>, and I have finally put out a new paper:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><strong><a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/164/">The Acrobatics of BQP</a></strong></p><p><strong>Abstract:</strong> We show that, in the black-box setting, the behavior of quantum polynomial-time (BQP) can be remarkably decoupled from that of classical complexity classes like NP.  Specifically:</p><p>– There exists an oracle relative to which NP<sup>BQP</sup>⊄BQP<sup>PH</sup>, resolving a 2005 problem of Fortnow. Interpreted another way, we show that AC<sup>0</sup> circuits cannot perform useful homomorphic encryption on instances of the Forrelation problem. As a corollary, there exists an oracle relative to which P=NP but BQP≠QCMA.</p><p>– Conversely, there exists an oracle relative to which BQP<sup>NP</sup>⊄PH<sup>BQP</sup>.</p><p>– Relative to a random oracle, PP=PostBQP is not contained in the “QMA hierarchy” QMA<sup>QMA^QMA^…</sup>, and more generally PP⊄(MIP*)<sup>(MIP*)^(MIP*)^…</sup> (!), despite the fact that MIP*=RE in the unrelativized world. This result shows that there is no black-box quantum analogue of Stockmeyer’s approximate counting algorithm.</p><p>– Relative to a random oracle, Σ<sub>k+1</sub>⊄BQP<sup>Σ_k</sup> for every k.</p><p>– There exists an oracle relative to which BQP=P<sup>#P</sup> and yet PH is infinite. (By contrast, if NP⊆BPP, then PH collapses relative to all oracles.)</p><p>– There exists an oracle relative to which P=NP≠BQP=P<sup>#P</sup>.</p><p>To achieve these results, we build on the 2018 achievement by Raz and Tal of an oracle relative to which BQP⊄PH, and associated results about the Forrelation problem. We also introduce new tools that might be of independent interest. These include a “quantum-aware” version of the random restriction method, a concentration theorem for the block sensitivity of AC<sup>0</sup> circuits, and a (provable) analogue of the Aaronson-Ambainis Conjecture for sparse oracles.</p></blockquote>



<p>Incidentally, particularly when I’ve worked on a project with students, I’m often tremendously excited and want to shout about it from the rooftops for the students’ sake … but then I also don’t want to use this blog to privilege my own papers “unfairly.”  Can anyone suggest a principle that I should follow going forward?</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-19T21:48:06Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-19T21:48:06Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <icon>https://scottaaronson.blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-Jacket-32x32.gif</icon>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T21:48:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/19/postdoc-at-georgia-institute-of-technology-apply-by-december-15-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/19/postdoc-at-georgia-institute-of-technology-apply-by-december-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PostDoc at Georgia Institute of Technology (apply by December 15, 2021)</title>
    <summary>Algorithms and Randomness Center (ARC) at Georgia Tech is seeking postdoctoral fellows starting Fall 2022. ARC has faculty associated with many departments including CS, Math, ISyE. The selected candidate may work on any aspect of algorithms, optimization, broadly interpreted. Qualified applicants must possess a PhD in CS, Math, OR or a related field. Apply by […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Algorithms and Randomness Center (ARC) at Georgia Tech is seeking postdoctoral fellows starting Fall 2022. ARC has faculty associated with many departments including CS, Math, ISyE. The selected candidate may work on any aspect of algorithms, optimization, broadly interpreted. Qualified applicants must possess a PhD in CS, Math, OR or a related field. Apply by December 15, 2021.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://arc.gatech.edu/node/384">http://arc.gatech.edu/node/384</a><br/>
Email: ftonge3@cc.gatech.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-19T20:01:19Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-19T20:01:19Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://toc4fairness.org/?p=1968</id>
    <link href="https://toc4fairness.org/our-2022-postdoc-program-is-up/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Our 2022 Postdoc Program is up</title>
    <summary>We are excited to announce our new postdoc program. We are seeking strong candidates from a diverse set of academic backgrounds and personal experiences who want to work with one ...</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We are excited to announce <a href="https://toc4fairness.org/postdoc-opportunities/">our new postdoc program</a>. We are seeking strong candidates from a diverse set of academic backgrounds and personal experiences who want to work with one or more of the PIs on algorithmic fairness and responsible computing more broadly. We expect to be extending multiple offers.  </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-19T13:45:11Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-19T13:45:11Z</published>
    <category term="Blog"/>
    <author>
      <name>Omer Reingold</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://toc4fairness.org</id>
      <logo>https://i1.wp.com/toc4fairness.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/cropped-favicon.png?fit=32%2C32&amp;ssl=1</logo>
      <link href="https://toc4fairness.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://toc4fairness.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a simons collaboration project</subtitle>
      <title>TOC for Fairness</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:39:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/164</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/164" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-164 |  The Acrobatics of BQP | 

	Scott Aaronson, 

	DeVon Ingram, 

	William Kretschmer</title>
    <summary>We show that, in the black-box setting, the behavior of quantum polynomial-time (${BQP}$) can be remarkably decoupled from that of classical complexity classes like ${NP}$. Specifically:

-There exists an oracle relative to which ${NP}^{{BQP}}\not \subset {BQP}^{{PH}}$, resolving a 2005 problem of Fortnow. Interpreted another way, we show that ${AC^0}$ circuits cannot perform useful homomorphic encryption on instances of the Forrelation problem. As a corollary, there exists an oracle relative to which ${P} = {NP}$ but ${BQP} \neq {QCMA}$.
-Conversely, there exists an oracle relative to which ${BQP}^{{NP}}\not \subset {PH}^{{BQP}}$.
-Relative to a random oracle, ${PP} = {PostBQP}$ is not contained in the "${QMA}$ hierarchy" ${QMA}^{{QMA}^{{QMA}^{\cdots}}}$, and more generally ${PP} \not\subset ({MIP}^*)^{({MIP}^*)^{({MIP}^*)^{\cdots}}}$ (!), despite the fact that ${MIP}^{\ast}={RE}$ in the unrelativized world. This result shows that there is no black-box quantum analogue of Stockmeyer's approximate counting algorithm.
-Relative to a random oracle, ${\Sigma}_{k+1}^{P} \not\subset {BQP}^{{\Sigma}_{k}^{P}}$ for every $k$.
-There exists an oracle relative to which ${BQP} = {P^{\# P}}$ and yet ${PH}$ is infinite. (By contrast, if ${NP}\subseteq{BPP}$, then ${PH}$ collapses relative to all oracles.)
-There exists an oracle relative to which ${P}={NP} \neq {BQP}={P}^{{\#P}}$.

To achieve these results, we build on the 2018 achievement by Raz and Tal of an oracle relative to which ${BQP}\not \subset {PH}$, and associated results about the Forrelation problem. We also introduce new tools that might be of independent interest. These include a "quantum-aware" version of the random restriction method, a concentration theorem for the block sensitivity of ${AC^0}$ circuits, and a (provable) analogue of the Aaronson-Ambainis Conjecture for sparse oracles.</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-19T13:02:40Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-19T13:02:40Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09762</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09762" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hybrid Super Intelligence and Polymetric Analysis</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637280000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dorofeev:Vladislav.html">Vladislav Dorofeev</a>, Petro Trokhimchuk <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09762">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The problem of possible applications Polymetric Analysis for the resolution
problems of artificial Intelligence is discussed. As example the hybrid super
intelligence system by N. Moiseev type was selected. The bond between
polymetric analysis and hybrid super intelligence system was shown. In
operational sense polymetric analysis is more general system. Therefore main
principles of Moiseev concept may be unify with the help of polymetric
analysis. Main peculiarities of this unification are analyzed.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-19T22:41:43Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09691</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09691" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the Recoverable Traveling Salesman Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637280000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Goerigk:Marc.html">Marc Goerigk</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lendl:Stefan.html">Stefan Lendl</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wulf:Lasse.html">Lasse Wulf</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09691">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper we consider the Recoverable Traveling Salesman Problem (TSP).
Here the task is to find two tours simultaneously, such that the intersection
between the tours is at least a given minimum size, while the sum of travel
distances with respect to two different distance metrics is minimized. Building
upon the classic double-tree method, we derive a 4-approximation algorithm for
the RecoverableTSP. We also show that if the required size of the intersection
between the tours is constant, a 2-approximation guarantee can be achieved,
even if more than two tours need to be constructed. We discuss consequences for
approximability results in the more general area of recoverable robust
optimization.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09671</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09671" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Variant of the VC-dimension with Applications to Depth-3 Circuits</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637280000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Frankl:Peter.html">Peter Frankl</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gryaznov:Svyatoslav.html">Svyatoslav Gryaznov</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Talebanfard:Navid.html">Navid Talebanfard</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09671">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We introduce the following variant of the VC-dimension. Given $S \subseteq
\{0, 1\}^n$ and a positive integer $d$, we define $\mathbb{U}_d(S)$ to be the
size of the largest subset $I \subseteq [n]$ such that the projection of $S$ on
every subset of $I$ of size $d$ is the $d$-dimensional cube. We show that
determining the largest cardinality of a set with a given $\mathbb{U}_d$
dimension is equivalent to a Tur\'an-type problem related to the total number
of cliques in a $d$-uniform hypergraph. This allows us to beat the
Sauer--Shelah lemma for this notion of dimension. We use this to obtain several
results on $\Sigma_3^k$-circuits, i.e., depth-$3$ circuits with top gate OR and
bottom fan-in at most $k$:
</p>
<p>* Tight relationship between the number of satisfying assignments of a
$2$-CNF and the dimension of the largest projection accepted by it, thus
improving Paturi, Saks, and Zane (Comput. Complex. '00).
</p>
<p>* Improved $\Sigma_3^3$-circuit lower bounds for affine dispersers for
sublinear dimension. Moreover, we pose a purely hypergraph-theoretic conjecture
under which we get further improvement.
</p>
<p>* We make progress towards settling the $\Sigma_3^2$ complexity of the inner
product function and all degree-$2$ polynomials over $\mathbb{F}_2$ in general.
The question of determining the $\Sigma_3^3$ complexity of IP was recently
posed by Golovnev, Kulikov, and Williams (ITCS'21).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-19T22:39:20Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09472</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09472" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Exploring Airline Gate-Scheduling Optimization Using Quantum Computers</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637280000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mohammadbagherpoor:Hamed.html">Hamed Mohammadbagherpoor</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dreher:Patrick.html">Patrick Dreher</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Ibrahim:Mohannad.html">Mohannad Ibrahim</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Oh:Young=Hyun.html">Young-Hyun Oh</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hall:James.html">James Hall</a>, Richard E Stone, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Stojkovic:Mirela.html">Mirela Stojkovic</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09472">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper investigates the application of quantum computing technology to
airline gate-scheduling quadratic assignment problems (QAP). We explore the
quantum computing hardware architecture and software environment required for
porting classical versions of these type of problems to quantum computers. We
discuss the variational quantum eigensolver and the inclusion of
space-efficient graph coloring to the Quadratic Unconstrained Binary
Optimization (QUBO). These enhanced quantum computing algorithms are tested
with an 8 gate and 24 flight test case using both the IBM quantum computing
simulator and a 27 qubit superconducting transmon IBM quantum computing
hardware platform.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-19T22:41:02Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09375</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.09375" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hypercontractivity on high dimensional expanders</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637280000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gur:Tom.html">Tom Gur</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lifshitz:Noam.html">Noam Lifshitz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Siqi.html">Siqi Liu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2111.09375">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We prove hypercontractive inequalities on high dimensional expanders. As in
the settings of the p-biased hypercube, the symmetric group, and the Grassmann
scheme, our inequalities are effective for global functions, which are
functions that are not significantly affected by a restriction of a small set
of coordinates. As applications, we obtain Fourier concentration, small-set
expansion, and Kruskal-Katona theorems for high dimensional expanders. Our
techniques rely on a new approximate Efron-Stein decomposition for high
dimensional link expanders.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-19T22:37:36Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2105.07305</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2105.07305" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Distributed Resilient Submodular Action Selection in Adversarial Environments</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1637280000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Jun.html">Jun Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhou:Lifeng.html">Lifeng Zhou</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tokekar:Pratap.html">Pratap Tokekar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Williams:Ryan_K=.html">Ryan K. Williams</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2105.07305">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this letter, we consider a distributed submodular maximization problem for
multi-robot systems when attacked by adversaries. One of the major challenges
for multi-robot systems is to increase resilience against failures or attacks.
This is particularly important for distributed systems under attack as there is
no central point of command that can detect, mitigate, and recover from
attacks. Instead, a distributed multi-robot system must coordinate effectively
to overcome adversarial attacks. In this work, our distributed submodular
action selection problem models a broad set of scenarios where each robot in a
multi-robot system has multiple action selections that may fulfill a global
objective, such as exploration or target tracking. To increase resilience in
this context, we propose a fully distributed algorithm to guide each robot's
action selection when the system is attacked. The proposed algorithm guarantees
performance in a worst-case scenario where up to a portion of the robots
malfunction due to attacks. Importantly, the proposed algorithm is also
consistent, as it is shown to converge to the same solution as a centralized
method. Finally, a distributed resilient multi-robot exploration problem is
presented to confirm the performance of the proposed algorithm.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-11-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/163</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/163" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-163 |  Algorithmizing the Multiplicity Schwartz-Zippel Lemma | 

	Siddharth Bhandari, 

	Prahladh Harsha, 

	Mrinal Kumar, 

	A. Shankar</title>
    <summary>The multiplicity Schwartz-Zippel lemma asserts that over a field, a low-degree polynomial cannot vanish with high multiplicity very often on a sufficiently large product set. Since its discovery in a work of Dvir, Kopparty, Saraf and Sudan [DKSS13], the lemma has found nu- merous applications in both math and computer science; in particular, in the definition and properties of multiplicity codes by Kopparty, Saraf and Yekhanin [KSY14].

In this work, we show how to algorithmize the multiplicity Schwartz-Zippel lemma for ar- bitrary product sets over any field. In other words, we give an efficient algorithm for unique decoding of multivariate multiplicity codes from half their minimum distance on arbitrary product sets over all fields. Previously, such an algorithm was known either when the un- derlying product set had a nice algebraic structure (for instance, was a subfield) [Kop15] or when the underlying field had large (or zero) characteristic, the multiplicity parameter was sufficiently large and the multiplicity code had distance bounded away from 1 [BHKS21]. In particular, even unique decoding of bivariate multiplicity codes with multiplicity two from half their minimum distance was not known over arbitrary product sets over any field.

Our algorithm builds upon a result of Kim &amp; Kopparty [KK17] who gave an algorithmic version of the Schwartz-Zippel lemma (without multiplicities) or equivalently, an efficient al- gorithm for unique decoding of Reed-Muller codes over arbitrary product sets. We introduce a refined notion of distance based on the multiplicity Schwartz-Zippel lemma and design a unique decoding algorithm for this distance measure. On the way, we give an alternate proof of Forney’s classical generalized minimum distance decoder that might be of independent interest.</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-18T23:12:39Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-18T23:12:39Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/18/postdocs-at-universite-de-lyon-ens-lyon-apply-by-january-4-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/18/postdocs-at-universite-de-lyon-ens-lyon-apply-by-january-4-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdocs at Université de Lyon / ENS Lyon (apply by January 4, 2022)</title>
    <summary>Two postdoctoral positions in mathematics, computer science and their interactions are open for the period 2022-2024. Website: https://milyon.universite-lyon.fr/postdoctoral-positions-2022-2024-130160.kjsp?RH=1571748911317 Email: [guillaume.hanrot,nicolas.trotignon]@ens-lyon.fr</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Two postdoctoral positions in mathematics, computer science and their interactions are open for the period 2022-2024.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://milyon.universite-lyon.fr/postdoctoral-positions-2022-2024-130160.kjsp?RH=1571748911317">https://milyon.universite-lyon.fr/postdoctoral-positions-2022-2024-130160.kjsp?RH=1571748911317</a><br/>
Email: [guillaume.hanrot,nicolas.trotignon]@ens-lyon.fr</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-18T11:27:50Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-18T11:27:50Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/162</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/162" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-162 |  Fast, Algebraic Multivariate Multipoint Evaluation in Small Characteristic and Applications | 

	Vishwas Bhargava, 

	Sumanta Ghosh, 

	Mrinal Kumar, 

	Chandra Kanta Mohapatra</title>
    <summary>Multipoint evaluation is the computational task of evaluating a polynomial given as a list of coefficients at a given set of inputs. Besides being a natural and fundamental question in computer algebra on its own, fast algorithms for this problem is also closely related to fast algorithms for other natural algebraic questions like polynomial factorization and modular composition. And while \emph{nearly linear time} algorithms have been known for the univariate instance of multipoint evaluation  for close to five decades due to a work of Borodin and Moenck \cite{BM74}, fast algorithms for the multivariate version have been much harder to come by. In a significant improvement to the state of art for this problem, Umans \cite{Umans08} and Kedlaya \&amp; Umans \cite{Kedlaya11} gave nearly linear time algorithms for this problem over field of small characteristic and over all finite fields respectively, provided that the number of variables $n$ is at most $d^{o(1)}$ where the degree of the input polynomial in every variable is less than $d$. They also stated the question of designing fast algorithms for the large variable case (i.e. $n \notin d^{o(1)}$) as an open problem. 

In this work, we show that there is a deterministic algorithm for multivariate multipoint evaluation over a field $\F_{q}$ of characteristic $p$ which evaluates an $n$-variate polynomial of degree less than $d$ in each variable on $N$ inputs in time $$\left((N + d^n)^{1 + o(1)}\poly(\log q, d, p, n)\right) \, ,$$ provided that $p$ is at most $d^{o(1)}$, and $q$ is at most $(\exp(\exp(\exp(\cdots (\exp(d)))))$, where the height of this tower of exponentials is fixed. When the number of variables is large (e.g. $n \notin d^{o(1)}$), this is the first {nearly linear} time algorithm for this problem over any (large enough) field.

Our algorithm is based on elementary algebraic ideas and this algebraic structure naturally leads to the following two independently interesting applications.

\begin{itemize}
\item We  show that there is an \emph{algebraic} data structure for univariate polynomial evaluation with nearly linear space complexity and sublinear time complexity over finite fields of small characteristic and quasipolynomially bounded size. This  provides a counterexample to a conjecture of Milterson \cite{M95} who conjectured that over small finite fields, any algebraic data structure for polynomial evaluation using  polynomial space must have linear query complexity. 

 \item We also show that over finite fields of small characteristic and quasipolynomially bounded size,  Vandermonde matrices are not rigid enough to  yield size-depth tradeoffs for linear circuits via the current quantitative bounds in Valiant's program \cite{Valiant1977}. More precisely, for every fixed prime $p$, we show that for every constant $\epsilon &gt; 0$, and large enough $n$, the rank of any $n \times n$ Vandermonde matrix $V$ over the field $\F_{p^a}$ can be reduced to $
   \left(n/\exp(\Omega(\poly(\epsilon)\sqrt{\log n}))\right) $ by changing at most $n^{\Theta(\epsilon)}$ entries in every row of $V$, provided $a \leq \poly(\log n)$. Prior to this work, similar upper bounds on rigidity were known only for special Vandermonde matrices. For instance, the Discrete Fourier Transform matrices and Vandermonde matrices with generators in a geometric progression \cite{DL20}. 
   
\end{itemize}</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-17T21:05:46Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-17T21:05:46Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-1208458514334119738</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/1208458514334119738/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/11/cs-slow-to-change.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1208458514334119738" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1208458514334119738" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/11/cs-slow-to-change.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>CS Slow to Change?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Back in March of 2019 <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/03/scooped.html">I wrote</a></p><blockquote><p>I was also going to post about Yann LeCun's Facebook rant about stodgy CS departments but then Yann goes ahead and wins a Turing award with Geoffrey Hinton and Yoshua Bengio for their work on machine learning. I knew Yann from when we worked together at NEC Research in the early 2000's and let's just congratulate him and the others and let them bask in glory for truly transforming how we think of computing today. I'll get back to his post soon enough.</p></blockquote><p>So not that soon. Yann's <a href="https://www.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=10152719972317143&amp;id=722677142">post</a> was from 2015 where he went after "stodgy" CS departments naming Yale, Harvard, Princeton and Chicago.</p><blockquote><p>CS is a quickly evolving field.  Because of excess conservatism, these departments have repeatedly missed important trends in CS and related field, such as Data Science. They seem to view CS as meaning strictly theory, crypto, systems and programming  languages, what some have called "core CS", paying lip service to graphics, vision, machine learning, AI, HCI, robotics, etc. But these areas are the ones that have been expanding the fastest in the last decades, particularly machine learning and computer vision in the last decade....It is quite common, and somewhat natural, that newer areas (eg ML) be looked down upon by members of older, more established areas (eg Theory and Systems). After all, scientists are professional skeptics. But in a fast evolving disciplines like CS and now Data Science, an excessive aversion to risk and change is a recipe for failure.</p></blockquote><p>We've seen some changes since. Yale's Statistics Department is now <a href="https://statistics.yale.edu/">Statistics and Data Science</a>. The University of Chicago has a new Data Science <a href="https://news.uchicago.edu/story/new-college-data-science-major-foundations-insight-impact">undergrad major</a> and <a href="https://cdac.uchicago.edu/insights/introducing-the-uchicago-data-science-institute/">institute</a>.</p><p>I wonder if that's the future. CS doesn't really change that much, at least not quickly. Data science, and perhaps cybersecurity, evolve as separate fields which only have limited intersection with traditional CS. The CS degree itself just focuses on those interested in how the machines work and the theory behind them. We're busy trying to figure this out at Illinois Tech as are most other schools. And what about augmented/virtual reality and the metaverse, quantum computing, fintech, social networks, human and social factors and so on? How do you choose which bets to make? </p><p>Most of all, universities, traditionally slowly moving machines, need to far more agile even in fields outside computing since the digital transformation is affecting everything. How do you plan degrees when the computing landscape when students graduate is different from when they start? </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-17T18:44:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-17T18:44:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T00:14:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6111</id>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6111" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6111#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=6111" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Scott Aaronson, when reached for comment, said…</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">About IBM’s new 127-qubit superconducting chip: As I told New Scientist, I look forward to seeing the actual details! As far as I could see, the marketing materials that IBM released yesterday take a lot of words to say absolutely nothing about what, to experts, is the single most important piece of information: namely, what […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><strong>About IBM’s new <a href="https://research.ibm.com/blog/127-qubit-quantum-processor-eagle">127-qubit superconducting chip</a>:</strong> As I <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/2297583-ibm-creates-largest-ever-superconducting-quantum-computer/">told <em>New Scientist</em></a>, I look forward to seeing the actual details!  As far as I could see, the marketing materials that IBM released yesterday take a lot of words to say absolutely nothing about what, to experts, is the single most important piece of information: namely, <em>what are the gate fidelities?</em>  How deep of a quantum circuit can they apply?  How have they benchmarked the chip?  Right now, all I have to go on is a <a href="https://quantum-computing.ibm.com/services?services=systems&amp;order=qubits%20DESC&amp;view=table&amp;system=ibm_washington">stats page</a> for the new chip, <s>which reports its average CNOT error as 0.9388—in other words, close to 1, or terrible! (But see also a <a href="https://twitter.com/decodoku/status/1460622008916627456?s=21">tweet by James Wootton</a>, which explains that such numbers are often highly misleading when a new chip is first rolled out.)  Does anyone here have more information?</s>  <strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update (11/17):</span></strong> As of this morning, the average CNOT error has been updated to 2%.  Thanks to multiple commenters for letting me know!</p>



<p><strong>About the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.14502">new simulation</a> of Google’s 53-qubit Sycamore chip in 5 minutes on a Sunway supercomputer (see also <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.01066">here</a>):</strong> This is an exciting step forward on the classical validation of quantum supremacy experiments, and—ironically, what currently amounts to almost the same thing—on the classical <em>spoofing</em> of those experiments.  Congratulations to the team in China that achieved this!  But there are two crucial things to understand.  First, “5 minutes” refers to the time needed to calculate a <em>single</em> amplitude (or perhaps, several correlated amplitudes) using tensor network contraction.  It doesn’t refer to the time needed to generate millions of <em>independent</em> noisy samples, which is what Google’s Sycamore chip does in 3 minutes.  For the latter task, more like a week still seems to be needed on the supercomputer.  (I’m grateful to Chu Guo, a coauthor of the new work who spoke in UT Austin’s weekly quantum Zoom meeting, for clarifying this point.)  Second, the Sunway supercomputer has parallel processing power equivalent to approximately ten million of your laptop.  Thus, even if we agreed that Google no longer had quantum supremacy as measured by time, it would still have quantum supremacy as measured by carbon footprint!  (And this despite the fact that the quantum computer itself requires a noisy, closet-sized dilution fridge.)  Even so, for me the new work underscores the point that quantum supremacy is not yet a done deal.  Over the next few years, I hope that Google and USTC, as well as any new entrants to this race (IBM? IonQ? Harvard? Rigetti?), will push forward with more qubits and, even more importantly, better gate fidelities leading to higher Linear Cross-Entropy scores.  Meanwhile, we theorists should try to do our part by inventing new and better protocols with which to demonstrate near-term quantum supremacy—<em>especially</em> protocols for which the classical verification is easier.</p>



<p><strong>About the new anti-woke <a href="https://bariweiss.substack.com/p/we-cant-wait-for-universities-to">University of Austin</a> (UATX):</strong> In general, I’m extremely happy for people to experiment with new and different institutions, and of course I’m happy for more intellectual activity in my adopted city of Austin.  And, as <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em> readers will know, I’m probably more sympathetic than most to the reality of the problem that UATX is trying to solve—living, as we do, in an era when one academic after another has been cancelled for ideas that a mere decade ago would’ve been considered unexceptional, moderate, center-left.  Having said all that, I wish I could feel more optimistic about UATX’s prospects.  I found its <a href="https://www.uaustin.org/">website</a> heavy on free-speech rhetoric but frustratingly light on what the new university is actually going to <em>do</em>: what courses it will offer, who will teach them, where the campus will be, etc. etc.  Arguably this is all excusable for a university still in ramp-up mode, but had I been in their shoes, I might have held off on the public launch until I had at least some sample content to offer.  Certainly, the fact that Steven Pinker has <a href="https://www.uaustin.org/news/uatx-statement-about-robert-zimmer-and-steven-pinker">quit UATX’s advisory board</a> is a discouraging sign.  If UATX asks me to get involved—to lecture there, to give them advice about their CS program, etc.—I’ll consider it as I would any other request.  So far, though, they haven’t.</p>



<p><strong>About the Association for Mathematical Research:</strong> Last month, some colleagues invited me to join a brand-new society called the <a href="https://amathr.org/">Association for Mathematical Research</a>.  Many of the other founders (Joel Hass, Abigail Thompson, Colin Adams, Richard Borcherds, Jeff Cheeger, Pavel Etingof, Tom Hales, Jeff Lagarias, Mark Lackenby, Cliff Taubes, …) were brilliant mathematicians who I admired, they seemed like they could use a bit of theoretical computer science representation, there was no time commitment, maybe they’d eventually do something good, so I figured why not?  Alas, to say that AMR has proved unpopular on Twitter would be an understatement: it’s received the same contemptuous reception that UATX has.  The argument seems to be: starting a new mathematical society, even an avowedly diverse and apolitical one, is really just an implicit claim that the existing societies, like the <a href="https://www.maa.org/">Mathematical Association of America (MAA)</a>  and the <a href="https://www.ams.org/home/page">American Mathematical Society (AMS)</a>, have been co-opted by woke true-believers.  But that’s paranoid and insane!  I mean, it’s not as if an <a href="https://blogs.ams.org/inclusionexclusion/">AMS blog</a> has called for the <a href="https://blogs.ams.org/inclusionexclusion/2017/05/11/get-out-the-way/#more-772">mass resignation</a> of white male mathematicians to make room for the marginalized, or the boycott of Israeli universities, or the abolition of the criminal justice system <font size="-3"><em>(what to do about Kyle Rittenhouse though?)</em></font>.  Still, even though claims of that sort of co-option are obviously far-out, rabid fantasies, yeah, I did decide to give a new organization the benefit of the doubt.  AMR might well fail or languish in obscurity, just like UATX might.  On the other hand, the barriers to making a positive difference for the intellectual world, the world I love, the world under constant threat from the self-certain ideologues of every side, do strike me as orders of magnitude smaller for a new professional society than they do for a new university.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-16T23:06:35Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-16T23:06:35Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Obviously I'm Not Defending Aaronson"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <icon>https://scottaaronson.blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-Jacket-32x32.gif</icon>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2021-11-19T21:48:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://dstheory.wordpress.com/?p=105</id>
    <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2021/11/16/thursday-nov-18th-nicole-immorlica-from-msr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Thursday Nov 18th — Nicole Immorlica  from Microsoft Research</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The next Foundations of Data Science virtual talk will take place on Thursday, Nov 18th at 10:00 AM Pacific Time (13:00 Eastern Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). Nicole Immorlica from Microsoft Research will speak about “Communicating with Anecdotes”. Please register here to join the virtual talk. Abstract: Classic models of communication in economics typically assume<a class="more-link" href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2021/11/16/thursday-nov-18th-nicole-immorlica-from-msr/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">"Thursday Nov 18th — Nicole Immorlica  from Microsoft Research"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="has-text-align-justify">The next <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory/home" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Foundations of Data Science</a> virtual talk will take place on <strong>Thursday, Nov 18</strong>th at <strong>10:00 AM Pacific Time</strong> (13:00 Eastern Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). <strong><a href="https://immorlica.com/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Nicole Immorlica</a></strong> from<strong> Microsoft Research</strong> will speak about “Communicating with Anecdotes”.</p>



<p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Please register here to join the virtual talk.</a></p>



<p class="has-text-align-justify"><strong>Abstract</strong>: Classic models of communication in economics typically assume agents can communicate any message.  However, many important communications, such as those in newspapers or politicians’ speeches, use data to convey information.  In this talk, we explore how the reliance on data impacts communication.  In our model, there are two Bayesian agents (a sender and a receiver) who wish to communicate. The receiver must take an action whose payoff depends on their personal preferences and an unknown state of the world. The sender has access to a collection of data points correlated with the state of the world and can send exactly one of these to the receiver in order to influence her choice of action. Importantly, the sender’s personal preferences may differ from the receiver’s, which affects the sender’s strategic choice of what to send. We show that in a Nash equilibrium even a small difference in preferences can lead to a significant bias in the communicated datum. This can significantly reduce informativeness of the communication, leading to substantial utility loss for both sides. One implication is informational homophily: a receiver can rationally prefer to obtain data from a poorly-informed sender with aligned preferences, rather than a knowledgeable expert whose preferences may differ from her own.  </p>



<p>Joint work with Nika Haghtalab, Brendan Lucier, Markus Mobius and Divya Mohan.</p>



<p>The series is supported by the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1934846&amp;HistoricalAwards=false">NSF HDR TRIPODS Grant 1934846</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-16T17:07:03Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-16T17:07:03Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>dstheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://dstheory.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Foundation of Data Science – Virtual Talk Series</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:39:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/161</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/161" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-161 |  On Worst-Case Learning in Relativized Heuristica | 

	Mikito Nanashima, 

	Shuichi Hirahara</title>
    <summary>A PAC learning model involves two worst-case requirements: a learner must learn all functions in a class on all example distributions. However, basing the hardness of learning on NP-hardness has remained a key challenge for decades. In fact, recent progress in computational complexity suggests the possibility that a weaker assumption might be sufficient for worst-case learning than the feasibility of worst-case algorithms for NP problems.

In this study, we investigate whether these worst-case requirements for learning are satisfied on the basis of only average-case assumptions in order to understand the nature of learning. First, we construct a strong worst-case learner based on the assumption that DistNP $\subseteq$ AvgP, i.e., in Heuristica. Our learner agnostically learns all polynomial-size circuits on all unknown P/poly-samplable distributions in polynomial time, where the complexity of learning depends on the complexity of sampling examples. Second, we study the limitation of relativizing constructions of learners based on average-case heuristic algorithms. Specifically, we construct a powerful oracle such that DistPH $\subseteq$ AvgP, i.e., every problem in PH is easy on average, whereas UP $\cap$ coUP and PAC learning on almost-uniform distributions are hard even for $2^{n/\omega(\log n)}$-time algorithms in the relativized world, which improves the oracle separation presented by Impagliazzo (CCC 2011). The core concept of our improvements is the consideration of a switching lemma on a large alphabet, which may be of independent interest. The lower bound on the time complexity is nearly optimal because Hirahara (STOC 2021) showed that DistPH $\subseteq$ AvgP implies that PH can be solved in time $2^{O(n / \log n)}$ under any relativized world.</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-16T15:16:47Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-16T15:16:47Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/16/assistant-professor-tenure-track-in-quantum-computing-quantum-information-theory-at-qici-department-of-computer-science-the-university-of-hong-kong-apply-by-december-15-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/16/assistant-professor-tenure-track-in-quantum-computing-quantum-information-theory-at-qici-department-of-computer-science-the-university-of-hong-kong-apply-by-december-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor (Tenure Track) in Quantum Computing/Quantum Information Theory at QICI, Department of Computer Science, The University of Hong Kong (apply by December 15, 2021)</title>
    <summary>Eligible candidates will have a strong track record in quantum computing and/or quantum information theory, and will hold a PhD in Computer Science, Physics, or Mathematics. The official deadline for applications is March 31 2022. To receive full consideration, candidates are recommended to submit their applications before December 15 2021. Website: https://qici.weebly.com/ Email: giulio@cs.hku.hk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Eligible candidates will have a strong track record in quantum computing and/or quantum information theory, and will hold a PhD in Computer Science, Physics, or Mathematics.</p>
<p>The official deadline for applications is March 31 2022. To receive full consideration, candidates are recommended to submit their applications before December 15 2021.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://qici.weebly.com/">https://qici.weebly.com/</a><br/>
Email: giulio@cs.hku.hk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-16T06:23:08Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-16T06:23:08Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/15/postdoc-at-the-university-of-texas-at-austin-apply-by-january-15-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/15/postdoc-at-the-university-of-texas-at-austin-apply-by-january-15-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at The University of Texas at Austin (apply by January 15, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The NSF AI Institute for Foundations of Machine Learning (https://ifml.institute/), and the NSF TRIPODS program at UT-Austin seek candidates for UT Machine Learning Postdoctoral Fellowships. Appointments will begin Summer or Fall 2022. Fellows can collaborate with researchers involved in IFML partner institutions: UT-Austin, UW, MSR Redmond, and WSU. Website: http://apply.interfolio.com/98753 Email: ifml@austin.utexas.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The NSF AI Institute for Foundations of Machine Learning (<a href="https://ifml.institute/">https://ifml.institute/</a>), and the NSF TRIPODS program at UT-Austin seek candidates for UT Machine Learning Postdoctoral Fellowships. Appointments will begin Summer or Fall 2022. Fellows can collaborate with researchers involved in IFML partner institutions: UT-Austin, UW, MSR Redmond, and WSU.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://apply.interfolio.com/98753">http://apply.interfolio.com/98753</a><br/>
Email: ifml@austin.utexas.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-15T23:50:42Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-15T23:50:42Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/160</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/160" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-160 |  Tight Bounds for General Computation in Noisy Broadcast Networks | 

	Klim Efremenko, 

	Gillat Kol, 

	Dmitry Paramonov, 

	Raghuvansh Saxena</title>
    <summary>Let $\Pi$ be a protocol over the $n$-party broadcast channel, where in each round, a pre-specified party broadcasts a symbol to all other parties. We wish to design a scheme that takes such a protocol $\Pi$ as input and outputs a noise resilient protocol $\Pi'$ that simulates $\Pi$ over the noisy broadcast channel, where each received symbol is flipped with a fixed constant probability, independently. What is the minimum overhead in the number of rounds that is incurred by any such simulation scheme?

A classical result by Gallager from the 80's shows that non-interactive $T$-round protocols, where the bit communicated in every round is independent of the communication history, can be converted to noise resilient ones with only an $\mathcal{O}(\log \log T)$ multiplicative overhead in the number of rounds. Can the same be proved for any protocol? Or, are there protocols whose simulation requires an $\Omega(\log T)$ overhead (which always suffices)? 

We answer both the above questions in the negative: We give a simulation scheme with an $\tilde{O}(\sqrt{\log T})$ overhead for every protocol and channel alphabet. We also prove an (almost) matching lower bound of $\Omega(\sqrt{\log T})$ on the overhead required to simulate the pointer chasing protocol with $T=n$ and polynomial alphabet.</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-15T21:18:44Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-15T21:18:44Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/11/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/11/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>How to tell someone how to get to your house without knowing where they’re starting (\(\mathbb{M}\)), how to tell someone how to get to your house without knowing where they’re starting, how to translate a Penn &amp; Teller trick into Spanish, and other applications of the Černý conjecture on synchronizing words. This video by Nóra Szakács is one of an enormous number of recent mathematics explanation videos in the “Some1” summer of math exposition video project.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4gsp3CZUtV0">How to tell someone how to get to your house without knowing where they’re starting</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107206208305724024">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> how to tell someone how to get to your house without knowing where they’re starting, how to translate a Penn &amp; Teller trick into Spanish, and other applications of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synchronizing_word">Černý conjecture on synchronizing words</a>. This video by Nóra Szakács is one of an enormous number of recent mathematics explanation videos in the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F3Qixy-r_rQ">“Some1” summer of math exposition video project</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>One of our instructor’s strategies for dealing with sites like Chegg that cater to homework answer-copiers <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107217545955814360">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span> seek out and assign homework questions that already have particularly bad answers on Chegg. That way the copiers are more easily caught and the students who actually do the work have a better chance to shine over their copying peers. And if doing this ends up causing Chegg to get more of a reputation for inaccuracy, that’s not a bad thing either.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02906-8">Facebook isn’t the only company changing its name in an unsuccessful attempt to separate itself from its poor reputation</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107223269542696792">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> Around when the FTC fined OMICS for predatory practices, it began rebranding its journals and past papers with other publisher names (Hilaris, Longdom, iMedPub, and Research &amp; Reviews), rewriting the editorship history of its journals, and even lifting other publishers’ papers to fabricate a legitimate-looking backlog for its journals.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constructible_number">Constructible number</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107233293561788882">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> now a Good Article on Wikipedia. This concerns the correspondence between compass-and-straightedge constructions and formulas using square roots, and the use of that correspondence to prove the impossibility of classical geometric construction problems. Relatedly, see <a href="http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-hierarchy-of-geometric-constructibility-can-we-go-back/">Joel Hamkins’ new blog post</a> on how constructibility of one set of points from another produces an equivalence relation on pairs of points.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.smh.com.au/national/nsw/quantum-computers-to-run-sydney-s-transport-network-20211107-p596r5.html">Quantum computers to run Sydney’s transport network</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107236800356354250">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=29139633">via</a>). In other news, Sydney politicians are unable to distinguish hype from actual technology advancements, or maybe more cynically unwilling to do so when the hype would let them dole out lucrative contracts.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2021/11/07/venn-and-euler-type-diagrams-for-vector-spaces-and-abelian-groups/">Terry Tao attempts to visualize vector spaces, linear maps, and exact sequences using arrows from arrows to arrows</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107240160987527319">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> Ok, some of the arrows are really supposed to be half-open intervals, but drawn with a barred closed end and a pointy open end they look a lot like <span style="white-space: nowrap;">\(\mapsto\).</span></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.inputmag.com/culture/pinterest-sucks-google-image-photo-search-ruining-internet">How Pinterest utterly ruined photo search on the internet</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107246007841558595">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=29151055">via</a>).</span> The title is a bit of an exaggeration given how easy it is to add <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">-pinterest</code> to every single image search you do (with quick feedback for why you need to do it when you forget). But they’re not wrong about it being a useless annoyance.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farthest-first_traversal">Farthest-first traversal / greedy permutation</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107251720248944263">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span> generate a sequence of points, choosing each one to be as far as possible from already chosen points. Its first \(k\) points form good cluster centers (approximating min-max-diameter or min-max-radius clustering) and are well separated (approximating max-min distance). Its applications include halftoning, color quantization, sensor network distribution, and underwater robot task planning. Now another Wikipedia Good Article.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Today in amusingly-named concepts: the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorentz%E2%80%93Lorenz_equation">Lorentz–Lorenz equation</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107257423214935119">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>)</span> relating refractive index to polarizability. Even more amusingly, it was not a deliberate collaboration: Lorentz and Lorenz discovered the equation independently! Via a comment over on that other site, in <a href="https://twitter.com/hollykrieger/status/1456321630733574144">a thread making fun of the new Meta logo for its resemblance to a strange attractor</a>. Now if only we could somehow connect it to <a href="https://read.somethingorotherwhatever.com/entry/ItislikeeggPaulLorenzenandthecollapseofproofsofconsistency">Paul Lorenzen</a>…</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@christianp/107258956124702057">How to search for number facts sites without searching for number facts sites</a> and <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@jsiehler/107259309683467429">how to search for the mathematics of poker without getting a bunch of sketchy gambling sites</a>: search for the numbers, not the words.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://eli.thegreenplace.net/2021/rust-data-structures-with-circular-references/">How memory-safe programming in Rust can complicate the design of data structures</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107271384674149840">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=29207397">via</a>, <a href="https://lobste.rs/s/ydstwh/rust_data_structures_with_circular">via2</a>). Rust data structures cannot have circular references, so if you need them you can either fall back to non-memory-safe techniques (reference counting or unsafe blocks) or make your top-level structure implement its own memory allocator and refer to everything by indexes into its vector of objects instead of by proper references.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/11/13/popl-2022-et-tu-brute/">Too few women at POPL 2022</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107272383946893132">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> The low 11% representation on the program committee is especially striking in contrast to the significant historical contributions of women to programming languages (Kathleen Booth, Cicely Popplewell, Grace Hopper, Jean Sammet, Mary Hawes, Gertrude Tierney, and Barbara Liskov among them). According to the same post, the major theoretical computer science conferences are only slightly better.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Handshaking_lemma">Handshaking lemma</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107284266077522291">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> now another Good Article on Wikipedia. This is really about two different but closely-related results, both proved by Euler in his 1736 paper that kicked off the field of graph theory: in any finite undirected graph, the sum of vertex degrees equals twice the number of edges, and the number of odd-degree vertices is even.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-15T18:25:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-15T18:25:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2021-11-16T07:29:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/159</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/159" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-159 |  Constructive Separations and Their Consequences | 

	Lijie Chen, 

	Ce Jin, 

	Rahul Santhanam, 

	Ryan Williams</title>
    <summary>For a complexity class $C$ and language $L$, a constructive separation of $L \notin C$ gives an efficient algorithm (also called a refuter) to find counterexamples (bad inputs) for every $C$-algorithm attempting to decide $L$. We study the questions: Which lower bounds can be made constructive? What are the consequences of constructive separations? We build a case that  ``constructiveness'' serves as a dividing line between many weak lower bounds we know how to prove, and strong lower bounds against $P$, $ZPP$, and $BPP$. Put another way, constructiveness is the opposite of a complexity barrier: it is a property we want lower bounds to have. Our results fall into three broad categories.
		
1. For many separations, making them constructive would imply breakthrough lower bounds. Our first set of results shows that, for many well-known lower bounds against streaming algorithms, one-tape Turing machines, and query complexity, as well as lower bounds for the Minimum Circuit Size Problem, making these lower bounds constructive would imply breakthrough separations ranging from $EXP \neq BPP$ to even $P \neq NP$. 

2. Most conjectured uniform separations can be made constructive. Our second set of results shows that for most major open problems in lower bounds against $P$, $ZPP$, and $BPP$, including $P \neq NP$, $P \neq PSPACE$, $P \neq PP$, $ZPP \neq EXP$, and $BPP \neq NEXP$, any proof of the separation would further imply a constructive separation. Our results generalize earlier results for $P \neq NP$ [Gutfreund, Shaltiel, and Ta-Shma, CCC 2005] and $BPP \neq NEXP$ [Dolev, Fandina and Gutfreund, CIAC 2013]. Thus any proof of these strong lower bounds must also yield a constructive version, compared to many weak lower bounds we currently know.
		
3. Some separations cannot be made constructive. Our third set of results shows that certain complexity separations cannot be made constructive. We observe that for all super-polynomially growing functions $t$, there are no constructive separations for detecting high $t$-time Kolmogorov complexity (a task which is known to be not in $P$) from any complexity class, unconditionally. We also show that under plausible conjectures, there are languages in $NP - P$ for which there are no constructive separations from any complexity class.</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-15T17:32:35Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-15T17:32:35Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-378272747883656707</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/378272747883656707/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/11/when-did-computer-science-theory-get-so.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/378272747883656707" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/378272747883656707" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/11/when-did-computer-science-theory-get-so.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>When did Computer Science Theory Get so Hard?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> I posted on <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/07/when-did-math-get-so-hard.html">When did Math get so hard?</a> a commenter pointed out that one can also ask </p><p><br/></p><p><i>When did Computer Science Theory Get so Hard?</i></p><p>For the Math-question I could only speculate. For CS- I WAS THERE! When I was in Grad School one could learn all of Complexity theory in a year-long course (a hard one, but still!). The main tools were logic and combinatorics. No Fourier Transforms over finite fields. I am NOT going to say</p><p><i>Those were the good old days.</i></p><p>I will say that it was easier to make a contribution without knowing much. Oddly enough, it is MORE common for ugrads and grad students to publish NOW then it was THEN, so that may be a pair of ducks.</p><p><b>Random Thoughts on This Question</b></p><p>1) The Graph Minor Theorem was when P lost its innocence. Before the GMT most (though not all)  problems in P had easy-to-understand  algorithms using algorithmic paradigms (e.g., Dynamic  Programming) and maybe some combinatorics. Computational Number Theory used.... Number Theory (duh), but I don't think it was hard number theory. One exception was Miller's Primality test which needed to assume the Extended Riemann Hypothesis- but you didn't have to understand ERH to use it. </p><p>1.5) GMT again. This did not only give hard-deep-math algorithms to get problems in P. It  also pointed to  how hard proving P NE NP would be--- to rule out something like a GMT-type result to get SAT in P seems rather hard. </p><p>2) Oracle Constructions were fairly easy diagonalizations. It was bummed out that I never had to use an infinite injury priority argument. That is, I knew some complicated recursion theory, but it was never used. </p><p>2.5) Oracles again. Dana Angluin had a paper which used some complicated combinatorics to construct an oracle, see <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0304397580900274?via%3Dihub">here</a>. Later Andy Yao showed that there is an oracle A such that  PH^A NE  PSPACE^A. You might know that result better as</p><p><i>Constant depth circuits for parity must have exponential size. </i></p><p>I think we now care about circuits more than oracles, see my post <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2015/04/the-new-oracle-result-new-circuit.html">here</a> about that issue. Anyway, oracle results since then have used hard combinatorial and other math arguments. </p><p>3) The PCP result was a leap forward for difficulty. I don't know which paper to pick as THE Leap since there were several. And papers after that were also rather difficult.  </p><p>4) I had a blog post <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/04/do-any-np-reductions-use-deep.html#comment-form">here</a> where I asked if REDUCTIONS ever use hard math. Some of the comments are relevant here:</p><p>Stella Biderman: The deepest part of the original PCP theorem is the invention of the VC paradigm in the 1990's.</p><p>Eldar: Fourier Theory was introduced to CS with Hastad's Optimal Approximation results. Today it might not be considered deep, but I recall when it was.</p><p>Also there are Algebraic Geometry codes which use downright arcane mathematics...</p><p>Hermann Gruber refers to Comp Topology and Comp Geometry and points to the result that 3-manifold knot genus is NP-complete, see <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/509907.510016">here</a>.</p><p>Anonymous (they leave many comments) points to the deep math reductions in arithmetic versions of P/NP classes, and Mulmuley's work (Geometric Complexity Theory).</p><p>Timothy Chow points out that `deep' could mean several things and points to a math overflow post on the issue of depth, <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/139607/what-are-some-deep-theorems-and-why-are-they-considered-deep">here</a>.</p><p>Marzio De Biasi points out that even back in 1978 there was a poly reduction that required a good amount of number theory: the NPC of the Diophantine binary quad equation</p><p>ax^2 + by + c = 0 </p><p>by Manders and Adelman, see <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0022000078900442?via%3Dihub">here</a>.</p><p>(Bill Comment) I tend to think this is an outlier- for the most part, CS theory back in the 1970's did not hard math. </p><p>4) Private Info Retrieval (PIR). k databases each have the same n-bit string and cannot talk to each other. a server wants the ith bit and (in the info-theoretic case) wants the DBs to know NOTHING about the question i. </p><p>Easy results (to understand) 2-server, n^{1/3}. <a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/TOPICS/pir/first.pdf">here</a>.</p><p>Hard results: 2-server n^{O(\sqrt{loglogn/log n)},  <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~zdvir/papers/DvirGopi14.pdf">here</a>.</p><p>(I have a website on PIR, not maintained,  <a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/TOPICS/pir/pir.html">here</a>.)</p><p>5) Babai's algorithm for GI in quasi-poly time used hard math. </p><p>6) If I knew more CS theory I am sure I would have more papers listed.</p><p>But now its your turn: </p><p>When did you realize Gee, <b>CS theory is harder than (a) you thought, (b) it used to be.</b></p><p><b><br/></b></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-15T03:50:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-15T03:50:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T00:14:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/15/faculty-at-northwestern-university-apply-by-december-10-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/15/faculty-at-northwestern-university-apply-by-december-10-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty at Northwestern University (apply by December 10, 2021)</title>
    <summary>We invite candidates to apply for new positions as Assistant, Associate and Full Professor of Computer Science. We are interested in applications from outstanding candidates in all areas of Computer Science. See the website for cross-cutting areas of interest. Website: https://www.mccormick.northwestern.edu/computer-science/careers/ Email: nu.cstheory@gmail.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We invite candidates to apply for new positions as Assistant, Associate and Full Professor of Computer Science. We are interested in applications from outstanding candidates in all areas of Computer Science. See the website for cross-cutting areas of interest.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.mccormick.northwestern.edu/computer-science/careers/">https://www.mccormick.northwestern.edu/computer-science/careers/</a><br/>
Email: nu.cstheory@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-15T01:34:05Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-15T01:34:05Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/14/postdoc-at-university-of-waterloo-apply-by-december-31-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/14/postdoc-at-university-of-waterloo-apply-by-december-31-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at University of Waterloo (apply by December 31, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Algorithms &amp; Complexity group at the University of Waterloo is offering postdoctoral positions starting in the Fall of 2022. We seek candidates from all areas of theoretical computer science. Interested applicants should have their CV, research statement, and three recommendation letters emailed to theory.waterloo@gmail.com. Applications are due December 31st. Website: https://algcomp.uwaterloo.ca/positions/ Email: theory.waterloo@gmail.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Algorithms &amp; Complexity group at the University of Waterloo is offering postdoctoral positions starting in the Fall of 2022. We seek candidates from all areas of theoretical computer science.</p>
<p>Interested applicants should have their CV, research statement, and three recommendation letters emailed to theory.waterloo@gmail.com. Applications are due December 31st.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://algcomp.uwaterloo.ca/positions/">https://algcomp.uwaterloo.ca/positions/</a><br/>
Email: theory.waterloo@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-14T20:59:51Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-14T20:59:51Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/11/14/random-independent-sets</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/11/14/random-independent-sets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Random independent sets in bounded-treewidth graphs</title>
    <summary>This week my student Daniel Frishberg posted our new preprint “Rapid mixing of the hardcore Glauber dynamics and other Markov chains in bounded-treewidth graphs”, arXiv:2111.03898. Despite the somewhat-technical title and content, it’s on an easy-to-explain problem, of generating random combinatorial objects (like independent sets in graphs) using random walks. Start with an undirected graph and an empty subset of its vertices, and then repeatedly choose a random vertex, flipping whether it is in or out of the subset whenever the resulting subset remains independent. How many of these steps does it take until the resulting random distribution on independent sets is nearly uniform?</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This week my student Daniel Frishberg posted our new preprint “Rapid mixing of the hardcore Glauber dynamics and other Markov chains in bounded-treewidth graphs”, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03898">arXiv:2111.03898</a>. Despite the somewhat-technical title and content, it’s on an easy-to-explain problem, of generating random combinatorial objects (like independent sets in graphs) using random walks. Start with an undirected graph and an empty subset of its vertices, and then repeatedly choose a random vertex, flipping whether it is in or out of the subset whenever the resulting subset remains independent. How many of these steps does it take until the resulting random distribution on independent sets is nearly uniform?</p>

<p>In general, this can take exponentially many steps, but our paper proves that in graphs of bounded <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treewidth">treewidth</a> it is only polynomial. Our proof’s exponent depends on the treewidth, but maybe a better proof can get the dependence on treewidth out of the exponent and into the constant factor of the polynomial instead. However, if all you want to do is generate random independent sets, this is not the right way to do it. The point of the paper is less about fast algorithms and more about the connectivity of the space of independent sets. So if you do want a fast algorithm for random generation, what should you do?</p>

<p>This is, unfortunately, an area where some care is required and much of the literature does not take the required care. Problematic issues include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>What is the model of computation for arithmetic operations? Much of the literature for the design and analysis of graph algorithms assumes without much attention that all arithmetic operations take unit time. This is a reasonable assumption for small numbers (of at most polynomial magnitude), as occur in many algorithms including the random walk above. In those cases it is a close match to the kind of operation that can be done in a single instruction on a modern CPU. It is not a reasonable assumption for counting algorithms dealing with numbers of exponential magnitude. Counting is an important subproblem for exact random generation, so we need large numbers. Typically, the number of independent sets is linear in the input size, the number of bits required to store this number is linear, and the amount of time needed to perform a single operation on a number this large should again be assumed to involve a bignum-package subroutine. The slow steps are multiplications, which can by <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.4007/annals.2021.193.2.4">recent results of Harvey and van der Hoeven</a> be assumed to take \(O(n\log n)\) time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>What is the model for generating random numbers? If random numbers are generated as bits, this only allows the direct generation of random choices with probabilities that are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyadic_rational">dyadic rational</a>. For independent sets, we need other probabilities. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rejection_sampling">Rejection sampling</a> leads to an algorithm whose running time is itself a random variable, so we need to use expected time or high-probability bounds instead of worst-case time analysis.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>How is the input presented? For the random-walk method, it is just a graph, but for other algorithms taking advantage of low treewidth we need a good <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tree_decomposition">tree decomposition</a>, and finding one is nontrivial. We should either state explicitly that a tree decomposition is given and that its width rather than the graph width controls the algorithm’s runtime, or factor in the time to find a decomposition and the width of decomposition that we find.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>With that all said, how might we go about computing a random independent set for a given \(n\)-vertex graph of treewidth \(w\), achieving the best theoretical performance?</p>

<p>First, we should find an approximate tree decomposition. There are many known algorithms for this problem, but I think the right choice is the one from the recent paper “An improvement of Reed’s treewidth approximation”, Belbasi and Fürer, WALCOM 2021, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.03105">arXiv:2010.03105</a>. It finds a tree decomposition of width at most \(5w\), in time \(O(2^{8.8w}n\log n)\). There are other algorithms with a linear dependence on \(n\), but much worse dependence on \(w\), and the \(n\log n\) part of the bound will be dominated by later steps. We can also bootstrap this decomposition, using dynamic programming on it to find a better decomposition, but I think this is too expensive for the savings it produces.</p>

<p>Second, we should count independent sets. Root the tree decomposition, so that we can talk about the subtree descending from any bag and the subgraph of the given graph that it corresponds to. Then for each bag of the decomposition (in bottom-up order), and each independent subset of the bag, we want to count the number of independent sets in the corresponding subgraph that intersect the bag in the given subset. These independent sets are formed by combining choices of independent sets in child nodes. Therefore, we need to find the numbers of independent sets in each child node that are consistent with the choice of subset at the parent, and multiply them together. Each subset of a bag contributes to exactly one such computation at its parent, so the total number of arithmetic operations for this computation is the product of the number of bags and the number of subsets per bag. With bignum arithmetic, the total time for computing all of these counts is \(O(2^{5w}n^2\log n)\). Our new preprint cites a paper for this subproblem that isn’t sufficiently careful about bignum arithmetic, but still somehow ends up with a slower cubic total time bound; I think they’re just being sloppy and overcounting somehow.</p>

<p>Third, we can then reverse the counting process and step downward through the tree decomposition choosing how the random independent set intersects each bag. When we do this for a bag, we already know the intersection of the independent set with the parent bag. Therefore, all we have to do is choose among the subsets of the child bag that are consistent with that already-made choice, using probabilities that are proportional to the numbers of independent sets that can be formed for each consistent subset. We know these numbers because we already computed them in the second stage. So it’s just a single random choice per bag, which (because it involves bignum probabilities that are not dyadic rational) can reasonably be assumed to take a random amount of time whose expectation is linear. For the overall algorithm, the total expected time is \(O(n^2)\). Also, this stage of the algorithm can be repeated over and over, generating new random independent sets, without having to generate new tree decompositions or new counts.</p>

<p>Putting it all together, it appears that the total time for randomly generating independent sets, using dynamic programming on the tree decomposition to count these sets, and assuming fast bignum arithmetic, is \(O(2^{O(w)}n^2\log n)\) for the preprocessing stages of the algorithm, and then \(O(n^2)\) for each successive generated set.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107278583702646630">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-14T16:41:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-14T16:41:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2021-11-16T07:29:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/14/postdoc-at-princeton-university-apply-by-december-1-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/14/postdoc-at-princeton-university-apply-by-december-1-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at Princeton University  (apply by December 1, 2021)</title>
    <summary>Princeton ORFE invites applications for a postdoctoral position, starting June 1, 2022, in deep learning theory supported through an NSF Grant of ORFE Assistant Professor Boris Hanin. The position is for one year with the possibility of reappointment for up to two years additional years based on satisfactory performance and availability of funding. Website: https://puwebp.princeton.edu/AcadHire/apply/application.xhtml?listingId=22221 […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Princeton ORFE invites applications for a postdoctoral position, starting June 1, 2022, in deep learning theory supported through an NSF Grant of ORFE Assistant Professor Boris Hanin. The position is for one year with the possibility of reappointment for up to two years additional years based on satisfactory performance and availability of funding.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://puwebp.princeton.edu/AcadHire/apply/application.xhtml?listingId=22221">https://puwebp.princeton.edu/AcadHire/apply/application.xhtml?listingId=22221</a><br/>
Email: Bhanin@princeton.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-14T13:07:41Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-14T13:07:41Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=956</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2021/11/14/i-doubt-that-there-will-be-eight-i-highly-doubt-there-will-be-eight/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>“I doubt that there will be eight, I highly doubt there will be eight.”</title>
    <summary>Says campaign strategist at 1:13 on this clip from almost exactly 3 years ago. For background readers can look at this tag. Where are we today? (Official communication.) Union Twist, 1158 Beacon Street in Newton Centre/Four Corners, has been unanimously approved by the City Council for its Special Permit. Union Twist plans to demolish the […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://www.nbcboston.com/news/local/newton-voters-reject-measures-to-ban-or-limit-marijuana-shops/104470/">Says campaign strategist at 1:13 on this clip from almost exactly 3 years ago.</a></p>



<p>For background readers can look <a href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/tag/marijuana/">at this tag</a>.</p>



<p>Where are we today?  (Official communication.)</p>



<ul><li>Union Twist, 1158 Beacon Street in Newton Centre/Four Corners, has been unanimously approved by the City Council for its Special Permit. Union Twist plans to demolish the current building on the site consisting of a dry cleaner and restaurant and build a new 2,300-square foot, one story retail building with 22 on-site parking spaces. For at least the first six months of operation, there will be an appointment only requirement for customers at the store. As their Special Permit has been approved, they can move forward with their state Cannabis Control Commission (CCC) licensing approval process.</li></ul>



<ul><li>Garden Remedies, Newton’s first adult-use retail marijuana store, opened at 697 Washington Street in Newtonville more than two years ago in May 2019. Since opening, Garden Remedies has sold to customers by appointment only. The request from Garden Remedies to amend its current Special Permit to remove the appointment only condition for their retail shop was approved by the City Council Land Use Committee. (The vote was 5-0, with three abstentions.) The full City Council will vote on lifting the appointment only condition at their meeting this Monday, Nov. 15.</li></ul>



<ul><li>Redi, Newton’s second adult-use retail marijuana establishment (formerly known as Cypress Tree) opened in July 2021 at 24 Eliot Street at the intersection with Boylston Street/Route 9 in Upper Falls. (It was (formerly known as Cypress Tree.) The Special Permit approved by the City Council requires that Redi’s retail customers must have an appointment to shop or pick-up products for at least the first six months of operation. </li></ul>



<ul><li>Ascend, 1089 Washington Street/58 Cross Street just outside West Newton Square, has a signed provisional HCA and an approved Special Permit. Construction is nearing completion and they are awaiting licensing approval by the CCC to open.</li></ul>



<ul><li>MedMen, 232 Boylston Street/ Rte. 9 in Chestnut Hill (at the former Shreve, Crump &amp; Low location), has a signed provisional Host Community Agreement (HCA) and an approved Special Permit. They are both awaiting licensing approval by the CCC to open as well as a building permit from the City of Newton to begin work on the building.</li></ul>



<ul><li>Green Lady, 740 Beacon Street in Newton Centre, a woman and minority owned business, has a signed provisional HCA and the City Council Land Use Committee is currently hearing its Special Permit application. If their Special Permit is approved, they can then move forward with their CCC licensing approval process </li></ul>



<ul><li>Verilife, 131 Rumford Avenue in Auburndale, has a signed provisional HCA and the City Council Land Use Committee is currently hearing its Special Permit application. If their Special Permit is approved, they can then move forward with their CCC licensing approval process.</li></ul>



<ul><li>Nuestra, 1185 Chestnut Street in Newton Upper Falls, has a signed provisional HCA. Nuestra is a Cannabis Control Commission certified Economic Empowerment Applicant. They have not yet started the City Council Special Permit approval process which they need to do before moving forward in the state licensing approval process.</li></ul>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-14T10:11:08Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-14T10:11:08Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="marijuana"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:38:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/14/tenure-track-assistant-professor-position-in-security-and-privacy-at-graz-university-of-technology-apply-by-november-30-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/14/tenure-track-assistant-professor-position-in-security-and-privacy-at-graz-university-of-technology-apply-by-november-30-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure-Track Assistant Professor Position in Security and Privacy at Graz University of Technology (apply by November 30, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The department for computer science and biomedical engineering at Graz University of Technology invites applications for the position of a tenure track professor of Security &amp; Privacy. The position will be part of a IAIK, which provides a research environment with more than 60 researchers in Security &amp; Privacy. Website: https://www.tugraz.at/fakultaeten/csbme/news/jobs-grants-calls/tenure-track-professor-in-security-and-privacy/ Email: Stefan.Mangard@iaik.tugraz.at</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The department for computer science and biomedical engineering at Graz University of Technology invites applications for the position of a tenure track professor of Security &amp; Privacy. The position will be part of a IAIK, which provides a research environment with more than 60 researchers in Security &amp; Privacy.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.tugraz.at/fakultaeten/csbme/news/jobs-grants-calls/tenure-track-professor-in-security-and-privacy/">https://www.tugraz.at/fakultaeten/csbme/news/jobs-grants-calls/tenure-track-professor-in-security-and-privacy/</a><br/>
Email: Stefan.Mangard@iaik.tugraz.at</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-14T06:14:43Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-14T06:14:43Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/14/tenure-track-faculty-at-cuny-baruch-college-apply-by-december-13-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/11/14/tenure-track-faculty-at-cuny-baruch-college-apply-by-december-13-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure-Track Faculty  at CUNY: Baruch College (apply by December 13, 2021)</title>
    <summary>We are forming a computer science program at CUNY’s Baruch College. Joining at the beginning of this process will give you a chance to influence how the program will look like: the research and teaching directions, the type of faculty that will be hired, and so on. We hope to have a diverse group of […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We are forming a computer science program at CUNY’s Baruch College. Joining at the beginning of this process will give you a chance to influence how the program will look like: the research and teaching directions, the type of faculty that will be hired, and so on. We hope to have a diverse group of computer scientists. Women and underrepresented minorities are encouraged to apply!</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.mathjobs.org/jobs/list/18748">https://www.mathjobs.org/jobs/list/18748</a><br/>
Email: adam.sheffer@baruch.cuny.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-11-14T02:52:39Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-14T02:52:39Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/158</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/158" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-158 |  Extremely Deep Proofs | 

	Noah Fleming, 

	Toniann Pitassi, 

	Robert Robere</title>
    <summary>We further the study of supercritical tradeoffs in proof and circuit complexity, which is a type of tradeoff between complexity parameters where restricting one complexity parameter forces another to exceed its worst-case upper bound. In particular, we prove a new family of supercritical tradeoffs between depth and size for Resolution, Res(k), and Cutting Planes proofs. For each of these proof systems we construct, for each c &lt;= n^{1-epsilon}, a formula with n^{O(c)} clauses and n variables that has a proof of size n^{O(c)} but in which any proof of size no more than roughly exponential in n^{1-epsilon}/c must necessarily have depth approximately n^c. By setting c = o(n^{1-epsilon}) we therefore obtain exponential lower bounds on proof depth; this far exceeds the trivial worst-case upper bound of n. In doing so we give a simplified proof of a supercritical depth/width tradeoff for tree-like Resolution from [Razborov16]. Finally, we outline several conjectures that would imply similar supercritical tradeoffs between size and depth in circuit complexity via lifting theorems.</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-14T02:27:35Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-14T02:27:35Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/157</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/157" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-157 |  The Complexity of Average-Case Dynamic Subgraph Counting | 

	Monika Henzinger, 

	Andrea Lincoln, 

	Barna Saha</title>
    <summary>Statistics of small subgraph counts such as triangles, four-cycles, and $s$-$t$ paths of short lengths reveal important structural properties of the underlying graph. These problems have been widely studied in social network analysis. In most relevant applications, the graphs are not only massive but also change dynamically over time. Most of these problems become hard in the dynamic setting when considering the worst case. In this paper, we ask whether the question of small subgraph counting over dynamic graphs is hard also in the average case.

We consider the simplest possible average case model where the updates follow an \ErdRen~graph: each update selects a pair of vertices $(u,v)$ uniformly at random and flips the existence of the edge $(u,v)$. 
We develop new lower bounds and matching algorithms in this model for counting four-cycles, counting triangles through a specified point $s$, or a random queried point, and $st$ paths of length $3$, $4$ and $5$. Our results indicate while computing $st$ paths of length $3$, and $4$ are easy in the average case with $O(1)$ update time (note that they are hard in the worst case), it becomes hard when considering $st$ paths of length $5$.

 We introduce new techniques which allow us to get average-case hardness for these graph problems from the worst-case hardness of the Online Matrix vector problem (OMv). Our techniques rely on recent advances in fine-grained average-case complexity. Our techniques advance this literature, giving the ability to prove new lower bounds on average-case dynamic algorithms.</summary>
    <updated>2021-11-14T02:26:23Z</updated>
    <published>2021-11-14T02:26:23Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-11-20T15:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
