<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2007-11-23T23:15:15Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>randomwalker</name>
    <email>randomwalker@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://feedworld.net/toc/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://feedworld.net/toc/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://feedworld.net/toc/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:11011110:123239</id>
    <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/123239.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>SODA hotels?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I tried making my hotel reservation for ALENEX and SODA today, only to be told that not only is the SODA block of rooms at that hotel sold out, but the hotel itself is booked full, and the nearest hotel the reservation agent could suggest was a mile away. It seems strange to me that this would happen nearly four weeks before the supposed deadline, but anyway. Is anyone else in this predicament? What other hotels in the area (near Van Ness and Geary in San Francisco) can anyone suggest?<br/><br/><b>ETA:</b> <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=l&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;time=&amp;date=&amp;ttype=&amp;q=hotel&amp;near=Bush+st+%26+Van+Ness+Ave,+San+Francisco,+San+Francisco,+California+94109,+United+States&amp;sll=37.786606,-122.421556&amp;sspn=0.010633,0.019419&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;ll=37.788488,-122.42192&amp;spn=0.010632,0.019419&amp;z=16&amp;om=1">Google maps to the rescue</a>. I ended up choosing the Carlton, only 1/4 mile away, for around 80% of the conference rate for the Holiday Inn. Looks like there are several other choices within a similar distance and price range.<br/><br/><b>ETA2:</b> According to David Johnson, the hotel does still have rooms, but you have to call the 415 number instead of the 800 number to get them.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-23T22:43:27Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-21T22:14:10Z</published>
    <category term="conferences"/>
    <source>
      <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:11011110</id>
      <author>
        <name>0xDE</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/data/atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>0xDE</subtitle>
      <title>0xDE</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T22:43:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=291</id>
    <link href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=291" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title xml:lang="en">Thanksgiving Special: D-Wave at MIT</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en">Some people think I have a vendetta against D-Wave Systems and its questionable quantum computer claims (see here, here, here, here, here, here, here, here, here for context). But actually, nothing could be further from the truth. I keep trying and trying to change the subject! Wouldn’t you all rather hear about Wolfram, I say? [...]
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Some people think I have a vendetta against D-Wave Systems and its questionable quantum computer claims (see <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=198">here</a>, <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=201">here</a>, <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=204">here</a>, <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=206">here</a>, <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=223">here</a>, <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=225">here</a>, <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=239">here</a>, <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=266">here</a>, <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=242">here</a> for context). But actually, nothing could be further from the truth. I keep trying and trying to change the subject! Wouldn’t you all rather hear about <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=284">Wolfram</a>, I say? Or <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=285">unparadoxes</a>? Or my #1 topic du jour, nothing whatsoever?</p>
<p>Apparently you wouldn’t. From my inbox to my comments section to the hallway, the masses have spoken, and what they want to know is: <em>did I attend D-Wave’s presentation at MIT on Monday, and if so what did I think?</em></p>
<p>Yes, I attended, in body though not in mind. You see, Monday was <em>also</em> the day of the STOC deadline, so if our guests from D-Wave (Mohammad Amin and Andrew Berkley) were expecting a ferocious skeptic, they instead got a bleary-eyed zombie with visions of MA<sub>EXP</sub>, P/poly, and 7:59PM EST cavorting in his head.</p>
<p>This meant that Ed Farhi, Isaac Chuang, Peter Shor, and Lorenza Viola had to do most of the questioning. As it turned out, they did a vastly better job than I could have.</p>
<p>As others have <a href="http://dwave.wordpress.com/2007/11/09/a-picture-of-the-demo-chip/#comment-16231">pointed out in stronger terms</a>, I’m not a physicist. (On the other hand, the gentleman linked to in the previous sentence is <em>not</em> correct about my being paid by the NSA to discredit Canadian quantum computing efforts: it’s actually the GCHQ and the Mossad.) As such, I can’t directly evaluate D-Wave’s central claim to have built an adiabatic quantum computer, nor have I ever tried to do so. All I can do is point out the many things D-Wave has said to the press (about NP-complete problems, for example) that I <em>know</em> are false, its history of making dramatic announcements without evidence, and its contemptuous attitude toward scientists who have asked for such evidence. For me, that’s more than enough to destroy D-Wave’s credibility on the claims I <em>can’t</em> directly evaluate. After all, <em>the burden of proof is not on me; it’s on them.</em></p>
<p>However, other people have not been satisfied with this line of argument. “We don’t care who the burden the proof is on,” they say. “We just care whether D-Wave built an adiabatic quantum computer.”</p>
<p>But my physicist colleagues don’t suffer from the same argumentative limitations that I do. At the group meeting preceding the talk, Farhi announced that he didn’t care what the press releases said, nor did he want to discuss what problems quantum computers can solve (since we academics can figure that out ourselves). Instead he wanted to focus on a single question: <span style="font-style: italic;">is D-Wave’s device a quantum computer or not?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-style: italic;"/><span style="font-style: italic;"/><span style="font-style: italic;"/>What followed was probably the most intense grilling of an invited speaker I’ve ever seen.</p>
<p>It quickly emerged that D-Wave wants to run a coherent quantum computation for microseconds, even though each of their superconducting qubits will have completely decohered within nanoseconds. Farhi had to ask Amin to repeat this several times, to make sure he’d gotten it right.</p>
<p>Amin’s claim was that what looks like total decoherence in the computational basis is irrelevant — since for adiabatic quantum computation, all that matters is what happens in the basis of energy eigenstates. In particular, Amin claimed to have numerical simulations showing that, if the temperature is smaller than the spectral gap, then one can do adiabatic quantum computation even if the conventional coherence times (the t<sub>1</sub> and t<sub>2</sub>) would manifestly seem to prohibit it.</p>
<p>The physicists questioned Amin relentlessly on this one claim. I think it’s fair to say that they emerged curious but severely skeptical, not at all convinced by the calculations Amin provided, and determined to study the issue for themselves.</p>
<p>In other words, this was science as it should be. In contrast to their bosses, Amin and Berkley made a genuine effort to answer questions. They basically admitted that D-Wave’s press releases were litanies of hype and exaggeration, but nevertheless <em>thought</em> they had a promising path to a quantum computer. On several occasions, they seemed to be struggling to give an honest answer that would still uphold the company line.</p>
<p>Two other highlights:</p>
<ul>
<li>I asked Amin and Berkley whether they could give any evidence for any sort of speedup over classical simulated annealing. They laughed at this. “It’s sixteen qubits!” they said. “<em>Of course</em> you’re not going to see a scaling effect with sixteen qubits.”
<p>I said I understood perfectly well (though I wondered silently whether the dozens of journalists covering D-Wave’s demo understood the same). But, I continued, surely you should be able to see a scaling effect by the end of 2008, when your business plan calls for 1024 qubits?</p>
<p>“Well, that’s what it says in the press release,” they said.</p>
<p>Forget about the press release, Farhi interjected. How many qubits are you <em>actually</em> going to make?</p>
<p>Amin and Berkley shrugged; they said they’d just try to make as many qubits as they could.</p></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Even though it hadn’t exhibited any sort of speedup, Amin and Berkley steadfastly maintained that their 16-qubit device was indeed a quantum computer. Their evidence was that simulations of its behavior that took quantum mechanics into account gave, they said, a better fit to the data than simulations that didn’t. On the other hand, they said they were <em>not</em> able to test directly for the presence of any quantum effect such as entanglement. (They agreed that entanglement was a non-negotiable requirement for quantum computing.)
<p>There was a Feynmanesque moment, when Ike Chuang asked Amin and Berkley an experimental question so simple even I understood it. Ike said: if you’re indeed seeing quantum effects, then by running your computer at higher and higher temperatures, at some point you should see a transition to classical behavior. Have you tried this simple control experiment?</p>
<p>Amin and Berkley said that they hadn’t, but that it sounded like a good idea.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>For a theorist like me — accustomed to talks ending with “if there are no questions, then let’s thank the speaker again” — this was exciting, heady stuff. And when it was over, I still had almost three hours until the STOC deadline.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://xkcd.com/54/"><img src="http://www.scottaaronson.com/science.jpg"/></a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-22T15:09:11Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-22T15:09:11Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Speaking Truth to Parallelism"/>
    <category scheme="http://scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Adventures in Meatspace"/>
    <category scheme="http://scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T04:27:50Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204.post-1529073812684571743</id>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2007/11/page-limits-on-journal-papers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=1529073812684571743" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1529073812684571743/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/1529073812684571743" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/1529073812684571743" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Page Limits on Journal Papers</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I know of at least two journals that I publish in that have page limits on the length of papers.  I am completely puzzled by this.  A journal paper should be as long as it needs to be to derive and explain the results the author intends to convey, since the paper should be the final record on that piece of research.   Some papers might need 20 pages;  others might be too long even at 10.  A hard rule of say 12 pages maximum just doesn't make sense. <br/><br/>I can imagine two reasons for instituting page limits on journal papers:  paper costs, and reviewer time.  Neither seems particularly compelling to me.  Are there other reasons I'm missing?  (Notice that both of these are more compelling in the case of conferences, where I would agree page limits make more sense.  And even in that setting, papers costs is rapidly disappearing as a reason, and at some point, the question of page limits should probably be reconsidered.) <br/><br/>I do admit that there are many papers where the author should be forced to edit things down further, and most authors have a tendency to write too much rather than too little.   But it seems the right answer to this is to have good reviewers and a good editor firmly tell an author that the paper is not yet ready and needs further editing.  A page limit doesn't adequately solve this problem and raises new, more unpleasant ones. <br/><br/>Anyone want to defend this practice?  Or at least suggest reasons for it I haven't thought of?</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1529073812684571743/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1529073812684571743/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=1529073812684571743">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1529073812684571743/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-21T06:25:41Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-21T06:10:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="research"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="papers"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="conferences"/>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204</id>
      <author>
        <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>My Biased Coin</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T15:46:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:11011110:117780</id>
    <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/117780.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Surfaces for symmetric groups</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inspired by my <a href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/116782.html">previous post</a> on a truncated-cube Cayley graph for permutations on four elements, I tried looking at similar presentations for larger permutation groups.<br/><br/><a name="cutid1"/>In the permutation group <i>S<sub>n</sub></i> on <i>n</i> items, let <i>x</i> denote the operation that swaps the first two elements of a permutation, and <i>y</i> denote the operation that rotates the remaining <i>n</i> − 1 elements. Then <i>xy</i> rotates all <i>n</i> elements by one position, so these operations satisfy the relations <i>x</i><sup>2</sup> = 1, <i>y</i><sup><i>n</i> − 1</sup> = 1, and (<i>xy</i>)<sup><i>n</i></sup> = 1. One can transpose any two adjacent elements by a composition of these operations of the form (<i>xy</i>)<sup><i>k</i></sup><i>x</i>(<i>xy</i>)<sup><i>n</i> − <i>k</i></sup>, so <i>x</i> and <i>y</i> generate the whole symmetric group.<br/><br/>The group presentation &lt;<i>x</i>, <i>y</i> | <i>x</i><sup>2</sup>, <i>y</i><sup><i>n</i> − 1</sup>, (<i>xy</i>)<sup><i>n</i></sup>&gt; can be interpreted for <i>n</i> &gt; 4 as defining a <a href="http://www.hadron.org/~hatch/HyperbolicTesselations/5_5_omnitrunc_512x512.gif">tiling of the hyperbolic plane by (<i>n</i> − 1)-gons and 2<i>n</i>-gons, meeting at vertices with one (<i>n</i> − 1)-gon and two 2<i>n</i>-gons per vertex</a>. Since this is an infinite tiling, the group presentation defines an infinite Cayley graph of an infinite group, but <i>S<sub>n</sub></i> is a quotient of this group, and inherits from it a structure as a Cayley graph embedded on a manifold. This embedded Cayley graph for <i>S<sub>n</sub></i> has the same types of vertices and faces as the hyperbolic tiling, but finitely many of them.<br/><br/>When <i>n</i> is even (as in the case of the truncated cube for permutations on four items) the (<i>n</i> − 1)-gons of this surface embedding form odd faces, preventing the surface from being an <i>xyz</i> surface in the sense defined in <a href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/117543.html">my recent paper</a>. But when <i>n</i> is odd, we do get an <i>xyz</i> surface, as we may three-color the faces of the embedding. The (<i>n</i> − 1)-gons all get a single color. Each 2<i>n</i>-gon consists of the <i>n</i> cyclic rotations of some permutation π, together with a set of <i>n</i> additional permutations that are not cyclic rotations of each other; we may choose π to be the permutation among these cyclic rotations that fixes the first element. With this choice, we can describe the 2<i>n</i>-gons that are adjacent to the 2<i>n</i>-gon defined by π: they are formed either by transposing adjacent pairs of elements in π other than the first element, or by applying <i>y</i><sup>-1</sup> to π and cyclically rotating the elements other than the first. When <i>n</i> is odd, each of these operations changes the parity of the permutation representing the cycle, so the adjacency structure of the 2<i>n</i>-gons is bipartite and we may two-color these faces.<br/><br/>We may determine the surface formed by <i>S<sub>n</sub></i> by checking the bipartiteness of the Cayley graph and the Euler characteristic of the surface. <i>S<sub>n</sub></i> forms a bipartite Cayley graph when <i>n</i> is odd (as each operation changes the permutation parity) and not when <i>n</i> is even (as the cycles <i>y</i><sup><i>n</i> − 1</sup> are odd). It has <i>n</i>! vertices, 3/2 <i>n</i>! edges, <i>n</i>!/(<i>n</i> − 1) (<i>n</i> − 1)-gonal faces, and (<i>n</i> − 1)! 2<i>n</i>-gonal faces.<br/><br/>For instance, for permutations on 5 elements, we get a nice map on a genus-4 oriented surface with 120 vertices, 180 edges, 30 quadrilaterals, and 24 decagons. It is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truncation_%28geometry%29">truncation</a> of an even nicer map, with 30 vertices, 60 edges, and 24 pentagons meeting four pentagons per vertex. Geometrically, the surface for the Cayley graph of <i>S</i><sub>5</sub> also appears to be the graph-encoded map (GEM) of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Small_stellated_dodecahedron">small stellated dodecahedron</a> or <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_dodecahedron">great dodecahedron</a>, and to be represented itself geometrically as the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truncated_dodecadodecahedron">truncated_dodecadodecahedron</a>:<br/><br/><div align="center"><img height="500" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/2/2d/Truncated_dodecadodecahedron.png" width="500"/><br/><br/><small>(This image, copied from Wikipedia, is by <a href="http://www.software3d.com/Stella.html">Robert C. Webb</a>.)</small></div><br/><br/>In this geometric representation, the <i>xyz</i>-surface faces' 3-coloring is clear: we have yellow squares, large blue decagons, and small red 10/3 stars.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-20T23:16:45Z</updated>
    <published>2007-09-27T20:23:32Z</published>
    <category term="xyz graphs"/>
    <category term="permutohedron"/>
    <source>
      <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:11011110</id>
      <author>
        <name>0xDE</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/data/atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>0xDE</subtitle>
      <title>0xDE</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T22:43:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947.post-4698913074114684810</id>
    <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/2007/11/author-contributions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=6555947&amp;postID=4698913074114684810" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/4698913074114684810/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/4698913074114684810" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/4698913074114684810" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Author contributions</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this conference season, it seems like a good time to think about the issue of author contributions. Here are some of the methods for author listing used in computer science:<br/><ul><li>Alphabetical (the norm in theoryCS and communities heavily influenced by it)</li><li>Advisor-student: student name comes first, advisor comes last.<br/></li><li>Work-ordering: first author did all the work, last author provided the funding, intermediate authors ordered by contribution (common in systems work)</li></ul>Of course, there are combinations: I've seen alphabetical modified by advisor-student ordering, or alphabetical with sub-level work-ordering pieces etc, although the latter is not common in theoryCS. The arguments for and against the various methods are well known I imagine:<br/><ul><li>alphabetical ordering conceals who did the real work ("but the cream rises to the top")</li><li>Work ordering allows advisors to slap their names on anything coming out of their lab ("But they did all the work needed to fund this research: grant writing, selling, etc")</li><li>alphabetical gives undue eminence to authors whose names begin with 'A', (<a href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/2006/12/author-ordering-and-game-theory.html">but see here for a counter-theory</a>)</li><li>alphabetical ordering makes <a href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/2006/04/author-ordering-on-papers.html">authors with names in the end of the alphabet lazy</a> (Who're you looking at, punk ?)</li><li>theory papers can't be work-ordered, because ideas "float in the air without ownership" (yes, I have heard this argument many times, so don't snicker)<br/></li></ul>But what is perhaps more interesting is the problem of assigning author contributions, especially in systems like the alphabetical one where author contributions are not signalled by placement. <a href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2007/11/acknowledging-author-contributions-to.html">Luca Aceto</a> points out an unusually detailed description of author contributions, and speculates as to what a similar note might look like on theory papers.<br/><br/>He also links to an <a href="http://www.math.ufl.edu/misc/hlrules.html">interesting set of axioms</a> that Hardy and Littlewood developed before their famous collaboration started. I actually admire this approach. As a general rule, theory folks tend to be very allergic towards detailed discussions about contributions and what-not, but in collaborations, it's critically important to lay out the ground rules in advance, and the Hardy-Littlewood axioms are good because they lay out rules in advance that eliminate any problems later on: for example,<br/><blockquote> And, finally, the fourth, and perhaps most important axiom, stated that it was quite indifferent if one of them had not contributed the least bit to the contents of a paper under their common name . . .</blockquote>Agreeing to such an axiom requires great trust between the collaborators, because of the immense potential for abuse, and maybe that's exactly the point: a good collaboration requires trust, and you can't agree to such an axiom unless trust already exists.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/4698913074114684810/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/4698913074114684810/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=6555947&amp;postID=4698913074114684810">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/4698913074114684810/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-20T19:23:13Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-20T19:04:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="community"/>
    <author>
      <name>Suresh</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947</id>
      <author>
        <name>Suresh</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/TheGeomblog" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>The Geomblog</title>
      <updated>2007-11-21T16:00:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?p=583</id>
    <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?p=583" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Losing your house…</title>
    <summary>The land of the coned?
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/20/opinion/20herbert.html?ref=opinion">The land of the coned</a>?</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-20T18:57:51Z</updated>
    <category term="Quickies"/>
    <author>
      <name>Sariel Har-Peled</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog</id>
      <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Sariel's weblog</subtitle>
      <title>Vanity of Vanities, all is Vanity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T18:57:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-8516147039842673546</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2007/11/acknowledging-author-contributions-to.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=8516147039842673546" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/8516147039842673546/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/8516147039842673546" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/8516147039842673546" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Acknowledging Author Contributions to Papers</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yesterday, I had a quick look at a <a href="http://www.galileonet.it/news/9101/simulazioni-contro-i-tumori">news item</a> published on the Italian on-line science magazine <a href="http://www.galileonet.it/">Galileo</a>. (Warning: It's in Italian.) The news item describes work on computational biology carried out by <a href="http://www.dbsse.ethz.ch/research/group_beerenwinkel/research" target="_blank">Niko Beerenwinkel</a> (ETH  Zürich) and co-workers. The authors develop a new mathematical model for the somatic evolution of colorectal cancers and use it to derive an analytical approximation for the expected waiting time to the cancer phenotype.<br/><br/>This all sounds very interesting, but what caught my eye as a casual observer was the following information on page 19 of the <a href="http://arxiv.org/ftp/arxiv/papers/0707/0707.3770.pdf">resulting paper</a>.<br/><blockquote><br/><span style="font-weight: bold;">Author Contributions</span><br/>K.W.K., V.E.V., and B.V. performed experiments; N.B., T.A., D.D., A.T., and M.A.N. developed the mathematical model; and N.B., T.A., D.D., B.V., and M.A.N. wrote the paper.<br/></blockquote>Have any of you ever written anything similar on any of your papers? I wonder what similar piece of text  might accompany a TCS paper. Will we ever see a TCS article stating anything like the following piece of text?<br/><blockquote><br/>X and Y proved Lemmas 1-4 and Theorem 2, Z proved Theorem 1, contributed ideas to the proof of Lemma 3 and found an error in the original proof of Theorem 1. Author W wrote the paper and was the main driving force in previous joint work that led to the development of this paper.<br/></blockquote><br/>And what about papers that also report on implementations? I can't imagine how detailed the description of author contributions would have to be then.<br/><br/>I feel relieved to live in a research environment where we collaborate and mainly use alphabetical order amongst the authors---and not just because my surname is Aceto :-) I personally like to work by closely following the <a href="http://www.math.ufl.edu/misc/hlrules.html">Hardy-Littlewood Rules</a> for collaboration, whose spirit is very much at odds with the identification of author contributions.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/8516147039842673546/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/8516147039842673546/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=8516147039842673546">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/8516147039842673546/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-20T13:55:49Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-20T13:23:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:09:19Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947.post-1062187463784432366</id>
    <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/2007/11/my-first-ipelet-1-medians.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=6555947&amp;postID=1062187463784432366" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/1062187463784432366/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/1062187463784432366" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/1062187463784432366" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>My first ipelet: 1-medians</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I just wrote my first <a href="http://tclab.kaist.ac.kr/ipe/">ipelet</a>, and it was an amazingly pleasant experience. Not to mention the thrill I got from marking a collection of points and whoosh! getting the answer right there on the screen.<br/><br/>The ipelet is for computing the discrete and geometric 1-median of a set of points. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geometric_median">geometric 1-median</a> of a set of points (also called the Fermat-Weber-Steiner-Torricelli-&lt; insert your name here &gt; point) is the point that minimizes the sum of distances to a set of points. The discrete 1-median is the same minimization, restricted to points in the input.<br/><br/>Computing the discrete 1-median of a set of points in the plane is trivial in n^2 time, and I didn't do anything clever there. Computing the geometric 1-median is more nontrivial though: there is no closed form solution beyond 4 points, and it can be shown that the point cannot be computed using arithmetic and k^th roots.<br/><br/>There are various approximation schemes: the most pertinent one here (in the plane) is a scheme by <a href="http://www.scs.carleton.ca/%7Ejit/publications/papers/bmm01.ps">Bose, Maheshwari and Morin</a> that uses a cone decomposition of the plane to yield an approximation scheme. In practice, researchers often use an iterative scheme developed by Weiszfeld; it's a simple iterative scheme built around the fact that the optimal solution must be a point such that the sum of unit vectors from it to all other points is zero (formally, this is the condition on the gradient).<br/><br/>The cost function is convex and differentiable except at the input points themselves. Thus, the Weiszfeld iteration is guaranteed to give the optimal solution as long as it doesn't get stuck at one of the data points. This algorithm is often referred to as the "founding algorithm of location science", and there are numerous modifications, extensions, and refinements. The ipelet implements the basic Weiszfeld scheme with a fairly brain-dead termination condition.<br/><br/>What possessed me to do such a thing ? Well, I'm trying to find counter examples for a conjecture involving 1-medians, and needed a way of visualizing examples :).<br/><br/><a href="http://www.cs.utah.edu/%7Esuresh/allmedians.cpp">The code is here</a>: feel free to use it, comment on it, modify it, etc.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/1062187463784432366/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/1062187463784432366/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=6555947&amp;postID=1062187463784432366">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/1062187463784432366/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-20T00:48:34Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-20T00:36:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="research"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="clustering"/>
    <author>
      <name>Suresh</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947</id>
      <author>
        <name>Suresh</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/TheGeomblog" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>The Geomblog</title>
      <updated>2007-11-21T16:00:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947.post-7833658100126063266</id>
    <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/2007/11/ikea-np.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=6555947&amp;postID=7833658100126063266" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/7833658100126063266/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/7833658100126063266" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/7833658100126063266" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>IKEA = NP ?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Brian Hayes, in a post with a <a href="http://bit-player.org/2007/until-nexptime">very catchy title</a>,  makes this painful, and yet not-off-the-mark comment about complexity class nomenclature:<br/><p/><blockquote>The sad truth is, the <a href="http://journal.davidbyrne.com/2007/11/11032007-social.html">naming conventions for furniture at Ikea</a> make for a more consistent language than those of complexity theory.</blockquote><p/>  Ouch ! For more on this, read <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2006/07/naming-complexity-classes.html">Lance's post from way back when</a>.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/7833658100126063266/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/7833658100126063266/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=6555947&amp;postID=7833658100126063266">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/7833658100126063266/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-19T21:59:56Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-19T21:56:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="community"/>
    <author>
      <name>Suresh</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947</id>
      <author>
        <name>Suresh</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/TheGeomblog" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>The Geomblog</title>
      <updated>2007-11-21T16:00:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6065118473532413190</id>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2007/11/advice-about-nsf-grants-not-from-me.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=6065118473532413190" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6065118473532413190" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6065118473532413190" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Advice about NSF grants (not from me)</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How to get an NSF grant? If I knew I would have
more Grant money. However, 
I was emailed the following
powerpoint slides with the request to post
them on my blog, so  

<a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/nsf.ppt">here they are</a></div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
          <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=6065118473532413190">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-19T17:57:30Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-19T17:56:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <author>
        <name>Lance</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:03:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-1845434724331701747</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2007/11/wonderful-read-on-gdels-theorem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=1845434724331701747" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/1845434724331701747/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/1845434724331701747" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/1845434724331701747" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>A Wonderful Read On Gödel's Theorem</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I recently finished reading the book <a href="http://www.akpeters.com/product.asp?ProdCode=2388">Gödel's Theorem: An Incomplete Guide to its Use and Abuse</a> by <a href="http://www.sm.luth.se/%7Etorkel/">Torkel Franzén</a>. This is a book I would recommend to all of the readers of this blog. (Not "This is a book I would recommend to all of the readers of this book", as I had written originally. Thanks to <a href="http://www.cs.berkeley.edu/%7Eluca/">Luca Trevisan</a> for spotting this embarrassing statement of mine. Haste generates monsters, alas :-() It is accessible yet precise, and it sets the record straight on what Gödel's theorem implies and what it does not imply. While reading it I quickly learned that, despite my previous reading of texts on Gödel's theorem, I suffered from some of the misunderstandings that Franzén discusses in his lovely book.<br/><br/>To quote from the overview chapter in the book:<br/><blockquote><br/>The aim of the present addition to the literature on Gödel’s theorem is to set out the content, scope and limits of the incompleteness theorem in such a way as to allow a reader with no knowledge of formal logic to form a sober and soundly based opinion of these various arguments and reflections invoking the theorem. To this end, a number of commonly occurring such arguments and reflections will be presented, in an attempt to counteract common misconceptions and clarify the issues. The formulations of these arguments and reflections, when not attributed to any specific author, are adaptations of statements found on the net, representative of many such reflections.<br/></blockquote>I think that the book succeeds beautifully to do just that, and will repay re-reading.<br/><br/>Torkel Franzén also maintained the page <a href="http://www.sm.luth.se/%7Etorkel/eget/godel.html">Gödel on the net</a>, from which the book eventually originated.<br/><br/>You might have noticed the use of the past tense in the previous sentence. Unfortunately, I just discovered that the author passed away in 2006. He left <a href="http://www.akpeters.com/author.asp?ID=1539">some books</a> that, like this one, have received <a href="http://www.ams.org/notices/200703/rev-raatikainen.pdf">praise</a> from <a href="http://www.cs.nyu.edu/pipermail/fom/2006-April/010463.html">many sources</a>. I certainly enjoyed reading this book, and I am feeling tempted to open my purse and purchase a copy of this volume for my personal library.<br/><br/><span style="font-weight: bold; font-style: italic;">Addendum (17 November 2007): </span>I encourage any reader who wants to catch a glimpse of what this book is about, and of the writing style of the author, to have a look at <a href="http://www.ams.org/notices/200604/fea-franzen.pdf">this short article</a> Torkel Franzén wrote for the Notices of the AMS (volume 53, number 4). Here is an example of one of the many things I personally learned from the book.<br/><br/>Let us say that a formal system has an <span style="font-style: italic;">arithmetical component</span> if it is possible to interpret some of its statements as statements about the natural numbers, in such a way that the system proves some basic principles of arithmetic having to do with summation and multiplication. Given this, we can produce (using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J._Barkley_Rosser">Barkley Rosser</a>’s strengthening of Gödel’s theorem in conjunction with the proof of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matiyasevich%27s_theorem#Matiyasevich.27s_theorem">Matiyasevich-Davis-Robinson-Putnam</a> theorem about the representability of recursively enumerable sets by Diophantine equations) a particular statement of the form “<span style="font-style: italic;">The Diophantine equation p(x1 , . . . , xn ) = 0 has no solution</span>” which is undecidable in the theory, provided it is consistent.<br/><br/>Franzén remarks that<br/><blockquote><br/>....it is mathematically a very striking fact that any sufficiently strong consistent formal system is incomplete with respect to this class of statements,....<br/><br/>However, no famous arithmetical conjecture has been shown to be undecidable in ZFC.....From a logician's point of view, it would be immensely interesting if some famous arithmetical conjecture turned out to be undecidable in ZFC, but it seems too much to hope for.<br/></blockquote>Wikipedia has a short list of mathematical statements that are independent of ZFC on  this <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_statements_undecidable_in_ZFC" rel="nofollow">page</a>. You may find it interesting.<br/><br/><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saharon_Shelah">Saharon Shelah</a>'s result to the effect that the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whitehead_problem">Whitehead problem </a>is undecidable in ZFC is discussed in <a href="http://www.jstor.org/view/00029890/di991617/99p1649q/0" rel="nofollow">this  paper</a> by  Eklof. Shelah has also shown that the problem is independent of ZFC+CH.<br/><br/>There is also an <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2007/11/it-was-stupid-question-or.html">interesting post</a> on a combinatorial problem that is independent of ZFC on the <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/">complexity blog</a>. That post also includes several pointers to pieces that are well worth reading.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/1845434724331701747/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/1845434724331701747/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=1845434724331701747">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/1845434724331701747/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-19T09:11:32Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-16T16:35:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:09:19Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://bit-player.org/?p=120</id>
    <link href="http://bit-player.org/2007/until-nexptime" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title xml:lang="en">Until NEXPTIME</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en">I have a few questions for the complexity theorists among us.
	Have you ever tried to explain to your grandmother why NP is named NP? Does she get it when you say that problems labeled NP-complete are the hardest problems in NP, but NP-hard problems might be harder, and not in NP?
	My concern here is not [...]
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I have a few questions for the complexity theorists among us.</p>
	<p>Have you ever tried to explain to your grandmother why NP is named NP? Does she get it when you say that problems labeled NP-complete are the hardest problems in NP, but NP-hard problems might be harder, and not in NP?</p>
	<p>My concern here is not with the difficulty of the concepts—there’s not much we can do about that—but with the notation and terminology. Do locutions like P<sup>#P</sup> and NISZK and (NP ∩ coNP)/poly roll trillingly off your tongue? How about EXP, EEXP, NEXP, PEXP and SUBEXP? And while we’re on the subject of EXP and friends, I’ve been wondering how to pronounce NEXPTIME. (I’m kind of hoping the “P” is silent, as in Pterodactyl.)</p>
	<p>Presumably, the argot of complexity theory works well enough for communication among members of the club—those of you, say, who know that “IP” is neither “internet protocol” nor “intellectual property” but “interactive proof.” If you’d ever like to talk to the rest of the world, however, I think there might be room for improvement. </p>
	<p>Let’s start with the term “complexity” itself. The root meaning of “complex” is “made up of many interconnected parts”; for example, the innards of a mechanical clock are complex. Is this the best word to describe the property of being hard to compute? To me, it seems the difficulty of an exponential algorithm is not the <em>complexity</em> of the task but the mere mind-numbing repetition of the same operations. An exponential heap of manure is no more complex than a polynomial heap of manure, it just takes longer to shovel it.</p>
	<p>Another gripe: WHAT’S WITH ALL THE CAPITAL LETTERS? IS IT REALLY NECESSARY TO SHOUT ALL THE TIME?</p>
	<p>But the thing that worries me most is a certain opacity in the names of complexity classes. According to the <a href="http://qwiki.caltech.edu/wiki/Main_Page">Complexity Zoo</a>, there are currently 465 named classes, which is quite a menagerie. It’s enough that you can’t really expect people to keep track of meanings and relations without some internal cues from the structure of the names themselves. </p>
	<p>There <em>are</em> hints of structure in the naming scheme, with terms assembled from stems, prefixes and suffixes, and combined according to quasi-grammatical rules. For example, the superscript in P<sup>#P</sup> indicates the action of an “oracle”: The class encompasses problems that can be solved in polynomial time with the help of a #P (”sharp-P” or “counting-P”) oracle. The prefix “co-” in “coNP” designates the complement of NP: If a “Does there exist…?” question is in NP, then the corresponding “Does there not exist…?” question is in coNP. These devices are applied consistently; as far as I can tell, superscripting and the “co-” prefix always mean the same thing. Unfortunately, other elements of the names are not so easy to parse. The letter P generally stands for “polynomial” (except where it’s “probabilistic”). N usually denotes “nondeterministic” (but NC is “Nick’s Class”). Likewise the prefix D is for “deterministic” (except that it’s usually omitted, and sometimes it means “difference” or “dynamical” instead). B stands for “bounded-error” (except that BH is “Boolean hierarchy” and “BPd(P)” is “Polynomial Size d-Times-Only Branching Program”). Q is for “quantum” (except “QH” is the “query hierarchy” and “QP” is “quasi-polynomial time”). </p>
	<p>The sad truth is, the <a href="http://journal.davidbyrne.com/2007/11/11032007-social.html">naming conventions for furniture at Ikea</a> make for a more consistent language than those of complexity theory.</p>
	<p>How did we get into this fix? Back in 1974, when complexity theory was still young and impressionable, Don Knuth published “A Terminological Proposal” in <em>SIGACT News</em>, the quarterly newsletter of what was then the ACM Special Interest Group on Automata and Computability Theory. (By the way, the issue in which Knuth’s letter appears, Vol. 6, No. 1, seems to be <a href="http://www.acm.org/publications/dl-documentation/missing_newsletters">missing</a> from the <a href="http://portal.acm.org/dl.cfm">ACM Digital Library</a>. Can anyone supply a copy for scanning?) Knuth had polled 30 of his friends, asking for advice on the best adjective to describe problems “at least as difficult to solve in polynomial time as those of the Cook-Karp class NP.” His own suggestions were “Herculean,” “formidable” and “arduous,” but none of those got strong support. The people he consulted had proposals of their own: “impractical,” “intractable,” “prodigious,” “exorbitant,” “Sisyphean” and several others. The idea I like best came from Shen Lin, who suggested the abbreviation PET:</p>
	<blockquote><p>
PET stands for “probably exponential time”. But if this gets proved, PET stands for “provably exponential time”. And if the proof goes the other way, it stands for “previously exponential time”.
</p></blockquote>
	<p>On the whole, I think it’s just as well that we are not now speaking of Herculean or Sisyphean or PET problems, but I haven’t much enthusiasm for the solution that <em>was</em> adopted, either:</p>
	<blockquote><p>
The “winning” write-in vote is the term <em>NP-hard</em>, which was put forward mainly by several people at Bell Labs, after what I understand was considerable discussion. Similar if not identical proposals were made by Steve Cook, by Ron Rivest, and in earlier publications by Sakti Sahni. This term is intended for use together with another new one, <em>NP-complete</em>, which abbreviates ‘polynomial complete’ and is at the same time more exact.
</p></blockquote>
	<p>Knuth endorses “NP-hard” and “NP-complete” primarily because they have precise definitions and thus meet the needs of the insiders, the “automata-theorists.” But he also goes on to address the issue of communicating with a wider audience, and his thoughts are worth quoting at some length:</p>
	<blockquote><p>
I don’t consider it a major goal to invent completely descriptive terminology for every conceivably interesting question of the type considered here; the major goal is to have a good term to use for the masses, in the one case which experience shows is almost omnipresent. To say NP-hard actually smacks of being a little too technical for a mass audience, but it’s not so bad as to be unusable; fortunately the term does easily generalize to a lot of other cases considered by automata theorists, so it appears to be a good compromise. When more technicalities are introduced, there is less need for a universally accepted term or notation. Although it’s very interesting to consider, e.g., log-space reductions, I don’t think it’s necessary to come up with a special short name for them.
</p></blockquote>
	<p>If I understand this passage correctly, Knuth is arguing that although “NP-complete” and “NP-hard” may be a bit abstruse for casual coffeeshop chatter, they are the only terms that nonspecialists will ever need to learn, and so they won’t be too much of a burden. But that’s not quite the way it has worked out.</p>
	<p>I suppose that if I’m going to complain about somebody else’s notation, I ought to propose an alternative of my own that I believe to be better. I can’t do that, but I would like to point out that certain other fields of study offer models that might be emulated. The most obvious model is organic chemistry, where the naming problem is orders of magnitude larger than the collection of 465 items in the complexity zoo. The sesquipedalian names of organic molecules are not exactly pretty, but the notational system has the wonderful property that if you know the name of a thing, you also know its composition and structure. Wouldn’t it be grand to have the same kind of perspicuous scheme for complexity classes, so that just naming a class would tell you where it lies in the <a href="http://www.math.ucdavis.edu/~greg/zoology/">inclusion diagram</a>?</p>
	<p>A saving grace of complexity theorists everywhere is that they are not without a sense of humor when it comes to the obscurity of their own jargon. For example, there is a complexity class named PINC, which the Zoo translates as “Polynomial Ignorance of Names of Classes.” And you don’t want to miss Alan T. Sherman’s discourse (or descant) on <a href="http://www.csee.umbc.edu/~sherman/Papers/superpoly.ps">superpolylogarithmic subexponential functions (.ps)</a>.</p>
	<p>Finally, I should mention a discovery I’ve made at the end of Knuth’s terminological proposal. Everyone knows that settling the P = NP question will earn you a prize of $1 million from the <a href="http://www.claymath.org/">Clay Mathematics Institute</a>. I suspect that many are unaware of another prize offer, made more than 30 years ago. Knuth writes:</p>
	<blockquote><p>
I’m willing to give a prize of one live turkey to the first person who proves that P = NP.
</p></blockquote>
	<p>Note that this appears to be a one-way-only offer. Proving that P ≠ NP won’t win you the turkey. (You have three days left until Thanksgiving.)
</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-19T00:36:59Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-19T00:36:59Z</published>
    <category term="computing"/>
    <author>
      <name>brian</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://bit-player.org</id>
      <link href="http://bit-player.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://bit-player.org/feed/atom/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <rights xml:lang="en">Copyright 2007</rights>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en">An amateur's outlook on computation and mathematics.</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en">bit-player</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T22:50:19Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204.post-1981496856222450939</id>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2007/11/david-parkes-talk-monday-4pm.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=1981496856222450939" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1981496856222450939/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/1981496856222450939" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/1981496856222450939" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>David Parkes talk Monday, 4pm</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://www.eecs.harvard.edu/%7Eparkes/">David Parkes</a> will be giving a talk on <a href="http://tools.fas.harvard.edu/cgi-bin/calendar/exporter.cgi?view=event_detail&amp;id=86076233">computational mechanism design</a> in Maxwell-Dworkin G115 at 4pm on the 19th.  This is what at Harvard we call the "tenure talk" -- it's a talk he gives giving an overview of his research and research area as he's coming up for tenure.  If you're a theorist in the area and want to hear a perhaps slightly different point of view on mechanism design and work at the intersection of economics/cs (David proves things, but he comes from the AI side), you should come.  Heck, if you're local, in any area, and interested in the economics/cs interface you should come.  It should be a very nice talk, and it would be great to have the room full to bursting as a sign of support of David.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1981496856222450939/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1981496856222450939/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=1981496856222450939">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1981496856222450939/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-19T00:14:39Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-19T00:03:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="tenure"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="Harvard"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="talks"/>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204</id>
      <author>
        <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>My Biased Coin</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T15:46:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-117/index.html</id>
    <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-117/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="2007/TR07-117/Paper.pdf" rel="enclosure" type="application/pdf"/>
    <title>An infinitely-often one-way function based on an average-case assumption</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<b>Authors:</b> <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hirsch:Edward_A=.html">Edward A. Hirsch</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Itsykson:Dmitry.html">Dmitry M. Itsykson</a><br/>
			<b>Download:</b> 
			<a href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-117/Paper.pdf">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>

We assume the existence of a function f that is computable in polynomial time but its inverse function is not computable in randomized average-case polynomial time. The cryptographic setting is, however, different: even for a weak one-way function, every possible adversary should fail on a polynomial fraction of inputs. Nevertheless, we show how to construct an _infinitely-often_ one-way function based on f.

		</div>
    </summary>
    <feedworld_mtime>1195430400</feedworld_mtime>
    <updated>2007-11-19</updated>
    <source>
      <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/</id>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-117/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <logo>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/icons/BigLogo.gif</logo>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
        <email>meinel@hpi.uni-potsdam.de</email>
      </author>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <rights>Prof. Dr. Christoph Meinel, Hasso Plattner Institute</rights>
      <subtitle>The latest papers from the ECCC-Website</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC Papers</title>
      <updated>2007-11-19</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-116/index.html</id>
    <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-116/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="2007/TR07-116/Paper.pdf" rel="enclosure" type="application/pdf"/>
    <title>Approximate Inclusion-Exclusion for Arbitrary Symmetric Functions</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<b>Authors:</b> <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sherstov:Alexander.html">Alexander Sherstov</a><br/>
			<b>Download:</b> 
			<a href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-116/Paper.pdf">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>

Let A_1,...,A_n be events in a probability space.  The
approximate inclusion-exclusion problem, due to Linial and
Nisan (1990), is to estimate Pr[A_1 OR ... OR  A_n] given
Pr[AND_{iin S}A_i] for all |S|&lt;=k. Kahn et al. (1996) solve
this problem optimally for each k. We study the following more
general question: given Pr[AND_{iin S}A_i] for all |S|&lt;=k,
estimate

Pr[the number of events among A_1,...,A_n that hold is in Z],

where Zsubseteq{0,1,...,n} is a given set. (In the Linial-Nisan
problem, Z={1,...,n}.) We solve this general problem for all
Z and k, giving an algorithm that runs in polynomial time and
achieves an approximation error that is essentially optimal.
We prove this optimal error to be 2^{-tildeTheta(k^2/n)} for
k above a certain threshold, and Theta(1) otherwise.

As part of our solution, we determine, for every predicate
D:{0,1,...,n}-&gt;{0,1} and every epsilonin[1/2^n, 1/3], the
least degree deg_{epsilon}(D) of a polynomial that approximates
D pointwise within epsilon. Namely, we show that

deg_{epsilon}(D)=tildeTheta(deg_{1/3}(D)+sqrt{n*log(1/epsilon)}),

where deg_{1/3}(D) is well-known for each D. Previously, the
answer for vanishing epsilon was known only for D=OR (Kahn et
al., 1996).  We construct the approximating polynomial explicitly
for every D and epsilon.

Our proof departs considerably from Linial and Nisan (1990)
and Kahn et al. (1996). Its key ingredient is the
Approximation/Orthogonality Principle, a certain equivalence
of approximation and orthogonality in Euclidean space,
recently proved by the author in the context of quantum lower
bounds (Sherstov 2007). Our polynomial constructions feature
new uses of the Chebyshev polynomials.

		</div>
    </summary>
    <feedworld_mtime>1195430400</feedworld_mtime>
    <updated>2007-11-19</updated>
    <source>
      <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/</id>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-116/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <logo>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/icons/BigLogo.gif</logo>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
        <email>meinel@hpi.uni-potsdam.de</email>
      </author>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <rights>Prof. Dr. Christoph Meinel, Hasso Plattner Institute</rights>
      <subtitle>The latest papers from the ECCC-Website</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC Papers</title>
      <updated>2007-11-19</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-115/index.html</id>
    <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-115/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="2007/TR07-115/Paper.pdf" rel="enclosure" type="application/pdf"/>
    <title>Combinatorial Construction of Locally Testable Codes</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<b>Authors:</b> Or Meir<br/>
			<b>Download:</b> 
			<a href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-115/Paper.pdf">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>

An error correcting code is said to be locally testable if there is a test that checks whether a given string is a codeword, or rather far from the code, by reading only a constant number of symbols of the string. Locally Testable Codes (LTCs) were first systematically studied by Goldreich and Sudan (J. ACM 53(4)) and since then several constructions of LTCs have been suggested.

While the best known construction of LTCs by Ben-Sasson and Sudan (STOC 2005) and Dinur (J. ACM 54(3)) achieves very efficient parameters, it relies heavily on algebraic tools and on PCP machinery. In this work we present a new and arguably simpler construction of LTCs that is purely combinatorial, does not rely on PCP machinery and matches the parameters of the best known construction. However, unlike the latter construction, our construction is not entirely explicit.

		</div>
    </summary>
    <feedworld_mtime>1195430400</feedworld_mtime>
    <updated>2007-11-19</updated>
    <source>
      <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/</id>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-115/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <logo>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/icons/BigLogo.gif</logo>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
        <email>meinel@hpi.uni-potsdam.de</email>
      </author>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <rights>Prof. Dr. Christoph Meinel, Hasso Plattner Institute</rights>
      <subtitle>The latest papers from the ECCC-Website</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC Papers</title>
      <updated>2007-11-19</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445.post-5068773389660939042</id>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/2007/11/le-balloon-rouge.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=5068773389660939042" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/5068773389660939042/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/5068773389660939042" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/21129445/posts/default/5068773389660939042" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Le Balloon Rouge</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fall days mean walk in the city with swirling leaves, flying hair, humans in scarves and coats, and children walking with their heads down, eyes averted. Some days I feel like an adult or world thrusts that upon me, and then there are days I feel like a boy or the world yanks the boy out of me. Today, I found a red balloon hobbling on the street, I picked it up and let it go, it flew, but followed me for an avenue block, so, I figured, like Lamorisse's hero, that it wants to with me, and I walked it home. Walking down the city blocks is a danger in itself some will tell you, walking with a red balloon in hand is even more so; I was glad when I managed to get home and shut the door behind safely. The red balloon, my treasure, is still holding its breath and hovering over me. Here is the media on the 1956 movie and its accidental enactment today.<br/><br/><table border="0" bordercolor="#c0c0c0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0"><tbody><tr><td align="center"> <br/></td><td align="center"><br/></td></tr></tbody></table><br/><br/><table border="0" bordercolor="#c0c0c0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0"><tbody><tr><td align="center"><br/><a href="http://bp0.blogger.com/_P70CDtPH4Rs/Rz82134YBwI/AAAAAAAAAQg/aWlTT6U2a6I/s1600-h/photo.jpg"><img alt="" border="0" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5133882399387027202" src="http://bp0.blogger.com/_P70CDtPH4Rs/Rz82134YBwI/AAAAAAAAAQg/aWlTT6U2a6I/s200/photo.jpg" style="float: left; margin: 0 0px 0px 0; cursor: pointer; cursor: hand;"/></a><br/></td><td align="center"><br/><a href="http://bp2.blogger.com/_P70CDtPH4Rs/Rz823X4YBxI/AAAAAAAAAQo/MkmgZvsU5ds/s1600-h/photo1.jpg"><img alt="" border="0" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5133882425156830994" src="http://bp2.blogger.com/_P70CDtPH4Rs/Rz823X4YBxI/AAAAAAAAAQo/MkmgZvsU5ds/s200/photo1.jpg" style="float: left; margin: 0 0px 0px 0; cursor: pointer; cursor: hand;"/></a><br/></td><td align="center"><br/><a href="http://bp0.blogger.com/_P70CDtPH4Rs/Rz82334YByI/AAAAAAAAAQw/PjZKa8kVkl8/s1600-h/photo4.jpg"><img alt="" border="0" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5133882433746765602" src="http://bp0.blogger.com/_P70CDtPH4Rs/Rz82334YByI/AAAAAAAAAQw/PjZKa8kVkl8/s200/photo4.jpg" style="float: left; margin: 0 0px 0px 0; cursor: pointer; cursor: hand;"/></a><br/></td><td align="center"><br/><a href="http://bp0.blogger.com/_P70CDtPH4Rs/Rz82434YB0I/AAAAAAAAARA/9vHa_aeYa6Q/s1600-h/photo2.jpg"><img alt="" border="0" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5133882450926634818" src="http://bp0.blogger.com/_P70CDtPH4Rs/Rz82434YB0I/AAAAAAAAARA/9vHa_aeYa6Q/s200/photo2.jpg" style="float: left; margin: 0 0px 0px 0; cursor: pointer; cursor: hand;"/></a><br/></td><td align="center"><br/><a href="http://bp2.blogger.com/_P70CDtPH4Rs/Rz824X4YBzI/AAAAAAAAAQ4/lUPNcSyN934/s1600-h/photo3.jpg"><img alt="" border="0" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5133882442336700210" src="http://bp2.blogger.com/_P70CDtPH4Rs/Rz824X4YBzI/AAAAAAAAAQ4/lUPNcSyN934/s200/photo3.jpg" style="float: left; margin: 0 0px 0px 0; cursor: pointer; cursor: hand;"/></a><br/></td></tr></tbody></table></div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/5068773389660939042/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/5068773389660939042/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=5068773389660939042">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/5068773389660939042/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-17T19:40:00Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-17T18:15:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>metoo</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445</id>
      <author>
        <name>metoo</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>my slice of pizza</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T05:40:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445.post-6779029706562261496</id>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/2007/11/past.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=6779029706562261496" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6779029706562261496/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/6779029706562261496" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/21129445/posts/default/6779029706562261496" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>A Past</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is the season of conference deadlines (STOC/SIGMOD/SIGMETRICS and many others), holidays, and the surge and ebb of traditions. In a break from a tradition, I have put myself outside the process of conferences (and embraced the holidays), and am now willing myself towards the end of the year. I will be away in India for a week, and on reflecting, found myself thinking of my <span style="font-style: italic;">alma mate</span>r, <a href="http://www.iitkgp.ac.in/">IIT Kharagpur</a> (the least known of the IITs in Theory <a href="http://www.cse-web.iitkgp.ernet.in/">CS</a>---there is always a linear combination in which one leads---but it is a <a href="http://sheermelody.blogspot.com/2006/12/alma-mater.html">gem</a> of course). The CS dept is <a href="http://cse.iitkgp.ac.in/silver/index.php?q=home">celebrating</a> its 25 years of existence this winter. I remembered the last time I visited the institute, it was 10 years ago, and googling yielded <a href="http://www.iarcs.org.in/activities/newsletter/vol3-1/randwkshp.html">this blurb</a>  by <a href="http://www.cs.chalmers.se/~dubhashi/">Devdatt Dubhashi</a>. This and other pasts often intrude in strange ways: watching a movie in a theater far away from Kharagpur, if someone yells "Tarapodo!", the <a href="http://sheermelody.blogspot.com/2006/12/alma-mater.html">legend </a>lives on; in a party in the village, I see Umesh and remember his fantastic <a href="http://www.iarcs.org.in/activities/newsletter/vol3-1/randwkshp.html">lecture</a> at Kharagapur in 97.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6779029706562261496/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6779029706562261496/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=6779029706562261496">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6779029706562261496/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-17T18:00:54Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-17T13:22:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>metoo</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445</id>
      <author>
        <name>metoo</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>my slice of pizza</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T05:40:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204.post-7043570491844045663</id>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2007/11/should-ip-issues-affect-our-research.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=7043570491844045663" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/7043570491844045663/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/7043570491844045663" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/7043570491844045663" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Should IP issues affect our research?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since I've done some legal consulting, I've become interested in  intellectual property (IP) issues, and the question of whether IP issues should affect my research agenda has recently occurred to me.<br/><br/>Let me explain.  As an algorithmist, a major interest for me is designing algorithms that people will actually use -- perhaps not in the original form that I describe them in, of course, but that the ideas make it out into the real world.   And while it is not my aim that every project I'm involved in should have a clear potential practical impact, it is the case that this goal guides my overall research agenda quite significantly. <br/><br/>IP issues have the potential to limit the practical impact of an algorithm I design.  For example, suppose someone has a patent on SuperHashSchemeX (SHSX).   (If you want something more specific, suppose Bloom filters were patented.)  I might come up to an improvement to SHSX, or a better analysis of SHSX, but if the patent is written well, the patent owner may have rights controlling who could use SHSX, including my improvement.   There may really be no hope that anyone else will actually be able to make use of my ideas, until the patent runs out, or unless the user is willing to buy a license.  Indeed, unless I go through the process of obtaining a patent, it's possible that my work might simply add value for the initial patent-holder, and I've actually rewarded those who are keeping my work from being used.  <br/><br/>Perhaps this wouldn't bother me if my theory blood ran pure, but I like being an "applied theorist".   In my mind, this affects the calculus I use in thinking about what I should work on.<br/><br/>Should it?  Has anyone actually run into this problem?</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/7043570491844045663/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/7043570491844045663/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=7043570491844045663">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/7043570491844045663/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-17T00:47:32Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-17T00:26:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="algorithms"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="society"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="consulting"/>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204</id>
      <author>
        <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>My Biased Coin</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T15:46:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-786333285568106173.post-1026413759476501924</id>
    <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/2007/11/good-friday.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=786333285568106173&amp;postID=1026413759476501924" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/1026413759476501924/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default/1026413759476501924" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default/1026413759476501924" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Good Friday</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><pre><br/>~/work% mkdir 4D<br/>~/work$ cp ~/bs/preamble.tex 4D/paper.tex<br/>~/work$ cp ~/bs/hacked-article.cls 4D/article.cls<br/>~/work$ cp ~/bs/hacked-size11.clo 4D/size11.clo<br/></pre>To: coauthor-1.  Sorry, I am a bit delayed due to another paper, and I still don't have a complete draft, but the paper is falling nicely into place. I promise to have a first draft out by Monday morning.<br/><br/>TODO:<br/><ul><li>title?</li><li>abstract</li><li>intro. Track down fractional cascading refs!<br/></li><li>figure out complete list of coauthors</li><li>figure out how to analyze Bob's side of the rectangle (NB: we're losing smthg like a log or log^2 in the density of queries, is the intuition still true?)</li><li>technical section</li><li>make nice drawing with 2 coupled trees</li><li>does a 2-sided lb seem doable? Figure out whether to claim it "in the full version".</li><li>announce social event Monday 4am, G575. Buy cookies for event.</li><li>confirm postdeadline beer @CBC, 8:30pm.</li></ul></div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/1026413759476501924/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/1026413759476501924/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=786333285568106173&amp;postID=1026413759476501924">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/1026413759476501924/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-16T19:10:27Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-16T18:48:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>MiP</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-786333285568106173</id>
      <author>
        <name>MiP</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/WebdiariosDeMotocicleta" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>WebDiarios de Motocicleta</title>
      <updated>2007-11-19T07:48:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-1803801999677267283</id>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2007/11/more-on-tables-problem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=1803801999677267283" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1803801999677267283" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1803801999677267283" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>More on the Tables Problem</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recall the tables problem, which I now state
more clearly than I did in my last post:

<blockquote>
n couples go to a resturant.
They will sit at a rectangular table
that has room for n on each side.
Each person sits either next to
across from their darling.
How many ways can they sit?
</blockquote>

Most people got the correct answer in the comments
on my last blog. But some other interesting points
were raised that I will address.

<ol>
<li>
I had commented that this was asked on the 2007
<a href="http://www.math.umd.edu/highschool/mathcomp/PartI2007.pdf">
Maryland High School Math Olympiad, Part I,</a>, problem 23,
which is  with Multiple Choice, for the case of n=5.
Some commenter wanted to know what the choices were:
360, 768, 5040, 19200, 30720.

</li><li>
Someone commented that the problem `was not new'
and gave <a href="http://mathcircle.berkeley.edu/original/Combinatorics1.pdf">this</a>, problem 4,
as a pointer to where it had been asked before.
Here is the problem they were referring to:

<blockquote>
Define a domino to be a 1x2 rectangle.
In how many ways can a nx2 rectangle be tiled
by dominos?
</blockquote>

This raises an interesting question:
When are two problems equivalent?
Does phrasing matter (I had people, they have dominos)?
Does making certain things distinguiable or not matter
(Dominos are not distinguiable, couples are)?
Does having different answers matter
(his is Fib(n+1) mine is a Fib(n+1) x 2^n x n!)?
More generally, its not clear when a problem is new.


</li><li>
Just to reiterate- there is math all around you if
you know where to look.

</li></ol></div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
          <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=1803801999677267283">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-15T17:28:12Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-15T17:27:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <author>
        <name>Lance</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:03:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-8095806210940208291</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2007/11/rejecta-mathematica.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=8095806210940208291" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/8095806210940208291/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/8095806210940208291" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/8095806210940208291" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Rejecta Mathematica</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Silvio Capobianco pointed out to me a new mathematical journal, whose existence he discovered by looking at <a href="http://www.math.rutgers.edu/%7Ezeilberg/Opinion77.html">this opinion</a> of Doron Zeilberger's. The journal is called <a href="http://math.rejecta.org/">Rejecta Mathematica</a>, and its description reads<br/><blockquote><br/>Rejecta Mathematica is a new, open access, online journal that publishes only papers that have been rejected from peer-reviewed journals (or conferences with comparable review standards) in the mathematical sciences.<br/></blockquote>A unique aspect of Rejecta Mathematica is that each paper will be published together with an open letter from the authors discussing the paper's original review process, disclosing any known flaws in the paper and stating the case for the paper's value to the community.<br/><br/>Is this a joke? This and other natural questions are discussed <a href="http://math.rejecta.org/frequently-asked-questions">here</a>. In case you wonder who the editors of this journal are, look <a href="http://math.rejecta.org/contacting-rejecta-mathematica">here</a>.<br/><br/>I am looking forward to seeing what papers will appear in the first volume of the journal :-)</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/8095806210940208291/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/8095806210940208291/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=8095806210940208291">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/8095806210940208291/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-15T17:27:46Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-15T17:18:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:09:19Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=289</id>
    <link href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=289" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title xml:lang="en">‘Tis the week before deadline</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en">and at least over here
Not a blogger is stirring
The reason is clear
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>and at least over here</p>
<p>Not a blogger is stirring</p>
<p>The <a href="http://research.microsoft.com/research/sv/STOC08/stoc2008-cfp.htm">reason</a> is clear</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-15T11:37:22Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-15T11:37:22Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T04:27:50Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-114/index.html</id>
    <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-114/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="2007/TR07-114/Paper.pdf" rel="enclosure" type="application/pdf"/>
    <title>A Simplified Way of Proving Trade-off Results for Resolution</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<b>Authors:</b> <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nordstr=ouml=m:Jakob.html">Jakob Nordström</a><br/>
			<b>Download:</b> 
			<a href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-114/Paper.pdf">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>

We present a greatly simplified proof of the length-space
trade-off result for resolution in Hertel and Pitassi (2007), and
also prove a couple of other theorems in the same vein.  We point
out two important ingredients needed for our proofs to work, and
discuss possible conclusions to be drawn regarding proving
trade-off results for resolution.  Our key trick is to look at
formulas of the type F = G land H, where G and H are over
disjoint set of variables and have very different length-space
properties with respect to resolution.  This trick is not present
in the proof of Hertel and Pitassi, and thus their techniques can
likely be used to prove results not obtainable by our methods.

		</div>
    </summary>
    <feedworld_mtime>1195084800</feedworld_mtime>
    <updated>2007-11-15</updated>
    <source>
      <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/</id>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-114/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <logo>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/icons/BigLogo.gif</logo>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
        <email>meinel@hpi.uni-potsdam.de</email>
      </author>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <rights>Prof. Dr. Christoph Meinel, Hasso Plattner Institute</rights>
      <subtitle>The latest papers from the ECCC-Website</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC Papers</title>
      <updated>2007-11-15</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-113/index.html</id>
    <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-113/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="2007/TR07-113/Paper.pdf" rel="enclosure" type="application/pdf"/>
    <title>Inapproximability of edge-disjoint paths and low congestion routing on undirected graphs</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<b>Authors:</b> <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chuzhoy:Julia.html">Julia Chuzhoy</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Andrews:Matthew.html">Matthew Andrews</a><a href="http://netlib.bell-labs.com/who/andrews/index.html"><img class="homeicon" src="images/homeicon.png"/></a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Lisa.html">Lisa Zhang</a><a href="http://cm.bell-labs.com/who/ylz/"><img class="homeicon" src="images/homeicon.png"/></a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Talwar:Kunal.html">Kunal Talwar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Khanna:Sanjeev.html">Sanjeev Khanna</a><a href="http://www.cis.upenn.edu/~sanjeev/"><img class="homeicon" src="images/homeicon.png"/></a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Guruswami:Venkatesan.html">Venkatesan Guruswami</a><a href="http://www.cs.washington.edu/homes/venkat/"><img class="homeicon" src="images/homeicon.png"/></a><br/>
			<b>Download:</b> 
			<a href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-113/Paper.pdf">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>

In the undirected Edge-Disjoint Paths problem with Congestion
(EDPwC), we are given an undirected graph with $V$ nodes, a set of
terminal pairs and an integer $c$. The objective is to route as many
terminal pairs as possible, subject to the constraint that at most
$c$ demands can be routed through any edge in the graph. When $c=1$,
the problem is simply referred to as the Edge-Disjoint Paths (EDP)
problem. In this paper, we study the hardness of EDPwC in undirected
graphs.

Our main result is that for every $ve&gt;0$ there exists an
$alpha&gt;0$ such that for $1le cle frac{alphaloglog
V}{logloglog V}$, it is hard to distinguish between instances
where we can route all terminal pairs on edge-disjoint paths, and
instances where we can route at most a $1/(log
V)^{frac{1-ve}{c+2}}$ fraction of the terminal pairs, even if we
allow congestion $c$. This implies a $(log
V)^{frac{1-ve}{c+2}}$ hardness of approximation for EDPwC and an
$Omega(loglog V/logloglog V)$ hardness of approximation for
the undirected congestion minimization problem. These results hold
assuming ${rm NP} notsubseteq cup_d {rm ZPTIME}(2^{log^d n})$.

In the case that we do not require perfect completeness, i.e. we do
not require that all terminal pairs are routed for
``yes-instances'', we can obtain a slightly better inapproximability
ratio of $(log V)^{frac{1-ve}{c+1}}$. Note that by setting $c=1$
this implies that the regular EDP problem is $(log
V)^{frac{1}{2}-ve}$ hard to approximate.

Using standard reductions, our results extend to the node-disjoint
versions of these problems as well as to the directed setting. We
also show a $(log V)^{frac{1-ve}{c+1}}$ inapproximability ratio
for the All-or-Nothing Flow with Congestion (ANFwC) problem, a
relaxation of EDPwC, in which the flow unit routed between the
source-sink pairs does not have to follow a single path, so the
resulting flow is not necessarily integral.

		</div>
    </summary>
    <feedworld_mtime>1195084800</feedworld_mtime>
    <updated>2007-11-15</updated>
    <source>
      <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/</id>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-113/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <logo>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/icons/BigLogo.gif</logo>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
        <email>meinel@hpi.uni-potsdam.de</email>
      </author>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <rights>Prof. Dr. Christoph Meinel, Hasso Plattner Institute</rights>
      <subtitle>The latest papers from the ECCC-Website</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC Papers</title>
      <updated>2007-11-15</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445.post-7965628234354150147</id>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/2007/11/hot-off-email.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=7965628234354150147" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/7965628234354150147/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/7965628234354150147" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/21129445/posts/default/7965628234354150147" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Hot off email</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://math.rejecta.org/"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://math.rejecta.org/files/barron_logo.gif" style="float: left; margin: 0 10px 10px 0; cursor: pointer; cursor: hand; width: 200px;"/></a><br/>I really shouldn't publicize getting an email with the Call For Papers for a new journal: <a href="http://math.rejecta.org/">Rejecta Mathematica</a>. As the website says: <blockquote/><span style="font-style: italic;">Rejecta Mathematica is a new, open access, online journal that publishes only papers that have been rejected from peer-reviewed journals (or conferences with comparable review standards) in the mathematical sciences.</span><blockquote/> Further, the website clarifies that the journal is interested in forms of "<span style="font-style: italic;">mapping the blind alleys of science, reinventing the wheel, applications of cold fusion, misunderstood genius</span>" etc. Enjoy!<br/><br/>Btw, you can imagine what an email invitation would say: "...in light of your reputation in the research community, we would like to extend a specific invitation to you to contribute a paper..." :) The website above counsels authors whose submissions to this journal get rejected!<br/><br/>ps: Mike Wakin, Chris Rozell, Mark Davenport and Jason Laska are involved. All are signal processors.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/7965628234354150147/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/7965628234354150147/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=7965628234354150147">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/7965628234354150147/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-14T22:38:40Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-14T20:47:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>metoo</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445</id>
      <author>
        <name>metoo</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>my slice of pizza</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T05:40:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:11011110:122872</id>
    <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/122872.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>O'Rourke at Swarthmore</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://www.sccs.swarthmore.edu/org/daily/2007/11/14/orourke-on-geometric-reductionism/">O'Rourke on Geometric Reductionism</a>. Student newspaper article by Neena Cherayil on a talk by Joe O'Rourke, “Geometric Folding Algorithms: Linkages, Origami, and Polyhedra,” including a description of the Houdini one-cut trick and segueing into a discussion of whether computational geometry is useful.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-14T17:19:45Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-14T17:19:45Z</published>
    <category term="computational geometry"/>
    <category term="talks"/>
    <category term="origami"/>
    <source>
      <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:11011110</id>
      <author>
        <name>0xDE</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/data/atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>0xDE</subtitle>
      <title>0xDE</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T22:43:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7474713628728312297</id>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2007/11/math-problems-from-everyday-life.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=7474713628728312297" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7474713628728312297" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7474713628728312297" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Math Problems from everyday life</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Often I see something in real life
that inspires a math problem. Could be a math
problem for an exam or a student project
or (more rarely) serious research.
(e.g., I give my 9 year old great nephew seven crayons
and he colors the numbers 1,...,2000 without
any monochromatic 3-AP's so I get a new VDW
number out of it.)

<br/>
<br/>

Here is one that inspired a problem that
ended up on the Maryland Math Olympiad,
Part I (which is 25 multiple choices questions).
(5 choices, 4 points for a correct answer,
2 points for a wrong answer. You really really
do not want to guess.)

<br/>
<br/>

Here is what happened: I went to dinner
with my darling, and my two sister-in-laws
and their husbands.
I sat across from my darling but the
other couples sat next to each other.
So here is the question:
I immediately thought about the following
question:

<blockquote>
$n$ couples go to dinner. They sit at
a rectangular table, but nobody sits at
the ends.  Each couple either sits
ACROSS FROM or NEXT TO their darling.
How many ways can they be seated?
</blockquote>

The problem on the exam was asked for 5 couples
and gave choices.
<br/>
<br/>

Its not a hard problem for the readers of this blog, so I leave it to
my commenters to solve it.  (If nobody does I'll post the solution later.)
Note that it would be hard for a high school student-
very few got it correct. (We suspected this would be the case. We try to order
the questions by difficulty and this was question 23.)</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
          <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=7474713628728312297">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-14T14:53:13Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-14T14:49:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <author>
        <name>Lance</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:03:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-786333285568106173.post-4523236087108089662</id>
    <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/2007/11/is-google-paying-you.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=786333285568106173&amp;postID=4523236087108089662" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/4523236087108089662/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default/4523236087108089662" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default/4523236087108089662" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Is Google paying you?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kamal Jain gave a talk today on "atomic economics". Here is my own description of what he meant, though it seemed Kamal disagrees with at least some of my description :)<br/><br/>Think of credit cards. Whenever I pay with one, the store only gets 1-x% of the posted price, i.e. the the credit card company makes x% of the money. That is nice profit for the CC company, but as always, competition is driving all profits towards zero. Since there are multiple banks willing to give me a CC, <span style="font-style: italic;">and they all retain the same percentage from a merchant</span>, they need to compete on the customer side --- they have to fight for the honor of counting me as their customer. So they start giving me points / miles / cash back / etc. Getting 1% of your money back is already quite standard, and customers need more to be impressed. To some extent, this incentivizing actually works (personally, I tend to use my AmEx card due to the better reward system).<br/><br/>Now, Google and Yahoo are making money because of me (merchants pay them when I click on an ad). In principle, this means we are not at an equilibrium: since these companies are competing for customers (equal ad revenue), one of them should start offering me a share of their profits whenever I click, and the other will have to follow suit.<br/><br/>Kamal sees several problems (market inefficiencies) that will prevent this welfare-maximizing scenario. I also see them as problems, but I have a different opinion on the degree of surmontability. Problems:<br/><ul><li>Customer abuse: profit sharing has to be tied to some actual buying event, or otherwise I will have an incentive to spend my day clicking on ads (and not buying anything), driving the merchant out of business. This is a problem for branding ads (e.g. eBay likes to display worthless ads all the time to build its name into collective conscience), and for ads that are separated from the actual purchase (e.g. an ad to a restaurant). But for e-commerce, which seems to be the raison d'etre of search advertising, this detail can be worked out by sharing information between Google and the merchant.<br/><br/></li><li>Merchant fraud: the merchant marks the price up by $5, adds $5 to the advertising budget (getting a top slot), and tells me that I will get $5 cash-back from Google (which means I don't care their price was $5 higher than the competition). Realistically, this won't happen, for several well-understood reasons. Common sense dictates that Google will only share a percentage of their profit, so I'll only get, say, $2.5 back, which means I care about the price markup. Like credit-card companies, Google and Yahoo have a weapon to enforce this common sense: customer differentiation. This is oligopolistic behavior, but one that is remarkably stable. What happens is that frequent buyers (resp. people with good credit histories) get better cash-bask deals, because they are presumed to have more authority to "negotiate".  Then, the merchant gets a mix of people with different cash-back percentages, but who look the same to the merchant.<br/><br/></li><li>Bounded rationality, a heavily used buzzword, and the really exciting consideration. Unlike traditional advertising, Google and Yahoo have really tiny costs. This means they can still make a ton of money with a razor-thin cut of the merchant's profit. For instance, if Google is paid 0.1% percent of the transaction value, what could they offer me as an incentive? Maybe 0.05% of the price. But that will be irrelevant to me -- the mental cost of remembering that Google gives me more cash back on lingerie gifts vastly outweighs the 0.05% payoff. <br/></li></ul>Kamal's point is that the last phenomenon is happening more and more often, as the economy moves to an atomic scale, making the relative cost of rationality in each decision increase. He draws a funny parallel to the Heisenberg uncertainty principle, which IMHO only goes as far as "on a small enough scale, things become funky".<br/><br/>The market inefficiency generated by the small scale of Web transactions is great for Web-based companies like Google, since it means they can make huge profits below the radar of competition forces. The sad news (for a scientist) is that it all becomes a social competition, instead of a scientific/economic one. It's much more important if I, the customer, like Google's colors than if I'm getting my fair share of cash back.<br/><br/>On a larger scale, is this a social problem? I guess so, but not a very big one. If our threshold for  irrationality is below 1%, the total income of such companies cannot grow above 1% of the money we all spend. But we're already paying the Federal government some 30% of what we make, and quite possibly many of us are happier with the success of Gmail than the hearts-and-minds campaign in Iraq.<br/><br/>PS: Given the topic, the number of jokes and anecdotes in Kamal's talk was too small by an order of magnitude. This reinforces my belief that we shouldn't be doing this kind of thing (i.e. study pure economics, because it is has something to do with networks or computers). If such pursuits will be more than wasted theoretical brain-cycles, they need to impact managers and policy-makers. But for that to happen, we need to give talks at the level of political speeches, and no self-respecting theorist is willing to do that. People in economics (who incidentally serve on policy-making boards every now and then) have already developed the art of communicating to politicians.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/4523236087108089662/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/4523236087108089662/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=786333285568106173&amp;postID=4523236087108089662">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/4523236087108089662/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-14T02:17:09Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-14T00:11:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>MiP</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-786333285568106173</id>
      <author>
        <name>MiP</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/WebdiariosDeMotocicleta" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>WebDiarios de Motocicleta</title>
      <updated>2007-11-19T07:48:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-5024280293383631067</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2007/11/my-web-page-has-moved.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=5024280293383631067" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/5024280293383631067/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/5024280293383631067" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/5024280293383631067" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>My Web Page Has Moved</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">My directories in Aalborg are about to be closed down, so after three years I have finally needed to move my web pages to Reykjavík University. I have been loathe to do so until now because Aalborg was ensuring adequate visibility on the web to my pages. My web page used to come out as first link in a Google search for "Luca Aceto" and was one of the top hits in a Google search for "Aceto" (where I am competing with the vinegar producers :-)).<br/><br/>My fears have now materialized. <a href="http://www.google.is/search?q=luca+aceto&amp;hl=is&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;rls=com.ubuntu:en-US:official&amp;hs=FWH&amp;start=0&amp;sa=N">This search</a> does not find my <a href="http://www.ru.is/faculty/luca">RU web page </a>on the first page, which is <span style="font-style: italic;">not</span> good. I'll have to explain to our web administrator that if Google can't find my home page, I basically don't exist.<br/><br/>Luckily, however, this blog is still visible and from there one can find my home page in a rather roundabout way :-)</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/5024280293383631067/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/5024280293383631067/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=5024280293383631067">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/5024280293383631067/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-13T18:31:51Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-13T15:24:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:09:19Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947.post-7585347013212777424</id>
    <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/2007/11/day-in-life.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=6555947&amp;postID=7585347013212777424" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/7585347013212777424/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/7585347013212777424" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/7585347013212777424" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>A day in the life...</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here's a list of things I did today:<br/><ul><li>I taught one lecture of my class</li><li>I attended a departmental committee meeting</li><li>I had a meeting with collaborators to work out a paper outline for something we're submitting</li><li>I met with my student and did some nontechnical advising</li><li>I had  a (brief) discussion with a collaborator about a pending grant proposal.</li></ul>In other words, I covered the entire gamut of activities one might expect of an academic - with one significant exception. Did you notice it ?<br/><br/>Nowhere in there was any actual research done ! Gaaaah !</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/7585347013212777424/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/7585347013212777424/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=6555947&amp;postID=7585347013212777424">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/7585347013212777424/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-13T09:52:26Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-13T09:49:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="personal"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="academy"/>
    <author>
      <name>Suresh</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947</id>
      <author>
        <name>Suresh</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/TheGeomblog" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>The Geomblog</title>
      <updated>2007-11-21T16:00:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-24557460.post-2854266465146635359</id>
    <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/2007/11/impagliazzo-hard-core-sets-via-finitary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=24557460&amp;postID=2854266465146635359" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/2854266465146635359/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/2854266465146635359" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/24557460/posts/default/2854266465146635359" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Impagliazzo Hard-Core Sets via "Finitary Ergodic-Theory"</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Impagliazzo hard-core set theorem we are a given a function $g:\{ 0, 1 \}^n \rightarrow \{ 0,1\}$ such that every algorithm in a certain class makes errors at least a $\delta$ fraction of the times when given a random input. We think of $\delta$ as small, and so of $g$ as exhibiting a weak form of average-case complexity. We want to find a large set $H\subseteq \{ 0,1 \}^n$ such  that $g$ is average-case hard in a stronger sense when restricted to $H$. This stronger form of average-case complexity will be that no efficient algorithm can make noticeably fewer errors while computing $g$ on $H$ than a trivial algorithm that always outputs the same value regardless of the input. The formal statement of what we are trying to do (see also the discussion in <a href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/2007/11/impagliazzo-hard-core-set-theorem.html">this previous post</a>) is:<br/><br/><blockquote><br/><b>Impagliazzo Hard-Core Set Theorem, "Constructive Version"</b><br/>Let $g:\{0,1\}^n \rightarrow \{0,1\}$ be a boolean function, $s$ be a size parameter, $\epsilon,\delta&gt;0$ be given. Then there is a size parameter $s' = poly(1/\epsilon,1/\delta) \cdot s +  exp(poly(1/\epsilon,1/\delta))$ such that the following happens.<br/><br/>Suppose that for every function $f:\{0,1\}^n \rightarrow \{0,1\}$ computable by a circuit of size $s'$ we have<br/><br/>$Pr_{x \in \{0,1\}^n} [ f(x) = g(x) ] \leq 1-\delta$<br/><br/>Then there is a set $H$ such that: (i) $H$ is recognizable by circuits of size $\leq s'$; (ii) $|H| \geq \delta 2^n$, and in fact the number of $x$ in $H$ such that $g(x)=0$ is at least $\frac 12 \delta 2^n$, and so is the number of $x$ in $H$ such that $g(x)=1$; and (iii) for every $f$ computable by a circuit of size $\leq s$,<br/><br/>$Pr_{x\in H} [ g(x) = f(x) ] \leq max \{ Pr_{x\in H}[ g(x) = 0] , Pr_{x\in H} [g(x)=1] \} + \epsilon$<br/></blockquote><br/><br/><br/>Our approach will be to look for a "regular partition" of $\{0,1\}^n$. We shall construct a partition $P= (B_1,\ldots,B_m)$ of $\{0,1\}^n$ such that: (i) given $x$, we can efficiently compute what is the block $B_i$ that $x$ belongs to; (ii) the number $m$ of blocks does not depend on $n$; (iii) $g$ restricted to most blocks $B_i$ behaves like a random function of the same density. (By "density" of a function we mean the fraction of inputs on which the function evaluates to one.)<br/><br/>In particular, we will use the following form of (iii): for almost all the blocks $B_i$, no algorithm has advantage more than $\epsilon$ over a constant predictor in computing $g$ in $B_i$.<br/><br/>Let $M_0$ be the union of all majority-0 blocks (that is, of blocks $B_i$ such that $g$ takes the value 0 on a majority of elements of $B_i$) and let $M_1$ be the union of all majority-1 blocks.<br/><br/>I want to claim that no algorithm can do noticeably better on $M_0$ than the constant algorithm that always outputs 0. Indeed, we know that within (almost) all of the blocks that compose $M_0$ no algorithm can do noticeably better than the always-0 algorithm, so this must be true for a stronger reason for the union. The same is true for $M_1$, with reference to the constant algorithm that always outputs 1. Also, if the partition is efficiently computable, then(in a non-uniform setting) $M_0$ and $M_1$ are efficiently recognizable. It remains to argue that either $M_0$ or $M_1$ is large and not completely unbalanced.<br/><br/>Recalling that we are in a non-uniform setting (where by "algorithms" we mean "circuits") and that the partition is efficiently computable, the following is a well defined efficient algorithm for attempting to compute $g$:<br/><br/><blockquote><br/><b>Algorithm. Local Majority</b><br/>On input $x$:<br/>determine the block $B_i$ that $x$ belongs to;<br/>output $1$ if $Pr_{z\in B_i} [g(z)=1] \geq \frac 12$; <br/>otherwise output $0$<br/></blockquote><br/><br/>(The majority values of $g$ in the various blocks are just a set of $m$ bits that can be hard-wired into the circuit.)<br/><br/>We assumed that every efficient algorithm must make at least a $\delta$ fraction of errors. The set of $\geq \delta 2^n$ inputs where the Local Majority algorithm makes mistakes is the union, over all blocks $B_i$, of the "minority inputs" of the block $B_i$. (If $b$ is the majority value of $g$ in a block $B$, then the "minority inputs" of $B$ are the set of inputs $x$ such that $g(x) = 1-b$.)<br/><br/>Let $E_0$ be the set of minority inputs (those where our algorithm makes a mistake) in $M_0$ and $E_1$ be the set of minority  inputs in $M_1$. Then at least one of $E_0$ and $E_1$ must have size at least $\frac {\delta}{2} 2^n$, because the size of their union is at least $\delta 2^n$. If $E_b$ has size at least $\frac {\delta}{2} 2^n$, then $M_b$ has all the properties of the set $H$ we are looking for.<br/><br/>It remains to construct the partition. We describe an iterative process to construct it. We begin with the trivial partition $P = (B_1)$ where $B_1 = \{ 0,1\}^n$. At a generic step of the construction, we have a partition $P = (B_1,\ldots,B_m)$, and we consider $M_0, M_1,E_0,E_1$ as above. Let $b$ be such that $E_b \geq \frac 12 \delta 2^n$. If there is no algorithm that has noticeable advantage in computing $g$ over $M_b$, we are done. Otherwise, if there is such an algorithm $f$, we refine the partition by splitting each block according to the values that $f$ takes on the elements of the block. <br/><br/>After $k$ steps of this process, the partition has the following form: there are $k$ functions $f_1,\ldots,f_k$ and each of the (at most) $2^k$ blocks of the partition corresponds to a bit string $b_1,\ldots,b_k$ and it contains all inputs $x$ such that $f_1(x)=b_1,\ldots,f_k(x)=b_k$. In particular, the partition is efficiently computable.<br/><br/>We need to argue that this process terminates with $k=poly(1/\epsilon,1/\delta)$. To this end, we define a potential function that measures the "imbalance" of $g$ inside the blocks the partition <br/><br/>$\Psi(B_1,\ldots,B_m) := \sum_{i=1}^m \frac {|B_i|}{2^n} \left( Pr_{x\in B_i} [g(x) = 1] \right)^2 $<br/><br/>and we can show that this potential function increases by at least $poly(\epsilon,\delta)$ at each step of the iteration. Since the potential function can be at most 1, the bound on the number of iterations follows.<br/><br/>A reader familiar with the proof of the Szemeredi Regularity Lemma will recognize the main ideas of iterative partitioning, of using a "counterexample" to the regularity property required of the final partition to do a refinement step, and of using a potential function argument to bound the number of refinement steps. <br/><br/>In which way can we see them as "finitary ergodic theoretic" techniques? As somebody who does not know anything about ergodic theory, I may not be in an ideal position to answer this question. But this kind of difficulty has not stopped me before, so I may attempt to answer this question in a future post.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/2854266465146635359/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/2854266465146635359/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=24557460&amp;postID=2854266465146635359">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/2854266465146635359/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-12T20:58:38Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-12T20:53:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-24557460</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>in theory</title>
      <updated>2007-11-21T20:31:22Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204.post-1712064760270605257</id>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2007/11/experiment-in-viral-marketing-buying.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=1712064760270605257" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1712064760270605257/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/1712064760270605257" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/1712064760270605257" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>An Experiment in Viral Marketing : Buying Tickets Online</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(Warning:  the following post is highly crass and commercial.  If that offends you in any way, please don't read on.)<br/><br/>Thanks to some friends who are working in Web marketing, I have a chance to try a viral marketing experiment right here on the blog.  I have been give some discount codes for a new ticket site -- <a href="http://ticketheroes.com/">ticketheroes.com</a> -- which offers tickets for sports/concerts/other events.  Anyone can use them, at least until 1/1/08, so you can use them, or tell a friend to use them, or have a friend tell a friend, or whatever.   According to that whole 6 degrees of separation thing, it's possible that <span style="font-style: italic;">everyone in the world</span> could learn my discount codes, which by the way are:<br/><br/>MMBLOG1 [$5 off any ticket purchase]<br/>MMBLOG2 [5% off any ticket purchase]<br/>[Yes, you can only use one of them...]<br/><br/>To be clear, I am officially acting as a consultant for the SEM company that is trying to drive traffic to TicketHeroes.  I <span style="font-style: italic;">am not</span> getting a direct cut back from sales using these codes.  (Though if this experiment is hugely successful, perhaps I'll try to negotiate one!)  But I will get back data -- I'll get to see how many sales used the codes.  (Don't worry, <span style="font-style: italic;">I</span> won't get your credit card number.)  I find this all very interesting.  Can this little blog, focusing primarily on academic topics, help sell things?  Really?  I kind of doubt it, but hey, I remember thinking around the year 1999 that it would be a really impressive thing if Google became a 1 billion dollar company, so clearly I don't know as much as I should about marketing.  <br/><br/>I've done my own checks and the site's prices look to be slightly less than or the same as other similar sites, even without the discount.   So this should be a win for anyone looking for tickets, although of course you shouldn't trust me, you should compare.<br/><br/>Next post, we'll return to less crass, commercial topics, like how to re-finance your mortgage.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1712064760270605257/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1712064760270605257/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=1712064760270605257">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/1712064760270605257/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-12T20:47:34Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-12T20:44:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="personal"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="society"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="consulting"/>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204</id>
      <author>
        <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>My Biased Coin</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T15:46:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-1058652655864746931</id>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2007/11/computational-complexity-conf-2008_12.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=1058652655864746931" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1058652655864746931" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/1058652655864746931" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>COMPUTATIONAL COMPLEXITY CONF 2008 SUBMISSIONS WEBSITE OPEN!</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Computational Complexity Conference 2008 (CCC 2008)
submissions website is now open:
<a href="http://ccc08.cs.washington.edu">go here for submissions
website</a>
or go
<a href="http://facweb.cs.depaul.edu/jrogers/complexity/">here
for more info on the conference</a>

<ol>
<li>
Submission deadline is Dec 6, 2007, 17:59 PST
</li><li>
Notification will be by Feb 8, 2008.
</li><li>
Conference will be in College Park Maryland
(details on that will be on the conference website
soon)
</li><li>
It will be <b>awesome!</b>
</li></ol>

<br/>
<br/>

Trivial question: Name everyone who has been to every single COMPLEXITY conference,
including when it as called STRUCTURES?
(I've been to all but one, Jack Lutz has been to all but two,
so we do not qualify.)</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
          <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=1058652655864746931">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-12T14:56:20Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-12T14:55:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <author>
        <name>Lance</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:03:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-3447097686928950526</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2007/11/origins-of-bisimulation-and-coinduction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=3447097686928950526" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/3447097686928950526/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/3447097686928950526" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/3447097686928950526" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>The Origins of Bisimulation and Coinduction</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I recently finished reading the paper <a href="http://www.cs.unibo.it/%7Esangio/DOC_public/history_bis_coind.pdf">On the Origins of Bisimulation, Coinduction, and  Fixed Points</a> by <a href="http://www.cs.unibo.it/%7Esangio/">Davide Sangiorgi.</a><br/><br/>I had the pleasure of hearing Davide give a talk on the topic of this survey paper during a <a href="http://www.icetcs.ru.is/luca/events/BICI/PA-05/">workshop</a> I co-organized in August 2005 in Bertinoro, and I had been waiting for the paper to appear in print ever since. The wait has now been vindicated by this truly excellent piece of scholarship. I suggest that any reader of this blog grabs a copy of this paper and reads it.  I myself learned something new from it and enjoyed reading it immensely.<br/><br/>In this well-organized paper, Davide takes us on a historical journey tracing back the origins of the ideas of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bisimulation">bisimulation</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coinduction">coinduction</a> through the three fields where they emerged independently: Computer Science, Modal Logic and Set Theory. He highlights the role played by some key figures in the development of bisimulation and co-induction, but he does not forget to mention the interesting contributions of less-known players. Each section of the paper ends with a discussion of the ideas it presents and speculates on the reasons why some authors went very close to defining bisimulation, but did not take the extra step needed to discover/invent bisimilarity.<br/><br/>The level of scholarship in the paper is outstanding. We need to thank Davide for making the effort to find appropriate sources, to read them so carefully and to present his findings in such a well-organized survey paper.<br/><br/>I trust that the writing of this paper took <span style="font-style: italic;">a lot </span>of work and I hope that our community will recognize the importance of writing articles like this one. Shouldn't journals accept historical papers of this quality? I believe they should!<br/><br/>Thanks again to Davide for making the effort to write this piece. I firmly believe that we should have more articles like this one and hope that this paper will enjoy a wide readership throughout the TCS community as a whole.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/3447097686928950526/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/3447097686928950526/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=3447097686928950526">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/3447097686928950526/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-12T11:47:31Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-12T11:22:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:09:19Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?p=582</id>
    <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?p=582" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The igTurn award?</title>
    <summary>So, there is no nobel prize in CS, but there is the “equivalent” Turing award. But we still dont have an equivalent to the ig Nobel prize. I suggest to establish a new prize to this effect named igTurn. As close as the winners are going to get to the Turing award (distance measured in [...]
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>So, there is no nobel prize in CS, but there is the “equivalent” Turing award. But we still dont have an equivalent to the ig Nobel prize. I suggest to establish a new prize to this effect named igTurn. As close as the winners are going to get to the Turing award (distance measured in edit distance, naturally).</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-12T02:03:32Z</updated>
    <category term="Research"/>
    <author>
      <name>Sariel Har-Peled</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog</id>
      <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Sariel's weblog</subtitle>
      <title>Vanity of Vanities, all is Vanity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T18:57:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-112/index.html</id>
    <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-112/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="2007/TR07-112/Paper.pdf" rel="enclosure" type="application/pdf"/>
    <title>Unbounded-Error Communication Complexity of Symmetric Functions</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<b>Authors:</b> <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sherstov:Alexander.html">Alexander Sherstov</a><br/>
			<b>Download:</b> 
			<a href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-112/Paper.pdf">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>

The sign-rank of a real matrix M is the least rank
of a matrix R in which every entry has the same sign as the
corresponding entry of M. We determine the sign-rank of every
matrix of the form M=[ D(|x AND y|) ]_{x,y}, where
D:{0,1,...,n}-&gt;{-1,+1} is given and x and y range over {0,1}^n.
Specifically, we prove that the sign-rank of M equals
2^{tilde Theta(k)}, where k is the number of times D changes
sign in {0,1,...,n}.

Put differently, we prove an optimal lower bound
on the unbounded-error communication complexity of every
symmetric function, i.e., a function of the form
f(x,y)=D(|x AND y|) for some D. The unbounded-error model is
essentially the most powerful of all models of communication
(both classical and quantum), and proving lower bounds in it
is a substantial challenge. The only previous nontrivial lower
bounds for this model appear in the groundbreaking work of
Forster (2001) and its extensions.  As corollaries to our
result, we give new lower bounds for PAC learning and for
threshold-of-majority circuits.

The technical content of our proof is diverse and
features random walks on (Z_2)^n, discrete approximation theory,
the Fourier transform on (Z_2)^n, linear-programming duality,
and matrix analysis.


		</div>
    </summary>
    <feedworld_mtime>1194825600</feedworld_mtime>
    <updated>2007-11-12</updated>
    <source>
      <id>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/</id>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc-reports/2007/TR07-112/index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <logo>http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/icons/BigLogo.gif</logo>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
        <email>meinel@hpi.uni-potsdam.de</email>
      </author>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://eccc.hpi-web.de/eccc/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <rights>Prof. Dr. Christoph Meinel, Hasso Plattner Institute</rights>
      <subtitle>The latest papers from the ECCC-Website</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC Papers</title>
      <updated>2007-11-12</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445.post-7738672841942859637</id>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/2007/11/ikea.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=7738672841942859637" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/7738672841942859637/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/7738672841942859637" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/21129445/posts/default/7738672841942859637" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>IKEA</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://www.freespiritart.com/kokanee-salmon.php"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://www.freespiritart.com/images/kokaneesalmon.jpg" style="float: left; margin: 0 10px 10px 0; cursor: pointer; cursor: hand; height: 200px; width: 250px;"/></a>I went to IKEA, an European equivalent of McDonalds (yes, $0.99 cheesburgers, $9.99 lava lamps). I know retailing is a difficult business and I not knocking their hard work. But retailing food is a harder business. I am mainly talking about the Salmon, the poor specimen that was born in captivity, lived within a large mesh I am sure, and eventually made its way, via the steam route, to one's plate: the piece was soggy,  served on a plate that was poorly washed, and accompanied by soggier vegetables; the patrons look at the plate without appetite, use the fork to cut it to pieces, move it around and play hockey, all the while talking, eating fries and drinking. I felt the need to rush home, paint a large, healthy, lively Salmon, and hang it somewhere in homage.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/7738672841942859637/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/7738672841942859637/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=7738672841942859637">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/7738672841942859637/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-11T00:15:53Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-10T23:59:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>metoo</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445</id>
      <author>
        <name>metoo</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>my slice of pizza</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T05:40:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204.post-3006523453610323626</id>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2007/11/koblitz-follow-up.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=3006523453610323626" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/3006523453610323626/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/3006523453610323626" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/3006523453610323626" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Koblitz follow-up</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/2007/11/december-issue-of-notices-of-ams.html">Luca points to</a> the <a href="http://www.ams.org/notices/200711/">letters to the editor</a> (and Koblitz's response) regarding <a href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2007/08/how-mathematicians-view-computer.html">the Koblitz affair</a>.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/3006523453610323626/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/3006523453610323626/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=3006523453610323626">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/3006523453610323626/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-10T22:19:32Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-10T22:15:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204</id>
      <author>
        <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>My Biased Coin</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T15:46:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445.post-1119155832406315866</id>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/2007/11/sponsored-search-market-index.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=1119155832406315866" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/1119155832406315866/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/1119155832406315866" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/21129445/posts/default/1119155832406315866" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Sponsored search market index</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://www.cs.umass.edu/%7Emicah/">Micah Adler</a> visited and it helped me recall shared experiences working on problems in a different world and context (parallel algorithms, scheduling problems, and a rope burning puzzle from long ago). Of course both of us had a life within a different context now, and so, we discussed a different set of problems.<br/><br/>In particular,  I got a chance to pose a problem I think of as a big picture question of some larger relevance (I am not an expert on markets, and this may not be such an interesting/challenging problem, but those disclaimers aside, in any case, here it is): Much like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stock_market_index">indices</a> for tracking the market for various materials/stocks, can we design one for tracking the market of sponsored search ads? Definitions aside, the engineering part of collecting relevant data may be fun too.<br/><br/>ps: <a href="http://intermexfreemarket.blogspot.com/2007/11/consultant-in-chief-what-mitt-romney.html">Mitt Romney: I Love Data</a>.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/1119155832406315866/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/1119155832406315866/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=1119155832406315866">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/1119155832406315866/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-10T19:00:54Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-10T18:34:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>metoo</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445</id>
      <author>
        <name>metoo</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>my slice of pizza</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T05:40:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-2555765375747888498</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2007/11/beatcs-is-open-access.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=2555765375747888498" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/2555765375747888498/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/2555765375747888498" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/2555765375747888498" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>BEATCS Is Open Access</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://www.ecs.soton.ac.uk/people/vs">Vladimiro Sassone</a>, the editor in chief of the Bulletin of the EATCS, has posted the appended message on several theory-related mailing lists. I hope that my readers will enjoy reading the Bulletin and will feel enticed to contribute to it by sending in survey articles for its columns, technical articles, conference and workshop reports, position papers, puzzles, obituaries etc.<br/><br/>I have always been a staunch supporter of an open-access Bulletin. A professional society like the EATCS must suppport the TCS research community in all possible ways. Having an open-access publication like the Bulletin is one of the contributions that the EATCS can have. Compare with <a href="http://sigact.acm.org/sigactnews/online.html">SIGACT News</a>, whose access is restricted to SIGACT members. Is this the best way to serve the TCS community?<br/><br/>I also believe that an open-access Bulletin of the EATCS will  entice more colleagues to contribute to the Bulletin  since their contributions will stand a better chance to be read and appreciated by anyone within the TCS community. This will also  increase the quality of the contributions.<br/><br/><br/>Support the EATCS and the open-access Bulletin by becoming a member of the EATCS!  Becoming a member is <a href="http://www.eatcs.org/organization/membership.html#how_to_join">easy,</a> and only costs € 30 for a period of one year. (In fact, it is only 25 € if you are also member of SIGACT.)   <span class="down" id="formatbar_CreateLink" style="display: block;" title="Link"/><br/>To quote from the classic Nike ad, "Just do it"<br/><br/>----------------------------------<br/><br/>Dear Colleagues,<br/><br/>    Since 2003 all issues of the Bulletin of the EATCS, the European<br/>Association for Theoretical Computer Science, have been produced<br/>entirely electronically and made available on the web for members only.<br/><br/>     The EATCS is now piloting the idea of Open Access for the Bulletin,<br/>in the spirit of best serving its research community. So, until<br/>further notice the volumes from no 79 onwards of the Bulletin of the<br/>EATCS will be available from<br/><br/>     <a href="http://www.eatcs.org/publications/bulletin.html" target="_blank">http://www.eatcs.org/publications/bulletin.html</a><br/><br/>With best regards (and apologies for cross-posting)<br/>\vs<br/><br/><br/><br/><br/></div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/2555765375747888498/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/2555765375747888498/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=2555765375747888498">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/2555765375747888498/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-10T11:00:19Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-09T10:08:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:09:19Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445.post-6626684414924792895</id>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/2007/11/brooklyn-blues.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=6626684414924792895" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6626684414924792895/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/6626684414924792895" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/21129445/posts/default/6626684414924792895" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Brooklyn Blues</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://profile.myspace.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=user.viewprofile&amp;friendID=69633190"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://a985.ac-images.myspacecdn.com/images01/18/m_605aadfd52fa7564da388734e4db3990.jpg" style="float: left; margin: 0 10px 10px 0; cursor: pointer; cursor: hand; height: 200px; width: 150px;"/></a><br/>What will move me several blocks away from my aptment, over the river and into Brooklyn? The Blues, beats and Jazz. Fridays and Saturdays, free and sweet at BAM, to be bottled at the moment, at the source, and sipped right then and later. Today, <a href="http://www.likewatermusic.com/html/itinerary.php">Chanda Rule</a> performed and freed the many who had gathered there after the long week.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6626684414924792895/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6626684414924792895/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=6626684414924792895">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6626684414924792895/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-10T04:18:07Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-10T03:53:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>metoo</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445</id>
      <author>
        <name>metoo</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>my slice of pizza</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T05:40:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-24557460.post-1332612161725071533</id>
    <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/2007/11/december-issue-of-notices-of-ams.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=24557460&amp;postID=1332612161725071533" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/1332612161725071533/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/1332612161725071533" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/24557460/posts/default/1332612161725071533" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>The December Issue of the Notices of the AMS</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The <a href="http://www.ams.org/notices/200711/">December issue</a> of the Notices of the AMS is now available online, and it includes letters written by Oded Goldreich, Boaz Barak, Jonathan Katz, and Hugo Krawczyk in response to Neal Koblitz's article which appeared in the <a href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/2007/08/swift-boating-of-modern-cryptography.html">September issue</a>.<br/><br/>Despite this, the readers of the Notices remain the losers in this "controversy." Koblitz's petty personal attacks and straw man arguments appeared in the same space that is usually reserved, in the Notices, for expository articles and obituaries of mathematicians. It is from those pages that I learned about the <a href="http://www.ams.org/notices/200103/fea-tao.pdf">Kakeya problem</a> and about the <a href="http://www.ams.org/notices/200409/fea-grothendieck-part1.pdf">life</a> of <a href="http://www.ams.org/notices/200410/fea-grothendieck-part2.pdf">Grothendieck</a> (who, I should clarify, is not dead, except perhaps in Erdos' use of the word).<br/><br/>I find it strange enough that Koblitz would submit his piece to such a venue, but I find it as mind-boggling that the editors would run his piece as if they had commissioned Grothendieck's biographical article to a disgruntled ex-lover, who would focus most of the article on fabricated claims about his personal hygiene.<br/><br/>I can only hope that the editors will soon run on those pages one or more expository articles on modern cryptography, not as rebuttals to Koblitz's piece (which has already been discussed more than enough), but as a service to the readers.<br/><br/>And while I am on the subject of Notices article, let me move on to <a href="http://www.ams.org/notices/200711/tx071101507p.pdf">this article</a> on how to write papers.<br/><br/>All beginning graduate students find the process of doing research mystifying, and I do remember feeling that way. (Not that such feelings have changed much in the intervening years.) One begins with a sense of hopelessness, <i>how am I going to solve a problem that people who know much more than I do and who are smarter than me have not been able to solve?</i>; then a breakthrough comes, out of nowhere, and one wonders, how is this ever going to happen <i>again</i>? Finally it's time to write up the results, and mathematical proofs definitely don't write themselves, not to mention coherent and compelling introductory sections. I think it's great when more experienced scholars take time to write advice pieces that can help students navigate these difficulties. And the number of atrociously badly written papers in circulation suggests that such pieces are good not just for students, but for many other scholars as well.<br/><br/>But I find that advice on "how to publish," rather than "how to write well" (like advice on "how to get a job" rather than "how to do research") misses the point (I am thinking of one of the few times I thought Lance Fortnow gave <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2004/06/dont-make-it-too-easy-or-too-much.html">bad advice</a>). For this reason, I found the first section of the Notices article jarring, and the following line (even if it was meant as a joke) made me cringe<br/><blockquote><br/>I have written more than 150 articles myself. (...) I have never written an article and then been unable to publish it.<br/></blockquote><br/>I think that this calls for an <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=40">Umeshism</a> in response.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/1332612161725071533/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/1332612161725071533/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=24557460&amp;postID=1332612161725071533">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/1332612161725071533/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-09T23:02:05Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-09T21:53:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-24557460</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>in theory</title>
      <updated>2007-11-21T20:31:22Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7898198581379740078</id>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2007/11/richard-beigel-is-at-nsf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=7898198581379740078" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7898198581379740078" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7898198581379740078" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Richard Beigel is at NSF</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Richard Beigel is now one of five Program Director at
NSF for CISE/CCS/TF (TF= Theoretical Foundations)
This is the job previously held by William Steiger
(who will stay on part time for two months, but is
already back at Rutgers.)
 
<br/>
<br/>
 
Lets all wish him well on the job- if he does well,
we do well.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
          <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=7898198581379740078">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-09T20:17:58Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-09T20:17:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <author>
        <name>Lance</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:03:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-786333285568106173.post-5617705239701882774</id>
    <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/2007/11/branding-and-stocfocs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=786333285568106173&amp;postID=5617705239701882774" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/5617705239701882774/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default/5617705239701882774" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default/5617705239701882774" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Branding and STOC/FOCS</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2007/11/resubmitting-rejected-focs-paper-to.html">Kamal Jain</a> gives some advice on resubmitting papers that got rejected from STOC/FOCS. That reminds me of a question I've had for while: can you build up a name by only submitting papers in the right places (i.e. where they get accepted)?<br/><br/>Personally, I feel very strongly about self-selection. In my (short) career, I have had a total of 2 rejects:<br/><ul><li>a paper rejected from ICALP, which got accepted to the subsequent SODA ;)</li><li>a "short paper" rejected from SODA, which essentially disappeared (we came up with new ideas and obtained much better results). Incidentally, I'm glad the short track at SODA was stopped. It was a temptation to do mediocre work -- if you write a really good result in 2 pages, you will always get accepted even without the short track.</li></ul>I self-select due to my own ethical beliefs, independent of the environment in the community. However, I'm often told that this is not career-optimal from a selfish perspective: if you shoot for a reasonable reject rate, say under 50%, you can often push papers up a notch, making for a better CV.<br/><br/>Is this advice short-sighted? Does having a low reject rate help you in getting more attention from reviewers? If a reviewer knows you're not a "deceiver", he will feel uneasy about rejecting, and will think about it for another minute -- at the very least, he knows one person in the world (you, the author) finds the paper interesting. If a reveiwer has already rejected a couple of your papers, he won't have so many moral problems -- after all, it's possible that you yourself don't think the paper is good enough.<br/><br/>What do you think? Can you get reviewer sympathy by active self-selection?</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/5617705239701882774/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/5617705239701882774/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=786333285568106173&amp;postID=5617705239701882774">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/5617705239701882774/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-09T18:41:38Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-09T18:19:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>MiP</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-786333285568106173</id>
      <author>
        <name>MiP</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/WebdiariosDeMotocicleta" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>WebDiarios de Motocicleta</title>
      <updated>2007-11-19T07:48:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?p=581</id>
    <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?p=581" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Now you know…</title>
    <summary>Why does the zebra wears pajamas? The answer.
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Why does the zebra wears pajamas? <a href="http://youtube.com/watch?v=HO-4NAgESns">The answer</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-09T16:21:28Z</updated>
    <category term="Quickies"/>
    <author>
      <name>Sariel Har-Peled</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog</id>
      <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Sariel's weblog</subtitle>
      <title>Vanity of Vanities, all is Vanity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T18:57:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-19908808.post-2463145648836843366</id>
    <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/2007/11/limits-of-transcendance-and-our-failure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=19908808&amp;postID=2463145648836843366" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/2463145648836843366/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/2463145648836843366" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/19908808/posts/default/2463145648836843366" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Limits of Transcendence: Our Failure to Protect Prisoners</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One thing I'd long been planning to post about is just how positive a role math has played in my own life.  Since I came to enjoy it (relatively late--around senior year in high school), I have become: less restless; less materialistic; clearer and more self-reliant in my thinking; able to think longer and more fruitfully about all kinds of things, with nothing but a pen and paper.<br/><br/>All of these beneficial effects constitute, to my mind, a 'practical application' for math that warrants mentioning in the same breath as its uses in science and technology.  In particular, I always thought these virtues seemed especially well-suited to empower and improve the constrained lives of prisoners.  I know of one example--<a href="http://www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk/~history/Biographies/Turan.html">Paul Turan</a> seems to have invented extremal graph theory in a Hungarian labor camp during WWII--but Turan was admittedly already a professional mathematician.  Of course math isn't for everyone, but I would be very interested to know whether it's been taught specifically for enjoyment in prisons, and with what results.<br/><br/>It's an exciting idea to me, and I hope it excites others.  However, it'd be irresponsible and dishonest to pursue it without acknowledging math's limits as a life practice.  Coping with boredom is one thing, but, speaking personally, my mathematical thinking goes to pieces when I'm in acute distress or suffering.  There's a limit to what we should reasonably expect to transcend through math, just as with art, religion, meditation, and other such 'soft' techniques... which brings me to what actually prompted this post: news from California that makes me ashamed of the state of affairs in my home state.  <br/><br/><br/>According to <a href="http://www.prnewswire.com/cgi-bin/stories.pl?ACCT=104&amp;STORY=/www/story/10-15-2007/0004682327&amp;EDATE=">this article</a> (see also this <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/19/opinion/19fri4.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin">Times editorial</a>), Gov. Schwarzenegger recently vetoed a bill that would allow nonprofits to distribute condoms in prisons. (He claimed it would conflict with the law against sexual contact between inmates.)  It seems he did something similar two years ago.  There are some condom distributions in CA prisons, and Schwarzenegger authorized one new, small-scale pilot program, but he derailed the state legislature's decision to make such distributions a statewide reality.<br/><br/>I hope the cruelty and stupidity of this decision speak for themselves, but I'll make a few comments to encourage further thought, because a decision this bad needs to be understood as well as denounced.  To try and make (partial) sense of his decision, let me suggest that, in policymaking and debate around HIV/AIDS and other sexually transmitted infections, there are various gradations of the position that would block direct public health initiatives.  <br/><br/>First, there are those who simply disapprove of a particular behavior, be it pre- or extramarital sex, same-gender sex, sex in prisons, or intravenous drug use.  It doesn't necessarily lead them to disregard other social issues or form a blanket policy statement.<br/><br/>Then there are those who, through a combination of wishful thinking and manipulation, reach the idea that the health threat posed by risky behaviors might itself be the best deterrent against these behaviors, superior from a moral <span style="font-style: italic;">and</span> public health perspective to interventions that would make those behaviors safer (condom distributions, needle exchanges, HPV vaccinations, etc).  They accept arguments to this effect without sufficient critical thought, and neglect contrary evidence.<br/><br/>Then there are those who publicly espouse this best-of-both-worlds notion, but whose prolonged refusal to engage with the evidence leads one to suspect that either <span style="font-style: italic;">(a)</span> they no longer feel compassion for victims of infection from their designated 'deviant' population groups, or <span style="font-style: italic;">(b)</span> they feel that infection's (supposed) role in discrediting and deterring 'deviant' behavior outweighs its human costs (so, in a sense, they <span style="font-style: italic;">ally themselves</span> with the epidemic).<br/><br/>Finally, at the far end you have those who feel only contempt for 'deviants', and openly exult in public health crises which they see as just punishment.<br/><br/>But can we explain Schwarzenegger's behavior as occupying a point along this spectrum?  I'm not so sure.  As soon as incarceration comes into play, the debate seems to get much more complex (i.e., crazier).  Are these notions of morality and deterrence even operative in the (supposedly kinda-socially-liberal) Governor's decision?  Is he offering a feeble cover for the prison industry from the already-widespread recognition that, in many cases, they fail to protect their inmates from sexual coercion? (For a discussion of the state of available statistics on prison rape see <a href="http://www.hrw.org/reports/2001/prison/report1.html">this Human Rights Watch page</a>.)  Or is he merely bowing to the time-honored tradition of abusing prisoners?<br/><br/>I would love to hear what others think, because I can't decide the issue myself.  All that's clear to me is that he's taken citizens in a position of enforced vulnerability, who are contracting HIV at <a href="http://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/49988.php">eight times</a> the rate outside prison, and cut off one of the most important means of protecting them.  (I don't believe the state was even asked to <span style="font-style: italic;">pay</span> for the condoms....!)<br/><br/>Meanwhile--Governor Schwarzenegger, withdraw your veto!</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/2463145648836843366/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/2463145648836843366/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=19908808&amp;postID=2463145648836843366">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/2463145648836843366/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-08T23:14:40Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-08T19:03:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Andy D</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-19908808</id>
      <author>
        <name>Andy D</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Andy's Math/CS page</title>
      <updated>2007-11-19T22:25:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204.post-427748167370258964</id>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/2007/11/service-and-nsf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=427748167370258964" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/427748167370258964/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/427748167370258964" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/8890204/posts/default/427748167370258964" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Service and the NSF</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I recently returned from an NSF (National Science Foundation) review panel.  (Of course, I'm not allowed to say when, or for what.)  On the way back, at the airport, I ran into a more senior colleague (from an entirely different field -- not EECS) coming back on the same flight.  It came up that he had <span style="font-style: italic;">never</span> served on an NSF review panel.  He admittedly seemed a bit sheepish about it, but offered the excuse that there were more important things to do, and I will give him the benefit of the doubt and assume that he meant other service activities, not research and such.  Essentially, his argument seemed to be that NSF panels were a waste of his time.<br/><br/>Having served on a half dozen or so NSF review panels, I have some sympathy for this point of view.  In particular, being anti-travel, I'm not sure why we have to fly in for a two-day meeting to make decisions;  it's expensive for the NSF and time-consuming for me.  (It's not clear to me that decisions are any better because of the face-to-face meeting.  Indeed, arguably, they can be worse, depending on the group interaction.  But government process is government process, so unlike for PCs, not having the face-to-face meeting is not currently an option...)<br/><br/>However, despite the time, I've tried to make myself available when the calls for NSF panels go out, because I've always figured that if the NSF is paying my summer salary (which, in large part, they do), they have the right to ask for some of my time.  Indeed, my gut reaction (without working through the arguments) is that it's objectionable that they don't actually <span style="font-style: italic;">require</span> people who have received funding to serve on a review panel at some point during the term of their grant, though I suppose the implementation of that rule could become unpleasant.  In short, my moral interpretation is that by taking their money, I'm part of their system, so when they come calling, I should respond, even without an explicit quid pro quo.<br/><br/>Even if one does not subscribe to this implicit understanding, I think it's important for us individually and as a community (including non-academics who don't get NSF funding directly) to do our service for the NSF, particularly in the way of review panels.  In general, citizens should be keeping an eye out on how the government uses their money, and in this specific case, as scientists, we should be paying especially close attention to how the government is distributing research money to scientists in our own and related fields, and we should be attempting to influence the process to move in the right directions as much as possible.   The panels give us some opportunity to influence the process, and these otherwise near-useless face-to-face meetings give us some opportunity to influence the NSF administrators who shape and make the decisions that affect us all.<br/><br/>So, with all due respect to my senior colleague, and any of you other slackers out there, get over yourselves, and go serve on an NSF panel every other year or so.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/427748167370258964/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/427748167370258964/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=8890204&amp;postID=427748167370258964">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/427748167370258964/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-08T19:08:33Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-08T12:50:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="travel"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="funding"/>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="administration"/>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8890204</id>
      <author>
        <name>Michael Mitzenmacher</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>My Biased Coin</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T15:46:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-590068913766798483</id>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2007/11/resubmitting-rejected-focs-paper-to.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=590068913766798483" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/590068913766798483" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/590068913766798483" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Resubmitting Rejected FOCS paper to STOC</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(Guest post by
<i>Kamal Jain</i>

Resubmitting the rejected papers from FOCS to STOC?

<br/>
<br/>

If your paper was rejected by FOCS and you're submitting it to STOC, here 
are my thoughts on how you can increase your chances of acceptance. Given the
low acceptance rate for FOCS, I am sure many of us will be resubmitting
our rejected papers to STOC. Many of us will be incorporating the FOCS PC 
comments. And there's also a realistic chance that FOCS PC misunderstood our
papers. So what should we do so that STOC committee does not repeat the
misunderstanding?

<br/>
<br/>

Let me first describe the general methods to contain the chances of
misunderstanding. I will then describe why the chance of misunderstanding 
has increased for STOC PC on resubmitted papers by giving you an insider view
of FOCS 2007 PC. We can then discuss what we could do to minimize that.

<br/>
<br/>

<b>Contain the chances of misunderstanding</b>

<br/>
<br/>

Well of course removing the items from the paper which gave rise to misunderstanding
could be beneficial. These items could arise either due to lack of explanation,
positioning of clarification, or overselling the results. Lack of explanation
happens because we fail to realize as authors that our mind is pre-conditioned
while researching on the paper and the reviewer's mind won't be pre-conditioned
in the same way. Therefore things which look clear to us may be confusing to a
reviewer. Positioning of clarification is very important because not every paper
is read word to word. So it is very important to put the clarification or a pointer
to it as close as possible to the place where confusion could potentially arise.
Overselling does not improve the chances of a paper getting accepted.
Overselling of results typically puts the reviewer in a defensive position.
A reviewer could look at other existing papers that have introduced similar                   
techniques and be at a loss for what is new, unique, and real about what this paper promises.

<br/>
<br/>


So how do you address these problems? One thing is to prepare the paper early
and seek feedback. Do not expect somebody, who is not genuinely interested in
your work, to provide you good quality feedback for free. You would need to pay.
How? Offer the same high quality service on their papers as you
 expect on your own papers. Posting your papers online, e.g., as a technical
report in some archive could also bring some early readership, which may
provide you feedback and opportunities to exchange feedback.

<br/>
<br/>
If you really need to sell your paper, what's the best way? Give talks --
as many as possible. Try to accept every invitation and try to get yourself
invited by marketing the results. In order to market the paper be open to 
discussing your results in small chats without pen and paper, e.g., over a
lunch table. Acknowledge all pre-publication discussions, including those which
were not explicitly used in the paper. Mentioning the names of the people
is very important, and in case of explicit usefulness, mentioning it
explicitly is equally important too. This is so that your colleagues feel
acknowledged and positively reinforced to collaborate with you in the future. In
the short term, these colleagues are also likely to see the papers more
positively vs the case if they find their assistance is not fully acknowledged.

<br/>
<br/>
What else can you do if you do not yet have enough opportunities to talk about
your paper? We have not done so, but there are cheap as well as free software
using which we can easily make a high quality screencast. For me personally,
a high quality screencast provides 80% of the benefit of watching
the talk in person. Much of the benefit of the remaining 20% can also be 
obtained if there is an open forum associated with the screencast to ask questions
which can either be answered by the authors or other viewers in a
relatively short time. Readers do not have the patience unless they are genuinely
interested in your result. And expect to count the number of the latter
on your fingers.:)

<br/>
<br/>

<b>An insider's view of FOCS:</b>

<br/>
<br/>

What's specific about paper reviewing these days? As part of the FOCS committee
we had access to reviews submitted by the previous STOC committee. We
paid a great deal of attention to whether the version we had had responded
to the STOC PC's reasons of rejecting the papers. Similarly expect STOC 2008
PC to have FOCS 2007 PC's reviews available. The intersection between STOC 2008 PC
and FOCS 2007 PC is non-empty. Even if you think FOCS PC misunderstood
your paper, and responding to those misunderstandings would make the
paper less readable, you should still try to respond to those misunderstandings
instead of ignoring them. In such cases you can respond to those
misunderstandings either in appropriate footnotes or in a one page appendix in
the end. If your footnotes and appendix are just for STOC PC, do mention "for
the reviewers only, will be removed from the published version."

<br/>
<br/>
What about the feedback that FOCS PC kept confidential and did not transmit
 to the authors? This part of the feedback must not be used by STOC committee
for three reasons. First, it was understood that only FOCS PC share that
 feedback. Second, this part of the feedback was a part of the process and
not the net outcome. The net outcome ideally must be included in the "send
to author" part of the feedback. Third, since this part of the feedback was
 not transmitted to the authors, they can't be expected to respond. If this
 part of the feedback did contain a reason why the paper should be rejected
 then authors must be sent the reason. If this was not done in some cases,
then STOC PC must work hard to rediscover the same reason for rejection.

<br/>
<br/>
This is my view from both having submitted (and received rejections) papers
 as well as been part of various PCs. I hope these give you additional practical
tical tips on how to best position your papers. I welcome other ideas so that
we could continue to improve the quality of our submissions.

<br/>
<br/>


Thanks,

<br/>
<br/>


Kamal Jain.

<br/>
<br/>


Note: FOCS means FOCS 2007. STOC means STOC 2008. Previous STOC means STOC =
2007.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
          <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=590068913766798483">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-07T23:24:31Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-07T21:49:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <author>
        <name>Lance</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:03:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445.post-1379588522591355591</id>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/2007/11/helvetica.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=1379588522591355591" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/1379588522591355591/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/1379588522591355591" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/21129445/posts/default/1379588522591355591" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Helvetica</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2007/09/12/arts/12helv600.jpg"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2007/09/12/arts/12helv600.jpg" style="float: left; margin: 0 10px 10px 0; cursor: pointer; cursor: hand; height: 200px; width: 300px;"/></a>I should have <a href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/2007/04/its-sans-serif-smackdown.html">listened to Suresh</a> and watched <a href="http://www.helveticafilm.com/index.html">the movie</a> long time ago. Instead, I watched it two days ago. There is the story of the NY grandmothers who would sit at their window and watch their 10 yr old grandson walk down the block, and the adventurous ones, let their grandson walk down the avenue block! Well, those NY grandmothers would have found it easy to track me as I walked all of 0.5 street blocks from my aptment to the IFC theater to watch it late night, the movie by now almost a midnight cult affair. The theater had 2 men fiddling with pen and paper, 2 couples (one hetero), an oldman with bulging backpack and beard flowing down to trip him when he walked, and me. I swear someone had a Mac in the theater, the movie was mainly a sublime homage to Apple. It was encouraging to see grown men (and 1 grown woman) speak passionately about fonts. The movie (<a href="http://movies.nytimes.com/2007/09/12/movies/12helv.html">NY Times Review</a> gets it right: "<span style="font-style: italic;">you’re guaranteed to spend the next few days scanning the world for Helvetica like a child on a cross-country car trip playing I Spy.</span>") was visually pleasing, moving from New to Old amsterdam/world, and I returned home, vowing to experiment with fonts. Save me.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/1379588522591355591/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/1379588522591355591/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=1379588522591355591">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/1379588522591355591/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-07T15:51:35Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-07T15:33:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>metoo</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445</id>
      <author>
        <name>metoo</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>my slice of pizza</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T05:40:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445.post-6373976828242878807</id>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/2007/11/math-in-nyer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=6373976828242878807" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6373976828242878807/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/6373976828242878807" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/21129445/posts/default/6373976828242878807" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Math in NYer</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, two of my favorites collide. NYer has a <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/talk/2007/11/12/071112ta_talk_widdicombe">fun writeup</a> on FireFighters Theorem, and quotes the work of Barry Cipra. Enjoy!</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6373976828242878807/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6373976828242878807/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=21129445&amp;postID=6373976828242878807">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/6373976828242878807/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-07T15:31:54Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-07T15:27:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>metoo</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-21129445</id>
      <author>
        <name>metoo</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>my slice of pizza</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T05:40:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:11011110:122234</id>
    <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/122234.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Six recent arXiv papers</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some recent uploads to <a href="http://arxiv.org">arxiv.org</a> that have caught my attention:<br/><br/><b>Lens sequences</b>, by J. Kocik, <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0710.3226">arXiv:0710.3226</a>. <a name="cutid1"/>Considers problems in which the lens-shaped space between two equal-radius circles is filled by a sequence of other circles, so that each circle inside the lens is tangent to the lens boundaries and to two other circles. The reciprocals of the radii of these circles form bi-infinite sequences in which the values are in many cases all integers; when this happens, the sequence is formed by products of consecutive values in some simpler "underground" integer sequence. For instance, one example has radii 1/3, 1/15, 1/35, 1/63, ...; the denominators of these numbers are products of consecutive odd numbers, so the underground sequence is the sequence of odd numbers. Other underground sequences involve Fibonacci numbers and Lucas numbers, or the sequences formed by shuffling pairs of such sequences.<br/><br/><b>Generalizations of Schöbi's tetrahedral dissection</b>, by Sloane and Vaishampayan, <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0710.3857">arXiv:0710.3857</a>. <a name="cutid2"/> If you start with a triangle with vertices (0,0), (0,1), and (1,1), cut off  a corner, and reattach the cut corner to the remaining part along the diagonal, you get a 1/2 × 1 prism. If you start with a tetrahedron with vertices (0,0,0), (0,0,1), (0,1,1), and (1,1,1), and make two cuts perpendicular to the main diagonal passing through the two non-main-diagonal vertices, the pieces can be rearranged to form an equilateral-triangle prism. (These two cuts partition the main diagonal of the tetrahedron into three equal pieces that become the edges of the prism, and partition the shorter diagonals into two equal pieces.) This paper generalizes this to a family of n-piece dissections of n-dimensional simplices (affine transforms of the "orthoschemes", simplices with 0-1 coordinates as above), into (n-1)-dimensional prisms. Iterating the construction leads to an n!-piece dissection of an orthoscheme into a parallelepiped.<br/><br/><b>Simple, linear-time modular decomposition</b>, by Tedder, Corneil, Habib, and Paul, <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0710.3901">arxiv:0710.3901</a>. <a name="cutid3"/>A module in a graph is a set of vertices that all have the same pattern of connections to the rest of the graph: they may have an arbitrary set of edges among themselves, but if one vertex in the set has an edge to a vertex outside the set, the rest of them must also have an edge to the same vertex. If a graph is disconnected or co-disconnected, the components are trivial modules, but one can also have modules of more complex types; in the nontrivial case the maximal modules form a partition of the graph (counting a single vertex as a module). Modular decomposition is what you repeatedly form this partition, then look for submodules within each maximal module, etc. There have been linear time algorithms known for doing this for over ten years now, and I've thought about adding them to <a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/PADS/">PADS</a>, but they're rather complicated. This paper seems a step in the right direction: still linear time, but closer to being implementable.<br/><br/><b>The lonely vertex problem</b>, by D. Frettlöh and A. Glazyrin, <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0710.4870">arxiv:0710.4870</a>. <a name="cutid4"/>It's possible to surround a point in the plane by finitely many convex polygons in such a way that it's the vertex of only two of them: for instance, consider the vertices of the standard "brick wall" tiling of the plane by dominos. But it's not possible to surround a point by convex polygons in such a way that it's a vertex of just one, because the complement of the polygon would form an angle strictly between 180 and 360 degrees, which cannot be filled by the 180 degree angles of nonvertex boundary points of polygons. But what about in higher dimensions? Can one surround a point of some higher dimensional Euclidean space by finitely many convex polytopes in such a way that one of the polytopes has a vertex that's not also a vertex of any other polytope? As the authors show, the answer is no. The 3d result can also be phrased in terms of partitions of a sphere surrounding the point: if one defines a "wedge" to be the shape bounded between two longitudes on a globe, one can't partition the globe into finitely many wedges and one leftover convex region.<br/><br/><b>Triangular peg solitaire unlimited</b>, by G. I. Bell, <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0711.0486">arxiv:0711.0486</a>. <a name="cutid5"/>You all know what peg solitaire is, right? Start with a grid of pegs, all but one empty, and then repeatedly jump one peg over another, removing the jumped peg, until all are gone or (more likely) you get stuck with a few scattered pegs and have to try again. If not, go to <a href="http://www.geocities.com/gibell.geo/pegsolitaire/tindex.html">George Bell's triangular peg solitaire page</a> and try playing his <a href="http://www.geocities.com/gibell.geo/pegsolitaire/Tools/Triangular/Triang.htm">javascript peg solitaire applet</a>. In this paper, Bell studies two problems related to this puzzle: how few moves are possible (if one counts a sequence of jumps by the same peg as a single move), and how many jumps are possible on the last move? In a single jump sequence, the points that can be positions of the jumping peg and the points that can be jumped turn out to be disjoint, so the problem of maximizing jump sequence length is related to forming Eulerian subgraphs of the triangular grid, but not every graph of this type can be formed as part of a valid solution to the whole puzzle.<br/><br/><b>Permutations defining convex permutominoes</b>, by Bernini, Disanto, Pinzani, and Rinaldi, <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0711.0582">arxiv:0711.0582</a>. <a name="cutid6"/>A permutomino is just a polyomino (polygon with axis-aligned sides and integer vertex coordinates) with the property that no two sides lie on the same line, the vertical sides lie on a contiguous sequence of vertical integer grid lines, and the horizontal sides lie on a contiguous sequence of horizontal integer grid lines. The authors describe a way of encoding a permutomino with two permutations, but not every pair of permutations works: some give disconnected boundaries or self-crossing boundaries. They characterize the permutations that do lead to simple polygons. This caught my attention because it seems relevant for <a href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/tag/xyz+graphs">xyz graphs</a>, and specifically for the problem of finding three permutations of the coordinates that eliminate all crossings of an xyz graph representation, if possible.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-07T06:14:42Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-06T18:59:45Z</published>
    <category term="xyz graphs"/>
    <category term="python"/>
    <category term="geometry"/>
    <category term="papers"/>
    <source>
      <id>urn:lj:livejournal.com:atom1:11011110</id>
      <author>
        <name>0xDE</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://11011110.livejournal.com/data/atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>0xDE</subtitle>
      <title>0xDE</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T22:43:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947.post-3226414513067858242</id>
    <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/2007/11/as-good-as-your-best-result.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=6555947&amp;postID=3226414513067858242" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/3226414513067858242/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/3226414513067858242" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default/3226414513067858242" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>"As good as your best result"</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><a href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/2007/11/numbers-game.html">Mihai makes the argument</a> that in theoryCS, you're as famous as your best result. I think the number of good results does matter a bit more than that, but getting well known for your best result is the best way to make a first splash and get on the radar.<br/><br/>I've actually heard the opposite claim made by systems researchers, and this has been extended to other empirical researchers as well. Namely, "you're as good as your worst result" (presumably thresholded to ignore grad school). The rationale here appears to be that in the conservative empirical sciences, where a badly designed experiment can cast a shadow on all your later work, it's your worst result that matters.<br/><br/>I can see how this works (sort of): in the more mathematical disciplines, a "proof" can to a large extent be validated independent of the author, so mistakes in past proofs can be tolerated (though if this becomes an endemic problem, then ...). <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_de_Branges_de_Bourcia">Louis de Branges</a> is famous for his proof of a conjecture in complex analysis known as the Bieberbach conjecture, and is currently well known for his claimed proof of the Riemann Hypothesis (Karl Sabbagh's book on this has more on de Branges). His proof of the Bieberbach conjecture was not without some initial skepticism from other mathematicians, because of some earlier false starts. However, it was soon seen as correct, and has opened up new areas of mathematics as well. As a consequence, his proofs of the Riemann hypothesis have received more cautious consideration as well (although I am not aware of the current status of his claims).<br/><br/>On the other hand, validating empirical work is largely on trust: you trust that the scientists have made faithful measurements, have kept proper lab notes etc, and I can see how a weakening of that trust can lead to much higher skepticism.<br/><br/>In this light, it's interesting to read <a href="http://gladwell.typepad.com/gladwellcom/2007/11/serial-killers.html">Malcolm Gladwell's latest article</a> for the New Yorker. He profiles the "profilers": the psych experts who help the FBI track down serial killers, and comes to this conclusion:<br/><blockquote>He seems to have understood only that, if you make a great number of predictions, the ones that were wrong will soon be forgotten, and the ones that turn out to be true will make you famous.<br/></blockquote></div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/3226414513067858242/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/3226414513067858242/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=6555947&amp;postID=3226414513067858242">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/3226414513067858242/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-07T04:13:25Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-07T03:58:00Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://www.blogger.com/atom/ns#" term="community"/>
    <author>
      <name>Suresh</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-6555947</id>
      <author>
        <name>Suresh</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/6555947/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://geomblog.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/TheGeomblog" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>The Geomblog</title>
      <updated>2007-11-21T16:00:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=288</id>
    <link href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=288" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title xml:lang="en">MIT sues Frank Gehry over Stata Center</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en">When I first saw the headline, I assumed it was from The Onion or (more likely) some local MIT humor publication.  But no, it’s from the Associated Press.
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center;"><img src="http://www.scottaaronson.com/statactr.jpg"/></p>
<p>When I first saw the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/us/AP-MIT-Suit-Architect.html?_r=2&amp;hp=&amp;oref=slogin&amp;pagewanted=print&amp;oref=slogin">headline</a>, I assumed it was from The Onion or (more likely) some local MIT humor publication.  But no, it’s from the Associated Press.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-07T02:42:40Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-07T02:42:40Z</published>
    <category scheme="http://scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <category scheme="http://scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Procrastination"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2007-11-23T04:27:50Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-19908808.post-2103400202051567382</id>
    <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/2007/11/goofball-dna-bonanza.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=19908808&amp;postID=2103400202051567382" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/2103400202051567382/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/2103400202051567382" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/19908808/posts/default/2103400202051567382" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Goofball DNA-Bonanza</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since this blog's readership is, I'm guessing, essentially a (very-)proper subset of the readership of <a href="http://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/">Shtetl-Optimized</a>, you may be familiar with his <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=287">recent musings and observations</a> on DNA rewriting rules (to which I refer readers before looking further at my post).  I've been finding this stuff a fun alternative to my usual research (the last time I got this worked up over DNA might've been when I heard about <a href="http://www.grg.org/OHSUmonkey.htm">ANDi the monkey</a>), and have come up with three simple results in the past couple of days.  The latest is a bit too long for Scott's comments section, so I wrote it up in LaTex and am putting it <a href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/andyd/dnacode.pdf">here</a>.  <br/><br/>I encourage all readers to generate, pose, and/or answer additional questions on related themes!  Collaborative online research is lots of fun in my experience, and something I'm considering trying to do more of with this blog.<br/><br/><br/>Let me explain the third result after reviewing the other two.  But before I begin, I want to emphasize that I make no claims as to the biological realism of any of the models under consideration, though I'm happy to try to work out results in more realistic models if they still seem like interesting puzzles.  <br/><br/>First, I showed that, in synthesizing a string <span style="font-style: italic;">x</span> via Scott's model of DNA rewrite rules, the substring-reversal rule can be eliminated at the cost of increasing by constant factors the number of steps and the size of intermediate strings.<br/><br/>Then, I showed that a factor-2 increase in steps allows one to hold the intermediate string to within a factor 2 of the final string length at all times.  This result, by constrast, holds whether one is trying to synthesize <span style="font-style: italic;">x</span> de novo or to transform some other string <span style="font-style: italic;">x'</span> into <span style="font-style: italic;">x</span> (although I only wrote up the first case, the other is essentially the same analysis).  In the process, I was especially pleased to introduce an analytical tool called 'garbage monsters'; Scott and I hope the terminology will catch on in mainstream biology.<br/><br/>The <a href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/andyd/dnacode.pdf">newest result</a> is the following: suppose you want to implement an error-correcting code <span style="font-style: italic;">x --&gt; C(x)</span> via DNA rewrite rules, where the choices of operations made can depend on <span style="font-style: italic;">x</span>; then unfortunately, something on the order of <span style="font-style: italic;">n/(lg n)</span> operations are needed in the encoding process to ensure that the code is actually robust.  A matching upper bound can be easily extracted from Scott's observations in his comments section, and it's a dispiriting bound because for that price, you could synthesize <span style="font-style: italic;">C(x)</span> without even manipulating the string <span style="font-style: italic;">x</span> that you're given! (A similar, simpler result holds for the decoding process, but I haven't written this up.)<br/><br/>For completeness, I'll reproduce my sketch proofs for the first two results below... but first let me note that monkeys <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/06/science/06tier.html?em&amp;ex=1194498000&amp;en=c15bbb924188a5d6&amp;ei=5087%0A">continue to make news</a> (thanks again, Chaya!).<br/><br/><br/><span style="font-weight: bold;">***First Result, Comment 21 on <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=287">Scott's post</a>***</span><br/><br/>"So how powerful is the reversal operation, really?<br/><br/>Suppose we can produce string x in k applications of operations (1)-(4). I claim we can do it in 4k + 1 operations, without reversals. (Of course, this will show that the Lempel-Ziv approach is also a constant-factor approximation in our setting.)<br/><br/>First, note that, if you can produce x in k steps with (1)-(4), you can also produce x^R, i.e. the reversal of x, in k steps with (1)-(4), by ‘flipping’ each operation.<br/><br/>Second, note that you can produce x.x^R, their concatenation, in 2k steps by running both productions in parallel, interleaving steps on the two halves. If the i’th step in the original production of x was s, then the 2i’th step in the new production will be s.s^R.<br/><br/>Now, in this ‘joint’ production we eliminate reversals as follows: say in the production of x, at the i’th stage we wish to move from<br/><br/>s = a.b.c to s’ = a.b^R.c …<br/><br/>well, in the joint production, at stage 2i we’ve got the string<br/><br/>a.b.c.c^R.b^R.a^R<br/><br/>By two copy and two deletion operations, we reach<br/><br/>a.b^R.c.c^R.b.a^R,<br/><br/>as needed to advance both sides’ progress.<br/><br/>Finally, when the joint production’s finished, delete the right-hand side to yield x. That’s 4k + 1 steps."<br/><br/><br/><span style="font-weight: bold;">***Second Result, Comments 30-31 on <a href="http://scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=287">Scott's post</a>***</span><br/><br/>"I believe I can show that, if we’re producing a string x of length n, we can keep the intermediate strings to length at most 2n, while incurring at most a factor-2 blowup in the number of steps used.<br/><br/>As Scott suggested to me in conversation, let’s keep track of which symbols in the intermediate workstring will and won’t make it into the final string x without deletion. If they won’t, call them ‘nonterminals’. (If a symbol will be replicated, and at least one of its descendants will be included in the final string, it’s not considered a nonterminal.)<br/><br/>First note that, if in a production of x there appears at some stage a block of consecutive nonterminals, we can modify the production so that they are treated as a ‘unit’ in subsequent steps, i.e. no string operation takes an endpoint that’s properly inside the block. They get shuffled around together and eventually destroyed together. The production’s length is not affected.<br/><br/>In a stage of such a production, for analysis purposes, we call a maximal block of nonterminals a ‘garbage monster’. Each time a new garbage monster is created (and many may be created by a single copy operation–even if there were no nonterminals in the original substring), we give it an unused, goofy monster name.<br/><br/>When string manipulations cause two garbage monsters to become adjacent, we combine them under one of their two names (and say that that one ‘eats’ the other one).<br/><br/>Key claim: in our modified type of production, at most one garbage monster gets eaten or destroyed at every step! Draw some pictures to see if you agree.<br/><br/>Now, with this fact in hand, we can modify the production again and argue it gives what we want.<br/>Here’s the strategy: given a production of x of the type we described, modify the production so that between each step, we stop and delete all garbage monsters, one deletion per monster.<br/><br/>This is a bit wasteful since some of these might’ve been eaten by other garbage monsters; but if our production had k steps to begin with, only at most k monsters got eaten total, and all garbage monsters must die somehow, so we only add at most k new steps.<br/><br/>Finally, observe that the string is culled to length at most n after every new round of ‘executions’, and since the workstring’s length is at most doubled by any string operation, its length is bounded by 2n throughout."</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/2103400202051567382/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/2103400202051567382/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=19908808&amp;postID=2103400202051567382">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/2103400202051567382/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-07T00:35:37Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-06T23:21:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Andy D</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-19908808</id>
      <author>
        <name>Andy D</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://andysresearch.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Andy's Math/CS page</title>
      <updated>2007-11-19T22:25:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-24557460.post-7598394102565279509</id>
    <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/2007/11/impagliazzo-hard-core-set-theorem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=24557460&amp;postID=7598394102565279509" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/7598394102565279509/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default/7598394102565279509" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/24557460/posts/default/7598394102565279509" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>The Impagliazzo Hard-Core-Set Theorem</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The <a href="http://www.cs.ucsd.edu/~russell/hardcore.ps">Impagliazzo hard-core set theorem</a> is one of the bits of magic of complexity theory. Say you have a function $g:\{ 0, 1 \}^n \rightarrow \{ 0,1\}$ such that every efficient algorithm makes errors at least $1%$ of the times when computing $g$ on a random input. (We'll think of $g$ as exhibiting a weak form of average-case complexity.) Clearly, different algorithms will fail on a different $1%$ of the inputs, and it seems that, intuitively, there should be functions for which no particular input is harder than any particular other input, per se. It's just that whenever you try to come up with an algorithm, some set of mistakes, dependent on the algorithmic technique, will arise. <br/><br/>As a good example, think of the process of generating $g$ at random, by deciding for every input $x$ to set $g(x)=1$ with probability $99%$ and $g(x)=0$ with probability $1%$. (Make the choices independently for different inputs.) With very high probability, every efficient algorithm fails with probability at least about $1%$, but, if we look at every efficiently recognizable large set $H$, we see that $g$ takes the value 1 on approximately $99%$ of the elements of $H$, and so the trivial algorithm that always outputs 1 has a pretty good success probability. <br/><br/>Consider, however, the set $H$ of size $\frac {2}{100} 2^n$ that you get by taking the $\approx \frac{1}{100} 2^n$ inputs $x$ such that $g(x)=0$ plus a random sample of $\frac{1}{100} 2^n$ inputs $x$ such that $g(x)=1$. Then we can see that no efficient algorithm can compute $g$ on much better than $50%$ of the inputs of $H$. This is the highest form of average-case complexity for a boolean function: on such a set $H$ no algorithm does much better in computing $g$ than an algorithm that makes a random guess.<br/><br/>The Impagliazzo hard-core theorem states that it is always possible to find such a set $H$ where the average-case hardness is "concentrated." Specifically, it states that if every efficient algorithm fails to compute $g$ on a $\geq \delta$ fraction of inputs, then there is a set $H$ of size $\geq \delta 2^n$ such that every efficient algorithm fails to compute $g$ on at least a $\frac 12 - \epsilon$ fraction of the elements of $H$. This is true for every $\epsilon,\delta$, and if "efficient" is quantified as "circuits of size $s$" in the premise, then "efficient" is quantified as "circuits of size $poly(\epsilon,\delta) \cdot s$" in the conclusion.<br/><br/>The example of the biased random function given above implies that, if one wants to prove the theorem for arbitrary $g$, then the set $H$ cannot be efficiently computable itself. (The example does not forbid, however, that $H$ be efficiently computable given oracle access to $g$, or that a random element of $H$ be samplable given a sampler for the distribution $(x,g(x))$ for uniform $x$.)<br/><br/>A number of proofs of the hard core theorem are known, and connections have been found with the process of <a href="http://www.cs.utexas.edu/~klivans/newhab3.ps"><i>boosting</i> in learning theory</a> and with the <a href="http://www.cs.berkeley.edu/~luca/pubs/xordecoding.ps">construction and the decoding of certain error-correcting codes</a>. Here is a precise statement.<br/><br/><blockquote><br/><b>Impagliazzo Hard-Core Set Theorem</b><br/>Let $g:\{0,1\}^n \rightarrow \{0,1\}$ be a boolean function, $s$ be a size parameter, $\epsilon,\delta&gt;0$ be given. Then there is a $c(\epsilon,\delta) = poly(1/\epsilon,1/\delta)$ such that the following happens.<br/><br/>Suppose that for every function $f:\{0,1\}^n \rightarrow \{0,1\}$ computable by a circuit of size $\leq c\cdot s$ we have <br/><br/>$Pr_{x \in \{0,1\}^n} [ f(x) = g(x) ] \leq 1-\delta$<br/><br/>Then there is a set $H$ of size $\geq \delta 2^n$ such that for every function $f$ computable by a circuit of size $\leq s$ we have<br/><br/>$Pr_{x\in H} [ f(x) = g(x) ] \leq \frac 12 + \epsilon$<br/></blockquote><br/><br/>Using the "finitary ergodic theoretic" approach of iterative partitioning, we (Omer Reingold, Madhur Tulsiani, Salil Vadhan and I) are able to prove the following variant.<br/><br/><blockquote><br/><b>Impagliazzo Hard-Core Set Theorem, "Constructive Version"</b><br/>Let $g:\{0,1\}^n \rightarrow \{0,1\}$ be a boolean function, $s$ be a size parameter, $\epsilon,\delta&gt;0$ be given. Then there is a $c(\epsilon,\delta) = exp(poly(1/\epsilon,1/\delta))$ such that the following happens.<br/><br/>Suppose that for every function $f:\{0,1\}^n \rightarrow \{0,1\}$ computable by a circuit of size $\leq c\cdot s$ we have<br/><br/>$Pr_{x \in \{0,1\}^n} [ f(x) = g(x) ] \leq 1-\delta$<br/><br/>Then there is a set $H$ such that: (i) $H$ is recognizable by circuits of size $\leq c\cdot s$; (ii) $|H| \geq \delta 2^n$, and in fact the number of $x$ in $H$ such that $g(x)=0$ is at least $\frac 12 \delta 2^n$, and so is the number of $x$ in $H$ such that $g(x)=1$; and (iii) for every $f$ computable by a circuit of size $\leq s$,<br/><br/>$Pr_{x\in H} [ g(x) = f(x) ] \leq max \{ Pr_{x\in H}[ g(x) = 0] , Pr_{x\in H} [g(x)=1] \} + \epsilon$<br/></blockquote><br/><br/>The difference is that $H$ is now an efficiently recognizable set (which is good), but we are not able to derive the same strong average-case complexity of $g$ in $H$ (which, as discussed as the beginning, is impossible in general). Instead of proving that a "random guess algorithm" is near-optimal on $H$, we prove that a "fixed answer algorithm" is near-optimal on $H$. That is, instead of saying that no algorithm can do better than a random guess, we say that no algorithm can do better than either always outputting 0 or always outputting 1. Note that this conclusion is meaningless if $g$ is, say, always equal to 1 on $H$, but in our construction we have that $g$ is not exceedingly biased on $H$, and if $\epsilon &lt; \delta/2$, say, then the conclusion is quite non-trivial.<br/><br/>One can also find a set $H'$ with the same type of average-case complexity as in the original Impagliazzo result by putting into $H'$ a $\frac 12 \delta 2^n$ size sample of elements $x$ of $H$ such that $g(x)=0$ and an equal size sample of elements of $H$ such that $g$ equals 1. (Alternatively, put in $H'$ all the elements of $H$ on which $g$ achieves the minority value of $g$ in $H$, then add a random sample of as many elements achieving the majority value.) Then we recover the original statement except that $c(\epsilon,\delta)$ is exponential instead of polynomial.<br/><br/>Coming up next, the proof of the "constructive hard core set theorem" and my attempt at explaining what the techniques have to do with "finitary ergodic theory."</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/7598394102565279509/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/7598394102565279509/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=24557460&amp;postID=7598394102565279509">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/7598394102565279509/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-06T21:50:25Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-06T21:45:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-24557460</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://in-theory.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>in theory</title>
      <updated>2007-11-21T20:31:22Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?p=579</id>
    <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?p=579" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The purpose of computing is insight, not numbers</title>
    <summary>The Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, in my opinion, has ruined more good scientists than any institution has created, judged by what they did before they came and judged by what they did after. Not that they weren’t good afterwards, but they were superb before they got there and were only good afterwards.

– Richard [...]
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
        </div>
      </span>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><blockquote><p>The Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, in my opinion, has ruined more good scientists than any institution has created, judged by what they did before they came and judged by what they did after. Not that they weren’t good afterwards, but they were superb before they got there and were only good afterwards.
</p><p>
– <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Hamming">Richard Hamming</a>. </p>
</blockquote>
<p>From <a href="http://www.cc.gatech.edu/~agray/hamming-on-research.pdf">here</a><a> - worth reading.</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-06T21:37:07Z</updated>
    <category term="Research"/>
    <author>
      <name>Sariel Har-Peled</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog</id>
      <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://valis.cs.uiuc.edu/blog/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Sariel's weblog</subtitle>
      <title>Vanity of Vanities, all is Vanity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T18:57:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-786333285568106173.post-2438490600907784895</id>
    <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/2007/11/cute-problem-wooden-convex-hull.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=786333285568106173&amp;postID=2438490600907784895" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/2438490600907784895/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default/2438490600907784895" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default/2438490600907784895" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Cute Problem: Wooden Convex Hull</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I didn't manage to keep an earlier promise to post olympiad-style problems... But here is a cute one.<br/><br/>You have <span style="font-style: italic;">n</span> trees at given coordinates in the plane. You want to build a polygonal fence around the trees. However, the only way to get wood for the fence is to cut down some trees in the first place! Let's say each tree gives you enough wood for <span style="font-style: italic;">M</span> meters of fence. The goal is to find the minimum <span style="font-style: italic;">k</span>, such that you can cut down some <span style="font-style: italic;">k</span> trees, and surround the rest by a fence of <span style="font-style: italic;">M</span>*<span style="font-style: italic;">k</span> meters.<br/><br/>What is the best algorithm you can find? Express your answer in terms on <span style="font-style: italic;">n</span> and <span style="font-style: italic;">k</span>.<br/><br/>As a bonus challenge, find a fast algorithm for the case when trees give you a different amount of wood <span style="font-style: italic;">M</span><sub>1</sub>, ..., <span style="font-style: italic;">M</span><sub style="font-style: italic;">i</sub>.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/2438490600907784895/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/2438490600907784895/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=786333285568106173&amp;postID=2438490600907784895">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/2438490600907784895/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-06T20:02:04Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-06T19:45:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>MiP</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-786333285568106173</id>
      <author>
        <name>MiP</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/WebdiariosDeMotocicleta" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>WebDiarios de Motocicleta</title>
      <updated>2007-11-19T07:48:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-786333285568106173.post-2313336436402789910</id>
    <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/2007/11/napkins.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=786333285568106173&amp;postID=2313336436402789910" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/2313336436402789910/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default/2313336436402789910" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default/2313336436402789910" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>Napkins</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inexhaustible <a href="http://www.cs.rutgers.edu/%7Emuthu/">Muthu</a> came up with the fantastic <a href="http://mysliceofpizza.blogspot.com/2007/11/formal-call-for-napkin-notes-and-other.html">idea</a> of assembling napkins used for research-related work. This could turn out to be very interesting.<br/><br/>Here is my own contribution: a Starbucks napkin filled during a 2 hour caffeinated discussion with <a href="http://www.mit.edu/%7Eandoni/">Alex</a>. It contains the proof of a communication-complexity lower bound for near-neighbor search in L<sub>∞</sub>, matching the <a href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/indyk/li3.ps">current upper bound</a> of <a href="http://people.csail.mit.edu/indyk/">Piotr</a> from FOCS'98. We were working on this problem during our summer internship at IBM Almaden (yes, yes, we're officemates but we had to go to California to write a paper together).  As you might expect, the fact that we're now trying to finish the details has some correlation with the <a href="http://research.microsoft.com/research/sv/STOC08/stoc2008-cfp.htm">Nov 19</a> fireworks party :)<br/><br/><a href="http://bp3.blogger.com/_u9iBO1Zjoks/Ry_EEbftlQI/AAAAAAAAAFA/I4TJcza4erY/s1600-h/Scan001.JPG"><img alt="" border="0" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5129534080977573122" src="http://bp3.blogger.com/_u9iBO1Zjoks/Ry_EEbftlQI/AAAAAAAAAFA/I4TJcza4erY/s400/Scan001.JPG" style="margin: 0px auto 10px; display: block; text-align: center; cursor: pointer; width: 399px; height: 485px;"/></a></div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/2313336436402789910/comments/default"/>
          <a href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/2313336436402789910/comments/default">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=786333285568106173&amp;postID=2313336436402789910">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/2313336436402789910/comments/default"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-06T01:50:13Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-05T21:20:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>MiP</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-786333285568106173</id>
      <author>
        <name>MiP</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/786333285568106173/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25&amp;redirect=false" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://infoweekly.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/WebdiariosDeMotocicleta" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>WebDiarios de Motocicleta</title>
      <updated>2007-11-19T07:48:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7923404146102863031</id>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/2007/11/it-was-stupid-question-or.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=7923404146102863031" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7923404146102863031" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7923404146102863031" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title>It was a stupid question!!!!!!!!!! or...</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On my last blog I asked the following:
TRUE OR FALSE:

<blockquote>
For every coloring of R (the reals) with a countable number of colors
there exists x,y,z,w of the same color such that
x+y=z+w.
</blockquote>

<br/>
<br/>

And I pointed out that when I asked this in seminar I got
5 thought it was TRUE,
4 thought it was FALSE,
5 thought it was a STUPID QUESTION.

<br/>
<br/>

The answer is: ITS A STUPID QUESTION.
More rigorously the following is true and was proven by Erdos:

<blockquote>
The statment above is true iff the Continuum Hypothesis is false.
(See
<a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/radozfc.pdf"> this (pdf)</a>
or
<a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/radozfc.ps"> this (ps)</a>.
for an exposition of the proof.
</blockquote>

<br/>
<br/>

SO, what to make of this?
This is a <b>natural</b> question that is ind of  ZFC.
How Natural is it? Erdos worked on it, not some logician
looking around for a problem to be ind of ZFC.

<br/>
<br/>

Does this make us think CH is true or false?
Actually, more is known:
<blockquote>
Let L(x<sub>1</sub>,..., x<sub>n</sub>) be a linear form over
the reals (but not x<sub>1</sub>-x<sub>2</sub>).
If CH is true then there is a coloring of the
reals with a countable number of colors such that
there is no
e<sub>1</sub>,..., e<sub>n</sub> which are all the same
color such that
L(e<sub>1</sub>,..., e<sub>n</sub>)=0.
(Exposition of proof in same document linked to above.)
</blockquote>

If CH is true then the entire theory of countable colorings
and linear forms is known. And boring.
If CH is false then much more interesting things happen.
Jacob Fox proved the following:

<br/>
<br/>

Let STAT(s) be the statement

<blockquote>
For every coloring of R with a countable number of colors
there exists x<sub>1</sub>, x<sub>2</sub>, ..., x<sub>{s+3}</sub> such that

they are all the same color, and

x<sub>1</sub> + sx<sub>2</sub> = x<sub>3</sub> + x<sub>4</sub> + ... + x<sub>{s+3}</sub>
</blockquote>

THEN

STAT(s) is true iff 2<sup>ℵ<sub>0</sub></sup> &gt; ℵ<sub>s</sub>

<br/>
<br/>

Jacob Fox is also (judging from his resume) not a logician.
He is a combinatorist. Actually he's a graduate student
so it may be too early to say what he <i>is</i>.

<br/>
<br/>To determine CH should we use its consequences as
reasons for or against assuming it? Even if we do,
do you want the entire theory to be known and boring?
I ask this non-rhetorically.
See <a href="http://www.math.rutgers.edu/~zeilberg/Opinion68.html">Opinion 68
of Zeilberg's blog</a> or
The papers of Penelope Maddy:
<a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/belaxioms1.pdf">believing the
axioms I</a>.
and
<a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/belaxioms2.pdf">believing the
axioms II</a>.</div>
      <span>
        <div class="commentbar">
          <p/>
          <div class="commentbutton" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
          <a href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml">
            <img src="/images/feed-icon.png"/>Subscribe to comments
          </a>  | 
          <a href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=3722233&amp;postID=7923404146102863031">
            <img src="/images/post-icon.png"/>Post a comment
          </a>
        </div>
        <div class="commentarea" href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml"/>
      </span>
    </content>
    <updated>2007-11-05T19:48:20Z</updated>
    <published>2007-11-05T19:38:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <author>
        <name>Lance</name>
      </author>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://weblog.fortnow.com/rss.xml" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2007-11-20T17:03:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
