<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2019-12-27T10:21:32Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16497</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/26/a-math-gift-for-all/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Math Gift For All</title>
    <summary>Happy holidays to all. Kathryn Farley is my dear wife. We just celebrated Christmas together and then went off to London for a holiday. Today I thought I would share a gift with you. Kathryn and I exchange books for the holiday. We do not wrap them—our tradition, which she started years ago. I like […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Happy holidays to all.</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/kathrynart.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-16499" height="300" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/kathrynart.jpg?w=158&amp;h=300" width="158"/></a></p>
<p>
Kathryn Farley is my dear wife. We just celebrated Christmas together and then went off to London for a holiday.</p>
<p>
Today I thought I would share a gift with you.</p>
<p>
Kathryn and I exchange books for the holiday. We do not wrap them—our tradition, which she started years ago. I like doing this. Ken’s family re-uses wrapping paper year-to-year. I am pleased to see that there is a call to save wrapping on three <a href="https://frugalkite.com/zero-waste-christmas-three-genius-wrapping-methods/">gifts</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> If every American family wrapped just 3 presents in reused materials, it would save enough paper to cover 45,000 football fields. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Kathryn gave me a wonderful collection of books. One of them is not the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Computers-Rigidity-Moduli-Large-Scale-Riemannian/dp/B01FJ1E910">book</a>: <i>Computers, Rigidity, and Moduli: The Large-Scale Fractal Geometry of Riemannian Moduli Space</i>. The author is Shmuel Weinberger a mathematician from the University of Chicago. I already had his book but finally took a look at it while browsing my other gifts. So it is a delayed gift, from a Christmas past.</p>
<p>
The book is a combination of computer results, basic math results, and advanced math results. The last are a variety of topics that are well outside of my zone. I did like the book. Weinberger is a terrific writer, a terrific explainer, a gifted selector of topics. I was surprised to see that his book contained a puzzle that I had not thought about before. The puzzle is, like all good puzzles, easy to state—but hard to solve. At least for me. I did not see how to solve it. I hope you like it.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> A Puzzle </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Imagine that there are <img alt="{2n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2n}"/> distinct points in the plane. No three points are collinear. Half of them, <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> are labeled <font color="red"><b>red</b></font> and the other half are labelled <font color="green"><b>green</b></font>. Festive colors. Your job is to connect each red point with a unique green point by a straight line. That is easy, of course. But we hate when lines cross. So your job is more: Please select the lines so that the fewest ones cross.</p>
<p>
Thus the problem is. Find the fewest line crossings possible. As usual we wish to know the answer as a function of <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>. Is it <img alt="{\sqrt{n}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7Bn%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{n}}"/>? Or <img alt="{\log(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log(n)}"/>? What is the best possible in the worst case?</p>
<p>
The artwork on the wall behind Kathryn suggests a possible arrangement, likewise the floor. The art object directly behind her is in 3D space which is not allowed—but this is a photograph so its points are projected onto a plane anyway. Again, it’s important that no three points are collinear. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> There is a Best </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
For start we note that there is always a best. Each of <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> red points can match one of <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> green points. So there are only a finite number of possible matchings, namely 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  n! = n \times (n-1) \times \cdots \times 1. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++n%21+%3D+n+%5Ctimes+%28n-1%29+%5Ctimes+%5Ccdots+%5Ctimes+1.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  n! = n \times (n-1) \times \cdots \times 1. "/></p>
<p>This shows that there is always a best answer; moreover, it can be found. But <img alt="{n!}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%21%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n!}"/> can be huge, so another part of the question is: Can you find the best answer fast? How about finding the best answer in polynomial time?</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> A Solution </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The best answer is that the number of crossings is always at most 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  b(n) = c \log(n), " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++b%28n%29+%3D+c+%5Clog%28n%29%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  b(n) = c \log(n), "/></p>
<p>where <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/> is the constant 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  10^{2}+11^{2}+12^{2}- 13^{2} - 14^{2}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++10%5E%7B2%7D%2B11%5E%7B2%7D%2B12%5E%7B2%7D-+13%5E%7B2%7D+-+14%5E%7B2%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  10^{2}+11^{2}+12^{2}- 13^{2} - 14^{2}. "/></p>
<p>
Here is a proof that this bound is correct. Suppose that you have selected the fewest number of line crossings. We will argue that there are at most <img alt="{b(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b(n)}"/> line crossings. The plan is to show that we can descend—that is given a matching we can try and decrease the number of lines that cross. </p>
<p>
Given any two red nodes and any two green nodes, we can define the operation <em>swap</em> by having them exchange partners. If their lines cross before the swap, then after the swap the lines will <em>not</em> cross. The following figure shows this:</p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/points.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-16500" height="217" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/points.png?w=300&amp;h=217" width="300"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
Oops. I thought the idea was to define an operation so that the number of line crossing could always be decreased. Wait the argument does not work. In the above figure the switch <em>increases</em> the number of crossings.</p>
<p>
There is a saving trick, however. Do not attempt to decrease the number of lines that cross. Instead decrease the total <i>length</i> of the lines selected. The above figure can be turned into a proof of a lemma that a <em>swap</em> of two crossing lines always decreases the sum of their lengths. The cool idea is that the swaps may actually increase the number of crossings, but they will always decrease the total length. </p>
<p>
In the end the length is minimal and there are <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0}"/> crossings. Thus 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  b(n) = 0. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++b%28n%29+%3D+0.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  b(n) = 0. "/></p>
<p>I cheated and used that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  10^{2}+11^{2}+12^{2} = 13^{2} + 14^{2}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++10%5E%7B2%7D%2B11%5E%7B2%7D%2B12%5E%7B2%7D+%3D+13%5E%7B2%7D+%2B+14%5E%7B2%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  10^{2}+11^{2}+12^{2} = 13^{2} + 14^{2}, "/></p>
<p>and so the constant <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/> is zero. Finally, no swap is ever undone—since the length always decreases—and so the process must finish within <img alt="{O(n^2)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E2%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n^2)}"/> swaps.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Hope that you liked this puzzle. I think it shows that are sometimes methods that while simple may be hard to find. Is <img alt="{O(n^2)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E2%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n^2)}"/> really the needed number of swaps? Are more than a linear number of swaps ever required?<br/>
 Happy holidays to all.</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-27T04:04:37Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-27T04:04:37Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="trick"/>
    <category term="Christmas"/>
    <category term="complexity"/>
    <category term="Kathryn Farley"/>
    <category term="puzzle"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=18835</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/27/the-google-quantum-supremacy-demo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Google Quantum Supremacy Demo and the Jerusalem HQCA debate.</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Below are 10 annotated slides from a spontaneous informal talk that I gave at the school on mathematics of quantum computing a weak ago. (Power point presentation.) Later in the afternoon we had  a panel/debate on quantum supremacy (clique for … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/27/the-google-quantum-supremacy-demo/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Below are 10 annotated slides from a spontaneous informal talk that I gave at the <a href="http://ias.huji.ac.il/SchoolCSE4">school on mathematics of quantum computing</a> a weak ago. (<a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-demo-blog.pptx">Power point presentation</a>.) Later in the afternoon we had  <strong>a panel/debate on quantum supremacy </strong>(<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H4t2G2gay7Q&amp;feature=youtu.be">clique for the video</a>) moderated by Sandy Irani and featuring Scott Aaronson, Dorit Aharonov, Boaz Barak, Sergio Boixo, Adam Bouland,  Umesh Vazirani, and me. It was a thoughtful and interesting discussion. (The presentation was initially prepared for the afternoon debate but at the end I gave it as a separate talk and presented just one slide at the panel itself. The plan was also to post it as a background material before the discussion, but not untypically, I was too slow, so here it is a week later.) I am thankful to Dorit for inviting me to the panel (and for organizing a great school!), to Sandy for her excellent moderation, and to all the panelists for their good spirit.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><strong>My assessment continues to be that both the Google supremacy claims and their other central claim about fidelity estimation are incorrect.</strong></span></p>
<p>(Dec 23, 2019: Following some <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450">renewed discussion</a> in the last days on the terminology I proposed to replace the term “quantum supremacy” with <strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">“HQCA – Huge Quantum Computational Advantage”</span></strong> and I myself may try to follow my new term in my own lectures/papers in the future and see how it goes. In fact, I already used HQCA in our Sunday’s Kazhdan seminar where I lectured about noise stability and sensitivity for Boolean functions, Boson Sampling, and quantum circuits (<a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/d7a1d7a8d799d7a7d7940006.pdf">lecture</a> <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/d7a1d7a8d799d7a7d7940007.pdf">notes</a>).)</p>
<h2>My Presentation on the Google Quantum Supremacy Demonstration</h2>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> you may click on a slide to see it in full screen.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide1.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18836" height="365" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide1.png?w=640&amp;h=365" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>My lecture is not about quantum computers and quantum supremacy in general but about the Google quantum supremacy claims. (If you want to know more about my general argument against quantum computers, quantum supremacy and quantum error correction go to the previous post <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/11/13/gils-collegial-quantum-supremacy-skepticism-faq/" rel="bookmark">Gil’s Collegial Quantum Supremacy Skepticism FAQ </a>and to <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/09/main-pr.pdf">several</a> of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02499">my</a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.02499">papers</a> and <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/09/cern.pptx">presentations</a> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oR-ufBz13Eg">linked</a> there.)</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide12.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18875" height="362" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide12.png?w=640&amp;h=362" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>In this presentation I will concentrate on aspects of the Google experiment that are “too good to be true”. (Which is a bad sign, not a good sign.)</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide13.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18874" height="350" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide13.png?w=640&amp;h=350" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>There is an amazing agreement between the fidelity as estimated from the experimental data and a very simple high-school model based on the probability of individual qubits and gates to malfunction.  (An even simplified version, below in purple, requires just three parameters – the number n of qubits, the number g1 of 1-qubit gates and the number g2 of 2-qubit gates.)</p>
<p>Formula (77) itself is not surprising but the terrific success of Formula (77) may serve as a smoking gun for the claim that the Google’s experiment has serious methodological problems.</p>
<p>I was not the only one to be amazed. Here is what John Martinis, the scientific leader of the Google supremacy experiment told about it. (Nov 1., 2019) Read carefully!</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide6.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18849" height="400" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide6.png?w=640&amp;h=400" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>The accuracy of Formula (77) is the most amazing thing about the data, something that came as a big surprise, and that (jokingly) will let quantum scientists keep their jobs.</p>
<p>And here is what I think</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide7.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18851" height="367" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide7.png?w=640&amp;h=367" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>No no, you cannot estimate with precision of 10-20% the probability of failure of a physical system with 1000 interacting elements as the product of 1000 error-probabilities.</p>
<p><strong>This remarkable agreement is a major new discovery, and it is <em>not needed</em> for building quantum computers. It is only needed for the extrapolation argument leading the Google team to supremacy.</strong></p>
<p>Even if quantum computers will be built this is something that we are not going to witness. It is interesting to check if we see anything remotely like this for the IBM quantum computers.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide8.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18853" height="334" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide8.png?w=640&amp;h=334" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>Here on the left you see for various values of <em>n</em>, the number of qubits, two experiments with different circuits that leads to entirely different probability distributions. Since each pair have a similar number of gates, Formula (77) leads to very close fidelity estimates which are so accurate that the green and blue lines coincide! We do not expect to see such close agreements in experimental data.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide9.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18857" height="350" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide9.png?w=640&amp;h=350" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>Blue, orange and green analytic smooth curves representing three distributions. For all three you see also empirical samples from the distributions. For two of them the samples are perfect, for the other one you see a sample based on a complicated physical experiment.</p>
<p><strong>Test your intuition:</strong> can you tell the difference? Can you tell which is which?</p>
<p>(You can also test your intuition which was the single slide presented at the afternoon debate.)</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide10.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18860" height="360" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide10.png?w=640&amp;h=360" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><strong>Blind tests</strong> are standard in scientific experiments and are quite easy to implement here.</p>
<p>The meaning of the surprising statistical success of Formula (77) should be <strong>carefully examined</strong>.</p>
<h2>Two extra slides</h2>
<p>To put my view in context,  I devote one slide for my general argument against quantum computers, quantum supremacy and quantum error correction.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide2.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18839" height="363" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide2.png?w=640&amp;h=363" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>I mentioned that most experts do not agree with my argument or do not even understand it, and for some of them, this may give reasons for skepticism also about my critique on the Google experiment. I  personally think that my general argument is good, but  I don’t think it is ironclad and I am pleased to see this matter explored experimentally (properly). I also think that my critique on the Google demo stands well on its own.</p>
<p>And what may convince me to change my mind? poetry!</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/dslide16.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19013" height="362" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/dslide16.png?w=640&amp;h=362" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>Let me add that all my critique as described here and elsewhere was first presented to the Google team.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/d3.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19012" height="281" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/d3.png?w=640&amp;h=281" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">From left to right (in reality from right to left): Sandy Irani, me, Boaz Barak, Adam Bouland, Dorit Aharonov (covered but can be seen in the small picture), and on the right Umesh Vazirani, Scott Aaronson, and Sergio Boixo. (More pictures – below.)</span></p>
<p><span id="more-18835"/></p>
<p><strong>Answer to Test your intuition:</strong> The orange graph is the one that comes from the experiments.</p>
<h2>Some recollections, reactions, and comments from the debate:</h2>
<h3>Uploading data for verification</h3>
<p>At the beginning of the debate, I nudged Sergio to upload some (additional; promised) data that is needed for verification and analysis of their results.</p>
<h3>Formula (77)</h3>
<p>Formula (77) was discussed in some details in Q/A of the the informal talk and also in the panel/debate. (I raised the question if the Google experiment is correct and specifically the issue with Formula (77) at <a href="https://youtu.be/H4t2G2gay7Q?t=2097">35:00</a> and Formula (77) was discussed for the next 25 minutes.) Of course, the surprising issue is the accurate predictions that Formula (77) gives.</p>
<p>Sergio briefly explained the statistical rationale for such a precision. The way I see it, the quality of the prediction for (77) requires two assumptions: (1) No systematic errors, (2) statistical independence. Both these assumptions seem utterly unrealistic. No systematic errors means that the average error estimation say for read-out errors or for gate errors are precise and fluctuations are symmetric. This is very unrealistic. The assumption of statistical independence also seems unrealistic. (Positive correlations will actually lead to better fidelity.)  Dorit, Boaz and several other people (and also Peter Shor earlier <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/11/13/gils-collegial-quantum-supremacy-skepticism-faq/#comment-61697">here on the blog</a>) proposed that the remarkable predictive power of (77) and, in particular, the required statistical independence may follow from having a random circuit. I don’t understand that.</p>
<p>Beside the concrete attempts to understand the predictive power of Formula (77) there were some general comments about it. Adam opined that <em>in physics</em> the data fits the models very well. Scott  joked that here I am arguing that the results fits the model too well and he could imagine me arguing in another universe that the results don’t fit the model well enough. At another point he said “First the data is not good enough, and now the data is too good, what will make you happy, Gil” and I answered that the data should be <em>reliable.</em></p>
<h3>The extended Church-Turing thesis (ECTT)</h3>
<p>Does “supremacy” (or HQCA), in general and in the context of Google’s experiment violates the extended Church-Turing thesis? Dorit claimed that the answer is negative since (roughly) the experiments cannot be scaled. Sergio sort of agreed and said they only claim to <em>challenge</em> the ECCT. (Indeed the fidelity goes exponentially to zero and even if producing such samples is beyond the power of a classical computer the sample sizes need to be exponential; it is an interesting question if every scalable supremacy demonstration requires quantum fault tolerance.)  A point that I made is that if we assume further certain “naturalness” principle, namely that, in practice,  constants in computational complexity asymptotic behavior are mild, then an astronomical speed-up as claimed by Google, can be considered as violating ECCT.</p>
<h3>Trillions</h3>
<p>Actually, in the early lecture I presented another slide about my initial feeling towards the Google (then licked) paper. I was surprised by the trillions-time speed up, and regarded the 300,000,000,000 speed-up as expressing some “supremacy fever:” why not start with a more modest speed-up but with convincing direct evidence?</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide3.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-18841" height="170" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/google-slide3.png?w=300&amp;h=170" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>Why the trillions speed up should not surprise us? Adam Bouland commented that this is to be expected when we think about exponential speed-up. BTW, Adam gave very nice lectures on quantum algorithms and quantum supremacy.</p>
<h3>Miscellaneous</h3>
<ol>
<li>I was slowly loosing my voice so in the earlier lecture Or Sattath read the quote from Martinis, and Adam read the poem by Renan. (I should try that also in talks where I am not loosing my voice.)</li>
<li> Sandy asked about other reasons for skepticism regarding the Google claims and Scott mentioned the possibility that much better classical algorithms will be found.</li>
<li>Both me and Scott (and perhaps others in the panel as well) emphasized the importance of replications.</li>
<li>Adam was Scott’s Ph. D student and Scott was Umesh’s Ph. D. student so we had on the panel three academic generations!</li>
<li>Toward the end Scott described briefly the decade-old history, theory+experiment, of quantum supremacy.</li>
<li>There were various other interesting issues that were raised.</li>
<li>For history: The video flipped left and right. In reality Sandy was right farthermost and I was second to the right.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Quantum error-correction</h3>
<p>Dorit asked about quantum error correction and I asked specifically about distance-3 surface code and Sergio said that the quality of gates is insufficient for that. If I understood correctly the error rate needs to be reduced by a factor of five. (The fact that good quality quantum error correction requires achieving lower error rate than what is required for quantum supremacy is an important ingredient of my general argument against quantum computers.)</p>
<h3>Noise models and the noisy data.</h3>
<p>Dorit and others raised the issue of the noise model and discussed some toy noise models.  There was some discussion on correlated errors. (This is unrelated to the statistical dependence of (77).) I pointed out that correlated errors are irrelevant to random circuits (but relevant to quantum error-correction). Later in the debate I mentioned the concern regarding not having large enough samples to determine the empirical noisy distribution.</p>
<p>At some point Umesh referred to another issue that I raised which is that the noisy model in the Google paper seems oversimplified. I came back to it briefly but we did not discuss this further. (At the Q/A part of my early lecture Boaz have made some interesting comments about identifying the effect of the errors in the last round of the computation.)</p>
<p>I also repeated my suggestion of “Beckner noise” (and correlated variants) as a good toy noise model for noisy quantum circuits.</p>
<h3>My argument against quantum computers</h3>
<p>At the panel I mentioned my general argument against quantum computers, quantum supremacy and quantum error correction only in a few sentences.</p>
<p>BTW, one way to think about the argument is as comparing four thresholds for the level of noise (on gates) <img alt="\rho_{\bf R}, \rho_{\bf S}, \rho_{\bf QEC}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+R%7D%2C+%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+S%7D%2C+%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+QEC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf R}, \rho_{\bf S}, \rho_{\bf QEC}"/> and <img alt="\rho_{\bf U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+U%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf U}"/>. <img alt="\rho_{\bf S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+S%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf S}"/> is what is required for <strong>HQCA</strong> (quantum supremacy); <img alt="\rho_{\bf QEC}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+QEC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf QEC}"/> is what is required for good quality quantum error correction (say, distance-5 surface code); <img alt="\rho_{\bf U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+U%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf U}"/> is what is required for universal quantum computing; <img alt="\rho_{\bf R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+R%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf R}"/> is the lower error rate that can realistically be achieved. I have a computational complexity argument (based on naturalness) that <img alt="\rho_{\bf R} &gt; \rho_{\bf S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+R%7D+%3E+%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+S%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf R} &gt; \rho_{\bf S}"/>. I also rely on <img alt="\rho_{\bf S} &gt; \rho_{\bf QEC}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+S%7D+%3E+%5Crho_%7B%5Cbf+QEC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0" title="\rho_{\bf S} &gt; \rho_{\bf QEC}"/>.</p>
<h3>Comparisons to Wright brothers’s first flight or to Fermi’s 1942 nuclear chain reaction</h3>
<p>Nobody in the afternoon panel discussion (to the best of my memory) repeated earlier enthusiastic comparisons between Google’s experiment and the first flight in 1903, the first landing on the moon in 1968 (well, I referred to that), Fermi’s 1942 nuclear chain reaction, the first vacuum tubes computers, the discovery of the Higgs boson, etc. etc.</p>
<h3>Silver lining (after-thought)</h3>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/silverlining.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-19048" height="192" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/silverlining.png?w=300&amp;h=192" width="300"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The beach of Tel Aviv</span></p>
<p>Major advances in human ability to simulate quantum physics and quantum chemistry are expected both if quantum supremacy can be demonstrated and quantum computers can be built and also if quantum supremacy cannot be demonstrated and quantum computers cannot be built.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Debate picture collage</span></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/panel-gallery.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-19042" height="371" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/panel-gallery.png?w=640&amp;h=371" width="640"/></a></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/panel-umesh.png"> </a></p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/daud3.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-19070" height="163" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/daud3.png?w=300&amp;h=163" width="300"/></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">The audience was happy</span></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-26T22:04:52Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-26T22:04:52Z</published>
    <category term="Controversies and debates"/>
    <category term="Quantum"/>
    <category term="Adam Bouland"/>
    <category term="Boaz Barak"/>
    <category term="Dorit Aharonov"/>
    <category term="Google"/>
    <category term="HQCA"/>
    <category term="Huge Quantum Computational Advantage"/>
    <category term="quantum supremacy"/>
    <category term="Sandy Irani"/>
    <category term="Scott Aaronson"/>
    <category term="Sergio Boixo"/>
    <category term="Umesh Vazirani"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/25/postdoctoral-research-associate-at-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-theory-of-distributed-systems-group-nancy-lynch-apply-by-february-28-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/25/postdoctoral-research-associate-at-massachusetts-institute-of-technology-theory-of-distributed-systems-group-nancy-lynch-apply-by-february-28-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral Research Associate at Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Theory of Distributed Systems Group, Nancy Lynch (apply by February 28, 2019)</title>
    <summary>Area: “Distributed Algorithms for Dynamic, Noisy Platforms: Wireless Networks, Robot Swarms, and Insect Colonies”. Candidates should have research experience with algorithms for at least one of these topics, preferably with noise and change. Strong background in probabilistic modeling/analysis is essential. Work will also involve simulation, and coordination with experimental researchers. Website: https://groups.csail.mit.edu/tds/reflist.html Email: lynch@csail.mit.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Area: “Distributed Algorithms for Dynamic, Noisy Platforms: Wireless Networks, Robot Swarms, and Insect Colonies”.</p>
<p>Candidates should have research experience with algorithms for at least one of these topics, preferably with noise and change. Strong background in probabilistic modeling/analysis is essential. Work will also involve simulation, and coordination with experimental researchers.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://groups.csail.mit.edu/tds/reflist.html">https://groups.csail.mit.edu/tds/reflist.html</a><br/>
Email: lynch@csail.mit.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-25T12:37:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-25T12:37:19Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=18930</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/24/numberphile-graph-theory-videos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Four Great Numberphile Graph Theory Videos</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A quick link to our previous post: Gil Bor, Luis Hernández-Lamoneda, Valentín Jiménez-Desantiago, and Luis Montejano-Peimbert: On the isometric conjecture of Banach.   We have mentioned the Numberphile video channel before (here, and here, and here). It has amazing videos for … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/24/numberphile-graph-theory-videos/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A quick link to our previous post: <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/23/gil-bor-luis-hernandez-lamoneda-valentin-jimenez-desantiago-and-luis-montejano-peimbert-on-the-isometric-conjecture-of-banach/" rel="bookmark">Gil Bor, Luis Hernández-Lamoneda, Valentín Jiménez-Desantiago, and Luis Montejano-Peimbert: On the isometric conjecture of Banach</a>.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>We have mentioned the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCoxcjq-8xIDTYp3uz647V5A">Numberphile video channel</a> before (<a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/01/an-interview-with-noga-alon/">here</a>, and <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/03/09/8866128975287528%c2%b3-8778405442862239%c2%b3-2736111468807040%c2%b3/">here</a>, and <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2018/06/20/beyond-the-g-conjecture-algebraic-combinatorics-of-cellular-spaces-i/">here</a>). It has amazing videos for the very general public about mathematics. And the general public is interested! The channel has more than 3 millions subscribers and a Numberphile video gets usually well over 100,000 views.  While the videos are for very general audiences it is quite common that I learn new mathematics while watching these videos. Today I mention four recent Numberphile videos on graph theory.</p>
<p>Before that, let me mention that, while combinatorics has a special appeal for general audiences, it is a hard challenge to explain to a very large audience (or even to the large audience of Quanta Magazine) some very abstract areas of mathematics. It is not impossible: Here is <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/with-category-theory-mathematics-escapes-from-equality-20191010/">Kevin Hartnett’s article</a> in Quanta Magazine on ∞-categories and Jacob Lurie’s work and here is a <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/peter-scholze-and-the-future-of-arithmetic-geometry-20160628/">2016 article by Erica Klarreich</a> on perfectoid spaces and Peter Schotze’s work. I hope to see Numberphile moving into these areas as well.</p>
<h2>A breakthrough in Graph theory:  Yaroslav Shitov’s counterexample to Hedetniemi’s conjecture as told by Erica Klarreich.</h2>
<p/>
<p>For more on this development see<a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/05/10/sansation-in-the-morning-news-yaroslav-shitov-counterexamples-to-hedetniemis-conjecture/"> this post</a>. The video contains nice pictures of Stephen Hedetniemi and his 1966 thesis. An exciting <strong>open question</strong> is: Given two graphs of chromatic number <em>n </em>is the chromatic number of their tensor product at least some <em>f(n)</em>, where <em>f(n)</em> tends to infinity with <em>n</em>.</p>
<h2>Maria Chudnovsky – perfect graphs</h2>
<p/>
<p>Starting with the definition and ending with the strong perfect graph theorem (conjectured by Claud Berge) by Chudnovsky, Seymour, Robertson and Thomas.</p>
<p>An exciting <strong>open question</strong>: Find a good definition for perfect <em>r</em>-uniform hypergraphs.</p>
<p>We discussed perfect graphs and related notions in <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/10/13/gerard-cornuejolss-bakers-eighteen-5000-dollars-conjectures/">this post</a>, <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/02/05/extremal-combinatorics-v-posets/">this one</a> and <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2014/12/19/when-a-few-colors-suffice/">this one</a>.</p>
<p>(<strong>Remark:</strong> Numberphile misguidedly regarded this video as a continuation of the “planar graph” video. The truth of the matter is that these are separated topics and the perfect graph video should be a separate Numperphile video.)</p>
<h2>Maria Chudnovsky – planar graphs</h2>
<p/>
<p>Planar graphs are deep and fascinating (and miraculous, and always surprising) mathematical objects.  In Hebrew we can say about the topic that it is “Olam Umelo’o” (עולם ומלואו) (=a whole world with all its content). There are many fascinating properties of planar graphs and many open problems about them.</p>
<p>There are also many fascinating generalizations. Let me mention <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2014/12/06/coloring-simple-polytopes-and-triangulations/">Abby Thompson’s </a><strong>problem:</strong> Suppose that <em>G</em> is the graph of a simple <em>d</em>-polytope with <em>n</em> vertices. Suppose also that <em>n</em> is even (this is automatic if <em>d</em> is odd). Can we always properly color the edges of <em>G</em> with <em>d</em> colors? (For <em>d=3</em>, the answer is yes and this is the four color theorem.)</p>
<p>(We discussed planar graphs here and on MO, many times.)</p>
<h2>Discussing vertex covers and Alcuin numbers for graphs – and a famous old puzzle. Filmed at MSRI with Annie Raymond.</h2>
<p/>
<p>We <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2018/01/21/hardness-of-approximating-vertex-cover-polytope-integrality-gap-the-alswede-kachaterian-theorem-and-more/">discussed here</a> and in other posts the important notion of vertex covers, but the mathematics of the video was completely new to me.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-24T10:32:12Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-24T10:32:12Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Abby Thompson"/>
    <category term="Annie Raymond"/>
    <category term="Erica Klarreich"/>
    <category term="Maria Chudnovsky"/>
    <category term="Numberphile"/>
    <category term="Yaroslav Shitov"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4476</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4476" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4476#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4476" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">NIPS vs. NeurIPS: guest post by Steven Pinker</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Scott’s Update (Dec. 26): Comments on this post are now closed, since I felt that whatever progress could be made, had been, and I wanted to move on to more interesting topics. Thanks so much to everyone who came here to hash things out in good faith—which, as far as I’m concerned, included the majority […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><strong>Scott’s Update (Dec. 26):</strong> Comments on this post are now closed, since I felt that whatever progress could be made, had been, and I wanted to move on to more interesting topics.  Thanks so much to everyone who came here to hash things out in good faith—which, as far as I’m concerned, included the majority of the participants on both sides.</p>



<p>If you want to see the position paper that led to the name change movement, see <a href="http://tensorlab.cms.caltech.edu/users/anima/pubs/NIPS_Name_Debate.pdf">What’s In A Name? The Need to Nip NIPS</a>, by Daniela Witten, Elana Fertig, Anima Anandkumar, and Jeff Dean.  I apologize for not linking to this paper in the original post.</p>



<p>To recap what I said many times in this post and the comments: I myself am totally fine with the name NeurIPS.  I think several of the arguments for changing the name were good arguments—and I thank some of the commenters on this post for elucidating those arguments without shaming anybody or calling them names.</p>



<p>The one part that I’m against is <em>the bullying of anyone who disagrees by smearing them as a misogynist</em>.  And then, recursively, the smearing as a misogynist of anyone who objected to <em>that</em> bullying, and so on and so on.  Most supporters of the name change did not engage in such bullying, but one leader of the movement very conspicuously did, and continues to do it even now (to, I’m told, the consternation even of many of her allies).</p>



<p>Since this post went up, something extremely interesting happened: Steven Pinker and I started getting emails from researchers in the NeurIPS community that said, in various words: “thank you for openly airing perspectives that we could not air, without jeopardizing our careers.”  We were told that even women in ML, and even those who agreed with the activists on most points, could no longer voice opposition without risking their hiring or tenure.  This put into a slightly different light, I thought, the constant claims of certain movement leaders about their own marginalization and powerlessness.</p>



<p>Since I was 7 or 8 years old, the moral lodestar of my life has been my yearning (too often left unfulfilled) to stand up to the world’s bullies.  Bullies come in all shapes and sizes: some are gangsters or men who sexually exploit vulnerable women; one, alas, is even the President of the United States.  But bullying knows no bounds of ideology or gender.  Some bullies resort to whisper networks, or Twitter shaming campaigns, or their power in academic hierarchies, to shut down dissenting voices.  With the latter kinds of bully—well, to whatever extent this blog is now in a position to make some difference, I’d feel morally complicit if it didn’t.</p>



<p>As I wrote in the comments: may the 2020s be an era of intellectual freedom, compassion, and understanding for all people regardless of background. –SA</p>



<p><strong>Scott’s prologue:</strong></p>



<p>Happy Christmas and Merry Chanukah!</p>



<p>As a followup to <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450">last Thursday’s post</a> about the term “quantum supremacy,” today all of us here at <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em> are humbled to host a guest post by <a href="https://stevenpinker.com/">Steven Pinker</a>: the Johnstone Professor of Psychology at Harvard University, and author of <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Language-Instinct-How-Mind-Creates/dp/1491514981">The Language Instinct</a></em>, <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/How-Mind-Works-Steven-Pinker/dp/0393318486">How the Mind Works</a></em>, <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Blank-Slate-Modern-Denial-Nature/dp/0142003344/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=the+blank+slate&amp;qid=1577123601&amp;s=books&amp;sr=1-1">The Blank Slate</a></em>, <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Enlightenment-Now-Science-Humanism-Progress/dp/0525427570">Enlightenment Now</a></em> (which I <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3654">reviewed here</a>), and other books.</p>



<p>The former NIPS—<a href="https://nips.cc/">Neural Information Processing Systems</a>—has been the premier conference for machine learning for 30 years.  As many readers might know, last year NIPS <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-07476-w">changed its name to NeurIPS</a>: ironically, giving greater emphasis to an aspect that I’m told has been <em>de</em>-emphasized at that conference over time.  The reason, apparently, was that some male attendees had made puns involving the acronym “NIPS” and nipples.</p>



<p>I confess that the name change took me by surprise, simply because it had never occurred to me to make the NIPS/nipples connection—not when I gave a <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=1246">plenary at NIPS</a> in 2012, and not when my collaborators and I coauthored a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1802.09025">NIPS paper</a>.  It’s not that I’m averse to puerile humor.  It’s just that neither I, nor anyone else I knew, had apparently ever felt the need for a shorthand for “nipples.”  Of course, once I <em>did</em> learn about this controversy, it became hard to hear “NIPS” without thinking about it.</p>



<p>Back when this happened, Steven Pinker <a href="https://twitter.com/sapinker/status/1070364941494992896?lang=en">tweeted</a> about NIPS being “forced to change its acronym … because some thought it was sexist. ?????,” apparently as part of a longer <a href="https://twitter.com/sapinker/status/1070364369207341056?lang=en">thread</a> about “the new Victorians.”  In response, a computer science professor sent Pinker an extremely stern email, saying that Pinker’s tweeting about this had “caused harm to our community” and “just [made] the world a bleaker place for everyone.”   After linking to a <em>National Academies</em> report on bias in STEM, the email ended: “I hope you will choose to inform yourself on the discussion to which you have just contributed and that you will offer a well-considered follow up.”   I won’t risk betraying confidences by quoting further.  Of course, the author is warmly welcomed to share anything they wish in the comments here (or I can add it to the main post).</p>



<p>Steve’s guest post today consists of his response to this email.  (He told me that, after sending it, he received no further responses.)</p>



<p>I don’t have any dog in the NIPS/NeurIPS debate, being at most on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margin_(machine_learning)">“margin”</a> (har!) of machine learning.  And in any case the debate ended a year ago: the name is now NeurIPS and it’s not changing back.  Reopening the issue would seem to invite a strong risk of social-media denunciation for no possible gain.</p>



<p>So why am I doing this?  Mostly because I thought it was in the interest of humanity to know that, even when Steven Pinker is answering someone’s email, with no expectation that his reply will be made public, he writes the same way he does in his books: with clarity, humor, and an amusing quote from his mom.</p>



<p>But also because—again, without taking a position on the NIPS vs. NeurIPS issue itself—there’s a tactic displayed by Pinker’s detractors that fundamentally grates on me.  This is where you pretend to an open mind, but it turns out that you’re open only to the possibility that your opponent might not have read enough reports and studies to “do better”—i.e., that they sinned out of ignorance rather than out of malice.  You don’t open your mind even a crack to the possibility that the opponent might have a point.</p>



<p><strong>Without further ado, here’s Steven Pinker’s email:</strong></p>



<p>I appreciate your frank comments. At the same time, I do not agree with them. Please allow me to explain.</p>



<p>If this were a matter of sexual harassment or other hostile behavior toward women, I would of course support strong measures to combat it. Any member of the Symposium who uttered demeaning comments toward or about women certainly deserves censure.</p>



<p>But that is not what is at issue here. It’s an utterly irrelevant matter: the three-decades-old acronym for the Neural Information Processing Symposium, the pleasingly pronounceable NIPS. To state what should be obvious: <em>nip</em> is not a sexual word. As Chair of the Usage Panel of the <em>American Heritage Dictionary, </em>I can <a href="https://www.ahdictionary.com/word/search.html?q=nip">support this claim</a>.</p>



<p>(And as my mother wrote to me: “I don’t get it. I thought Nips was a brand of caramel candy.”)  [<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Nips-Coffee-Candy-4-Ounce-Boxes/dp/B000V9EIEE">Indeed</a>, I enjoyed those candies as a kid. –SA]  Even if people with an adolescent mindset think of nipples when hearing the sound “nips,” the society should not endorse the idea that the concept of nipples is sexist. Men have nipples too, and women’s nipples evolved as organs of nursing, not sexual gratification. Indeed, many feminists have argued that it’s sexist to conceptualize women’s bodies from the point of view of male sexuality.</p>



<p>If some people make insulting puns that demean women, the society should condemn them for the insults, not concede to their puerility by endorsing their appropriation of an innocent sound. (The Linguistics Society of America and Boston Debate League do not change their names to disavow jejune clichés about cunning linguists and master debaters.) To act as if anything with the remotest connection to sexuality must be censored to protect delicate female sensibilities is insulting to women and reminiscent of prissy Victorian taboos against uncovered piano legs or the phrase “with the naked eye.”</p>



<p>Any harm to the community of computer scientists has been done not by me but by the pressure group and the Symposium’s surrender. As a public figure who hears from a broad range of people outside the academic bubble, I can tell you that this episode has not played well. It’s seen as the latest sign that academia has lost its mind—that it has traded reasoned argument, conceptual rigor, proportionality, and common sense for prudish censoriousness, snowflake sensibility, and virtue signaling. I often hear from intelligent non-leftists, “Why should I be impressed by the scientific consensus on climate change? Everyone knows that academics just fall into line with the politically correct position.” To secure the credibility of the academy, we have to make reasoned distinctions, and stop turning our enterprise into a laughingstock.</p>



<p>To repeat: none of this deprecates the important effort to stamp out harassment and misogyny in science, which I’m well aware of and thoroughly support, but which has nothing to do with the acronym NIPS.</p>



<p>You are welcome to share this note with interested parties.</p>



<p>Best,<br/>Steve</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-23T17:45:59Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-23T17:45:59Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Procrastination"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T07:49:59Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/23/postdoctoral-fellowships-in-theoretical-computer-science-at-department-of-computer-science-faculty-of-science-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-february-10-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/23/postdoctoral-fellowships-in-theoretical-computer-science-at-department-of-computer-science-faculty-of-science-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-february-10-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral Fellowship(s) in Theoretical Computer Science  at Department of Computer Science, Faculty of Science at University of Copenhagen (apply by February 10, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Department of Computer Science, Faculty of Science at University of Copenhagen (DIKU) is offering Postdoctoral positions in theoretical computer science expected to commence 1 September 2020 or as soon as possible thereafter. The postdoctoral researchers will be working in the research group of Jakob Nordström. Website: https://candidate.hr-manager.net/ApplicationInit.aspx?cid=1307&amp;ProjectId=150961&amp;DepartmentId=18970&amp;MediaId=4638 Email: jn@di.ku.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Department of Computer Science, Faculty of Science at University of Copenhagen (DIKU) is offering Postdoctoral positions in theoretical computer science expected to commence 1 September 2020 or as soon as possible thereafter.</p>
<p>The postdoctoral researchers will be working in the research group of Jakob Nordström.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://candidate.hr-manager.net/ApplicationInit.aspx?cid=1307&amp;ProjectId=150961&amp;DepartmentId=18970&amp;MediaId=4638">https://candidate.hr-manager.net/ApplicationInit.aspx?cid=1307&amp;ProjectId=150961&amp;DepartmentId=18970&amp;MediaId=4638</a><br/>
Email: jn@di.ku.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-23T12:51:53Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-23T12:51:53Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16481</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/22/predicting-when-pnp-is-resolved/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Predicting When P=NP is Resolved</title>
    <summary>Has it outlasted the ability to estimate when? Composite of src1, src2 Ryohei Hisano and Didier Sornette wrote in 2012 a paper titled, “On the distribution of time-to-proof of mathematical conjectures.” Today Ken and I discuss predicting the end to mathematical conjectures. This is apart from considering odds on which way they will go, which […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Has it outlasted the ability to estimate when?</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hisanosornette.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16483" height="121" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hisanosornette.png?w=180&amp;h=121" width="180"/></a><p/>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Composite of <a href="https://www.canon-igs.org/en/fellows/ryohei_hisano.html#pagelink01">src1</a>, <a href="https://speakerpedia.com/speakers/didier-sornette?__cf_chl_jschl_tk__=4e11570b77f5f043ebc63651af3c0ef50f684838-1577033444-0-AfVE-STCWNo-pMrTMB8DpB_rxfTWW5USE22lii9M6Mi3YbMsXknkzICr-grDZMxgnFeDJKqJFc_at8dhV8bJNE2R6Kxo8ZxcNq2fYc1C5vto6qZl8la1PjqByUjUXAIzTIoC973jn-rMAwXhSgm9wsgFdwshxfNGF34QSN3pFntcxdI4opKAQx1XKYEb-c1czoOq9Walf7aIOxuuGKo9e_euhCtW6rSyG9V0rlZnhNkGPgyMdMZdQMXK22h0-ebBRJ83f3AkztQtY-TBfgxF1JOsOY4Pp232qF_TRyksu4kH">src2</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Ryohei Hisano and Didier Sornette wrote in <b>2012</b> a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1202.3936">paper</a> titled, “On the distribution of time-to-proof of mathematical conjectures.”</p>
<p>
Today Ken and I discuss predicting the end to mathematical conjectures. This is apart from considering odds on which way they will go, which we also talk about.<br/>
<span id="more-16481"/></p>
<p>
Nine years ago the Christmas issue of the <em>New Scientist</em> magazine analyzed a small set of solved mathematical conjectures and used it to forecast when the P vs. NP conjecture would be solved. The article estimated that the “probability for the P vs. NP problem to be solved by the year <b>2024</b> is roughly 50%”. </p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/pnp.jpg"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-16485" height="200" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/pnp.jpg?w=300&amp;h=200" width="300"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2"><i>New Scientist</i> 2019 “biggest problem” <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/2198151-we-could-solve-the-biggest-problem-in-maths-in-the-next-decade/">source</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
This was done without any special insight into P vs. NP, just its prominence among the world’s best mathematicians and time since inception. How can one make the case that this argument is not silly, that it is not a wild guess? </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Time to Solve a Conjecture </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The <b>2010</b> <em>New Scientist</em> article could be considered a bagatelle since they looked at only 18 conjectures, but Hisano and Sornette took the idea seriously. They widened the data field to Wikipedia’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_conjectures">list</a> of mathematical conjectures. They removed a dozen-plus conjectures whose origin dates and/or solution dates are not firmly known, leaving 144 conjectures: 60 solved and 84 still open as of <b>2012</b>. </p>
<p>
It should be understood that their conclusions about the whole enterprise are negative. They say in their abstract:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> We find however evidence that the mathematical process of creation is too much non-stationary, with too little data and constraints, to allow for a meaningful conclusion. … In conclusion we cannot really reject the simplest model of an exponential rate of conjecture proof with a rate of 0.01/year for the dataset that we have studied, translating into an average waiting time to proof of 100 years. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
They found exponential growth in notable conjectures being formulated, which they ascribe to growth in the number of mathematicians. They try adjusting for this by invoking the overall growth curve of the world population. </p>
<p>
Then they find a dearth of conjectures with midrange solution times, compared to the number needed to give strong fits to simple models. They try cutting quickly-resolved conjectures (ones solved in under 20 years) from the dataset to improve the fits, and obtain only an enhancement of evidence for a slow exponential curve of solution time. Here is a figure from their paper showing the exponential curves:</p>
<p/><p><br/>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/conjplot.jpg"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-16486" height="360" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/conjplot.jpg?w=345&amp;h=360" width="345"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
In the end they are not able to find many hard distinctions between possible models. Most in particular, they conclude by calling the simple <img alt="{0.01}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0.01%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0.01}"/>-solution-chance-per-year model “our best model.”</p>
<p>
But that model in turn, without memory of the age of the conjecture, struck me—Ken writing here—as running counter to a famous controversial argument of recent vintage. So Dick and I put our heads together again…</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Doomsday For Conjectures? </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doomsday_argument">Doomsday</a> <a href="http://www.anthropic-principle.com/?q=anthropic_principle/doomsday_argument">Argument</a> can be phrased as a truism:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> If your hearing about <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{X}"/> is a uniformly random event in the lifespan of <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{X}"/>, which began <img alt="{t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t}"/> years ago, then the odds are 50-50 that the future lifetime <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> of <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{X}"/> will be no less than <img alt="{\frac{t}{3}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bt%7D%7B3%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\frac{t}{3}}"/> years and no more than <img alt="{3t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B3t%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{3t}"/> years. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This extends to say the probability is 90% that <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> will be no less than <img alt="{\frac{t}{19}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bt%7D%7B19%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\frac{t}{19}}"/> and no more than <img alt="{19t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B19t%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{19t}"/>. The numbers come from considering the middle half or middle 90% of the span.</p>
<p>
The key word in our phrasing is <em>if</em>—if your cognizance is a uniformly random event of the lifespan. The argument’s force comes from taking your birthday as a random event in the span of humanity. We can adjust for the population growth curve and our ignorance of prehistoric times by taking <img alt="{t}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t}"/> to be your ordinal in human lives ordered by birthday and projecting <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> in the same units. If there were 50 billion people before you, this speaks 95% confidence that the sum of human lives will not reach a trillion.</p>
<p>
We can try the same reasoning on conjectures. Suppose you just learned about the P vs. NP problem from catching a reference to this blog. By Kurt Gödel’s <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/the-gdel-letter/">letter</a> to John von Neumann we date the problem to <b>1956</b>, which makes <img alt="{t = 63}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt+%3D+63%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t = 63}"/> years. Presuming your encounter is random, you can conclude a 50-50 chance of the conjecture being solved between the years <b>2040</b> (which is 21 years from now) and <b>2208</b> (which is still shorter than Fermat’s Last Theorem lasted). The less you knew about P vs. NP, the more random the encounter—and the stronger the inference.</p>
<p>
Perhaps Wikipedia’s <b>1971</b> origin for P vs. NP from its precise statement by Steve Cook is more realistic. Was my learning about it in <b>1979</b> (<img alt="{t=8}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt%3D8%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t=8}"/>) a random event? If so, I should have been 75% confident of a solution by <b>2003</b>. Its lasting 16 more years and counting busts the 83.3% confidence interval. Well, Dick learned about it within weeks, at most months, after inception. If that was random then its longevity counts as a 99.9% miss. Of course, Dick’s learning about it was far from random. But.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Doomsday Conflict </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Our point, however, is this: Consider <em>any</em> conjecture that has lasted <img alt="{t = 87}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt+%3D+87%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t = 87}"/> years. That’s the point at which the <img alt="{0.01}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0.01%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0.01}"/> exponential and Doomsday models come into conflict:</p>
<ul>
<li>
By Doomsday, there is 75% confidence of the conjecture lasting at least <img alt="{\frac{t}{3} = 29}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bt%7D%7B3%7D+%3D+29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\frac{t}{3} = 29}"/> more years. <p/>
</li><li>
But since <img alt="{0.99^{29} &lt; 0.75}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0.99%5E%7B29%7D+%3C+0.75%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0.99^{29} &lt; 0.75}"/>, by the H-S best model, one should have less confidence.
</li></ul>
<p>
The longer a conjecture lasts, the greater this conflict. We are not addressing the issue of uniform sampling over the lifespan of the conjecture, but this conflict applies to <b>all</b> observers past the 87-year mark. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honeycomb_conjecture">honeycomb</a> conjecture was documented by 36 BCE and finally solved by Thomas Hales in <b>1999</b>. </p>
<p>
Note that since <img alt="{0.99^{87} = 0.417\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0.99%5E%7B87%7D+%3D+0.417%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0.99^{87} = 0.417\dots}"/>, one cannot evade our model conflict by saying only a small fraction of conjectures last that long. Despite H-S noting that the honeycomb conjecture and Fermat and some others break their curve, their curve at left below shows excellent agreement up to and beyond the 100-year mark. </p>
<p/><p/>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hsfigs5-6.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-16487" height="298" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hsfigs5-6.png?w=600&amp;h=298" width="600"/></a></p>
<p/><p><br/>
The curve at right shows that a <img alt="{0.02}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0.02%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0.02}"/> rate fits even better when short-lived conjectures are deleted. Since <img alt="{0.98^{14.33} &lt; 0.75}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0.98%5E%7B14.33%7D+%3C+0.75%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0.98^{14.33} &lt; 0.75}"/>, that makes the conflict set in at <img alt="{t = 43}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt+%3D+43%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t = 43}"/> years old. Then it applies even for P vs. NP dated to Cook. At <img alt="{t = 100}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bt+%3D+100%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{t = 100}"/> the conflict is considerable: Doomsday 66.7% of its lasting at least 50 more years, versus <img alt="{0.98^{50} \approx \frac{1}{e} \approx 36.4\%}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0.98%5E%7B50%7D+%5Capprox+%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Be%7D+%5Capprox+36.4%5C%25%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0.98^{50} \approx \frac{1}{e} \approx 36.4\%}"/> chance of its lasting that long by H-S.</p>
<p>
This conflict says there must be a factor that invalidates either or both lines of reasoning. But the Hisano-Sornette estimates are supported by data, while our Doomsday representation is quite generic. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Do Odds Matter? </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
A further wrinkle is whether the collective balance of opinion on whether a conjecture is true or false has any bearing. If the field is evenly divided, does that argue that the conjecture will take longer to resolve?</p>
<p>
The idea of “odds” is hard to quantify and has come into play only recently. Despite <a href="http://blog.oddhead.com/2010/08/11/betting-on-p-equals-np/">lots</a> of <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2009/12/probability-of-pnp.html">chat</a> about <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2009/09/15/theory-has-bet-on-pnp/">betting</a> on P vs. NP, and Bill Gasarch’s wonderful <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/users/gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/pollpaper3.pdf">polls</a> on which side is true, data for other problems is scant. </p>
<p>
This prompts us to mention that the Springer LNCS 10,000 anniversary <a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-319-91908-9">volume</a> came out in October. It includes a <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-91908-9_12">contribution</a> by Ken titled, “Rating Computer Science Via Chess”—the title refers both to how the chess ratings of the best chess computers mirrored Moore’s Law and how they draw on many general CS achievements in both hardware and software. For now we note also the <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-91908-9_2">contribution</a> by Ryan Williams titled, “Some Estimated Likelihoods for Computational Complexity.” Ryan places only 80% on <img alt="{\mathsf{P \neq NP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BP+%5Cneq+NP%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{P \neq NP}}"/> and puts <img alt="{\mathsf{NC}^1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BNC%7D%5E1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{NC}^1}"/> versus <img alt="{\mathsf{TC^0}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BTC%5E0%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\mathsf{TC^0}}"/> at 50-50. </p>
<p>
There are also non-betting and non-opinion senses in which conjectures are regarded as “almost certainly true.” We recently <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/11/11/goldbach-a-curious-conjecture/">posted</a> about this. Perhaps something more can be gleaned from highlighting those conjectures in the H-S data set to which such criteria apply.</p>
<p>
All of this speculation may be less idle and less isolated if it can be carried over to unsolved problems in other walks of life. Corporations and consortia doing open-ended research may already need to quantify the average time to achieve potential breakthroughs—or dismiss them—because they deal with many “feelers” at a time. The Doomsday assumption of random encounters probably doesn’t apply there. But there could be large-scale tests of it by “punters” seeking out random lifespans they can bet on, such as runs of shows or the time to make a movie of <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/arts-entertainment/2019/12/20/biggest-disaster-decade-roundup-most-memorable-cats-reviews/"><i>Cats</i></a>, and profit by applying it.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
What do you think about attempts to forecast the time to solve P vs. NP, or to forecast breakthroughs on larger scales? </p>
<p>
There are many rebuttals to the Doomsday Argument, some general and some context-specific. Is our argument that it conflicts generally with memoryless exponential models subsumed by any of them?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-22T17:30:08Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-22T17:30:08Z</published>
    <category term="algorithms"/>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="conjectures"/>
    <category term="Didier Sornette"/>
    <category term="Doomsday Argument"/>
    <category term="odds"/>
    <category term="predictions"/>
    <category term="Ryan Williams"/>
    <category term="Ryohei Hisano"/>
    <category term="statistical models"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-22-dolev-strong/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-22-dolev-strong/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dolev-Strong Authenticated Broadcast</title>
    <summary>This post is about the classic result from 1983 on authenticated broadcast against a Byzantine adversary: Theorem (Dolev-Strong [1983]): there exists an authenticated protocol for solving broadcast, against any adversary controlling $t&lt;n$ out of $n$ parties, in $t+1$ rounds, using $O(n^2t)$ words Recall Broadcast properties: (1) Termination - all honest...</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-22T17:05:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-22T17:05:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Ittai Abraham</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2019-12-26T23:22:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/184</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/184" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-184 |  Extractors for Adversarial Sources via Extremal Hypergraphs | 

	Eshan Chattopadhyay, 

	Jesse Goodman, 

	Vipul Goyal, 

	Xin Li</title>
    <summary>Randomness extraction is a fundamental problem that has been studied for over three decades. A well-studied setting assumes that one has access to multiple independent weak random sources, each with some entropy. However, this assumption is often unrealistic in practice. In real life, natural sources of randomness can produce samples with no entropy at all or with unwanted dependence. Motivated by this and applications from cryptography, we initiate a systematic study of randomness extraction for the class of adversarial sources defined as follows.

A weak source $\mathbf{X}$ of the form $\mathbf{X}_1,...,\mathbf{X}_N$, where each $\mathbf{X}_i$ is on $n$ bits, is an $(N,K,n,k)$-source of locality $d$ if the following hold:

(1) Somewhere good sources: at least $K$ of the $\mathbf{X}_i$'s are independent, and each contains min-entropy at least $k$. We call these $\mathbf{X}_i$'s good sources, and their locations are unknown. (2) Bounded dependence: each remaining (bad) source can depend arbitrarily on at most $d$ good sources.

We focus on constructing extractors with negligible error, in the regime where most of the entropy is contained within a few sources instead of across many (i.e., $k$ is at least polynomial in $K$). In this setting, even for the case of $0$-locality, very little is known prior to our work. For $d \geq 1$, essentially no previous results are known. We present various new extractors for adversarial sources in a wide range of parameters, and some of our constructions work for locality $d = K^{\Omega(1)}$. As an application, we also give improved extractors for small-space sources.

The class of adversarial sources generalizes several previously studied classes of sources, and our explicit extractor constructions exploit tools from recent advances in extractor machinery, such as two-source non-malleable extractors and low-error condensers. Thus, our constructions can be viewed as a new application of non-malleable extractors. In addition, our constructions combine the tools from extractor theory in a novel way through various sorts of explicit extremal hypergraphs. These connections leverage recent progress in combinatorics, such as improved bounds on cap sets and explicit constructions of Ramsey graphs, and may be of independent interest.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-22T07:10:31Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-22T07:10:31Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/21/postdoc-at-cedas-university-of-bergen-apply-by-january-27-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/21/postdoc-at-cedas-university-of-bergen-apply-by-january-27-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at CEDAS, University of Bergen (apply by January 27, 2019)</title>
    <summary>### four years position (25% teaching etc.) ### possible research topics include == multivariate algorithmics, == structure-aware visual data science, == semi-automatic topological data analysis of high-dimensional data, == as well as others that fit into CEDAS Website: https://www.jobbnorge.no/en/available-jobs/job/179374/postdoctoral-research-fellow-in-informatics-data-science Email: Helwig.Hauser@UiB.no</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>### four years position (25% teaching etc.)</p>
<p>### possible research topics include<br/>
== multivariate algorithmics,<br/>
== structure-aware visual data science,<br/>
== semi-automatic topological data analysis<br/>
of high-dimensional data,<br/>
== as well as others that fit into CEDAS</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.jobbnorge.no/en/available-jobs/job/179374/postdoctoral-research-fellow-in-informatics-data-science">https://www.jobbnorge.no/en/available-jobs/job/179374/postdoctoral-research-fellow-in-informatics-data-science</a><br/>
Email: Helwig.Hauser@UiB.no</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-21T14:07:57Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-21T14:07:57Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/183</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/183" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-183 |  Randomness Extraction from Somewhat Dependent Sources | 

	Marshall Ball, 

	Oded Goldreich, 

	Tal Malkin</title>
    <summary>We initiate a comprehensive study of the question of randomness extractions from two somewhat dependent sources of defective randomness. 
Specifically, we present three natural models, which are based on different natural perspectives on the notion of bounded dependency between a pair of distributions.
Going from the more restricted model to the less restricted one, our models and main results are as follows. 

\begin{enumerate}
\item{\em Bounded dependence as bounded coordination}:
Here we consider pairs of distributions that arise from independent random processes that are applied to the outcome of a single global random source, which may be viewed as a mechanism of coordination (which is adversarial from our perspective). 

We show that if the min-entropy of each of the two outcomes is larger than the length of the global source, then extraction is possible (and is, in fact, feasible). We stress that the extractor has no access to the global random source nor to the internal randomness that the two processes use, but rather gets only the two dependent outcomes.

This model is equivalent to a setting in which the two outcomes are generated by two independent sources, but then each outcome is modified based on limited leakage (equiv., communication) between the two sources.  (Here this leakage is measured in terms of the number of bits that were communicated, but in the next model we consider the actual influence of this leakage.)

\item{\em Bounded dependence as bounded cross influence}:
Here we consider pairs of outcomes that are produced by a pair of sources such that each source has bounded (worst-case) influence on the outcome of the other source.  We stress that the extractor has no access to the randomness that the two processes use, but rather gets only the two dependent outcomes.

We show that, while (proper) randomness extraction is impossible in this case, randomness condensing is possible and feasible; specifically, the randomness deficiency of condensing is linear in our measure of cross influence, and this upper-bound is tight.  We also discuss various applications of such condensers, including for cryptography, standard randomized algorithms, and sublinear-time algorithms, while pointing out their benefit over using a seeded (single-source) extractor. 

\item{\em Bounded dependence as bounded mutual information}:
Due to the average-case nature of this mutual information, here there is a trade-off between the error (or deviation) probability and the randomness deficiency.  Loosely speaking, for joint distributions of mutual information $t$, we can condense with randomness deficiency $O(t/\epsilon)$ and error $\epsilon$, and this trade-off is optimal.  
\end{enumerate}
All positive results are obtained by using a standard two-source extractor (or condenser) as a black-box.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-20T23:18:53Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-20T23:18:53Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/ibm-goldstine-postdoctoral-fellowship-at-ibm-research-apply-by-january-20-2019/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/ibm-goldstine-postdoctoral-fellowship-at-ibm-research-apply-by-january-20-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>IBM Goldstine Postdoctoral Fellowship at IBM Research (apply by January 20, 2019)</title>
    <summary>The Mathematical Sciences department of the IBM T.J. Watson Research Center invites applications for the Herman Goldstine Memorial Postdoctoral Fellowship for research in mathematical and computer sciences. The department provides an atmosphere in which basic research is combined with work on practical applications. Areas of interest include theoretical computer science and optimization. Website: https://www.research.ibm.com/goldstine/ Email: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Mathematical Sciences department of the IBM T.J. Watson Research Center invites applications for the Herman Goldstine Memorial Postdoctoral Fellowship for research in mathematical and computer sciences. The department provides an atmosphere in which basic research is combined with work on practical applications. Areas of interest include theoretical computer science and optimization.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.research.ibm.com/goldstine/">https://www.research.ibm.com/goldstine/</a><br/>
Email: postdoc@us.ibm.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-20T20:46:16Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-20T20:46:16Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/theory-group-postdoc-at-uc-berkeley-apply-by-january-10-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/theory-group-postdoc-at-uc-berkeley-apply-by-january-10-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Theory Group Postdoc at UC Berkeley (apply by January 10, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Postdoc inquiries will be viewable by all our group’s faculty. Individual faculty may then reach out in the case of matched interests. Please send a cover letter, CV, and research statement to the email below. In CV please list at least 3 references. In cover letter please identify faculty of interest. Also, have references submit […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Postdoc inquiries will be viewable by all our group’s faculty. Individual faculty may then reach out in the case of matched interests. Please send a cover letter, CV, and research statement to the email below. In CV please list at least 3 references. In cover letter please identify faculty of interest. Also, have references submit letters to the e-mail below, with your name in the subject line.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://theory.cs.berkeley.edu/">http://theory.cs.berkeley.edu/</a><br/>
Email: tcs-postdoc-inquiries@lists.eecs.berkeley.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-20T18:24:56Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-20T18:24:56Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/associate-professor-in-computer-science-at-department-of-computer-science-faculty-of-it-aalborg-university-technical-apply-by-february-1-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/associate-professor-in-computer-science-at-department-of-computer-science-faculty-of-it-aalborg-university-technical-apply-by-february-1-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Associate Professor in Computer Science at Department of Computer Science, Faculty of IT,  Aalborg University, Technical  (apply by February 1, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at Aalborg University’s Technical Faculty of IT is looking to appoint a number of Associate Professors from June 1, 2020 or soon hereafter. As Associate Professor in Computer Science, you are expected to conduct research and teaching at an international standard. Website: https://www.stillinger.aau.dk/vis-stilling/?vacancy=1081769 Email: est-st-hr@adm.aau.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at Aalborg University’s Technical Faculty of IT is looking to appoint a number of Associate Professors from June 1, 2020 or soon hereafter. As Associate Professor in Computer Science, you are expected to conduct research and teaching at an international standard.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.stillinger.aau.dk/vis-stilling/?vacancy=1081769">https://www.stillinger.aau.dk/vis-stilling/?vacancy=1081769</a><br/>
Email: est-st-hr@adm.aau.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-20T14:39:24Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-20T14:39:24Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/assistant-professor-in-computer-science-with-possibility-of-tenure-track-at-department-of-computer-science-technical-faculty-of-it-aalborg-university-apply-by-february-1-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/assistant-professor-in-computer-science-with-possibility-of-tenure-track-at-department-of-computer-science-technical-faculty-of-it-aalborg-university-apply-by-february-1-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor in Computer Science (with possibility of tenure-track)  at Department of Computer Science, Technical Faculty of IT, Aalborg University (apply by February 1, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at Aalborg University’s Technical Faculty of IT is looking to appoint a number of Assistant Professors (with the possibility of tenure-track) from June 1, 2019 or soon hereafter. As Assistant Professor in Computer Science, you are expected to conduct research and teaching at an international standard. Website: https://www.stillinger.aau.dk/vis-stilling/?vacancy=1081773 Email: jesper@cs.aau.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at Aalborg University’s Technical Faculty of IT is looking to appoint a number of Assistant Professors (with the possibility of tenure-track) from June 1, 2019 or soon hereafter. As Assistant Professor in Computer Science, you are expected to conduct research and teaching at an international standard.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.stillinger.aau.dk/vis-stilling/?vacancy=1081773">https://www.stillinger.aau.dk/vis-stilling/?vacancy=1081773</a><br/>
Email: jesper@cs.aau.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-20T14:34:06Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-20T14:34:06Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/phd-positions-in-tcs-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-february-10-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/phd-positions-in-tcs-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-february-10-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PhD positions in TCS at University of Copenhagen (apply by February 10, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for PhD positions in TCS. The application deadline is February 10, 2020. See http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/PhD-TCS-DIKU-200210.php for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jn@di.ku.dk or jakob.nordstrom@cs.lth.se. Website: http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/PhD-TCS-DIKU-200210.php Email: jn@di.ku.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for PhD positions in TCS. The application deadline is February 10, 2020. See <a href="http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/PhD-TCS-DIKU-200210.php">http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/PhD-TCS-DIKU-200210.php</a> for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jn@di.ku.dk or jakob.nordstrom@cs.lth.se.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/PhD-TCS-DIKU-200210.php">http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/PhD-TCS-DIKU-200210.php</a><br/>
Email: jn@di.ku.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-20T13:40:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-20T13:40:00Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/postdoc-positions-in-tcs-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-february-10-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/postdoc-positions-in-tcs-at-university-of-copenhagen-apply-by-february-10-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc positions in TCS at University of Copenhagen (apply by February 10, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for postdoc positions in TCS. The application deadline is February 10, 2020. See http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/Postdoc-TCS-DIKU-200210.php for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jn@di.ku.dk or jakob.nordstrom@cs.lth.se. Website: http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/Postdoc-TCS-DIKU-200210.php Email: jn@di.ku.dk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The CS department at the University of Copenhagen invites applications for postdoc positions in TCS. The application deadline is February 10, 2020. See <a href="http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/Postdoc-TCS-DIKU-200210.php">http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/Postdoc-TCS-DIKU-200210.php</a> for the full announcement with more information and instructions for how to apply. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jn@di.ku.dk or jakob.nordstrom@cs.lth.se.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/Postdoc-TCS-DIKU-200210.php">http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/Postdoc-TCS-DIKU-200210.php</a><br/>
Email: jn@di.ku.dk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-20T13:18:24Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-20T13:18:24Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/phd-position-in-cs-focused-on-sat-solving-and-combinatorial-optimization-at-lund-university-apply-by-february-10-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2019/12/20/phd-position-in-cs-focused-on-sat-solving-and-combinatorial-optimization-at-lund-university-apply-by-february-10-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PhD position in CS focused on SAT solving and combinatorial optimization at Lund University (apply by February 10, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The CS department at Lund Unversity invites applications for a PhD position focusing on algorithms for solving the Boolean satisfiability problem (SAT) and other NP-hard optimization problems very efficiently in practice. The application deadline is February 10, 2020. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jakob.nordstrom@cs.lth.se . Website: http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/PhD-SAT-LTH-200210.php Email: jakob.nordstrom@cs.lth.se</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The CS department at Lund Unversity invites applications for a PhD position focusing on algorithms for solving the Boolean satisfiability problem (SAT) and other NP-hard optimization problems very efficiently in practice. The application deadline is February 10, 2020. Informal enquiries are welcome and may be sent to jakob.nordstrom@cs.lth.se .</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/PhD-SAT-LTH-200210.php">http://www.csc.kth.se/~jakobn/openings/PhD-SAT-LTH-200210.php</a><br/>
Email: jakob.nordstrom@cs.lth.se</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-20T03:30:31Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-20T03:30:31Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/12/20/asymptotics-recamans-sequence</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/12/20/asymptotics-recamans-sequence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Asymptotics of Recamán’s sequence</title>
    <summary>Recamán’s sequence is a sequence of natural numbers in which the zeroth number is zero and the th number adds or subtracts from the previous number, subtracting if that would lead to a new value and adding otherwise. It was popularized in a 2018 Numberphile video that showed both an interesting visualization of it using nested circles and a spooky piano composition obtained by using its values as notes.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recam%C3%A1n%27s_sequence">Recamán’s sequence</a> is a sequence of natural numbers in which the zeroth number is zero and the th number adds or subtracts  from the previous number, subtracting if that would lead to a new value and adding otherwise. It was popularized in a 2018 Numberphile video that showed both an interesting visualization of it using nested circles and a spooky piano composition obtained by using its values as notes.</p>



<p>In <a href="https://oeis.org/A005132">the OEIS entry for this sequence</a> Benjamin Chaffin claims to have computed and plotted its first  numbers. Can it really be done this fast?
And until recently, the sequence’s Wikipedia article claimed that when computing this sequence, each number takes  time to compute, sourced to the analysis in <a href="https://blogs.mathworks.com/cleve/2018/07/09/the-oeis-and-the-recaman-sequence/">a blog post with a MATLAB implementation</a>. Can it really be this slow?</p>

<p>In analyzing the complexity of computing integer sequences, it’s often important to consider numerical precision. The standard computational model used for algorithm analysis, the unit-cost RAM, allows constant-time arithmetic on -bit integers, enough to allow the model to index its memory. Models of computing with larger word sizes are less standard. And some sequences need linearly many bits just to represent a single sequence value, too many to handle in constant time. But that’s not an issue for Recamán’s sequence. Even a sequence that always added  at each step, rather than sometimes, subtracting, would grow at most quadratically, allowing the first  numbers to be computed using only -bit arithmetic.</p>

<p>Using this model, we can analyze a naive algorithm for the sequence that directly implements its recurrence while maintaining a set data structure to keep track of what has been seen already.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">recaman</span><span class="p">():</span>
    <span class="n">visited</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nb">set</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
    <span class="k">while</span> <span class="bp">True</span><span class="p">:</span>
        <span class="k">yield</span> <span class="n">a</span>
        <span class="n">n</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
        <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="ow">and</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="ow">not</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">visited</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">-=</span> <span class="n">n</span>
        <span class="k">else</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="n">a</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="n">n</span>
        <span class="n">visited</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">add</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">)</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>If sets are represented using hash tables with provable constant expected time per operation (say, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_probing#Choice_of_hash_function">linear probing with tabulation hashing</a>), then this takes constant expected time per number, or  for the first  numbers. So much for being quadratic. Alternatively, if we knew that the sequence grew only linearly, we could avoid hashing and expected time analysis by using a bitvector to get deterministic constant time per number.</p>

<p>So the next question to ask is: does the sequence grow only linearly, or more quickly? Before running an experiment to test this, my intuition was that if the choice to add or subtract were uniformly random, then the sequence would grow like a random walk, typically  steps away from the origin, which with step size  would give growth . On the other hand, to achieve equal probability of going up or down you need roughly half of the integers to be visited, and for that to happen the sequence should grow only as . For any faster growth rate, the density of visited integers would be less than half and the sequence would be pulled downward. So I expected that the true growth rate should be at a level where the upward pressure of a uniform random walk and the downward pressure of less-than-half occupancy balance each other, but I didn’t have a strong a priori feeling whether this meant linear growth (with constant but somewhat less than half occupancy) or slightly superlinear growth.</p>

<p>This is something we can check experimentally, so I used the naive algorithm to generate a quarter-billion sequence elements, sampled them down to 629 pairs of  by keeping only elements at cubic positions, and fit a line to their log-log plot using Siegel’s repeated median estimator in R. The result has weird stripy patterns that don’t look much like a line, but its exponent looks a lot like a 1 to me.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Log-log plot of samples from Recam&#xE1;n's sequence" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/density.png"/></p>

<p>We can get a cleaner curve (and a more informative picture of how big a bitvector we might need) by plotting only the points where the sequence reaches a new high point. There were too many data points to fit easily, so I thinned them out by including only high points that were half a percent higher than the previous one, giving me 254 data points. To look more carefully at near-linear growth rates, I plotted  against  this time. Again, the results had weird stripy patterns that I didn’t expect (I thought filtering for the high points would have eliminated that), but the plot seems to clearly show that the growth rate of the sequence is nonlinear. Although the fit line shows growth of the form , I don’t think the data is clear enough to conclude that this is the right growth rate.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Plot of high points of Recam&#xE1;n's sequence, divided by n" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/highpoint.png"/></p>

<p>So, sadly, the bitvector solution doesn’t appear to give us a deterministic solution with constant time per element. It takes a nonlinear amount of time to initialize a nonlinear number of bits. Maybe instead some deterministic choice of hash function allows the hashing solution to work without randomization, but proving that seems difficult. On the other hand there’s a lot of other structure in the sequence. Maybe we can take advantage of it and get even faster, computing an implicit representation of the sequence (rather than an explicit list of each of its elements) in time sublinear in the number of elements generated? Surely, if the claim of having generated  elements is to be believed, this must be possible.</p>

<p>A hint comes from the plots in the MATLAB post showing that Recamán’s sequence contains long alternations between addition and subtraction that fill in two contiguous blocks of integers. A comment by Jan Van lent from <a href="https://mathlesstraveled.com/2016/06/12/the-recaman-sequence/">a 2016 blog post on <em>The Math Less Traveled</em></a> suggests that there should be few (maybe ) of these blocks, and that we can save space using a data structure that stores blocks rather than individual numbers. This would have advantages even in the naive algorithm: when I tried bumping my data sets to a full billion elements they bogged down, not because I didn’t have enough time to run four times slower, but because I ran out of memory for the hash table.</p>

<p>We can use a data structure that allows for integer predecessor queries to store only the starting endpoints of each block of occupied integers, associating with each start the end of the same block. Then, we could test whether a query integer  is in one of the blocks by finding the predecessor of  (the first block start at or before ) and checking whether its block extends as far as . A similar but more complicated calculation could also be used, for each sequence element, to find the length of the alternation starting at that element (stopping the alternation when the negative steps in the alternation run into another block), and then to update the collection of blocks to cover all of the elements encountered during this alternation. The obvious choice of predecessor data structure would be a balanced binary search tree, but (because we’re dealing with integers of polynomial magnitude) it’s better in theory to use a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Emde_Boas_tree">Van Emde Boas tree</a>, which can handle each data structure operation in time . If we generate Recamán’s sequence one alternation at a time in this way, and it has  alternations and  blocks in its first  elements, then the improved generation algorithm will take time  and space . I have a VEB-tree implementation, but it lacks predecessor queries, and four times more elements are only a small step on my log plots, so I haven’t tested this. But we can still use the naive algorithm to compute  and  and study how they grow. Here, first, is .</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Plot of number of alternating subsequences of Recam&#xE1;n's sequence" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/alternations.png"/></p>

<p>The number of alternations looks like a reasonable fit for .
The number of blocks can be at most twice the number of alternations, but it could well be smaller as blocks coalesce after they are formed. The plot of numbers of blocks looks almost the same as the one above, so instead I plotted a ratio. I don’t think the fit line in the plot is particularly convincing. Nevertheless to me this looks like  and  have the same exponent but differ by a lower-order factor like a log or log-log.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Plot of ratio of alternating subsequences to contiguous occupied blocks for Recam&#xE1;n's sequence" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/blocks.png"/></p>

<p>So what have we learned?</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Even the obvious hashtable-based methods can achieve constant expected time per element. But their limiting factor is memory, not time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It’s tempting to use bitvectors instead, and that might not be a bad choice in practice, but in theory that appears to take more than constant time per element. Deterministic hashing might take constant time per element but this is unproven.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Generating the sequence implicitly in terms of its alternations, and using a data structure that represents the generated elements in terms of their blocks, looks like it can achieve something like  in both time and space,
but again this is unproven.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>This is still not anywhere near fast enough to get  elements, nor even  as the largest generated value. So either something is wrong with that claim (most likely a typo in the number of elements), or there are significant algorithmic improvements possible beyond just using alternations and blocks.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>For the source code for these plots, see <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/density.py">density generation</a>/<a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/density.R">analysis</a>, <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/highpoint.py">high point generation</a>/<a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/highpoint.R">analysis</a>, <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/alternations.py">alternation generation</a>/<a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/alternations.R">analysis</a>, and <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/blocks.py">block generation</a>/<a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/recaman/blocks.R">analysis</a>.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103339144033179034">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-20T00:02:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-20T00:02:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-12-21T08:46:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2019/12/19/15th-international-computer-science-sysmposium-in-russia/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2019/12/19/15th-international-computer-science-sysmposium-in-russia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>15th International Computer Science Sysmposium in Russia</title>
    <summary>June 29 – July 3, 2020 Yekaterinburg, Russia https://csr2020.sciencesconf.org/ Submission deadline: January 10, 2020 CSR is an annual international conference held in Russia that is designed to cover a broad range of topics in Theoretical Computer Science. The list of previous CSR conferences can be found at https://logic.pdmi.ras.ru/~csr/ .</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-19T20:25:13Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-19T20:25:13Z</published>
    <category term="other"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:21:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4450#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4450" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Quantum Dominance, Hegemony, and Superiority</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Yay! I’m now a Fellow of the ACM. Along with my fellow new inductee Peter Shor, who I hear is a real up-and-comer in the quantum computing field. I will seek to use this awesome responsibility to steer the ACM along the path of good rather than evil. Also, last week, I attended the Q2B […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Yay!  I’m <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/news/2019/professor-scott-aaronson-named-acm-fellow">now</a> a Fellow of the ACM.  Along with my <a href="https://www.acm.org/media-center/2019/december/fellows-2019">fellow new inductee</a> Peter Shor, who I hear is a real up-and-comer in the quantum computing field.  I will seek to use this awesome responsibility to steer the ACM along the path of good rather than evil.</p>



<p>Also, last week, I attended the <a href="https://q2b.qcware.com/">Q2B</a> conference in San Jose, where a central theme was the outlook for practical quantum computing in the wake of the first clear demonstration of quantum computational supremacy.  Thanks to the folks at <a href="https://qcware.com/">QC Ware</a> for organizing a fun conference (full disclosure: I’m QC Ware’s Chief Scientific Advisor).  I’ll have more to say about the actual scientific things discussed at Q2B in future posts.</p>



<p>None of that is why you’re here, though.  You’re here because of the battle over “quantum supremacy.”</p>



<p>A week ago, my good friend and <a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/the-talk-3">collaborator</a> Zach Weinersmith, of <a href="http://smbc-comics.com/">SMBC Comics</a>, put out a <a href="http://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/classical">cartoon</a> with a dark-curly-haired scientist named “Dr. Aaronson,” who’s revealed on a hot mic to be an evil “quantum supremacist.”  Apparently a rush job, this cartoon is far from Zach’s finest work.  For one thing, if the character is supposed to be me, why not draw him as me, and if he isn’t, why call him “Dr. Aaronson”?  In any case, I learned from talking to Zach that the cartoon’s timing was purely coincidental: Zach didn’t even <em>realize</em> what a hornet’s-nest he was poking with this.</p>



<p>Ever since John Preskill <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1203.5813">coined</a> it in 2012, “quantum supremacy” has been an awkward term.  Much as I admire John Preskill’s wisdom, brilliance, generosity, and good sense, in physics as in everything else—yeah, “quantum supremacy” is not a term I would’ve coined, and it’s certainly not a hill I’d choose to die on.  Once it had gained common currency, though, I sort of took a liking to it, mostly because I realized that I could mine it for dark one-liners in my talks.</p>



<p>The thinking was: even as white supremacy was making its horrific resurgence in the US and around the world, here we were, physicists and computer scientists and mathematicians of varied skin tones and accents and genders, coming together to pursue a different and better kind of supremacy—a small reflection of the better world that we still believed was possible.  You might say that we were <strong>reclaiming</strong> the word “supremacy”—which, after all, just means a state of being supreme—for something non-sexist and non-racist and inclusive and good.</p>



<p>In the world of 2019, alas, perhaps it was inevitable that people wouldn’t leave things there.</p>



<p>My first intimation came a month ago, when <a href="https://twitter.com/LeonieMueck?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor">Leonie Mueck</a>—someone who I’d gotten to know and like when she was an editor at <em>Nature</em> handling quantum information papers—emailed me about her view that our community should abandon the term “quantum supremacy,” because of its potential to make women and minorities uncomfortable in our field.  She advocated using “quantum advantage” instead.</p>



<p>So I sent Leonie back a friendly reply, explaining that, as the father of a math-loving 6-year-old girl, I understood and shared her concerns—but also, that I also didn’t know an alternative term that really worked.</p>



<p>See, it’s like this.  Preskill meant “quantum supremacy” to refer to a <em>momentous event</em> that seemed likely to arrive in a matter of years: namely, the moment when programmable quantum computers would first outpace the ability of the fastest classical supercomputers on earth, running the fastest algorithms known by humans, to simulate what the quantum computers were doing (at least on special, contrived problems).  And … “the historic milestone of quantum advantage”?  It just doesn’t sound right.  Plus, as many others pointed out, the term “quantum advantage” is already used to refer to … well, quantum <em>advantages</em>, which might fall well short of supremacy.</p>



<p>But one could go further.  Suppose we did switch to “quantum advantage.”  Couldn’t that term, too, remind vulnerable people about the unfair advantages that some groups have over others?  Indeed, while “advantage” is certainly subtler than “supremacy,” couldn’t that make it all the more insidious, and therefore dangerous?</p>



<p>Oblivious though I sometimes am, I realized Leonie would be unhappy if I offered that, because of my wholehearted agreement, I would henceforth never again call it “quantum supremacy,” but only “quantum superiority,” “quantum dominance,” or “quantum hegemony.”</p>



<p>But maybe you now see the problem.  What word does the English language provide to describe one thing <em>decisively beating or</em> <em>being better than</em> a different thing for some purpose, and which <em>doesn’t</em> have unsavory connotations?</p>



<p>I’ve heard “quantum ascendancy,” but that makes it sound like we’re a UFO cult—waiting to ascend, like ytterbium ions caught in a laser beam, to a vast quantum computer in the sky.</p>



<p>I’ve heard “quantum inimitability” (that is, inability to imitate using a classical computer), but who can pronounce that?</p>



<p>Yesterday, my brilliant former student <a href="https://ewintang.com/">Ewin Tang</a> (yes, <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3880">that one</a>) relayed to me a suggestion by Kevin Tian: “quantum eclipse” (that is, the moment when quantum computers first eclipse classical ones for some task).  But would one want to speak of a “quantum eclipse experiment”?  And shouldn’t we expect that, the cuter and cleverer the term, the harder it will be to use unironically?</p>



<p>In summary, while someone <em>might</em> think of a term so inspired that it immediately supplants “quantum supremacy” (and while I welcome suggestions), I currently regard it as an open problem.</p>



<p>Anyway, evidently dissatisfied with my response, last week Leonie teamed up with 13 others to publish a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03781-0">letter in <em>Nature</em></a>, which was originally entitled “Supremacy is for racists—use ‘quantum advantage,'” but whose title I see has now been changed to the less inflammatory “Instead of ‘supremacy’ use ‘quantum advantage.'”  Leonie’s co-signatories included four of my good friends and colleagues: Alan Aspuru-Guzik, Helmut Katzgraber, Anne Broadbent, and Chris Granade (the last of whom got started in the field by helping me edit <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Quantum-Computing-since-Democritus-Aaronson/dp/0521199565"><em>Quantum Computing Since Democritus</em></a>).</p>



<p>(<strong>Update:</strong> Leonie pointed me to a longer list of signatories <a href="https://www.quantumresponsibility.org/openletter">here</a>, at their website called “quantumresponsibility.org.”  A few names that might be known to <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em> readers are Andrew White, David Yonge-Mallo, Debbie Leung, Matt Leifer, Matthias Troyer.)</p>



<p>Their letter says:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>The community claims that quantum supremacy is a technical term with a specified meaning.  However, any technical justification for this descriptor could get swamped as it enters the public arena after the intense media coverage of the past few months.</p><p>In our view, ‘supremacy’ has overtones of violence, neocolonialism and racism through its association with ‘white supremacy’.  Inherently violent language has crept into other branches of science as well — in human and robotic spaceflight, for example, terms such as ‘conquest’, ‘colonization’ and ‘settlement’ evoke the <em>terra nullius</em> arguments of settler colonialism and must be contextualized against ongoing issues of neocolonialism.</p><p>Instead, quantum computing should be an open arena and an inspiration for a new generation of scientists.</p></blockquote>



<p>When I did an “Ask Me Anything” session, as the closing event at Q2B, <a href="https://www.sckaiser.com/">Sarah Kaiser</a> asked me to comment on the <em>Nature</em> petition.  So I repeated what I’d said in my emailed response to Leonie—running through the problems with each proposed alternative term, talking about the value of reclaiming the word “supremacy,” and mostly just trying to diffuse the tension by getting everyone laughing together.  Sarah later <a href="https://twitter.com/crazy4pi314/status/1205288610297069568">tweeted</a> that she was “really disappointed” in my response.</p>



<p>Then the <em>Wall Street Journal</em> got in on the action, with a brief <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/achieving-quantum-wokeness-11576540808">editorial</a> (warning: paywalled) mocking the <em>Nature</em> petition:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>There it is, folks: Mankind has hit quantum wokeness.  Our species, akin to Schrödinger’s cat, is simultaneously brilliant and brain-dead.  We built a quantum computer and then argued about whether the write-up was linguistically racist.</p><p>Taken seriously, the renaming game will never end.  First put a Sharpie to the Supremacy Clause of the U.S. Constitution, which says federal laws trump state laws.  Cancel Matt Damon for his 2004 role in “The Bourne Supremacy.”  Make the Air Force give up the term “air supremacy.”  Tell lovers of supreme pizza to quit being so chauvinistic about their toppings.  Please inform Motown legend Diana Ross that the Supremes are problematic.</p><p>The quirks of quantum mechanics, some people argue, are explained by the existence of many universes.  How did we get stuck in this one? </p></blockquote>



<p>Steven Pinker also weighed in, with a linguistically-informed <a href="https://twitter.com/sapinker/status/1206662965614825472">tweetstorm</a>:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>This sounds like something from The Onion but actually appeared in Nature … It follows the wokified stigmatization of other innocent words, like “House Master” (now, at Harvard, Residential Dean) and “NIPS” (Neural Information Processing Society, now NeurIPS).  It’s a familiar linguistic phenomenon, a lexical version of Gresham’s Law: bad meanings drive good ones out of circulation.  Examples: the doomed “niggardly” (no relation to the n-word) and the original senses of “cock,” “ass,” “prick,” “pussy,” and “booty.”  Still, the prissy banning of words by academics should be resisted.  It dumbs down understanding of language: word meanings are conventions, not spells with magical powers, and all words have multiple senses, which are distinguished in context.  Also, it makes academia a laughingstock, tars the innocent,  and does nothing to combat actual racism &amp; sexism.</p></blockquote>



<p>Others had a stronger reaction.  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curtis_Yarvin">Curtis Yarvin</a>, better known as Mencius Moldbug, is one of the founders of “neoreaction” (and a significant influence on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Bannon">Steve Bannon</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Anton">Michael Anton</a>, and other Trumpists).  Regulars might remember that Yarvin argued with me in <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em>‘s comment section, under a <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3167">post</a> in which I denounced Trump’s travel ban and its effects on my Iranian PhD student.  Since then, Yarvin has sent me many emails, which have ranged from long to <em>extremely</em> long, and whose message could be summarized as: “[labored breathing] Abandon your liberal Enlightenment pretensions, young Nerdwalker.  Come over the Dark Side.”</p>



<p>After the “supremacy is for racists” letter came out in <em>Nature</em>, though, Yarvin sent me his shortest email ever.  It was simply a link to the letter, along with the comment “I knew it would come to this.”</p>



<p>He meant: “What more proof do you need, young Nerdawan, that this performative wokeness is a cancer that will eventually infect everything you value—even totally apolitical research in quantum information?  And by extension, that my whole worldview, which warned of this, is fundamentally correct, while your faith in liberal academia is naïve, and will be repaid only with backstabbing?”</p>



<p>In a subsequent email, Yarvin predicted that in two years, the whole community will be saying “quantum advantage” instead of “quantum supremacy,” and in five years I’ll be saying “quantum advantage” too.  As Yarvin <a href="https://www.unqualified-reservations.org/2009/01/gentle-introduction-to-unqualified/">famously wrote</a>: “Cthulhu may swim slowly.  But he only swims left.”</p>



<p>So what do I <em>really</em> think about this epic battle for (and against) supremacy?</p>



<p>Truthfully, half of me just wants to switch to “quantum advantage” right now and be done with it.  As I said, I know some of the signatories of the <em>Nature</em> letter to be smart and reasonable and kind.  They don’t wish to rid the planet of everyone like me.  They’re not Amanda Marcottes or Arthur Chus.  Furthermore, there’s little I despise more than a meaty scientific debate devolving into a pointless semantic one, with brilliant friend after brilliant friend getting sucked into the vortex (“you too?”).  I’m strongly in the Pinkerian camp, which holds that words are just arbitrary designators, devoid of the totemic power to dictate thoughts.  So if friends and colleagues—even just a few of them—tell me that they find some word I use to be offensive, why not just be a <em>mensch</em>, apologize for any unintended hurt, switch words midsentence, and continue discussing the matter at hand?</p>



<p>But then the other half of me wonders: once we’ve ceded an open-ended veto over technical terms that remind anyone of anything bad, <em>where does it stop?</em>  How do we ever certify a word as kosher?  At what point do we all get to stop arguing and laugh together? </p>



<p>To make this worry concrete, look back at <a href="https://twitter.com/crazy4pi314/status/1205288610297069568">Sarah Kaiser’s Twitter thread</a>—the one where she expresses disappointment in me.  Below her tweet, someone remarks that, besides “quantum supremacy,” the word “ancilla” (as in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ancilla_bit">ancilla qubit</a>, a qubit used for intermediate computation or other auxiliary purposes) is problematic as well.  Here’s Sarah’s response:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>I agree, but I wanted to start by focusing on the obvious one, Its harder for them to object to just one to start with, then once they admit the logic, we can expand the list</p></blockquote>



<p>(What would Curtis Yarvin say about that?)</p>



<p>You’re probably now wondering: what’s wrong with “ancilla”?  <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1705.06768">Apparently</a>, in ancient Rome, an <a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/ancilla">“ancilla”</a> was a female slave, and indeed that’s the Latin root of the English adjective <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/ancillary">“ancillary”</a> (as in “providing support to”).  I confess that I hadn’t known that—had you?  Admittedly, once you <em>do</em> know, you might never again look at a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Controlled_NOT_gate">Controlled-NOT gate</a>—pitilessly flipping an ancilla qubit, subject only to the whims of a nearby control qubit—in quite the same way.</p>



<p>(Ah, but the ancilla can fight back against her controller!  And she does—in the Hadamard basis.)</p>



<p>The thing is, if we’re gonna play this game: what about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creation_and_annihilation_operators">annihilation operators</a>?  Won’t those need to be … annihilated from physics?</p>



<p>And what about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unitary_matrix">unitary matrices</a>?  Doesn’t their very name negate the multiplicity of perspectives and cultures?</p>



<p>What about Dirac’s oddly-named <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bra%E2%80%93ket_notation">bra/ket notation</a>, with its limitless potential for puerile jokes, about the “bra” vectors displaying their contents horizontally and so forth?  (Did you smile at that, you hateful pig?)</p>



<p>What about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermitian_adjoint">daggers</a>?  Don’t we need a less violent conjugate tranpose?</p>



<p>Not to beat a dead horse, but once you hunt for examples, you realize that the whole dictionary is shot through with domination and brutality—that you’d have to massacre the English language to take it out.  There’s nothing special about math or physics in this respect.</p>



<p>The same half of me also thinks about my friends and colleagues who oppose claims of quantum supremacy, or even the quest for quantum supremacy, on various <em>scientific</em> grounds.  I.e., either they don’t think that the Google team achieved what it said, or they think that the task wasn’t hard enough for classical computers, or they think that the entire goal is misguided or irrelevant or uninteresting.</p>



<p>Which is fine—these are precisely the arguments we <em>should </em>be having—except that I’ve personally seen some of my respected colleagues, while arguing for these positions, opportunistically tack on ideological objections to the term “quantum supremacy.”  Just to goose up their case, I guess.  And I confess that every time they did this, it made me want to keep saying “quantum supremacy” from now till the end of time—<em>solely to deny these colleagues a cheap and unearned “victory,” one they apparently felt they couldn’t obtain on the merits alone.</em>  I realize that this is childish and irrational.</p>



<p>Most of all, though, the half of me that I’m talking about thinks about Curtis Yarvin and the <em>Wall Street Journal</em> editorial board, cackling with glee to see their worldview so dramatically confirmed—as theatrical wokeness, that self-parodying modern monstrosity, turns its gaze on (of all things) quantum computing research.  More red meat to fire up the base—or at least that sliver of the base nerdy enough to care.  And the left, as usual, walks right into the trap, sacrificing its credibility with the outside world to pursue a runaway virtue-signaling spiral.</p>



<p>The same half of me thinks: do we <em>really</em> want to fight racism and sexism?  Then let’s work together to assemble a broad coalition that can defeat Trump.  And Jair Bolsonaro, and Viktor Orbán, and all the other ghastly manifestations of humanity’s collective lizard-brain.  Then, if we’re really fantasizing, we could liberalize the drug laws, and get contraception and loans and education to women in the Third World, and stop the systematic disenfranchisement of black voters, and open up the world’s richer, whiter, and higher-elevation countries to climate refugees, and protect the world’s remaining indigenous lands (those that didn’t burn to the ground this year).</p>



<p>In this context, the trouble with obsessing over terms like “quantum supremacy” is not merely that it diverts attention, while contributing nothing to fighting the world’s actual racism and sexism.  The trouble is that the obsessions are actually <em>harmful</em>.  For they make academics—along with progressive activists—look silly.  They make people think that we must not have meant it when we talked about the existential urgency of climate change and the world’s other crises.  They pump oxygen into right-wing echo chambers.</p>



<p>But it’s worse than ridiculous, because of the message that I fear is received by many outside the activists’ bubble.  When you <em>say</em> stuff like “[quantum] supremacy is for racists,” what’s <em>heard</em> might be something more like:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“Watch your back, you disgusting supremacist.  Yes, <em>you</em>.  You claim that you mentor women and minorities, donate to good causes, try hard to confront the demons in your own character?  Ha!  None of that counts for anything with us.  You’ll never be with-it enough to be our ally, so don’t bother trying.  We’ll see to it that you’re never safe, not even in the most abstruse and apolitical fields.  We’ll comb through your words—even words like ‘ancilla qubit’—looking for any that we can cast as offensive by our opaque and ever-shifting standards.  And once we find some, we’ll have it within our power to end your career, and you’ll be reduced to groveling that we don’t.  Remember those popular kids who bullied you in second grade, giving you nightmares of social ostracism that persist to this day?  We plan to achieve what even those bullies couldn’t: to shame you with the full backing of the modern world’s moral code.  See, we’re the <em>good guys</em> of this story.  It’s goodness itself that’s branding you as racist scum.”</p></blockquote>



<p>In short, I claim that the message—not the message <em>intended</em>, of course, by anyone other than a Chu or a Marcotte or a SneerClubber, but the message <em>received</em>—is basically a Trump campaign ad.  I claim further that our civilization’s current self-inflicted catastrophe will end—i.e., the believers in science and reason and progress and rule of law will claw their way back to power—when, and only when, a generation of activists emerges that understands these dynamics as well as <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/31/us/politics/obama-woke-cancel-culture.html">Barack Obama</a> did.</p>



<p>Wouldn’t it be awesome if, five years from now, I could say to Curtis Yarvin: <em>you were wrong</em>?  If I could say to him: <em>my colleagues and I still use the term ‘quantum supremacy’ whenever we care to, and none of us have been cancelled or ostracized for it—so maybe you should revisit your paranoid theories about Cthulhu and the Cathedral and so forth</em>?  If I could say: <em>quantum computing researchers now have bigger fish to fry than arguments over words—like moving beyond quantum supremacy to the first useful quantum simulations, as well as the race for scalability and fault-tolerance</em>?  And even: <em>progressive activists now have bigger fish to fry too—like retaking actual power all over the world</em>?</p>



<p>Anyway, as I said, that’s how half of me feels.  The other half is ready to switch to “quantum advantage” or any other serviceable term and get back to doing science.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-19T09:17:02Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-19T09:17:02Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Obviously I'm Not Defending Aaronson"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T07:49:59Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=18781</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/18/abel-in-jerusalem-sunday-january-12-2020-and-other-events/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Abel in Jerusalem – SUNDAY, January 12, 2020, and other events</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I would like to report on seven eight nine mathematical events taking place in Jerusalem, the Tel Aviv area, and Haifa in the next few weeks. (Probably I missed quite a few other mathematical events, feel free to update in … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/18/abel-in-jerusalem-sunday-january-12-2020-and-other-events/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I would like to report on <del>seven</del> <del datetime="2019-12-25T15:21:45+02:00">eight</del> nine mathematical events taking place in Jerusalem, the Tel Aviv area, and Haifa in the next few weeks. (Probably I missed quite a few other mathematical events, feel free to update in the comment section.)</p>
<p>1. <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/event/abel-jerusalem">Abel in Jerusalem: Sunday, January 12, 2020, 09:45-19:00</a>, featuring: <strong>Christopher Hacon, Ulrike Tillmann, Claire Voisin, and François Labourie</strong>.</p>
<p>2. <a href="http://ias.huji.ac.il/SchoolCSE4">Winter School: The Mathematics of Quantum computing</a> (starting  Dec. 15, 2019, <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1OcFzE1PHxBN4l87sOQB033FZLTgY934GHxnpVKi3NaM/edit">program</a>): The <a href="https://huji.cloud.panopto.eu/Panopto/Pages/Viewer.aspx?id=599bc3e9-855e-42c1-ab1d-ab1f0062c481">Rabin lecture</a> by <strong>Boaz Barak</strong> Monday Dec 16 14:00 CS building;  and also including <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H4t2G2gay7Q&amp;feature=youtu.be"><strong>a panel/debate on quantum supremacy</strong></a> moderated by <strong>Sandy Irani</strong>, Dec. 19 , 2019 16:00 CS building. (I am one of the seven panelists and for an introduction to my stance, see <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tau-theory-fest/home">this post</a>.) There are great <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLTn74Qx5mPsS2dqTpEq_2zxq8kWBmPUfb">videotaped lectures</a>!</p>
<p>3. <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tau-theory-fest/home">TAU Theory Fest  December 29, 2019  – January, 3, 2020.</a> Great line of speakers, and various workshops.</p>
<p>4. <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/boolean-functions/home">Boolean function day, Friday, January 3, 2020,</a> featuring <strong>Esty Kelman, Noam Lifschitz, Renan Gross, Ohad Klein, and Naomi Kirshner</strong>.</p>
<p>5. <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/node/92491">Zabrodsky’s lecture, <strong>Paul Seidel</strong>, December 19, 23, 24 2019, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem.</a> (See <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/12/14/old-lecture-notes-by-alex-zabrodsky/">this previous post</a>.)</p>
<p>6. <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/node/96554">Dvoretzky’s lectures, <strong>Sylvia Serfaty</strong>,  January 15,16, 2020, the Hebrew University of Jerusalem</a>. (See this post about <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/12/26/lior-aryeh-and-michael/">Aryeh Dvoretzky</a>.)</p>
<p>7. <a href="https://cms-math.net.technion.ac.il/prof-sergei-tabachnikov/">Distinguished lectures by <strong>Sergey Tabachnikov</strong>, January, 6, 8, 9 the Technion.</a></p>
<p>8. <a href="http://u.math.biu.ac.il/~schiff/wrkshpam25.html?fbclid=IwAR1kxSI4W9M1wCS0ebNUzF3d200d4QnYRRIlml4Y6bobjhn9fECgpufp44c">The Twenty-fifth Israeli Mini-Workshop in Applied and Computational Mathematics</a>, Wednesday December 25. Bar-Ilan University. Great line of speakers.</p>
<p>9. January 14,15 2020, <strong><a href="https://l.facebook.com/l.php?u=https%3A%2F%2Fsites.google.com%2Fview%2Ffeigefest%2F%3Ffbclid%3DIwAR0r36mN9rFp3oHFwzDaOncCtJzS4wg1k4O2_wnz8sxewAO_DBAy_HZpyck&amp;h=AT0lrk8x8-8UZJJUQdC3kOxkN9SHDSRigCkXzytEogsMV1iZXNW5aJCWdrTh4yxhA17TCKmAdZ3jtdo6SuUE3xgkms_CzkVXSI41Jbt1gRsozThxdOIJKOfPtopHMYSzzA">Games, Optimization and Optimism</a></strong>: in Honor of Uri Feige</p>
<h2>Abel In Jerusalem, Sunday, January 12, 2020.</h2>
<p>The Einstein Institute of mathematics is happy to host the Abel in Jerusalem Conference. The location of the conference in Manchester House, Lecture Hall 2. Each year the Abel Committee holds a symposium where members of the Abel Committee and some of the world’s top mathematicians will be speaking. “Abel in Jerusalem” will be the 10th one-day conference with lectures aimed at a mathematically educated and interested audience, with the objective of increasing public awareness of mathematics and of the Abel Prize.</p>
<p>The day starts (09:40) with opening remarks by <strong>Hans Petter Graver</strong>, President of the Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters, followed by lectures by  <strong>Christopher Hacon</strong> (University of Utah) 10:00-11:00; <strong>Ulrike Tillmann</strong> (Oxford University) 11:30-12:30; <strong>Claire Voisin</strong> (Collège de France) 14:30-15:30; and <strong>François Labourie</strong> (Université Côte d’Azur) 16:00-17:00. Participation, including lunch, and reception at the King David Hotel is free but registration is needed. Organizers: <strong>Gil Kalai</strong> and <strong>Tamar Ziegler</strong>; For more detail <a href="https://mathematics.huji.ac.il/event/abel-jerusalem">see this page</a>. If you are interested in attending please <a href="https://forms.gle/fEL7KgQxE8hHtb9q8" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="">register here</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/abelinj.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-18866" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/abelinj.png?w=640"/></a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-18T06:08:07Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-18T06:08:07Z</published>
    <category term="Algebra"/>
    <category term="Analysis"/>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Computer Science and Optimization"/>
    <category term="Conferences"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <category term="Updates"/>
    <category term="Christopher Hacon"/>
    <category term="Claire Voisin"/>
    <category term="Fran&#xE7;ois Labourie"/>
    <category term="Ulrike Tillmann"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16469</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/15/an-ancient-conjecture-on-primes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Ancient Conjecture on Primes</title>
    <summary>After 50 years we still are baffled by the primes. Cornell faculty album source Juris Hartmanis needs no introduction. But we can note this long interview last February by the Heidelberg Laureate Foundation. His sister, Astrid Ivask, was a world–recognized poet. Today Ken and I wish to discuss one of his old conjectures. We have […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>After 50 years we still are baffled by the primes.</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hartmaniswhiteboard-1.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16473" height="200" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hartmaniswhiteboard-1.png?w=134&amp;h=200" width="134"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Cornell faculty album <a href="https://digital.library.cornell.edu/catalog/ss:547397">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Juris Hartmanis needs no introduction. But we can note this long <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AxbKu7MrqA4">interview</a> last February by the Heidelberg Laureate Foundation. His sister, Astrid Ivask, was a <a href="https://www.worldliteraturetoday.org/blog/literary-tributes/tribute-astrid-ivask-literary-light">world</a>–<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astrid_Ivask">recognized</a> poet.</p>
<p>
Today Ken and I wish to discuss one of his old conjectures.<br/>
<span id="more-16469"/></p>
<p>
We have previously discussed one of his conjectures <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2009/02/24/a-conjecture-of-hartmanis/">here</a>. The conjecture we are interested in his one made in his joint <a href="https://ecommons.cornell.edu/handle/1813/5864">paper</a> with Herbert Shank titled, “On the Recognition of Primes by Automata.”</p>
<p>
Shank once wrote a paper <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-symbolic-logic/article/on-the-undecidability-of-finite-planar-cubic-graphs1/84518469D4AF1774ADE070EBA56601C9">On the undecidability of finite planar cubic graphs</a> with Solomon Garfunkel. I, Dick, liked this paper because it honestly pointed out that a predecessor paper by them was erroneous:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> In the March, 1971 issue of this Journal (JSL) a paper of ours was published purporting to prove the hereditary undecidability of the first-order theory of finite planar graphs. The proof presented there contains an error which is unfortunately “unfixable” by the methods of that paper. The theorem however is true and we demonstrate here a generalization to finite cubic (exactly three edges at each vertex) planar graphs. The method involves coding the halting problem for a Turing machine into the theory of these graphs by considering special printouts of computations. Let us first consider a discussion of the aforementioned mistake and see what can be learned from it <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\dots}"/> </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Primality Space Conjecture </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Hartmanis and Shank (HS) asked the following conjecture—over fifty years ago—about testing whether an integer is a prime number: </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  01,11,101,111,1101,1011,10001, \dots " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++01%2C11%2C101%2C111%2C1101%2C1011%2C10001%2C+%5Cdots+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  01,11,101,111,1101,1011,10001, \dots "/></p>
<p>We’ve written them in binary notation with the ones’ place first—just the way to give numbers on the input tape of a Turing machine. No error in their Turing representation here—just their brilliant conjecture connecting space to number theory: Suppose that primality is computed in space <img alt="{S(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S(n)}"/>. Then 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  S(n) \ge cn, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++S%28n%29+%5Cge+cn%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  S(n) \ge cn, "/></p>
<p>for some <img alt="{c&gt;0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%3E0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c&gt;0}"/>. That is, any primality test must take linear space. </p>
<p>
As usual, space is the measure of how much storage the algorithm must use. The input tape is read-only and does count against the storage bound. The famous AKS primality test showed that whether a given <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>-bit number <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> is prime can be determined in <img alt="{n^{O(1)}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7BO%281%29%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n^{O(1)}}"/> time but did not improve the linear upper bound on space, which HS showed by trivial means: Try all possible divisors between <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/> and <img alt="{\sqrt{x}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Csqrt%7Bx%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\sqrt{x}}"/>. The arithmetic and loop for this method can all be conducted in <img alt="{O(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n)}"/> space.</p>
<p>
What is some intuition for this conjecture? Why insist the space be <em>linear</em> when <img alt="{n^{1-\epsilon}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7B1-%5Cepsilon%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n^{1-\epsilon}}"/> space is plenty—given that polynomial time could still be equal to logspace? Well, suppose <img alt="{S(n) \ll n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%28n%29+%5Cll+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S(n) \ll n}"/> and consider the integers <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> from <img alt="{2^{n-1}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7Bn-1%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{n-1}}"/> to <img alt="{2^n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5En%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^n}"/>, that is all having <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> bits in binary notation. The number of machine configurations apart from the content <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> of the input tape is at most:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<img alt="{2^{O(S(n))}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5E%7BO%28S%28n%29%29%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^{O(S(n))}}"/> possible contents of the <img alt="{S(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S(n)}"/> worktape cells, times <p/>
</li><li>
<img alt="{n+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n+1}"/> input head positions, times <img alt="{S(n)+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%28n%29%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S(n)+1}"/> or so worktape head positions, times <p/>
</li><li>
the finite number of states.
</li></ul>
<p>
This is <img alt="{\ll N = 2^n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cll+N+%3D+2%5En%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\ll N = 2^n}"/>. In fact, it is <img alt="{\ll \frac{N}{n} = \frac{N}{\ln N}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cll+%5Cfrac%7BN%7D%7Bn%7D+%3D+%5Cfrac%7BN%7D%7B%5Cln+N%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\ll \frac{N}{n} = \frac{N}{\ln N}}"/> which is asymptotically the number of those <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x}"/> that are prime according to the Prime Number Theorem. This means that the vast majority of prime numbers have <em>no</em> worktape configuration that is unique to their accepting computation, not even close. Thus each configuration would be shared with many other primes—and most would be shared with many non-primes as well. Whereas many non-primes are composite for the same reason—such as all strings beginning with <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0}"/> being even—the intuition is that each prime has its distinct track of reasons that ought not to come together with other primes.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Less Space </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The HS paper notes that since the set of primes is not regular, it needs at least order-of <img alt="{\log\log(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog%5Clog%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log\log(n)}"/> space. This is a weak lower bound. </p>
<p>
Both the bound and the above intuition become sharper if we require that the input tape be <em>one-way</em> as well as read-only: its head cannot go left to re-read lower-order bits. Every non-regular language requires order-of <img alt="{\log(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log(n)}"/> space by such 1-way machines. </p>
<p>
If we write the prime numbers in unary notation—that is, <img alt="{\{0^m : m \text{ is prime}\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%7B0%5Em+%3A+m+%5Ctext%7B+is+prime%7D%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\{0^m : m \text{ is prime}\}}"/>—then we can prove they cannot be recognized by a machine <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{M}"/> in <img alt="{o(\log m)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bo%28%5Clog+m%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{o(\log m)}"/> space. Having the input tape be unary makes the whole computation depend on the configuration of <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{M}"/> as described above. In consequence, <img alt="{L(M)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BL%28M%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{L(M)}"/> has infinite arithmetic progressions of accepted strings. But by the celebrated theorem of Gustav Dirichlet, each such progression contains infinitely many primes as well as infinitely-many non-primes.  </p>
<p>
Scaling back from unary to binary seems to scale the space up to linear, so perhaps this result supports the HS conjecture. HS make related observations about log space and the density of the primes in the paper.  On the other hand, polynomial time could still be equal to logspace (with two-way input tape), which would make their conjecture wrong. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Another Prime Conjecture </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
We believe that the HS conjecture is hard, is related to some interesting questions, and could be false. That is, there might be some way to check that a number is prime in <img alt="{o(n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bo%28n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{o(n)}"/> space. Proving lower bounds on space remains, after many decades, hopeless.</p>
<p>
Here is a related conjecture. Using the same binary representation as above—where <img alt="{1011}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1011%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1011}"/> is 13 and <img alt="{10001}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B10001%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{10001}"/> is 17—Jeffrey Shallit has <a href="https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/~shallit/Talks/bc4.pdf">asked</a> whether we can determine whether a given finite automaton accepts <i>some</i> input so that it is a prime number. We believe it is still open. Let’s assume for the moment that it is true. Then we can solve some open questions in number theory related to primes. This problem unlike the HS is worth some money. For example, the above would pay 50 British pounds—about $66.62. </p>
<p>
Jeff points out that if the above is decidable then one can solve the famous problem: Are there any Fermat primes that are not known? Recall a Fermat prime is one of the form 	 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  2^{2^{\ell}} + 1. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++2%5E%7B2%5E%7B%5Cell%7D%7D+%2B+1.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  2^{2^{\ell}} + 1. "/></p>
<p>The largest one known is </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  2^{2^{4}} + 1 = 65,\!537." class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++2%5E%7B2%5E%7B4%7D%7D+%2B+1+%3D+65%2C%5C%21537.&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  2^{2^{4}} + 1 = 65,\!537."/></p>
<p>All such primes match the regular expression <img alt="{10^*1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B10%5E%2A1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{10^*1}"/> in binary notation, which is easy for a finite automaton to recognize. This expression matches numbers of the form <img alt="{2^k + 1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5Ek+%2B+1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2^k + 1}"/>, but as we discussed <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2018/06/01/almost-fermat-primes/">here</a>, they can be prime only when <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{k}"/> is a power of <img alt="{2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2}"/>.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Why are simple complexity questions about primes so hard? Why indeed?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-15T22:46:56Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T22:46:56Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="primes"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="complexity"/>
    <category term="conjecture"/>
    <category term="Hartmanis"/>
    <category term="Herbert Shank"/>
    <category term="space complexity"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-asynchrony-uncommitted-lower-bound/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-asynchrony-uncommitted-lower-bound/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The FLP Impossibility, Asynchronous Consensus Lower Bound via Uncommitted Configurations</title>
    <summary>In this third post, we conclude with the celebrated Fischer, Lynch, and Paterson impossibility result from 1985. It is the fundamental lower bound for consensus in the asynchronous model. Theorem 1 (FLP85): Any protocol $\mathcal{P}$ solving consensus in the asynchronous model that is resilient to even just one crash failure...</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-15T17:15:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T17:15:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Ittai Abraham</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2019-12-26T23:22:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-synchrony-uncommitted-lower-bound/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-synchrony-uncommitted-lower-bound/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Synchronous Consensus Lower Bound via Uncommitted Configurations</title>
    <summary>In this second post, we show the fundamental lower bound on the number of rounds for consensus protocols in the synchronous model. Theorem 1: Any protocol solving consensus in the synchronous model that is resilient to $t$ crash failures must have an execution with at least $t+1$ rounds. Bad news:...</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-15T17:05:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T17:05:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Ittai Abraham</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2019-12-26T23:22:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-consensus-model-for-FLP/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-15-consensus-model-for-FLP/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Consensus Lower Bounds via Uncommitted Configurations</title>
    <summary>In this series of three posts, we discuss two of the most important consensus lower bounds: Lamport, Fischer [1982]: any protocol solving consensus in the synchronous model that is resilient to $t$ crash failures must have an execution with at least $t+1$ rounds. Fischer, Lynch, and Patterson [1983, 1985]: any...</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-15T17:03:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T17:03:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Ittai Abraham</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2019-12-26T23:22:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/12/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2019/12/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>Figures show 11,000 academics have left UK universities in the three years since the Brexit referendum.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/education/2019/dec/01/lib-dems-brexit-brain-drain-eu-academics">Figures show 11,000 academics have left UK universities in the three years since the Brexit referendum</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2019-12-02/american-computer-expert-arrested-north-korea-talk-cryptocurrency">US arrests an American computer scientist for giving a talk at a conference</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103242730915859586"/>). It was in North Korea, on cryptocurrency, but from the story doesn’t appear to have covered anything that isn’t widely known elsewhere.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Mathematicians get riled up about mandatory diversity statements and recommendations that above-average contributions to diversity be used as a hard filter for all faculty job candidates (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103248639071738786"/>, <a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2019/11/19/mathematician-comes-out-against-mandatory-diversity-statements-while-others-say-they">via</a>, <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@pkra/103237286846736065">via2</a>, <a href="https://cybre.space/@zardoz/103310868212435260">via3</a>): <a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/201911/rnoti-p1778.pdf">Abigail Thompson sees mandated loyalty to political positions (such as prioritizing diversity) as anti-academic freedom</a>, kicking off the debate. <a href="https://ilaba.wordpress.com/2019/12/01/diversity-statements/">Izabella Laba disagrees but prefers institutional action to lip-service statements of good intentions</a> and argues that unrealistic expectations on faculty (like that they all be simultaneously outstanding in teaching, research, and now also diversity) can backfire by favoring the kind of male faculty member who takes advantage of an unpaid wife as his assistant. <a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/202001/rnoti-o1.pdf">Many others weigh in</a> in the letters to the editor of the <em>Notices</em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.chronicle.com/article/5-Ways-to-Welcome-Women-to/247541">Five ways to welcome women to computer science</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103256355399857427"/>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://theaggie.org/2019/12/05/yuval-peres-math-professor-with-series-of-sexual-misconduct-allegations-levied-against-him-gives-lecture-at-uc-davis/">Davis student newspaper provides thorough roundup of sexual harassment charges against Yuval Peres</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103259258824223410"/>). They missed the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Sockpuppet_investigations/Pedantisch/Archive">side drama of sockpuppets and meatpuppets cleaning this from his Wikipedia article</a>, though, or maybe omitted it for lack of evidence connecting it to Peres himself. This is sad. Why would someone with so much to give to the field be so self-destructive and so destructive of the lives and careers of others around him?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>More stupid commercial journal publisher tricks (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103264128297632805"/>): Wiley won’t honor my institutional subscription unless I enable third-party cookies in my browser. So I can</p>

    <ol>
      <li>
        <p>decrease my browser security on all sites,</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>not read papers by László Babai on J. Graph Theory,</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>ask my librarian for a copy, making much more work and delay for all but maybe letting the publisher know how much negative value-added they’re providing, or</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>become a pirate.</p>
      </li>
    </ol>

    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sci-Hub">Sci-Hub</a> to the rescue! Yo ho!</p>

    <p>Also while I’m picking on Wiley, how did <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/cpe.5484">He et al., “A polynomial‐time algorithm for simple undirected graph isomorphism”</a> ever pass peer review for their journal <em>Concurrency and Computation, Practice and Experience</em>, or even a basic sanity check that it has a coherent topic that fits the mission of the journal?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/roots-of-unity/the-surprising-link-between-recreational-math-and-undecidability/">The surprising link between recreational math and undecidability</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103267941967518229"/>). Evelyn Lamb describes how a seemingly isolated fact about Fibonacci numbers () led to Matiyasevich’s solution to Hilbert’s 10th problem, that there is no general algorithm for solving Diophantine equations.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.maureeneppstein.com/mve_journal/?p=2028">My mother has a new book of poetry coming out</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103273857130169711"/>). I think this is her fifth, after Earthward (Finishing Line Press, 2014), Rogue Wave at Glass Beach (March Street Press, 2009), Quickening (March Street Press, 2007), and A Place Called Home (Monday Press, 1995).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Osculating_circles_of_the_Archimedean_spiral.svg">This image by Adam Majewski</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103279309793264877"/>) shows the osculating circles of an Archimedean spiral. The spiral itself is not shown, but you can see it anyway, where the circles become dense.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Osculating circles of the Archimedean spiral" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2019/archimedean-osculation.svg"/></p>

    <p>It is not unusual that the circles nest. By the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tait%E2%80%93Kneser_theorem">Tait–Kneser theorem</a> this happens whenever the curvature along a curve is monotonic. And on most smooth curves, the curvature is monotonic except at a small number of points called vertices.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://chalkdustmagazine.com/front-page-banner/constructing-the-cover-of-issue-10/">Chalkdust magazine provides a compass-and-straightedge construction for the girih pattern on the cover of a recent issue</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103284659404495472"/>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://twitter.com/textfiles/status/1204428311553642496">How archive.org preserves the history of the web, and why you should care</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103291205125122328"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21764592">via</a>). Meanwhile, <a href="https://modsandmembersblog.wordpress.com/2019/12/08/verizon-yahoo-bad-form/">Verizon sabotages efforts to archive Yahoo Groups content, in the face of their plans to shut much of it down</a> (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21737696">via</a>, <a href="https://boingboing.net/2019/12/08/oath-makes-you-swear-2.html">via2</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://randomascii.wordpress.com/2019/12/08/on2-again-now-in-wmi/"> in Windows Management Instrumentation</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103299014968956821"/>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21743424">via</a>). This is why understanding algorithm analysis is important: even when the constant factors are very small (here, a nine-instruction loop), quadratic time can mean significant delays. The post also introduces “Dawson’s first law of computing:  is the sweet spot of badly scaling algorithms: fast enough to make it into production, but slow enough to make things fall down once it gets there.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Two recently-posted geometry puzzles (neither of which I have seriously attempted to answer (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103304781327067493"/>):</p>

    <ol>
      <li>
        <p><a href="https://discrete-notes.github.io/polygon%20problem">If you expand a convex polygon along one coordinate axis while leaving the other coordinate unchanged, can the original polygon always fit into the expanded copy (perhaps with some rotation or translation)?</a></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/can-you-solve-a-particularly-prismatic-puzzle/">How many different integer rectangular cuboids have (ignoring units) volume = surface area?</a></p>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/permutations/">John Baez collects more than you wanted to know about the statistics of random permutations</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103310641851251562"/>). The really pretty ones are Part 3 puzzle 8: What is the probability that a chosen element of an -element permutation lies in a cycle of length ? And part 6 puzzle 7 (don’t ask me how the numbering works): What is the expected number of -cycles in a random -element permutation?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://wild.maths.org/folding-fractions">Folding fractions</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/103314218243317735"/>). There’s a standard compass-and-straightedge construction for dividing a line segment evenly into a given number of smaller segments, and origami folding constructions are (depending on the model of what is allowed) at least as powerful, so it shouldn’t be surprising that you can fold arbitrary even subdivisions of the side of an origami square. But this construction of  from  by Kazuo Haga is particularly elegant.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-15T15:41:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T15:41:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2019-12-21T08:46:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/182</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/182" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-182 |  The Limitations of Few Qubits: One-way and Two-way Quantum Finite Automata and the Group Word Problem | 

	Zachary Remscrim</title>
    <summary>The two-way finite automaton with quantum and classical states (2QCFA), defined by Ambainis and Watrous, is a model of quantum computation whose quantum part is extremely limited; however, as they showed, 2QCFA are surprisingly powerful: a 2QCFA with only a single-qubit can recognize the language $L_{pal}=\{w \in \{a,b\}^*:w \text{ is a palindrome}\}$ with bounded-error in expected exponential time. We prove that their result essentially cannot be improved upon: a 2QCFA (of any finite size) cannot recognize $L_{pal}$ with bounded-error in expected time $2^{o(n)}$, on inputs of length $n$. To our knowledge, this is the first example of a language that can be recognized with bounded-error by a 2QCFA in exponential time but not in subexponential time. A key tool in our result is a generalization to 2QCFA of a technical lemma that was used by Dwork and Stockmeyer to prove a lower bound on the expected running time of any two-way probabilistic finite automaton that recognizes a non-regular language with bounded-error. 

Furthermore, we prove strong lower bounds on the expected running time of any 2QCFA that recognizes a group word problem with bounded-error. In a recent paper, we showed that 2QCFA can recognize, with bounded-error, a broad class of group word problems in expected exponential time, and a more narrow class of group word problems in expected polynomial time. As a consequence, we can now exhibit a large family of natural languages that can be recognized with bounded-error by a 2QCFA in expected exponential time, but not in expected subexponential time. Moreover, we obtain significant progress towards a precise classification of those group word problems that can be recognized with bounded-error in expected polynomial time by a 2QCFA.

We also consider the one-way measure-once quantum finite automaton (1QFA), defined by Moore and Crutchfield, as well as a natural generalization to one-way measure-once finite automata with quantum and classical states (1QCFA). We precisely classify those groups whose word problem may be recognized with positive one-sided error (for both the bounded-error and unbounded-error cases) by a 1QFA or 1QCFA with any particular number of quantum states and any particular number of classical states; we also obtain partial results in the negative one-sided error case. As an immediate corollary, we show that allowing a 1QFA or 1QCFA to have even a single additional quantum or classical state enlarges the class of languages that may be recognized with positive one-sided error (of either type).</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-15T06:18:59Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-15T06:18:59Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/181</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/181" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-181 |  A Separator Theorem for Hypergraphs and a CSP-SAT Algorithm | 

	Navid Talebanfard, 

	Michal Koucky, 

	Vojtech Rodl</title>
    <summary>We show that for every $r \ge 2$ there exists $\epsilon_r &gt; 0$ such that any $r$-uniform hypergraph on $m$ edges with bounded vertex degree has a set of at most $(\frac{1}{2} - \epsilon_r)m$ edges the removal of which breaks the hypergraph into connected components with at most $m/2$ edges. We use this to give a satisfiability algorithm for $n$-variable $(d, k)$-CSPs in which every variable appears in at most $r$ constraints in time $d^{(1 - \epsilon_r)n}$ where $\epsilon_r$ depends only on $r$, provided that $k$ is small enough as a function of $m$. We will also show that unsatisfiable $(2, k)$-CSPs with variable frequency $r$ can be refuted in tree-like resolution in size $2^{(1 - \epsilon_r)n}$. Furthermore for Tseitin formulas on graphs with degree at most $k$ (which are $(2, k)$-CSPs) we give a deterministic algorithm finding such a refutation.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-13T14:39:31Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-13T14:39:31Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7376087648863245436</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7376087648863245436/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/why-is-there-no-all-encompassing-term.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7376087648863245436" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7376087648863245436" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/why-is-there-no-all-encompassing-term.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Why is there no all-encompassing term for a course on Models of Computation?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In my <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/what-do-you-call-your-ugrad-non.html">last blog post</a> I asked my readers to leave comments saying what the name of the course that has some of Regular Languages, Context Free Languages  Decideability, P, NP (any maybe other stuff) in it.  I suspected there would be many different names and their were. I was able to put all but 6 into 4 equivalence classes. So that's 10 names. Thats a lot  especially compared to<br/>
<br/>
(Introduction to) Algorithms<br/>
<br/>
and<br/>
<br/>
(Introduction to) Cryptography<br/>
<br/>
which I suspect have far fewer names. One commenter pointed out that the reason for the many different names is that there are many versions of the course. That's not quite an explanation since there are also many different versions of Cryptography---at UMCP  crypto is cross listed in THREE departments (CS, Math, EE) and its taught by 6 or so different people who don't talk to each other (I am one of them). I think Algorithms is more uniform across colleges.<br/>
<br/>
I think that terms Algorithms and Cryptography are both rather broad and can accommodate many versions of the courses, whereas no term seems to be agreed upon to encompass the DFA etc course.<br/>
Even saying DFA etc is not quite right since some of the courses spend little or even no time on DFA's.<br/>
<br/>
Below is a list of all the names I got and some comments. Note that some schools appear twice since they have two courses along these lines.<br/>
<br/>
-----------------------------------------<br/>
TITLE: (Introduction to) Theory of Computation:<br/>
<br/>
Swarthmore:                                            Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
UCSD:                                                     Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
Saint Michaels:                                        Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
Univ of Washington: Introduction to the Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
Waterloo:                  Introduction to the Theory of Computing<br/>
<br/>
COMMENT: Theory of Computation could have been the term that encompasses all of these courses. I speculate that it didn't catch on since it sounds too much like computability theory which is only one part of the course.<br/>
<br/>
------------------------<br/>
TITLE: Formal Languages and XXX<br/>
<br/>
CMU:                                                Formal Languages, Automata, and Computability<br/>
<br/>
Florida Tech:                                    Formal Languages and Automata Theory<br/>
<br/>
UC-Irvine:                                        Formal Languages and Automata Theory<br/>
<br/>
Univ of Chicago:    Introduction to Formal Languages<br/>
<br/>
University of Bucharest:                 Formal Language and Automata<br/>
<br/>
TU Darmstadt:                                Formal Foundations of CS I: Automata, Formal Languages, and Decidability<br/>
<br/>
TUK Germany:                               Formal Languages and Computability<br/>
<br/>
COMMENT: The title makes it sound like they don't cover P and NP. I do not know if thats true; however, I speculate that, it could never be the encompassing term.<br/>
<br/>
Spell Check things Automata and Computability are not words, but I've googled them and they seem to be words.<br/>
<br/>
--------------------------<br/>
TITLE: Computability/Decidability and Complexity/Intractability<br/>
<br/>
Reed College: Computability and Complexity<br/>
<br/>
Caltech:          Decidability and Intractability<br/>
<br/>
COMMENT: The title makes it sound like they don't cover regular or context free languages. I do not know if that's true; however, I speculate that, since the terms sound that way, they never caught on as the general term.<br/>
<br/>
Spellecheck thinks that neither Decidability nor Decideability is a word. Google seems to say that I should leave out the e, so I will.<br/>
<br/>
------------------------------<br/>
TITLE:  Blah MODELS Blah<br/>
<br/>
Tel-Aviv (a long time ago) Computational Models<br/>
<br/>
UIUC:                               Algorithms and Models of Computation (also has some algorithms in it)<br/>
<br/>
Waterloo:                                                   Models of Computation (enriched version)<br/>
<br/>
COMMENT: Models of Computation sounds like a good name for the course! Too bad it didn't catch on.  It would also be able to withstand changes in the content like more on parallelism or more on communication complexity.<br/>
<br/>
------------------------------<br/>
TITLE: MISC<br/>
<br/>
CMU:                                          Great Ideas in Theoretical Computer Science<br/>
<br/>
UCLouvain (Belgium)                Calculabilite (Computability)<br/>
<br/>
Moscow Inst. of  Phy. and Tech.: Mathematical logic and Theory of Algorithms<br/>
<br/>
Portland State University:            Computational Structures<br/>
<br/>
Germany:                                     Informatik III (Not all of Germany)<br/>
<br/>
Univ of Chicago:                         Introduction to Complexity<br/>
<br/>
COMMENT: All of these terms are to narrow to have served as a general term.<br/>
<div>
<br/></div>
<br/>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-12T20:24:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-12T20:24:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T09:31:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://theorydish.blog/?p=1541</id>
    <link href="https://theorydish.blog/2019/12/09/quantum-dna-sequencing-the-ultimate-hardness-hypothesis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Quantum DNA sequencing &amp; the ultimate hardness hypothesis</title>
    <summary>Longest common subsequence (LCS) and edit distance (ED) are fundamental similarity measures of interest to genomic applications (insertions/deletions/substitutions are a pretty good proxy for both mutations and read errors). The fastest known algorithms for computing the LCS/ED between two -character strings run in nearly quadratic time. Breakthroughs in fine-grained complexity [BI18][AHWW16] from the last few years provide some nice formal barriers further progress: in particular, substantially faster algorithms would refute NC-SETH, the hypothesis that given an NC circuit with input bits,  deciding if the circuit has any satisfying assignment requires time. (Note that this is a weaker, aka safer, hypothesis than the standard SETH.)   Quantum algorithms for edit distance? One way to try to circumvent the computational barriers is by approximation algorithms (see my blog post). A different approach is to go with quantum algorithms: Grover’s search can solve NC-SAT in time. Even those of us less skeptic than Gil Kalai can probably agree that quadratic quantum speedups won’t be practical anytime soon. But in theory, I find the question of whether we can design subquadratic quantum algorithms for edit distance very interesting (see also [BEG+18]). Alas, even with the power of quantum computers we don’t know any truly [...]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Longest common subsequence (LCS) and edit distance (ED) are fundamental similarity measures of interest to genomic applications (insertions/deletions/substitutions are a pretty good proxy for both mutations and read errors). The fastest known algorithms for computing the LCS/ED between two <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n"/>-character strings run in nearly quadratic time. Breakthroughs in fine-grained complexity <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1412.0348">[BI18]</a><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1511.06022">[AHWW16]</a> from the last few years provide some nice formal barriers further progress: in particular, substantially faster algorithms would refute <em>NC-SETH</em>, the hypothesis that given an NC circuit with <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n"/> input bits,  deciding if the circuit has any satisfying assignment requires <img alt="2^{(1-o(1))n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2%5E%7B%281-o%281%29%29n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="2^{(1-o(1))n}"/> time. (Note that this is a weaker, aka safer, hypothesis than the standard SETH.)</p>
<p> </p>
<h2>Quantum algorithms for edit distance?</h2>
<p>One way to try to circumvent the computational barriers is by approximation algorithms (see my <a href="https://theorydish.blog/2018/07/20/approximating-edit-distance/">blog post</a>). A different approach is to go with quantum algorithms: Grover’s search can solve NC-SAT in <img alt="2^{n/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=2%5E%7Bn%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="2^{n/2}"/> time. Even those of us less skeptic than <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/11/13/gils-collegial-quantum-supremacy-skepticism-faq/">Gil Kalai</a> can probably agree that quadratic quantum speedups won’t be practical anytime soon. But in theory, I find the question of whether we can design subquadratic quantum algorithms for edit distance very interesting (see also <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.04178">[BEG+18]</a>).</p>
<p>Alas, even with the power of quantum computers we don’t know any truly subquadratic algorithms for computing LCS/ED. On the other hand, it is not clear how to rule out even linear-time algorithms. A few weeks ago, Buhrman, Patro, and Speelman, posted a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.05686">paper</a> that gives a <img alt="n^{3/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B3%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n^{3/2}"/> quantum <em>query complexity </em>lower bound for LCS/ED.</p>
<blockquote><p>Open Problem: Close the <img alt="n^{3/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B3%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n^{3/2}"/> vs <img alt="n^2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n^2"/> gap for quantum query complexity of ED/LCS.</p></blockquote>
<p>What is “query complexity” of ED/LCS? Buhrman et al. consider the following query model: In LCS, we want a <strong>maximum monotone matching</strong> between the characters of the two strings, where we can match two characters if they’re identical. Now suppose that in the query complexity problem we still want to find a maximum monotone matching, but instead of the character-equality graph (which is a union of disjoint cliques), we have an arbitrary bipartite graph, and <strong>given a pair of vertices, the oracle tells you if there is an edge between them</strong>.</p>
<p>This model may seem a bit counter-intuitive at first since the graphs may not correspond to any pair of strings; and indeed other models have been considered before <a href="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=321922">[UAH76]</a><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1005.4033">[AKO10]</a>. But it turns out that this model is well-motivated by the NC-SETH lower bound (see discussion below).</p>
<p> </p>
<h2>The ultimate hardness hypothesis</h2>
<p>What does the <img alt="n^{3/2}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n%5E%7B3%2F2%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="n^{3/2}"/> query complexity lower bound mean for algorithms on actual strings? Instead of a black box oracle, our algorithms have access to an NC-circuit that implements it. Intuitively, we don’t know how to do very much with white box circuits, so it seems plausible to hypothesize that the running time will be lower bound by the query complexity. In some sense, this is a special case of the following <em>ultimate hardness hypothesis </em>that unifies a lot of the computational hardness assumptions that we like to assume but have no idea how to prove (e.g. P!=NP, P!=BQP, NC-SETH, FP!=PPAD, etc):</p>
<blockquote><p>[Ultimate Hardness Hypothesis] For every problem, the white-box computational complexity is lower bounded by the black-box query complexity.”</p></blockquote>
<p>In communication complexity similar statements are known and are called simulation/lifting theorems (see e.g. <a href="https://theory.stanford.edu/~mika/thesis.pdf">Mika’s thesis</a>). For computational complexity, there are obvious counter examples such as “decide if the oracle can be implemented by a small circuit”. So it only makes sense to continue to assume the ultimate hardness hypothesis for “reasonable problems” instead of “every problem”.</p>
<p>But Burhman et al. identify the following variant of the ultimate hardness hypothesis which I find very interesting. It is defined with respect to a function <img alt="T:\{0,1\}^{2^n} \rightarrow \{0,1\}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=T%3A%5C%7B0%2C1%5C%7D%5E%7B2%5En%7D+%5Crightarrow+%5C%7B0%2C1%5C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="T:\{0,1\}^{2^n} \rightarrow \{0,1\}"/> which takes as input the truth-table of a circuit and outputs True or False. Roughly, they hypothesize that:</p>
<blockquote><p>[Burhman et al.-QSETH, paraphrased] For <em>every</em> <img alt="T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=T&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="T"/>, deciding if <img alt="T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=T&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="T"/> is true or false is as hard whether we’re given the actual circuit, or only the guarantee that the oracle is implemented by a small circuit”</p></blockquote>
<p>At a first read, I thought that arguments a-la impossibility of obfuscation <a href="https://www.iacr.org/archive/crypto2001/21390001.pdf">[BGI+01]</a> should refute this hypothesis, but a few weeks later I still don’t know how to prove it. Do you?</p>
<p> </p>
<h2>A tip for the upcoming holidays</h2>
<p>During my postdoc, I worked on the quantum query complexity of ED/LCS with Shalev Ben-David, Rolando La Placa, and John Wright. I was a bit bummed to find out that we got scooped by Buhrman et al, but I know of at least 3 other groups that were also scooped by the same paper, so at least we’re in good company <img alt="&#x1F642;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s0.wp.com/wp-content/mu-plugins/wpcom-smileys/twemoji/2/72x72/1f642.png" style="height: 1em;"/></p>
<p>At the time, a fellow postdoc from Psychology asked me what I was working on. I resisted the temptation to try to explain the various quantum variants of NC-SETH, and instead told him I was working on “DNA sequencing with quantum computers”. His reaction was priceless. Regardless of what you’re actually working on, try this line during the holidays when your relatives ask you about your work.</p>
<p> </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-09T18:20:46Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-09T18:20:46Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>aviad.rubinstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://theorydish.blog</id>
      <logo>https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/cropped-nightdish1.jpg?w=32</logo>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Stanford's CS Theory Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Theory Dish</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:21:14Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-693865784966232415</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/693865784966232415/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/what-do-you-call-your-ugrad-non.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/693865784966232415" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/693865784966232415" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/12/what-do-you-call-your-ugrad-non.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What do you call your ugrad non-algorithms theory course?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am in the process of reviewing<br/>
<br/>
<i>                     What can be computed: A Practical Guide to the Theory of Computation</i><br/>
<i>                     by John MacCormick</i><br/>
<br/>
<br/>
and I need YOUR help for the first SENTENCE.  I began by saying<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
                    This is a text book for a course on <i>Formal Language Theory</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
but then I realized that this is not what we call the course at UMCP. Then I got to thinking: what do other schools call it? I have the following so far:<br/>
<br/>
UMCP: Elementary Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
Harvard: Introduction to Theory of Computation<br/>
<br/>
MIT: Automata, Computability, and, Complexity<br/>
<br/>
Clark: Automata Theory<br/>
<br/>
(My spellcheck does not think Automata is a word. Also Computability. Usually I listen to my spellcheckers, but I checked and YES, I spelled them right.)<br/>
<br/>
For some other schools I either hit a place I needed an account, or I just got titles without a description so I could not be sure.<br/>
<br/>This is where YOU come in!<br/>
<br/>
Please leave comments with your school and the title of the course at your school that covers a reasonable overlap with: Regular Sets, Context Free Sets, Decidable and Undecidble and r.e. sets, P, NP, perhaps other complexity classes, and NP-completeness. Its FINE if your answer is one of the above ones, or one of the other comments--- I plan to later set this up as a pigeonhole principle problem.<br/>
<br/>
I suspect that courses in algorithms are called <i>Algorithms </i>or <i>Introduction to Algorithms.</i><br/>
<i><br/></i>
I suspect that courses in cryptography are called <i>Cryptography </i><i> </i>or <i>Intro to Cryptography.</i><br/>
<br/>
<br/>
Why does the non-algorithm, non-crypto theory course have more names?<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
<i><br/></i>
<br/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-09T04:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-09T04:00:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>GASARCH</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03615736448441925334</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T09:31:53Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=16454</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/12/08/hctor-garcia-molina-1953-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Héctor Garcia-Molina, 1953–2019</title>
    <summary>We all lost a great person Cropped from Mexican NotiCyTI obit Héctor Garcia-Molina died just before Thanksgiving. He was a computer scientist and Professor in both the Departments of Computer Science and Electrical Engineering at Stanford University. Today Ken and I write in sadness about his passing and to express some personal appreciations. We at […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>We all lost a great person</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/29-11-19-molina.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-16456" height="180" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/29-11-19-molina.jpg?w=165&amp;h=180" width="165"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Cropped from Mexican NotiCyTI <a href="https://noticyti.com/politica-cyt-i/742-muere-h%C3%A9ctor-garc%C3%ADa-molina,-el-mexicano-que-contribuy%C3%B3-al-estrellato-de-google-y-cisco.html">obit</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Héctor Garcia-Molina <a href="https://news.stanford.edu/2019/12/06/hector-garcia-molina-influential-computer-scientist-database-expert-dies-65/">died</a> just before Thanksgiving. He was a computer scientist and Professor in both the Departments of Computer Science and Electrical Engineering at Stanford University.</p>
<p>
Today Ken and I write in sadness about his passing and to express some personal appreciations.<br/>
<span id="more-16454"/></p>
<p>
We at GLL have talked about him before. See <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2015/03/08/lint-for-math/">this</a> for his story about the fun of using an IBM mainframe for teaching. Or see <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2011/11/03/whos-afraid-of-arrows-paradox/">this</a> for a story about Héctor and meetings.</p>
<p>
I, Dick, had the pleasure to have worked with him, while we were both faculty at Princeton in the 1980’s and beyond.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> His Clock </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Héctor was the chair of the Stanford Computer Science Department from January 2001 to December 2004. Stanford then rotated the chair so all took their turn. I know that he “hated” being an administrator in general. But of course being a team player he took his turn. </p>
<p>
One way to see his real feelings about being a chair was to look at the clock his students constructed for him. The clock was a digital timer that counted down the seconds that remained in his term as the chair. It started at roughly 126227808. I am sure he did fine, but the clock was a statement. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> His Worst Paper </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
While Héctor was at Princeton we worked together on a project—the <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2010/05/20/sorting-out-chess-endgames/">MMM</a> project. It led to one of his least cited papers—a 1984 <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/1676454">paper</a> with me and Jacobo Valdes. OK, it has 48 citations according to IEEE. The idea of the project was to use memory rather than processors to speed up computations. He was a joy to work with: he was careful, and thoughtful, and just fun to work with on any project. </p>
<p>
We did write a second <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=AMrcBwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA565&amp;lpg=PA565&amp;dq=The+Massive+Memory+Machine+Project&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=_QFT07G56P&amp;sig=ACfU3U0-KV060yO3PHRllCnj3Y5o10BX-w&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwj7o67o-abmAhXHwFkKHRfzDs4Q6AEwDXoECAkQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=The Massive Memory Machine Project&amp;f=false">paper</a> with Richard Cullingford instead of Valdes, which Héctor presented at a meeting on knowledge-based management systems. The above Google Books link goes to the end with a <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=AMrcBwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA565&amp;lpg=PA565&amp;dq=The+Massive+Memory+Machine+Project&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=_QFT07G56P&amp;sig=ACfU3U0-KV060yO3PHRllCnj3Y5o10BX-w&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwj7o67o-abmAhXHwFkKHRfzDs4Q6AEwDXoECAkQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=The Massive Memory Machine Project&amp;f=false">discussion</a> in which a simple issue was raised—we paraphrase:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Won’t it take forever just to write all zeros to the memory? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Héctor had a scientist’s answer: the project was still not at the prototype stage so he didn’t know. He said the project should be viewed as a scientific experiment to find out. Maybe he also had an inkling that what was coming was a decade of breakthroughs in CPU design and parallel/pipeline processing after all. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> His Predictions </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Héctor was unparalleled at seeing the future. I always thought that one of his abilities, one that set him apart, was his ability to predict directions of research. This allowed him, and his students, to write early papers in research areas before they became hot. This is one of the talents that made him so amazing.</p>
<p>
I recall way before the world wide web was created he had students working on adding links to documents. I recall a talk by one of his students at Princeton that discussed what we now call URLs. One question that was raised during the talk was: How were the links going to be created? There was a lively discussion about this. Could they be created automatically? If not why would people take the time to create the links? Indeed.</p>
<p>
Héctor saw that links would be created. That people would take the effort to create them. I must admit that he was right, and he saw the future better than most. I wish I had a fraction of his ability to see directions like he did.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Guiding Students </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Héctor told me that when he first got to Stanford the fund managers and investors roamed the halls. They would ask anyone they could if they had an idea for a company or a startup. It was a constant issue that Héctor had to deal with. They were continually trying to steal away students. </p>
<p>
He told me he felt like he was the head of an abbey and was always having to protect his charges within the walls.</p>
<p>
When the impetus came from within it was different. Of course, Héctor was the advisor of Sergey Brin at the time he and Larry Page conceived Google. Brin and Page found that their search engine prototypes were so good the dataflow was constantly straining Stanford’s machines. They needed to scrounge for more disks and processors to mount their servers. Héctor already oversaw the Stanford Digital Libraries Project and he <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2018/09/04/8-surprising-facts-you-might-not-know-about-googles-early-days.html">arranged</a> for funds to purchase spare parts for the data servers. </p>
<p>
It is interesting that in this 2001 <a href="https://sigmod.org/publications/interviews/pdf/hector-final1.pdf">interview</a> in the <em>SIGMOD Record</em>, Héctor did not have a high opinion of the industrial side of his area:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Again, I don’t think industry really does very much research. They come up with an idea and they try to sell it. If it was a good idea, maybe they will make money. Even if it was a bad idea, if they have good marketing people, they might still make money and we never know … I don’t think they have an advantage over [academics] in testing the ideas and evaluating them and performing measurements and really understanding what are the right techniques. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
In the same interview, he had sage advice for students after completing their PhDs and during the tenure process, mainly on the side of not trying to play the system but focus on doing what you love.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Stanford Home Team </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Héctor had been a graduate student at Stanford. So his return there as a professor was a kind of homecoming. He was a home-team player in many senses. One of them is shown by this photo:</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hector-garcia-molina-sports.jpg"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-16457" height="200" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2019/12/hector-garcia-molina-sports.jpg?w=300&amp;h=200" width="300"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Stanford University obituary <a href="https://news.stanford.edu/2019/12/06/hector-garcia-molina-influential-computer-scientist-database-expert-dies-65/">source</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
He was a registered Stanford sports photographer. He also taught a course at Stanford on photography. We don’t know if he had special insights on detecting “deepfake” photos and videos. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Our condolences go to all his family. Héctor you will be missed. You are missed. </p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-08T23:27:02Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-08T23:27:02Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="databases"/>
    <category term="Hector Garcia-Molina"/>
    <category term="memorial"/>
    <category term="memory machines"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/180</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/180" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-180 |  Covering Codes for Insertions and Deletions | 

	Andreas Lenz, 

	Cyrus Rashtchian, 

	Paul Siegel, 

	Eitan Yaakobi</title>
    <summary>A covering code is a set of codewords with the property that the union of balls, suitably defined, around these codewords covers an entire space. Generally, the goal is to find the covering code with the minimum size codebook. While most prior work on covering codes has focused on the Hamming metric, we consider the problem of designing covering codes defined in terms of  insertions and  deletions. First, we provide new sphere-covering lower bounds on the minimum possible size of such codes. Then, we provide new existential upper bounds on the size of optimal covering codes for a single insertion or a single deletion that are tight up to a constant factor. Finally, we derive improved upper bounds for covering codes using $R\geq 2$ insertions or deletions. We prove that codes exist with density that is only a factor $O(R \log R)$ larger than the lower bounds for all fixed $R$. In particular, our upper bounds have an optimal dependence on the word length, and we achieve asymptotic density matching the best known bounds for Hamming distance covering codes.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-08T09:03:55Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-08T09:03:55Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4279</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/12/07/postdoc-position-at-bocconi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc Position at Bocconi</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am recruiting for two postdoctoral positions, each for one year renewable to a second, to work with me at Bocconi University on topics related to average-case analysis of algorithms, approximation algorithms, and combinatorial constructions. The positions have a very … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2019/12/07/postdoc-position-at-bocconi/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I am recruiting for two postdoctoral positions, each for one year renewable to a second, to work with me at Bocconi University on topics related to average-case analysis of algorithms, approximation algorithms, and combinatorial constructions. </p>
<p>The positions have a very competitive salary and relocation benefits. Funding for travel is available.</p>
<p>Application information is at <a href="https://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/3ecc85da-ac66-46ac-9db7-09ac0ef9b715/Call-2ADR-01B1-Bidsa-Erc.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&amp;CVID=mUjaHAv">this link</a>. The deadline  is <b>December 15</b>. If you apply, please also send me an email (L.Trevisan at unibocconi.it) to let me know.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-07T23:07:19Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-07T23:07:19Z</published>
    <category term="theory"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/179</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/179" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-179 |  Towards Optimal Separations between Quantum and Randomized Query Complexities | 

	Avishay Tal</title>
    <summary>The query model offers a concrete setting where quantum algorithms are provably superior to randomized algorithms. Beautiful results by Bernstein-Vazirani, Simon,  Aaronson, and others presented partial Boolean functions that can be computed by quantum algorithms making much fewer queries compared to their randomized analogs. To date, separations of $O(1)$ vs. $\sqrt{N}$ between quantum and randomized query complexities remain the state-of-the-art (where $N$ is the input length), leaving open the question of whether $O(1)$ vs. $N^{1/2+\Omega(1)}$ separations are possible?

We answer this question in the affirmative. Our separating problem is a variant of the Aaronson-Ambainis $k$-fold Forrelation problem. We show that our variant:
(1) Can be solved by a quantum algorithm making $2^{O(k)}$ queries to the inputs.
(2) Requires at least $\tilde{\Omega}(N^{2(k-1)/(3k-1)})$ queries for any randomized algorithm.

For any constant $\varepsilon&gt;0$, this gives a  $O(1)$  vs. $N^{2/3-\varepsilon}$ separation between the quantum and randomized query complexities of partial Boolean functions. 

Our proof is Fourier analytical and uses new bounds on the Fourier spectrum of classical decision trees, which could be of independent interest. 

Looking forward, we conjecture that the Fourier bounds could be further improved in a precise manner, and show that such conjectured bounds imply optimal $O(1)$ vs. $N^{1-\varepsilon}$ separations between the quantum and randomized query complexities of partial Boolean functions.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-07T14:25:04Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-07T14:25:04Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/178</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/178" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-178 |  Almost Tight Lower Bounds on Regular Resolution Refutations of Tseitin Formulas for All Constant-Degree Graphs | 

	Dmitry Itsykson, 

	Artur Riazanov, 

	Petr Smirnov, 

	Danil Sagunov</title>
    <summary>We show that the size of any regular resolution refutation of Tseitin formula $T(G,c)$ based on a graph $G$ is at least $2^{\Omega(tw(G)/\log n)}$, where $n$ is the number of vertices in $G$ and $tw(G)$ is the treewidth of $G$. For constant degree graphs there is known upper bound $2^{O(tw(G))}$ [AR11, GTT18], so our lower bound is tight up to a logarithmic factor in the exponent.

In order to prove this result we show that any regular resolution proof of Tseitin formula $T(G,c)$ of size $S$ can be converted to a read-once branching program computing satisfiable Tseitin formula $T(G,c')$ of size $S^{O(\log n)}$. Then we show that any read-once branching program computing satisfiable Tseitin formula $T(G,c')$ has size at least $2^{\Omega(tw(G))}$; the latter improves the recent result of Glinskih and Itsykson [GI19].</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-07T01:51:51Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-07T01:51:51Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-06-dce-the-three-scalability-bottlenecks-of-state-machine-replication/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2019-12-06-dce-the-three-scalability-bottlenecks-of-state-machine-replication/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Data, Consensus, Execution: Three Scalability Bottlenecks for State Machine Replication</title>
    <summary>If anyone asks you: how can I scale my State Machine Replication (Blockchain) system? You should answer back with a question: what is your bottleneck? Is it Data, Consensus or Execution? Data: Shipping the commands to all the replicas. For example, if a block contains 1MB of commands, then you...</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-06T17:05:00Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-06T17:05:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Ittai Abraham</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2019-12-26T23:22:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/177</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/177" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR19-177 |  Pseudo-deterministic Streaming | 

	Shafi Goldwasser, 

	Ofer Grossman, 

	Sidhanth Mohanty, 

	David Woodruff</title>
    <summary>A pseudo-deterministic algorithm is a (randomized) algorithm which, when run multiple times on the same input, with high probability outputs the same result on all executions. Classic streaming algorithms, such as those for finding heavy hitters, approximate counting, $\ell_2$ approximation, finding a nonzero entry in a vector (for turnstile algorithms) are not pseudo-deterministic. For example, in the instance of finding a nonzero entry in a vector, for any known low-space algorithm $A$, there exists a stream $x$ so that running $A$ twice on $x$ (using different randomness) would with high probability result in two different entries as the output.

In this work, we study whether it is inherent that these algorithms output different values on different executions. That is, we ask whether these problems have low-memory pseudo-deterministic algorithms. For instance, we show that there is no low-memory pseudo-deterministic algorithm for finding a nonzero entry in a vector (given in a turnstile fashion), and also that there is no low-dimensional pseudo-deterministic sketching algorithm for $\ell_2$ norm estimation.  We also exhibit problems which do have low memory pseudo-deterministic algorithms but no low memory deterministic algorithm, such as outputting a nonzero row of a matrix, or outputting a basis for the row-span of a matrix.

We also investigate multi-pseudo-deterministic algorithms: algorithms which with high probability output one of a few options. We show the first lower bounds for such algorithms. This implies that there are streaming problems such that every low space algorithm for the problem must have inputs where there are many valid outputs, all with a significant probability of being outputted.</summary>
    <updated>2019-12-06T14:44:41Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-06T14:44:41Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2019-12-27T10:20:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1227</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1227" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for November 2019</title>
    <summary>We hit the mother-lode of property testing papers this month. Stick with us, as we cover 10 (!) papers that appeared online in November. EDIT: We actually have 11 papers, check out Optimal Adaptive Detection of Monotone Patterns at the bottom. Testing noisy linear functions for sparsity, by Xue Chen, Anindya De, and Rocco A. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We hit the mother-lode of property testing papers this month. Stick with us, as we cover 10 (!) papers that appeared online in November.</p>



<p>EDIT: We actually have 11 papers, check out <em>Optimal Adaptive Detection of Monotone Patterns</em> at the bottom.</p>



<p><strong>Testing noisy linear functions for sparsity</strong>, by Xue Chen, Anindya De, and Rocco A. Servedio (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.00911">arXiv</a>). Given samples from a noisy linear model \(y = w\cdot x + \mathrm{noise}\), test whether \(w\) is \(k\)-sparse, or far from being \(k\)-sparse. This is a property testing version of the celebrated sparse recovery problem, whose sample complexity is well-known to be \(O(k\log n)\), where the data lies in \(\mathbb{R}^n\). This paper shows that the testing version of the problem can be solved (tolerantly) with a number of samples independent of \(n\), assuming technical conditions: the distribution of coordinates of \(x\) are i.i.d. and non-Gaussian, and the noise distribution is known to the algorithm. Surprisingly, all these conditions are needed, otherwise the dependence on \(n\) is \(\tilde \Omega(\log n)\), essentially the same as the recovery problem.</p>



<p><strong>Pan-Private Uniformity Testing</strong>, by Kareem Amin, Matthew Joseph, Jieming Mao (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01452">arXiv</a>). Differentially private distribution testing has now seen significant study, in both the local and central models of privacy. This paper studies a distribution testing in the pan-private model, which is intermediate: the algorithm receives samples one by one in the clear, but it must maintain a differentially private internal state at all time steps. The sample complexity turns out to be qualitatively intermediate to the two other models: testing uniformity over \([k]\) requires \(\Theta(\sqrt{k})\) samples in the central model, \(\Theta(k)\) samples in the local model, and this paper shows that \(\Theta(k^{2/3})\) samples are necessary and sufficient in the pan-private model.</p>



<p><strong>Almost Optimal Testers for Concise Representations</strong>, by Nader Bshouty (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/156/">ECCC</a>). This work gives a unified approach for testing for a plethora of different classes which possess some sort of <em>sparsity</em>. These classes include \(k\)-juntas, \(k\)-linear functions, \(k\)-terms, various types of DNFs, decision lists, functions with bounded Fourier degree, and much more. </p>



<p><strong>Unified Sample-Optimal Property Estimation in Near-Linear Time</strong>, by Yi Hao and Alon Orlitsky (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.03105">arXiv</a>). This paper presents a unified approach for estimating several distribution properties with both near-optimal time and sample complexity, based on piecewise-polynomial approximation. Some applications include estimators for Shannon entropy, power sums, distance to uniformity,  normalized support size, and normalized support coverage. More generally, results hold for all Lipschitz properties, and consequences include high-confidence property estimation (outperforming the “median trick”) and differentially private property estimation.</p>



<p><strong>Testing linear-invariant properties</strong>, by Jonathan Tidor and Yufei Zhao (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.06793">arXiv</a>). This paper studies property testing of functions which are in a formal sense, definable by restrictions to subspaces of bounded degree. This class of functions is a broad generalization of testing whether a function is linear, or a degree-\(d\) polynomial (for constant \(d\)). The algorithm is the oblivious one, which simply repeatedly takes random restrictions and tests whether the property is satisfied or not (similar to the classic linearity test of BLR, along with many others). </p>



<p><strong>Approximating the Distance to Monotonicity of Boolean Functions</strong>, by Ramesh Krishnan S. Pallavoor, Sofya Raskhodnikova, Erik Waingarten (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/163/">ECCC</a>). This paper studies the following fundamental question in tolerant testing: given a Boolean function on the hypercube, test whether it is \(\varepsilon’\)-close or \(\varepsilon\)-far from monotone. It is shown that there is a non-adaptive polynomial query algorithm which can solve this problem for \(\varepsilon’ = \varepsilon/\tilde \Theta(\sqrt{n})\), implying an algorithm which can approximate distance to monotonicity up to a multiplicative \(\tilde O(\sqrt{n})\) (addressing an <a href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=250">open problem</a> by Sesh). They also give a lower bound demonstrating that improving this approximating factor significantly would necessitate exponentially-many queries. Interestingly, this is proved for the (easier) erasure-resilient model, and also implies lower bounds for tolerant testing of unateness and juntas.</p>



<p><strong>Testing Properties of Multiple Distributions with Few Samples</strong>, by Maryam Aliakbarpour and Sandeep Silwal (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.07324">arXiv</a>). This paper introduces a new model for distribution testing. Generally, we are given \(n\) samples from a distribution which is either (say) uniform or far from uniform, and we wish to test which is the case. The authors here study the problem where we are given a <em>single sample</em> from \(n\) different distributions which are either all uniform or far from uniform, and we wish to test which is the case. By additionally assuming a structural condition in the latter case (it is argued that <em>some</em> structural condition is necessary), they give sample-optimal algorithms for testing uniformity, identity, and closeness.</p>



<p><strong>Random Restrictions of High-Dimensional Distributions and Uniformity Testing with Subcube Conditioning</strong>, by Clément L. Canonne, Xi Chen, Gautam Kamath, Amit Levi, and Erik Waingarten (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2019/165/">ECCC</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.07357">arXiv</a>). By now, it is well-known that testing uniformity over the \(n\)-dimensional hypercube requires \(\Omega(2^{n/2})\) samples — the curse of dimensionality quickly makes this problem intractable. One option is to assume that the distribution is product, which causes the complexity to drop to \(O(\sqrt{n})\). This paper instead assumes one has stronger access to the distribution — namely, one can receive samples conditioned on being from some subcube of the domain. With this, the paper shows that the complexity drops to the near-optimal \(\tilde O(\sqrt{n})\) samples. The related problem of testing whether a distribution is either uniform or has large mean is also considered. </p>



<p><strong>Property Testing of LP-Type Problems</strong>, by Rogers Epstein, Sandeep Silwal (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.08320">arXiv</a>). An LP-Type problem (also known as a generalized linear program) is an optimization problem sharing some properties with linear programs. More formally, they consist of a set of constraints \(S\) and a function \(\varphi\) which maps subsets of \(S\) to some totally ordered set, such that \(\varphi\) possesses monotonicity and locality properties. This paper considers the problem of testing whether \(\varphi(S) \leq k\), or whether at least an \(\varepsilon\)-fraction of constraints in \(S\) must be removed for \(\varphi(S) \leq k\) to hold. This paper gives an algorithm with query complexity \(O(\delta/\varepsilon)\), where \(\delta\) is a dimension measure of the problem. This is applied to testing problems for linear separability, smallest enclosing ball, smallest intersecting ball, smallest volume annulus. The authors also provide lower bounds for some of these problems as well.</p>



<p><strong>Near-Optimal Algorithm for Distribution-Free Junta Testing</strong>, by Xiaojin Zhang (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.10833">arXiv</a>). This paper presents an (adaptive) algorithm for testing juntas, in the distribution-free model with one-sided error. The query complexity is \(\tilde O(k/\varepsilon)\), which is nearly optimal. Algorithms with this sample complexity were previously known under the uniform distribution, or with two-sided error, but this is the first paper to achieve it in the distribution-free model with one-sided error.</p>



<p><strong>Optimal Adaptive Detection of Monotone Patterns</strong>, by Omri Ben-Eliezer, Shoham Letzter, Erik Waingarten (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01169">arXiv</a>). Consider the problem of testing whether a function has no monotone increasing subsequences of length \(k\), versus being \(\varepsilon\)-far from having this property. Note that this is a generalization of testing whether a function is monotone (decreasing), which corresponds to the case \(k = 2\). This work shows that the adaptive sample complexity of this problem is \(O_{k,\varepsilon}(\log n)\), matching the lower bound for monotonicity testing. This is in comparison to the non-adaptive sample complexity, which is \(O_{k,\varepsilon}((\log n)^{\lfloor \log_2 k\rfloor})\). In fact, the main result provides a certificate of being far, in the form of a monotone increasing subsequence of length \(k\).</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2019-12-06T04:41:03Z</updated>
    <published>2019-12-06T04:41:03Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam Kamath</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2019-12-26T23:21:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
