<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-11-09T13:38:50Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/165</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/165" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-165 |  Interactive Oracle Proofs of Proximity to Algebraic Geometry Codes | 

	Sarah Bordage, 

	Jade Nardi</title>
    <summary>In this work, we initiate the study of proximity testing to Algebraic Geometry (AG) codes. An AG code $C = C(\mathcal C, \mathcal P, D)$ is a vector space associated to evaluations on $\mathcal P$ of functions in the Riemann-Roch space $L_\mathcal C(D)$. The problem of testing proximity to an error-correcting code $C$ consists in distinguishing between the case where an input word, given as an oracle, belongs to $C$ and the one where it is far from every codeword of $C$. AG codes are good candidates to construct \emph{short} proof systems, but there exists no efficient proximity tests for them. We aim to fill this gap.

We construct an Interactive Oracle Proof of Proximity (IOPP) for some families of AG codes by generalizing an IOPP for Reed-Solomon codes, known as the \textsf{FRI} protocol and introduced by Ben-Sasson, Bentov, Horesh and Riabzev in 2018. We identify suitable requirements for designing efficient IOPP systems for AG codes. In addition to proposing the first proximity test targeting AG codes, our IOPP admits quasilinear prover arithmetic complexity and sublinear verifier arithmetic complexity with constant soundness for meaningful classes of AG codes. We take advantage of the algebraic geometry framework that makes any group action on the curve that fixes the divisor $D$ translate into a decomposition of the code $C$. Concretely, our approach relies on Kani's result that splits the Riemann-Roch space of any invariant divisor under this action into several explicit Riemann-Roch spaces on the quotient curve. Under some hypotheses, these spaces behave well enough to define an AG code $C'$ on the quotient curve so that a proximity test to $C$ can be reduced to one to $C'$. Iterating this process thoroughly, we end up with a membership test to a code with significantly smaller length.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-09T12:45:06Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-09T12:45:06Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/164</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/164" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-164 |  Direct Sum and Partitionability Testing over General Groups | 

	Gautam Prakriya, 

	Andrej Bogdanov</title>
    <summary>A function $f(x_1, \dots, x_n)$ from a product domain $\mathcal{D}_1 \times \cdots \times \mathcal{D}_n$ to an abelian group $\mathcal{G}$ is a direct sum if it is of the form $f_1(x_1) + \cdots + f_n(x_n)$.  We present a new 4-query direct sum test with optimal (up to constant factors) soundness error.  This generalizes a result of Dinur and Golubev (RANDOM 2019) which is tailored to the target group $\mathcal{G} = \mathbb{Z}_2$.  As a special case, we obtain an optimal affinity test for $\mathcal{G}$-valued functions on domain $\{0, 1\}^n$ under product measure.  Our analysis relies on the hypercontractivity of the binary erasure channel.

We also study the testability of function partitionability over product domains into disjoint components. A $\mathcal{G}$-valued $f(x_1, \dots, x_n)$ is $k$-direct sum partitionable if it can be written as a sum of functions over $k$ nonempty disjoint sets of inputs.  A function $f(x_1, \dots, x_n)$ with unstructured product range $\mathcal{R}^k$ is  direct product partitionable if its outputs depend on disjoint sets of inputs.  

We show that direct sum partitionability and direct product partitionability are one-sided error testable with $O((n - k)(\log n + 1/\epsilon) + 1/\epsilon)$ adaptive queries and $O((n/\epsilon) \log^2(n/\epsilon))$ nonadaptive queries, respectively.  Both bounds are tight up to the logarithmic factors for constant $\epsilon$ even with respect to adaptive, two-sided error testers.  We also give a non-adaptive one-sided error tester for direct sum partitionability with query complexity $O(kn^2 (\log n)^2 / \epsilon)$.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-09T12:43:18Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-09T12:43:18Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7627871032207660441</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7627871032207660441/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/random-thoughts-on-election-2020.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7627871032207660441" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7627871032207660441" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/random-thoughts-on-election-2020.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Random Thoughts on the Election (2020)</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><br/></p><p>1) Biden will be the oldest president (measuring by when they take the oath of office), at 78. The next two are Trump 70 and Reagan 69. Biden will be older entering office then Reagan was leaving office. </p><p>After Biden, Trump, Reagan:</p><p>William Henry Harrison 68. Why do some people have middle names that are commonly spoken and some do not? Others with middle names spoken: Lee Harvey Oswald, John Wilkes Booth. </p><p>James Buchanan 65</p><p>George H. W. Bush 64. Why do some people have their initials commonly spoken and others do not? In this case it may be to distinguish from W. Why are some people known by their middle initial? Well, actually one that I know of, W.</p><p>Youngest was Theodore Roosevelt 42 who took the office after McKinley was assassinated . Kennedy was youngest to take the oath after being ELECTED at 43. Theodore Roosevelt was known as TR. John F Kennedy is often called JFK. Franklin D Roosevelt was called FDR. Why are some people known by their initials? In these cases maybe to distinguish them from other Roosevelts and Kennedys.</p><p>2) Right now it looks like GA will go for Biden. This surprises me. I had heard `GA is on the verge of turning blue and always will be.'</p><p>3) Dem-Blue, Rep-Red always puzzled me since I thought Red was associated with communism.</p><p>4) A quote from the Trump/Schwartz  book THE ART OF THE DEAL about why Carter was a one-termer  is rather predictive:</p><p>See <a href="https://www.thewrap.com/drudge-trump-election-con/">here</a></p><p>(I've heard Schwartz referred to as a ghost writer. That is not true-- Tony Schwartz's name is ON THE COVER, so he is not a ghostwriter.)</p><p>5) During the Trump administration UAE, Bahrain, and Sudan all recognized Israel (gee, when I see it on a map I recognize it, why did it take them so long :-) ). See <a href="https://apnews.com/article/donald-trump-bahrain-israel-united-arab-emirates-sudan-07fe32a9ac1bd3afe5c503d4ff6bc859">here</a>. All three deals were brokered by the US so Trump could  take credit here. So why didn't he? One answer is that the left-wing lame stream media didn't cover it much. But FOX didn't cover it much. Trump didn't mention it much. Trump didn't even mention it as a way to complain about media coverage. So- independent of if you think Trump deserves credit here or not, I am interested in why he didn't brag about this one. (When I have asked this question people point out that Trump's base would not care about this. But Trump could complain that Obama got a Nobel Peace prize for nothing, and he got these deals done and hasn't, gotten a Nobel Prize because of the fake-Nobel-Committee and channel this into anti-Obama sentiment.)</p><p>6) Truth avoids imitating  art: Watch Season five of the HBO show VEEP for how messy a close election can be. </p><p>7) I think Biden will end up being president and the transition will be peaceful. Why? Fox News and other conservative organizations are urging Trump to concede. Republican state legislators are NOT trying to find ways to overturn the results in their states. Judges have found NO evidence for the kinds of fraud that Trump is complaining about. Many Republicans are silent (John Oliver says that means they SUPPORT  Trumps allegations, but I think it means they are NOT supporting Trump's allegations.) </p><p> Why is the Republican establishment NOT backing Trumps claims of fraud? Here are some thoughts.</p><p>a) Because the allegations of fraud are not just false but obviously false.  </p><p>b) Because they think that it is better for the country to have a clean transition.</p><p>c) Because they are tired of Trump also and realize he is not good for the party brand (a bit late now).</p><p>d) Corrupting the electoral process is a bridge to far. (Where did that phrase come from?)</p><p>e) I wonder if Trump himself would have preferred to lose in 2016 and go around having rallies, perhaps have his own TV network. RALLIES are fun, RUNNING THE COUNTRY is not. So those around him may want him to go back to his original plan. </p><p>8) Did Nate (the only pollster with a one-word-name) do well this time around  He thinks so, see <a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/nate-silver-tells-fivethirtyeight-critics-fuck-you-we-did-a-good-job">here</a>. Its not even clear he did badly in 2016- he gave Trump a 20% chance in 2016 and a 10% chance this time. </p><p>9) I think that if  we had not had a pandemic then  Trump would have won. Two reasons: the country thinks he handled it badly, and it may have literally killed some of his voters.  As a final note on that: Mark Meadows (WH Chief of staff) has COVID. I am surprised Pence didn't get it-- thought maybe he did or will. </p><p>10) Why did people in the Trump WH who one assumes know that Covid is serious and that masks and social distancing were  way to prevent it, not do these simple things?  Perhaps they thought (correctly) that the more people thing about covid, the more likely Trump loses, so they took a risk. Alas, those that trade their health for electability get neither. </p><p>11) Neither Pence nor Harris is particularly young or old as VP's go. </p><p>Youngest: John Breckenridge, 36. Buchanan's VP</p><p>Second Youngest: Richard Nixon, 40, Eisenhower's VP</p><p>Oldest: Alben Barkley, 71, Truman's VP</p><p>Second oldest: Charles Curtis, 69, Hoover's VP</p><p>Pence was 57 when took the oath, Harris will be 56. </p><p>12) If Biden wins then on Jan 20 when he takes the oath there will be 5 living Ex-presidents:Carter, Clinton, W, Obama, Trump (assuming they all stay alive until then). This ties the record for most living ex-presidents. See <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2018/12/george-hw-bush-passed-away-some-non.html">here</a> for my blog post on this. Getting to 6 will be difficult since Carter is 96 years old. </p><p>13) Neither Lance nor I have blogged much about the election, or even about politics. One reason is that whatever I want to say Scott says better (Scott and Lance are the only theory bloggers known by just their first names). I was going to point to Scott's  political blogs but that was hard since he often has blog posts about multiple topics (Like his post about  Mike Pence thinking that the Ind of CH is a sort of relativism that also allows for adultery to be considered okay (see <a href="https://archive.thinkprogress.org/mike-pence-argued-for-criminalization-of-adultery-before-joining-trump-ticket-e27e8a423caa/">here</a> for Pence's pre-Trump views on adultery)  Actually Scott never blogged about Pence and CH  but after reading his posts they kind of blur in my mind.) I will point to one blog entry of his  that I suspect will NOT be relevant but is still very interesting: <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4845">Will he go?</a></p><p>14) Trump claimed the polls showing he was behind were false and part of a conspiracy. I am not sure how this conspiracy would work. If people think their candidate is ahead or behind, then does that affect how or if they vote? Do people say `Gee X is winning, I'll vote for them' ? I doubt it. There are two ways such a conspiracy could work (1)  claim was that some candidate was WAY ahead (it would not matter which one) so you should not bother to vote (2)   in a primary where you are voting on who you think will win the general election.  He also claimed that the early returns saying Biden was winning was a conspiracy. Same problem there- how would that work. This isn't just Trump, other politicians in diff  years claim that early-returns saying X is winning might make it harder for Y to win. I can't see how. </p><p>15) Kamala Harris will be the first women, the first African-American, and the first Asian Veep.  Trivia: There has been a Native American Veep- who was it? More trivia- who coined the term <i>Veep? </i>I won't answer these here, but they might be on my Prez Quiz that I will post after the new President is sworn in.  </p><p>Can she be BOTH the first African-American and the first Asian? Yes.</p><p>16) In my lifetime the election for President was  SETTLED when the losing candidate conceded. This was good for the country's mindset that YES the president is known and even the other candidate agrees. What if Trump does not concede? I doubt this has any practical affect, except that  on Jan 20 he might be trying to arrange a moving van at the last minute. But if the losing candidate does not concede then when is the matter settled?  When the major news venues say it is? Which ones are major? What if there was a really close election and diff news networks declared diff candidates to have won? This does not seem to be a problem for this election cycle, but it is a question: When is the matter SETTLED in that the country ACCEPTS the result, if the losing candidate does not concede?</p><p>17) Carter beat incumbent Ford, but they became friends. Clinton beat incumbent Bush Sr, but they became friends. This is understandable in that so few people are president so they have a shared experience. I doubt that Trump and Biden will become friends.</p><p>18)   Bill Clinton's staff removed W's from the typewriters and did some other damage before W moved into the WH see <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/12/us/white-house-vandalized-in-transition-gao-finds.html">here</a>.  This is NOT a tradition, nor is it acceptable in any way, shape. or form.  I do not know of any other similar cases in America (if you do, let me know in the comments).  I wonder if Trump will do damage  to the WH before he leaves. Do presidents put a deposit down on the WH so that any damage they do, they pay for? I  doubt it, but it would be a good idea. </p><p>19)  Obama and Trump had a cordial 90 minute meeting, see <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/11/11/us/politics/white-house-transition-obama-trump.html">here</a>, after Trump won but before he moved in. This makes perfect sense--outgoing presidents know stuff and have experiences worth sharing with the next president.   Obama said North Korea would be a problem and it is (Trump later tried to spin this--`Obama said it would be hard, but it was easy') I wonder if Trump and Biden will have any kind of meeting, cordial or not. </p><p>20) Every state that went for H Clinton in 2016 went for Biden in 2020. The following states went for Trump in 2016 but went for Biden in 2020: Wisc, Mich, PA, AZ, and maybe Georgia and maybe NC (frankly I doubt NC). There was a plausible  scenario (I forget what it was) where Biden would have won 270-268. </p><p>21) Did Third parties matter? In PA the Libertarian Candidate Jo Jorgenson got 1.1% of the vote which was larger than the diff between Biden (49.7) and Trump (49.1) (The Green party either wasn't on the ballot or got so few votes it was not counted). If most of the Libertarians voted for Trump then he would have won PA and possibly the election. However, Trump is not really a Libertarian, so I doubt that would have happened As for the entire country: (1) . The Libertarians got 1.14% of the total vote in 2020, as opposed to 3.25% in 2016, (2)  The Green party got 1.06% in 2016 and 0.02% in 2020. </p><p>21) I was not particular impressed with the satires of the debates and other political satire on SNL this year. Not sure why- maybe Trump is too wild  to satirize and Joltin Jo is too boring. But the following I DID like and is now more relevant. Watch the whole thing since the first half looks like a real ad.</p><p><a href="https://deadline.com/2020/10/snl-cast-members-2020-trump-1234603033/">here</a><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-08T15:26:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-08T15:26:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T08:19:03Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/163</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/163" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-163 |  Expander Random Walks: A Fourier-Analytic Approach | 

	Gil Cohen, 

	Amnon Ta-Shma, 

	Noam Peri</title>
    <summary>In this work we ask the following basic question:  assume the vertices of an expander graph are labelled by $0,1$. What "test" functions $f : \{ 0,1\}^t \to \{0,1\}$ cannot  distinguish  $t$ independent samples from those obtained by a random walk? The expander hitting property due to Ajtai, Komlos and Szemeredi (STOC 1987) is captured by the $\mathrm{AND}$ test function, whereas the fundamental expander Chernoff bound due to Gillman (SICOMP 1998), Heally (Computational Complexity 2008) is about test functions indicating whether the weight is close to the mean. In fact, it is known that all threshold functions are fooled by a random walk (Kipnis and Varadhan, Communications in Mathematical Physics 1986).  Recently, it was shown that even the highly sensitive $\mathrm{PARITY}$ function is fooled by a random walk (Ta-Shma; STOC 2017).  

We focus on balanced labels. Our first main result is proving that all symmetric functions are fooled by a random walk. Put differently, we prove a central limit theorem (CLT) for expander random walks with respect to the total variation distance, significantly strengthening the classic CLT for Markov Chains that is established with respect to the Kolmogorov distance due to Kipnis and Varadhan. Our approach significantly deviates from prior works. We first study how well a Fourier character $\chi_S$ is fooled by a random walk as a function of $S$. Then, given a test function $f$, we expand $f$ in the Fourier basis and combine the above with known results on the Fourier spectrum of $f$. 

We also proceed further and consider general test functions - not necessarily symmetric. As our approach is Fourier analytic, it is general enough to analyze  such versatile test functions. For our second result, we prove that random walks on sufficiently good expander graphs fool tests functions computed by $\mathbf{AC}^0$ circuits, read-once branching programs, and functions with bounded query complexity.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-08T11:09:24Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-08T11:09:24Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/162</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/162" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-162 |  High-Probability List-Recovery, and Applications to Heavy Hitters | 

	Dean Doron, 

	Mary Wootters</title>
    <summary>An error correcting code $\mathcal{C} \colon \Sigma^k \to \Sigma^n$ is list-recoverable from input list size $\ell$ if for any sets $\mathcal{L}_1, \ldots, \mathcal{L}_n \subseteq \Sigma$ of size at most $\ell$, one can efficiently recover the list $\mathcal{L} = \{ x \in \Sigma^k : \forall j \in [n],  \mathcal{C}(x)_j \in \mathcal{L}_j \}$.  While list-recovery has been well-studied in error correcting codes, all known constructions with "efficient" algorithms are not efficient in the parameter $\ell$.  In this work, motivated by applications in algorithm design and pseudorandomness, we study list-recovery with the goal of obtaining a good dependence on $\ell$.  We make a step towards this goal by obtaining it in the weaker case where we allow a randomized encoding map and a small failure probability, and where the input lists are derived from unions of codewords.  As an application of our construction, we give a data structure for the heavy hitters problem in the strict turnstile model that, for some parameter regimes, obtains stronger guarantees than known constructions.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-08T11:06:59Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-08T11:06:59Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>http://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1436</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1436" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for October 2020</title>
    <summary>Sorry for the delay in writing this monthly digest: we hope you didn’t spend the week frantically refreshing your browsers! We found four papers this month: let’s dive in. A Structural Theorem for Local Algorithms with Applications to Coding, Testing, and Privacy, by Marcel Dall’Agnol, Tom Gur, and Oded Lachish (ECCC). This paper introduces the […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Sorry for the delay in writing this monthly digest: we hope you didn’t spend the week frantically refreshing your browsers! We found four papers this month: let’s dive in.</p>



<p><strong>A Structural Theorem for Local Algorithms with Applications to Coding, Testing, and Privacy</strong>, by Marcel Dall’Agnol, Tom Gur, and Oded Lachish (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/154/">ECCC</a>). This paper introduces the notion of “robust (local) algorithm,” an abstraction which encompasses may types of algorithms: e.g., property testing algorithms, locally decodable codes, etc. The main result of this work is that any (possibly adaptive) \(q\)-query robust local algorithm can be transformed into a non-adaptive, <em>sample-based</em> one making \(n^{1-1/(q^2\log q)}\) queries (where \(n\) is the input size). Here, “sample-based” means that the algorithm doesn’t get to make arbitrary queries, but just gets to observe randomly chosen coordinates of the input. As application of this result, the authors derive new upper and lower bounds for several of the types of local algorithms mentioned above, resolving open questions from previous works.</p>



<p><strong>Testing Tail Weight of a Distribution Via Hazard Rate</strong>, by Maryam Aliakbarpour, Amartya Shankha Biswas, Kavya Ravichandran, Ronitt Rubinfeld (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.02888">arXiv</a>). The authors consider, from the point of view of distribution testing, the question of deciding whether data is <em>heavy-tailed</em>: as would, for instance, data following a power law. The paper first sets out to formalize the question, and discusses various possible definitional choices before setting on one; after which it provides a test, and analyzes its sample complexity as a function of various parameters (such as smoothness of the unknown distribution). The authors finally back these results with empirical evaluation of their algorithm.</p>



<p><strong>On Testing of Samplers</strong>, by Kuldeep S. Meel, Yash Pote, Sourav Chakraborty (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.12918">arXiv</a>). Suppose you are given a (known) distribution \(p\) over some domain \(\Omega\), and want to sample from it conditioned on some predicate \(\varphi\). Now someone comes to you with an algorithm which does exactly that, efficiently, and cheaply: great! But can you easily check that you’re not getting fooled, and that this sampler actually does what it claims? This paper provides this: an algorithm which accepts if the sampled distribution is \(\varepsilon\)-close to what it should (roughly, in a multiplicative, KL divergence sense), and rejects if it’s \(\varepsilon’\)-far (in total variation distance). The number of samples required is polynomial in \(\varepsilon’-\varepsilon\), and depends on some characteristic of \(p\) and \(\varphi\), the “tilt” (ratio between max and min probability of the conditional distribution).</p>



<p>Finally, an omission from late September:<br/><strong>Sample optimal Quantum identity testing via Pauli Measurements</strong>, by Nengkun Yu (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.11518">arXiv</a>). The abstract is concise and clear enough to speak for itself: “In this paper, we show that \(\Theta(\textrm{poly}(n)\cdot\frac{4^n}{\varepsilon^2})\) is the sample complexity of testing whether two \(n\)-qubit quantum states \(\rho\) and \(\sigma\) are identical or \(\varepsilon\)-far in trace distance using two-outcome Pauli measurements.”</p>



<p>Please let us know if you spotted a paper we missed!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-08T04:53:24Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-08T04:53:24Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Clement Canonne</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?feed=rss2" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2020-11-08T22:50:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5088</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5088" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5088#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5088" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Five Thoughts</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">(1) A friend commented that Biden’s victory becomes more impressive after you contemplate the enthusiasm gap: Trump’s base believed that Trump was sent by God, whereas Biden’s base believed that Biden probably wasn’t a terrible human being. I replied that what we call the “Enlightenment” was precisely this, the switch from cowering before leaders who […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>(1) A friend commented that Biden’s victory becomes more impressive after you contemplate the enthusiasm gap: Trump’s base believed that Trump was sent by God, whereas Biden’s base believed that Biden probably wasn’t a terrible human being.  I replied that what we call the “Enlightenment” was precisely this, the switch from cowering before leaders who were sent by God to demanding leaders who probably aren’t terrible human beings.</p>



<p>(2) I would love for Twitter to deactivate Trump’s account—<em>not</em> for any ideological reason, simply for Trump’s hundreds of past violations of Twitter’s Terms of Service, and for there no longer being a compelling public interest in what Trump has to say that would override all his Terms of Service violations.</p>



<p>(3) When Biden appeared last night, and then again tonight, it wasn’t merely that he came across like a President-Elect of the US, but rather that he came across like a President-Elect of the US <em>who’s filling a vacant position</em>.  Until Biden starts, there won’t <em>be</em> a president of the US; there will only continue to be the president of those who voted for him.</p>



<p>(4) Now that Trump has gone this far in shattering all the norms of succession, part of me <em>wants</em> to see him go the rest of the way … to being physically dragged out of the Oval Office by Secret Service agents on January 20, in pathetic and humiliating footage that would define how future generations remembered him.</p>



<p>(5) I had an idea for something that could make a permanent contribution to protecting liberal democracy in the US, and that anti-Trump forces could implement unilaterally for a few tens of millions of dollars—no need to win another election.  The idea is to build a Donald J. Trump Historical Museum in Washington, DC.  But, you see, this museum would effectively be the opposite of a presidential library.  It would be designed by professional historians; they might solicit cooperation from former members of Trump’s inner circle, but would never depend on it.  It would, in fact, be a museum that teenage students might tend to be taken to on the same DC field trips that also brought them to the Vietnam Memorial and the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM).  Obviously, the new museum would be <em>different</em> from those bleak places; it would (thankfully) have a little less tragedy and more farce … and that’s precisely the role that the new museum would fill.  To show the kids on the field trips that it’s not <em>always</em> unmitigated horribleness, that here was a case where we Americans took a gigantic stumble backwards, seeming to want to recreate the first few rooms in the USHMM exhibition, the one where the macho-talking clown thrills Germany by being serious rather than literal.  <em>But then, here in the US, we successfully stopped it before it got to the later rooms</em>.  Sure, the victory wasn’t as decisive as we would’ve liked, it came at a great cost, but it was victory nonetheless.  A 244-year-old experiment in self-governance is back in operation.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-08T01:20:35Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-08T01:20:35Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-11-08T15:51:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.03004</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.03004" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Smart Backtracking Algorithm for Computing Set Partitions with Parts of Certain Sizes</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1604793600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nofal:Samer.html">Samer Nofal</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.03004">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Let $\alpha=\{a_1,a_2,a_3,...,a_n\}$ be a set of elements, $\delta &lt; n$ be a
positive integer, and $\Gamma: \alpha \to \{0, 1, 2, ..., n\}$ be a total
mapping. Then, we call $\Gamma$ a \emph{partition} of $\alpha$ if and only if
for all $x \in \alpha$, $\Gamma(x) \neq 0$. Further, we call $\Gamma$ a
$\delta$-\emph{partition} of $\alpha$ if and only if $\Gamma$ is a partition of
$\alpha$ and for all $i \in \{1, 2, 3, ..., n\}$, $|\{x: \Gamma(x)=i\}| &gt;
\delta$. The so-far open issue that we close in this paper is regarding whether
the $\delta$-partitions of $\alpha$ can be computed without computing the
partitions of $\alpha$ in advance. As we show in this paper, this issue is not
as trivial as it might seem at first sight, especially if any naive
generate-and-test procedure has to be avoided. To resolve this issue, we give a
formal proof of the correctness of a smart backtracking algorithm that computes
the $\delta$-partitions of $\alpha$ efficiently without a prior construction of
the partitions of~$\alpha$. The algorithm does so by checking (ahead) two
properties identifying parts of the search space that are devoid of any
$\delta$-partition of~$\alpha$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-08T22:38:03Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02868</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02868" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postulate-based proof of the P != NP hypothesis</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1604793600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>O. V. German <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.02868">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The paper contains a proof for the P != NP hypothesis with the help of the
two "natural" postulates. The postulates restrict capacity of the Turing
machines and state that each independent and necessary condition of the problem
should be considered by a solver (Turing machine) individually, not in groups.
That is, a solver should spend at least one step to deal with the condition
and, therefore, if the amount of independent conditions is exponentially
growing with polynomially growing problem sizes then exponential time is needed
to find a solution. With the postulates, it is enough to build a natural (not
pure mathematical) proof that P != NP.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-08T22:37:33Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02761</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02761" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Instance Based Approximations to Profile Maximum Likelihood</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1604793600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Anari:Nima.html">Nima Anari</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Charikar:Moses.html">Moses Charikar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Shiragur:Kirankumar.html">Kirankumar Shiragur</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sidford:Aaron.html">Aaron Sidford</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.02761">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper we provide a new efficient algorithm for approximately
computing the profile maximum likelihood (PML) distribution, a prominent
quantity in symmetric property estimation. We provide an algorithm which
matches the previous best known efficient algorithms for computing approximate
PML distributions and improves when the number of distinct observed frequencies
in the given instance is small. We achieve this result by exploiting new
sparsity structure in approximate PML distributions and providing a new matrix
rounding algorithm, of independent interest. Leveraging this result, we obtain
the first provable computationally efficient implementation of PseudoPML, a
general framework for estimating a broad class of symmetric properties.
Additionally, we obtain efficient PML-based estimators for distributions with
small profile entropy, a natural instance-based complexity measure. Further, we
provide a simpler and more practical PseudoPML implementation that matches the
best-known theoretical guarantees of such an estimator and evaluate this method
empirically.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-08T22:46:13Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02743</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02743" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A revisited branch-and-cut algorithm for large-scale orienteering problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1604793600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kobeaga:Gorka.html">Gorka Kobeaga</a>, María Merino, Jose A. Lozano <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.02743">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The orienteering problem is a route optimization problem which consists in
finding a simple cycle that maximizes the total collected profit subject to a
maximum distance limitation. In the last few decades, the occurrence of this
problem in real-life applications has boosted the development of many heuristic
algorithms to solve it. However, during the same period, not much research has
been devoted to the field of exact algorithms for the orienteering problem. The
aim of this work is to develop an exact method which is able to obtain
optimality certification in a wider set of instances than with previous
methods, or to improve the lower and upper bounds in its disability.
</p>
<p>We propose a revisited version of the branch-and-cut algorithm for the
orienteering problem which includes new contributions in the separation
algorithms of inequalities stemming from the cycle problem, in the separation
loop, in the variables pricing, and in the calculation of the lower and upper
bounds of the problem. Our proposal is compared to three state-of-the-art
algorithms on 258 benchmark instances with up to 7397 nodes. The computational
experiments show the relevance of the designed components where 18 new optima,
76 new best-known solutions and 85 new upper-bound values were obtained.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-08T22:46:03Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02615</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02615" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Competitive Data-Structure Dynamization</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1604793600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mathieu:Claire.html">Claire Mathieu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rajaraman:Rajmohan.html">Rajmohan Rajaraman</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Young:Neal_E=.html">Neal E. Young</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yousefi:Arman.html">Arman Yousefi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.02615">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Data-structure dynamization is a general approach for making static data
structures dynamic. It is used extensively in geometric settings and in the
guise of so-called merge (or compaction) policies in big-data databases such as
Google Bigtable and LevelDB (our focus). Previous theoretical work is based on
worst-case analyses for uniform inputs -- insertions of one item at a time and
constant read rate. In practice, merge policies must not only handle batch
insertions and varying read/write ratios, they can take advantage of such
non-uniformity to reduce cost on a per-input basis. To model this, we initiate
the study of data-structure dynamization through the lens of competitive
analysis, via two new online set-cover problems. For each, the input is a
sequence of disjoint sets of weighted items. The sets are revealed one at a
time. The algorithm must respond to each with a set cover that covers all items
revealed so far. It obtains the cover incrementally from the previous cover by
adding one or more sets and optionally removing existing sets. For each new set
the algorithm incurs build cost equal to the weight of the items in the set. In
the first problem the objective is to minimize total build cost plus total
query cost, where the algorithm incurs a query cost at each time $t$ equal to
the current cover size. In the second problem, the objective is to minimize the
build cost while keeping the query cost from exceeding $k$ (a given parameter)
at any time. We give deterministic online algorithms for both variants, with
competitive ratios of $\Theta(\log^* n)$ and $k$, respectively. The latter
ratio is optimal for the second variant.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-08T22:43:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02601</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02601" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fast, Exact and Scalable Dynamic Ridesharing</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1604793600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Buchhold:Valentin.html">Valentin Buchhold</a>, Peter Sanders, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wagner:Dorothea.html">Dorothea Wagner</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.02601">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the problem of servicing a set of ride requests by dispatching a set
of shared vehicles, which is faced by ridesharing companies such as Uber and
Lyft. Solving this problem at a large scale might be crucial in the future for
effectively using large fleets of autonomous vehicles. Since finding a solution
for the entire set of requests that minimizes the total driving time is
NP-complete, most practical approaches process the requests one by one. Each
request is inserted into any vehicle's route such that the increase in driving
time is minimized. Although this variant is solvable in polynomial time, it
still takes considerable time in current implementations, even when inexact
filtering heuristics are used. In this work, we present a novel algorithm for
finding best insertions, based on (customizable) contraction hierarchies with
local buckets. Our algorithm finds provably exact solutions, is still 30 times
faster than a state-of-the-art algorithm currently used in industry and
academia, and scales much better. When used within iterative transport
simulations, our algorithm decreases the simulation time for largescale
scenarios with many requests from days to hours.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-08T22:39:02Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02075</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.02075" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal Mixing of Glauber Dynamics: Entropy Factorization via High-Dimensional Expansion</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1604793600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Zongchen.html">Zongchen Chen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Kuikui.html">Kuikui Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Vigoda:Eric.html">Eric Vigoda</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.02075">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We prove an optimal mixing time bound on the single-site update Markov chain
known as the Glauber dynamics or Gibbs sampling in a variety of settings. Our
work presents an improved version of the spectral independence approach of
Anari et al. (2020) and shows $O(n\log{n})$ mixing time on any $n$-vertex graph
of bounded degree when the maximum eigenvalue of an associated influence matrix
is bounded. As an application of our results, for the hard-core model on
independent sets weighted by a fugacity $\lambda$, we establish $O(n\log{n})$
mixing time for the Glauber dynamics on any $n$-vertex graph of constant
maximum degree $\Delta$ when $\lambda&lt;\lambda_c(\Delta)$ where
$\lambda_c(\Delta)$ is the critical point for the uniqueness/non-uniqueness
phase transition on the $\Delta$-regular tree. More generally, for any
antiferromagnetic 2-spin system we prove $O(n\log{n})$ mixing time of the
Glauber dynamics on any bounded degree graph in the corresponding tree
uniqueness region. Our results apply more broadly; for example, we also obtain
$O(n\log{n})$ mixing for $q$-colorings of triangle-free graphs of maximum
degree $\Delta$ when the number of colors satisfies $q \geq \alpha \Delta + 1$
where $\alpha \approx 1.763$, and $O(m\log{n})$ mixing for generating random
matchings of any graph with bounded degree and $m$ edges.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-08T22:38:19Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-06T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://francisbach.com/?p=64</id>
    <link href="https://francisbach.com/cauchy-residue-formula/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Cauchy residue trick: spectral analysis made “easy”</title>
    <summary>In many areas of machine learning, statistics and signal processing, eigenvalue decompositions are commonly used, e.g., in principal component analysis, spectral clustering, convergence analysis of Markov chains, convergence analysis of optimization algorithms, low-rank inducing regularizers, community detection, seriation, etc. Understanding how the spectral decomposition of a matrix changes as a function of a matrix is...</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="justify-text">In many areas of machine learning, statistics and signal processing, eigenvalue decompositions are commonly used, e.g., in principal component analysis, spectral clustering, convergence analysis of Markov chains, convergence analysis of optimization algorithms, low-rank inducing regularizers, community detection, seriation, etc.</p>



<p class="justify-text">Understanding how the spectral decomposition of a matrix changes as a function of a matrix is thus of primary importance, both algorithmically and theoretically. We thus need a perturbation analysis or more generally some differentiability properties for eigenvalues or eigenvectors [1], or any spectral function [2]. These properties can be obtained from many angles, but a generic tool can be used for all of these: it is a surprising and elegant application of Cauchy’s residue formula, which is due to Kato [3].</p>



<p class="justify-text">Before diving into spectral analysis, I will first present the Cauchy residue theorem and some nice applications in computing integrals that are needed in machine learning and kernel methods.</p>



<h2>Cauchy residue formula </h2>



<p class="justify-text">A function \(f : \mathbb{C} \to \mathbb{C}\) is said <em>holomorphic</em> in \(\lambda \in \mathbb{C}\) with derivative \(f'(\lambda) \in \mathbb{C}\), if is differentiable in \(\lambda\), that is if \(\displaystyle \frac{f(z)-f(\lambda)}{z-\lambda}\) tends to \(f'(\lambda)\) when \(z\) tends to \(\lambda\). Many classical functions are holomorphic on \(\mathbb{C}\) or portions thereof, such as the exponential, sines, cosines and their hyperbolic counterparts, rational functions, portions of the logarithm.</p>



<p class="justify-text">We consider a function which is holomorphic in a region of \(\mathbb{C}\) except in \(m\) values \(\lambda_1,\dots,\lambda_m \in \mathbb{C}\), which are usually referred to as <em>poles</em>. We also consider a simple closed directed contour \(\gamma\) in \(\mathbb{C}\) that goes strictly around the \(m\) values above. </p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img alt="" class="wp-image-5002" height="236" src="https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/contour_generic-1-1024x440.png" width="549"/></figure></div>



<p class="justify-text">The Cauchy residue formula gives an explicit formula for the contour integral along \(\gamma\):<br/> $$ \oint_\gamma f(z) dz = 2 i \pi \sum_{j=1}^m {\rm Res}(f,\lambda_j), \tag{1}$$<br/> where \({\rm Res}(f,\lambda)\) is called the <em>residue</em> of \(f\) at \(\lambda\) . If around \(\lambda\),  \(f(z)\) has a series expansions in powers of \((z − \lambda)\), that is, \(\displaystyle f(z) =  \sum_{k=-\infty}^{+\infty}a_k (z −\lambda)^k\), then \({\rm Res}(f,\lambda)=a_{-1}\).</p>



<p class="justify-text">For example, if \(\displaystyle f(z) =   \frac{g(z)}{z-\lambda}\) with \(g\) holomorphic around \(\lambda\), then \({\rm Res}(f,\lambda) = g(\lambda)\), and more generally, if \(\displaystyle f(z) = \frac{g(z)}{(z-\lambda)^k}\) for \(k \geqslant  1\), then \(\displaystyle {\rm Res}(f,\lambda) = \frac{g^{(k-1)}(\lambda) }{(k-1)!}\). For more details on complex analysis, see [4].</p>



<p class="justify-text">The result above can be naturally extended to vector-valued functions (and thus to any matrix-valued function), by applying the identity to all components of the vector.</p>



<p class="justify-text">This result is due to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augustin-Louis_Cauchy">Cauchy</a> [<a href="https://archive.org/details/mmoiresurlesin00cauc">10</a>] in 1825. The <a href="https://archive.org/details/mmoiresurlesin00cauc">original paper</a> where this is presented is a nice read in French where you can find some pepits like “la fonction s’évanouit pour \(x = \infty\)”.</p>



<p>If you are already familiar with complex residues, you can skip the next section.</p>



<h2>Where does it come from?</h2>



<p class="justify-text">At first, the formula in Eq. (1) seems unsettling. Why doesn’t the result depend more explicitly on the contour \(\gamma\)? Where does the multiplicative term \( {2i\pi}\) come from? Here is a very partial and non rigorous account (go to the <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/tag/residue-theorem/">experts</a> for more rigor!).</p>



<p class="justify-text">Complex-valued functions on \(\mathbb{C}\) can be seen as functions from \(\mathbb{R}^2\) to itself, by writing $$ f(x+iy) = u(x,y) + i v(x,y),$$ where \(u\) and \(v\) are real-valued functions. We have thus a function \((x,y) \mapsto (u(x,y),v(x,y))\) from \(\mathbb{R}^2\) to \(\mathbb{R}^2\). Expanding \(f(z+dz) = f(z) + f'(z) dz\), which is the definition of complex differentiability, into real and imaginary parts, we get (using \(i^2 = -1\)): $$\left\{ \begin{array}{l} u(x+dx,y+dy) = u(x,y) + {\rm Re}(f'(z)) dx\ – {\rm Im}(f'(z)) dy \\ v(x+dx,y+dy) = v(x,y) + {\rm Re}(f'(z)) dy + {\rm Im}(f'(z)) dx. \end{array}\right.$$ This leads to $$\left\{ \begin{array}{l} \displaystyle \frac{\partial u}{\partial x}(x,y) = {\rm Re}(f'(z)) \\ \displaystyle \frac{\partial u}{\partial y}(x,y) = \ – {\rm Im}(f'(z)) \\ \displaystyle \frac{\partial v}{\partial x}(x,y) = {\rm Im}(f'(z)) \\ \displaystyle \frac{\partial v}{\partial y}(x,y) = {\rm Re}(f'(z)). \end{array}\right.$$</p>



<p class="justify-text">This in turn leads to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cauchy%E2%80%93Riemann_equations">Cauchy-Riemann equations</a> \(\displaystyle \frac{\partial u}{\partial x} = \frac{\partial v}{\partial y}\) and \(\displaystyle \frac{\partial u}{\partial y} = -\frac{\partial v}{\partial x}\), which are essentially necessary and sufficient conditions to be holomorphic. Thus holomorphic functions correspond to differentiable functions on \(\mathbb{R}^2\) with some equal partial derivatives. These equations are key to obtaining the Cauchy residue formula.</p>



<p class="justify-text"><strong>Contour integral with no poles. </strong>We first consider a contour integral over a contour \(\gamma\) enclosing a region \(\mathcal{D}\) where the function \(f\) is holomorphic everywhere. The contour \(\gamma\) is defined as a differentiable function \(\gamma: [0,1] \to \mathbb{C}\), and the integral is equal to $$\oint_\gamma f(z) dz = \int_0^1 \!\!f(\gamma(t)) \gamma'(t) dt = \int_0^1 \!\![u(x(t),y(t)) +i v(x(t),y(t))] [ x'(t) + i y'(t)] dt,$$ where \(x(t) = {\rm Re}(\gamma(t))\) and \(y(t) = {\rm Im}(\gamma(t))\). By expanding the product of complex numbers, it is thus equal to $$\int_0^1 [ u(x(t),y(t)) x'(t) \ – v(x(t),y(t))y'(t)] dt +i  \int_0^1 [ v(x(t),y(t)) x'(t) +u (x(t),y(t))y'(t)] dt,$$ which we can rewrite in compact form as (with \(dx = x'(t) dt\) and \(dy = y'(t)dt\)): $$\oint_\gamma ( u \, dx\  – v \, dy ) + i \oint_\gamma ( v \, dx + u \, dy ).$$ We can then use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%27s_theorem">Green’s theorem</a> because our functions are differentiable on the entire region \(\mathcal{D}\) (the set “inside” the contour), to get $$\oint_\gamma ( u \, dx\ – v \, dy ) + i \oint_\gamma ( v \, dx + u \, dy ) =\  – \int\!\!\!\!\int_\mathcal{D} \! \Big( \frac{\partial v}{\partial x} + \frac{\partial u}{\partial y} \Big) dx dy \ – i \!\! \int\!\!\!\!\int_\mathcal{D} \!\Big( \frac{\partial u}{\partial x} – \frac{\partial v}{\partial y} \Big) dx dy.$$ Thus, because of the Cauchy-Riemann equations, the contour integral is always zero within the domain of differentiability of \(f\). Note that this extends to piecewise smooth contours \(\gamma\).</p>



<p class="justify-text"><strong>Circle and rational functions.</strong> For a circle contour of center \(\lambda \in \mathbb{C}\) and radius \(r\), we have, with \(\gamma(t) = \lambda + re^{ 2i \pi t}\): $$\oint_{\gamma} \frac{dz}{(z-\lambda)^k} =\int_0^{1} \frac{ 2r i \pi e^{2i\pi t}}{ r^k e^{2i\pi kt}}dt= \int_0^{1} r^{1-k} i e^{2i\pi (1-k)t} dt,$$ which is equal to zero if \(k \neq 1\), and to \(\int_0^{1} 2i\pi dt = 2 i \pi\) for \(k =1\). Thus, for a function with a series expansion, the Cauchy residue formula is true for the circle around a single pole, because only the term in \(\frac{1}{z-\lambda}\) contributes.</p>



<p class="justify-text"><strong>No dependence on the contour.</strong> Now that the Cauchy formula is true for the circle around a single pole, we can “deform” the contour below to a circle.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img alt="" class="wp-image-5021" height="207" src="https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/contour_generic_circle-1024x532.png" width="398"/></figure></div>



<p>This can be done considering two contours \(\gamma_1\) and \(\gamma_2\) below with no poles inside, and thus with zero contour integrals, and for which the integrals along the added lines cancel.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img alt="" class="wp-image-5022" height="205" src="https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/contour_generic_circle_cut-1-1024x537.png" width="391"/></figure></div>



<p class="justify-text">This “shows” that the integral does not depend on the contour, and so in applications we can be quite liberal in the choice of contour. Note that similar constructions can be used to take into account several poles.</p>



<p class="justify-text">Before going to the spectral analysis of matrices, let us explore some cool choices of contours and integrands, and (again!) some positive definite kernels.</p>



<h2>Classical examples</h2>



<p class="justify-text">The Cauchy residue theorem can be used to compute integrals, by choosing the appropriate contour, looking for poles and computing the associated residues. Here are classical examples, before I show applications to kernel methods. See more examples in <a href="http://residuetheorem.com/">http://residuetheorem.com/</a>, and many in [11].</p>



<p class="justify-text"><strong>Fourier transforms. </strong> For \(\omega&gt;0\), we can compute \( \displaystyle \int_{-\infty}^\infty \!\! f(x) e^{ i \omega x} dx\) for holomorphic functions \(f\) by integrating on the real line and a big upper circle as shown below, with \(R\) tending to infinity (so that the contribution of the half-circle goes to zero because of the exponential term). This leads to \(2i \pi\) times the sum of all residues of the function \(z \mapsto f(z) e^{ i \omega z}\) in the upper half plane. See an example below related to kernel methods.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img alt="" class="wp-image-5026" height="214" src="https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/contour_upper-circle-2-1024x570.png" width="385"/></figure></div>



<p class="justify-text"><strong>Trigonometric integrals</strong>. For holomorphic functions \(Q\), we can compute the integral \(\displaystyle \int_0^{2\pi} \!\!\! Q(\cos \theta, \sin \theta) d\theta\). Indeed, letting \(f(z) = \frac{1}{iz} Q\big( \frac{z+z^{-1}}{2}, \frac{z-z^{-1}}{2i} \big)\), it is exactly equal to the integral on the unit circle. The desired integral is then equal to \(2i\pi\) times the sum of all residues of \(f\) within the unit disk.</p>



<p class="justify-text">For example, when \(Q(\cos \theta, \sin \theta) = \frac{1}{2 + \sin \theta}\), we have \(f(z) = \frac{2}{z^2+4iz-1}\), with a single pole inside the unit circle, namely \(\lambda = i ( \sqrt{3}-2)\), and residue equal to \(-i / \sqrt{3}\), leading to \(\int_0^{2\pi} \frac{d\theta}{2+\sin \theta} = \frac{2\pi}{\sqrt{3}}\).</p>



<p class="justify-text"><strong>Series.</strong> If the function \(f\) is holomorphic and has no poles at integer real values, and satisfies some basic boundedness conditions, then $$\sum_{n \in \mathbb{Z}} f(n) = \ – \!\!\! \sum_{ \lambda \in {\rm poles}(f)} {\rm Res}\big( f(z) \pi \frac{\cos \pi z}{\sin \pi z} ,\lambda\big).$$ This is a simple consequence of the fact that the function \(z \mapsto \pi \frac{\cos \pi z}{\sin \pi z}\) has all integers \(n \in \mathbb{Z}\) as poles, with corresponding residue equal to \(1\). This is obtained from the contour below with \(m\) tending to infinity.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img alt="" class="wp-image-5028" height="250" src="https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/contour_square-1-1024x903.png" width="284"/></figure></div>



<p class="justify-text">The same trick can be applied to  \(\displaystyle \sum_{n \in \mathbb{Z}} (-1)^n f(n) =\  –  \!\!\! \sum_{ \lambda \in {\rm poles}(f)} {\rm Res}\big( f(z) \pi \frac{1}{\sin \pi z} ,\lambda\big).\) See [7, Section 11.2] for more details. Experts will see an interesting link with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%E2%80%93Maclaurin_formula">Euler-MacLaurin formula</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernoulli_polynomials">Bernoulli polynomials</a>.</p>



<p class="justify-text"><strong>Applications to kernel methods.</strong> In non-parametric estimation, regularization penalties are used to constrain real-values functions to be smooth. One such examples are combinations of squared \(L_2\) norms of derivatives. For functions \(f\) defined on an interval \(I\) of the real line, penalties are typically of the form \(\int_I \sum_{k=0}^s \alpha_k | f^{(k)}(x)|^2 dx\), for non-negative weights \(\alpha_0,\dots,\alpha_k\). For these Sobolev space norms, a positive definite kernel \(K\) can be used for estimation (see, e.g., <a href="https://francisbach.com/hermite-polynomials/">last month blog post</a>). </p>



<p class="justify-text">A classical question is: given the norm defined above, how to compute \(K\)? For \(I = \mathbb{R}\), then this can be done using Fourier transforms as: $$K(x,y) =  \frac{1}{2\pi} \int_\mathbb{R} \frac{e^{i\omega(x-y)}}{\sum_{k=0}^s \alpha_k \omega^{2k}} d\omega.$$ This is exactly an integral of the form above, for which we can use the contour integration technique. For example, for \(\alpha_0=1\) and \(\alpha_1=a^2\), we get for \(x-y&gt;0\), one pole \(i/a\) in the upper half plane for the function \(\frac{1}{1+a^2 z^2} = \frac{1}{(1+iaz)(1-iaz)}\), with residue \(-\frac{i}{2a} e^{-(x-y)/a}\), leading to the familiar exponential kernel \(K(x,y) = \frac{1}{2a} e^{-|x-y|/a}\). More complex kernels can be considered (see, e.g., [8, page 277], for \(\sum_{k=0}^s \alpha_k \omega^{2k} = 1 + \omega^{2s}\)).</p>



<p class="justify-text">We can also consider the same penalty on the unit interval \([0,1]\) with periodic functions, leading to the kernel (see [9] for more details): $$ K(x,y) = \sum_{n \in \mathbb{Z}} \frac{ e^{2in\pi(x-y)}}{\sum_{k=0}^s \alpha_k( 2n\pi)^s}.$$ For the same example as above, that is, \(\alpha_0=1\) and \(\alpha_1=a^2\), this leads to an infinite series on which we can apply the Cauchy residue formula as explained above. This leads to, for \(x-y \in [0,1]\), \(K(x,y) =  \frac{1}{2a}  \frac{ \cosh (\frac{1-2(x-y)}{2a})}{\sinh (\frac{1}{2a})}\). We can then extend by \(1\)-periodicity to all \(x-y\). See the detailed computation at the end of the post.</p>



<p>Now that you are all experts in residue calculus, we can move on to spectral analysis.</p>



<h2>Spectral analysis of symmetric matrices</h2>



<p class="justify-text">We consider a symmetric matrix \(A \in \mathbb{R}^{n \times n}\), with its \(n\) ordered real eigenvalues \(\lambda_1 \geqslant  \cdots \geqslant \lambda_n\), counted with their orders of multiplicity, and an orthonormal basis of their eigenvectors \(u_j \in \mathbb{R}^n\), \(j=1,\dots,n\). We have \(A = \sum_{j=1}^n \lambda_j u_j u_j^\top\).  When we consider eigenvalues as functions of \(A\), we use the notation \(\lambda_j(A)\), \(j=1,\dots,n\). These functions are always well-defined even when eigenvalues are multiple (this is not the case for eigenvectors because of the invariance by orthogonal transformations).</p>



<p class="justify-text">The key property that we will use below is that we can express the so-called resolvent matrix \((z I – A)^{-1} \in \mathbb{C}^{n \times n}\), for \(z \in \mathbb{C}\), as: $$  (z I- A)^{-1}  = \sum_{j=1}^n \frac{1}{z-\lambda_j} u_j u_j^\top. $$ The dependence on \(z\) of the form \( \displaystyle \frac{1}{z- \lambda_j}\)  leads to a nice application of Cauchy residue formula.</p>



<p class="justify-text">Assuming the \(k\)-th eigenvalue \(\lambda_k\) is simple, we consider the contour \(\gamma\) going strictly around \(\lambda_k\) like below (for \(k=5\)).</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img alt="" class="wp-image-5039" height="182" src="https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/contour_single_eigenvalue-1024x433.png" width="431"/></figure></div>



<p class="justify-text">We consider integrating the matrix above, which leads to: $$ \oint_\gamma<br/>  (z I- A)^{-1} dz = \sum_{j=1}^m \Big( \oint_\gamma \frac{1}{z – \lambda_j} dz \Big) u_j u_j^\top<br/>  = 2 i \pi \  u_k u_k^\top $$  using the identity \(\displaystyle \oint_\gamma \frac{1}{z – \lambda_j} dz = 1\) if \(j=k\) and \(0\) otherwise (because the pole is outside of \(\gamma\)). We thus obtain an expression for projectors on the one-dimensional eigen-subspace associated with the eigenvalue \(\lambda_k\).</p>



<p class="justify-text">With simple manipulations, we can also access the eigenvalues. Indeed, we have: $$ \oint_\gamma<br/>   (z I- A)^{-1} z dz = \sum_{j=1}^m \Big( \oint_\gamma \frac{z}{z – \lambda_j} dz \Big) u_j u_j^\top<br/>  = 2 i \pi \lambda_k  u_k u_k^\top, $$ and by taking the trace, we obtain $$ \oint_\gamma<br/>  {\rm tr} \big[ z (z I- A)^{-1} \big]  dz    = \lambda_k. $$ The key benefit of these representations is that when the matrix \(A\) is slightly perturbed, then the same contour \(\gamma\) can be used to enclose the corresponding eigenvalues of the perturbed matrix, and perturbation results are simply obtained by taking gradients within the contour integral. Note that several eigenvalues may be summed up by selecting a contour englobing more than one eigenvalues.</p>



<h2>Gradients of eigenvalues</h2>



<p class="justify-text">The expression with contour integrals allows to derive simple formulas for gradients of eigenvalues. These can be obtained by other means [5], but using contour integrals shows that this is simply done by looking at the differential of \((z I – A)^{-1}\) and integrating it. The central component is the following expansion, which is a classical result in matrix differentiable calculus, with \(\|\Delta\|_2\) the operator norm of \(\Delta\) (i.e., its largest singular value):  $$<br/> (z I- A – \Delta)^{-1} = (z I – A)^{-1} + (z I- A)^{-1} \Delta (z I- A)^{-1} + o(\| \Delta\|_2).  $$ Note here that the asymptotic remainder \(o(\| \Delta\|_2)\) can be made explicit. </p>



<p class="justify-text">By expanding the expression on the basis of eigenvectors of \(A\), we get  $$<br/> z (z I- A – \Delta)^{-1}  – z (z I- A)^{-1}  =  \sum_{j=1}^n \sum_{\ell=1}^n u_j u_\ell^\top  \frac{ z \cdot u_j^\top \Delta u_\ell}{(z-\lambda_j)(z-\lambda_\ell)} + o(\| \Delta \|_2).<br/> $$ Taking the trace, the cross-product terms \({\rm tr}(u_j u_\ell^\top) =  u_\ell^\top u_j\) disappear for \(j \neq \ell\), and we get: $$<br/> {\rm tr} \big[ z (z I – A – \Delta)^{-1}  \big] – {\rm tr} \big[ z (z I – A)^{-1}  \big]=  \sum_{j=1}^n   \frac{ z \cdot u_j^\top \Delta u_j}{(z-\lambda_j)^2} + o(\| \Delta \|_2).<br/> $$ This leads to, by contour integration:<br/>$$<br/> \lambda_{k}(A+\Delta) -\lambda_k(A)<br/> =<br/> \frac{1}{2i \pi} \oint_\gamma \Big[ <br/>   \sum_{j=1}^n   \frac{ z \cdot u_j^\top \Delta u_j}{(z-\lambda_j)^2} \Big] dz +  o(\| \Delta \|_2).<br/> $$ By keeping only the pole \(\lambda_k\) which is inside the contour \(\gamma\), we get  $$ \lambda_{k}(A+\Delta) -\lambda_k(A)<br/>  =<br/> \frac{1}{2i \pi} \oint_\gamma \Big[ <br/>    \frac{ z \cdot u_k^\top \Delta u_k}{(z-\lambda_k)^2} \Big] dz +  o(| \Delta |_2) \<br/>    =  u_k^\top \Delta u_k + o(\| \Delta \|_2),<br/> $$ using the identity \(\displaystyle <br/>  \oint_\gamma \frac{z dz}{(z – \lambda_k)^2} dz = <br/>   \oint_\gamma \Big( \frac{\lambda_k}{(z – \lambda_k)^2}  + \frac{1}{z – \lambda_k} \Big) dz = 1\).  </p>



<p class="justify-text">Thus the gradient of \(\lambda_k\) at a matrix \(A\) where the \(k\)-th eigenvalue is simple is simply \( u_k u_k^\top\), where \(u_k\) is a corresponding eigenvector. Note that this result can be simply obtained by the simple (rough) calculation: if \(x\) is a unit eigenvector of \(A\), then \(Ax =\lambda x\), and \(x^\top x = 1\), leading to \(x^\top dx = 0\) and \(dA\ x + A dx = d\lambda \ x + \lambda dx\), and by taking the dot product with \(x\), \(d\lambda = x^\top dA\ x + x^\top A dx = x^\top dA \ x + \lambda x^\top  dx = x^\top dA \ x\), which is the same result. However, this reasoning is more cumbersome, and does not lead to neat approximation guarantees, in particular in the extensions below.</p>



<h2>Other perturbation results</h2>



<p class="justify-text">Given the gradient, other more classical perturbation results could de derived, such as Hessians of eigenvalues, or gradient of the projectors \(u_k u_k^\top\).  Here I derive a perturbation result for the projector \(\Pi_k(A)=u_k u_k^\top\), when \(\lambda_k\) is a simple eigenvalue. Using the same technique as above, we get: $$ \Pi_k(A+\Delta )\  – \Pi_k(A) = \frac{1}{2i \pi} \oint_\gamma (z I- A)^{-1} \Delta (z I – A)^{-1}dz  + o(\| \Delta\|_2),$$ which we can expand to the basis of eigenvectors as $$ \frac{1}{2i \pi} \oint_\gamma \sum_{j=1}^n \sum_{\ell=1}^n u_j u_j^\top \Delta u_\ell u_\ell^\top \frac{  dz}{(z-\lambda_\ell) (z-\lambda_j)  } + o(\| \Delta\|_2).$$ We can then split in two, with the two terms (all others are equal to zero by lack of poles within \(\gamma\)): $$ \frac{1}{2i \pi} \oint_\gamma \sum_{j \neq k}  u_j^\top \Delta u_k  ( u_j u_k^\top + u_k u_j^\top)   \frac{  dz}{(z-\lambda_k) (z-\lambda_j)  }= \sum_{j \neq k}  u_j^\top \Delta u_k  ( u_j u_k^\top + u_k u_j^\top) \frac{1}{\lambda_k – \lambda_j}  $$ and $$\frac{1}{2i \pi} \oint_\gamma   u_k^\top \Delta u_k   u_k u_k^\top  \frac{  dz}{(z-\lambda_k)^2  } = 0 ,$$ finally leading to $$\Pi_k(A+\Delta ) \ – \Pi_k(A) =  \sum_{j \neq k}  \frac{u_j^\top \Delta u_k}{\lambda_k – \lambda_j}    ( u_j u_k^\top + u_k u_j^\top)    + o(\| \Delta\|_2),$$ from which we can compute the Jacobian of \(\Pi_k\).</p>



<h2>Spectral functions</h2>



<p class="justify-text">Spectral functions are functions on symmetric matrices defined as \(F(A) = \sum_{k=1}^n f(\lambda_k(A))\), for any real-valued function \(f\). For \(f(x) = x\), we get back the trace, for \(f(x) = \log x\) we get back the log determinant, and so on. The function \(F\) can be represented as $$F(A) = \sum_{k=1}^n f(\lambda_k(A)) = \frac{1}{2i \pi} \oint_\gamma f(z) {\rm tr} \big[ (z I  – A)^{-1} \big] dz,$$ where the contour \(\gamma\) encloses all eigenvalues (as shown below).</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img alt="" class="wp-image-5087" height="185" src="https://francisbach.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/contour_all_eigenvalues-1024x433.png" width="438"/></figure></div>



<p class="justify-text">This representation can be used to compute derivatives of \(F\), by simple derivations, to obtain the same result as [<a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/pdf/10.1137/S089547980036838X">12</a>].</p>



<h2>Singular values of rectangular matrices</h2>



<p class="justify-text">Singular value decompositions are also often used, for a rectangular matrix \(W \in \mathbb{R}^{n \times d}\). It consists in finding \(r\) pairs \((u_j,v_j) \in \mathbb{R}^{n} \times \mathbb{R}^d\), \(j=1,\dots,r\), of singular vectors and \(r\) positive singular values \(\sigma_1 \geqslant \cdots \geqslant \sigma_r &gt; 0\) such that \(W = \sum_{j=1}^r \sigma_j u_j v_j^\top\) and  \((u_1,\dots,u_r)\) and \((v_1,\dots,v_r)\) are orthonormal families.</p>



<p class="justify-text">There are two natural ways to relate the singular value decomposition to the classical eigenvalue decomposition of a symmetric matrix, �first through \(WW^\top\) (or similarly \(W^\top W\)). Here it is more direct to consider the so-called Jordan-Wielandt matrix, defined by blocks as $$<br/> \bar{W} = \left( \begin{array}{cc}<br/>0 &amp; W \\<br/>W^\top &amp; 0 \end{array} \right). $$ The matrix \(\bar{W}\) is symmetric, and its non zero eigenvalues are \(+\sigma_i\) and \(-\sigma_i\), \(i=1,\dots,r\), associated with the eigenvectors \(\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}  \left( \begin{array}{cc}<br/>u_i \\ v_i \end{array} \right)\) and \(\frac{1}{\sqrt{2}}  \left( \begin{array}{cc}<br/>u_i \\ -v_i \end{array} \right)\).</p>



<p class="justify-text">All necessary results (derivatives of singular values \(\sigma_j\), or projectors \(u_j v_j^\top\) can be obtained from there); see more details, in, e.g., the appendix of [6].</p>



<h2>Going beyond</h2>



<p class="justify-text">In this post, I have shown various applications of the Cauchy residue formula, for computing integrals and for the spectral analysis of matrices. I have just scratched the surface of spectral analysis, and what I presented extends to many interesting situations, for example, to more general linear operators in infinite-dimensional spaces [3], or to the analysis fo the eigenvalue distribution of random matrices (see a nice and reasonably simple derivation of the semi-circular law from <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/2010/02/02/254a-notes-4-the-semi-circular-law/">Terry Tao’s blog</a>).</p>



<h2>References</h2>



<p class="justify-text">[1] Gilbert W. Stewart and Sun Ji-Huang. <em>Matrix Perturbation Theory</em>. Academic Press, 1990.<br/>[2] Adrian Stephen Lewis. Derivatives of spectral functions. <em>Mathematics of Operations Research</em>, 21(3):576–588, 1996. <br/>[3] Tosio Kato. <em>Perturbation Theory for Linear Operators</em>, volume 132. Springer, 2013. <br/>[4] Serge Lang. <em>Complex Analysis</em>, volume 103. Springer, 2013. <br/>[5] Jan R. Magnus. On differentiating eigenvalues and eigenvectors. <em>Econometric Theory</em>, 1(2):179–191, 1985. <br/>[6] Francis Bach. Consistency of trace norm minimization. <em>Journal of Machine Learning Research</em>, 9:1019-1048, 2008.<br/>[7] Joseph Bak, Donald J. Newman. <em>Complex analysis</em>. New York: Springer, 2010.<br/>[8] Alain Berlinet, and Christine Thomas-Agnan. <em>Reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces in probability and statistics</em>. Springer Science &amp; Business Media, 2011.<br/>[9] Grace Wahba. <a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/book/10.1137/1.9781611970128">Spline models for observational data</a>. Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics, 1990.<br/>[10] Augustin Louis Cauchy, <a href="https://archive.org/details/mmoiresurlesin00cauc">Mémoire</a><a href="http://www.numdam.org/article/BSMA_1874__7__265_0.pdf"> sur les intégrales définies, prises entre des limites imaginaires</a>, 1825, <a href="http://www.numdam.org/article/BSMA_1874__7__265_0.pdf">re-published</a> in Bulletin des Sciences Mathématiques et Astronomiques, Tome 7, 265-304, 1874.<br/>[11] Dragoslav S. Mitrinovic, and Jovan D. Keckic. <em>The Cauchy method of residues: theory and applications</em>. Vol. 9. Springer Science &amp; Business Media, 1984.<br/>[12] Adrian S. Lewis, and Hristo S. Sendov. <a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/pdf/10.1137/S089547980036838X">Twice differentiable spectral functions</a>. <em>SIAM Journal on Matrix Analysis and Applications</em> 23.2: 368-386, 2001.</p>



<h2>Computing the Sobolev kernel</h2>



<p class="justify-text">The goal is to compute the infinite sum $$\sum_{n \in \mathbb{Z}} \frac{e^{2i\pi q \cdot n}}{1+(2a \pi n)^2}$$ for \(q \in (0,1)\). We consider the function $$f(z) = \frac{e^{i\pi (2q-1) z}}{1+(2a \pi z)^2} \frac{\pi}{\sin (\pi z)}.$$ It is holomorphic on \(\mathbb{C}\) except at all integers \(n \in \mathbb{Z}\), where it has a simple pole with residue \(\displaystyle \frac{e^{i\pi (2q-1) n}}{1+(2a \pi n)^2} (-1)^n = \frac{e^{i\pi 2q n}}{1+(2a \pi n)^2}\), at \(z = i/(2a\pi)\) where it has a residue equal to \(\displaystyle \frac{e^{ – (2q-1)/(2a)}}{4ia\pi} \frac{\pi}{\sin (i/(2a))} = \ – \frac{e^{ – (2q-1)/(2a)}}{4a} \frac{1}{\sinh (1/(2a))}\), and at \(z = -i/(2a\pi)\) where it has a residue equal to \(\displaystyle \frac{e^{  (2q-1)/(2a)}}{4ia\pi} \frac{\pi}{\sin (i/(2a))} =\ – \frac{e^{ (2q-1)/(2a)}}{4a} \frac{1}{\sinh (1/(2a))}\). With all residues summing to zero (note that this fact requires a precise analysis of limits when \(m\) tends to infinity for the contour defined in the main text), we get: $$\sum_{n \in \mathbb{Z}} \frac{e^{2i\pi q \cdot n}}{1+(2a \pi n)^2} =\frac{e^{ – (2q-1)/(2a)}}{4a} \frac{1}{\sinh (1/(2a))}+ \frac{e^{ (2q-1)/(2a)}}{4a} \frac{1}{\sinh (1/(2a))} = \frac{1}{2a} \frac{ \cosh (\frac{2q-1}{2a})}{\sinh (\frac{1}{2a})}.$$</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-07T12:10:25Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-07T12:10:25Z</published>
    <category term="Tools"/>
    <author>
      <name>Francis Bach</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://francisbach.com</id>
      <link href="https://francisbach.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://francisbach.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Francis Bach</subtitle>
      <title>Machine Learning Research Blog</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:38:49Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/07/faculty-at-university-of-rochester-apply-by-january-1-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/07/faculty-at-university-of-rochester-apply-by-january-1-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>faculty at University of Rochester (apply by January 1, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Computer Science Department at the University of Rochester seeks applicants for tenure-track faculty positions. We are particularly eager to hire in theory, security/privacy/cryptography, quantum computing, data management, natural language processing, and machine learning. Candidates at any level of seniority are encouraged to apply. Website: https://www.rochester.edu/faculty-recruiting/positions/show/10942 Email: stefanko@cs.rochester.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Computer Science Department at the University of Rochester seeks applicants for tenure-track faculty positions. We are particularly eager to hire in theory, security/privacy/cryptography, quantum computing, data management, natural language processing, and machine learning. Candidates at any level of seniority are encouraged to apply.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.rochester.edu/faculty-recruiting/positions/show/10942">https://www.rochester.edu/faculty-recruiting/positions/show/10942</a><br/>
Email: stefanko@cs.rochester.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-07T12:09:14Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-07T12:09:14Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=509</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2020/11/06/tcs-talk-wednesday-november-11-shuai-shao-uw-madison/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, November 11 — Shuai Shao, UW-Madison</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, November 11th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). Shuai Shao from UW-Madison will speak about “A Dichotomy for Real Boolean Holant Problems” (abstract below). You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, November 11th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). <strong>Shuai Shao</strong> from UW-Madison will speak about “<em>A Dichotomy for Real Boolean Holant Problems</em>” (abstract below). </p>



<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk/live-seat-reservation">the online form</a>. Due to security concerns, <em>registration is required</em> to attend the interactive talk. As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/">the website</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-quote">Abstract: In this talk, we present a complexity dichotomy for Holant problems on the boolean domain with arbitrary sets of real-valued constraint functions. These constraint functions need not be symmetric nor do we assume any auxiliary functions as in previous results. It is proved that for every set <img alt="F" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=F&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="F"/> of real-valued constraint functions, <img alt="\text{Holant}(F)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctext%7BHolant%7D%28F%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\text{Holant}(F)"/> is either <img alt="P" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=P&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="P"/>-time computable or <img alt="\#P" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%23P&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\#P"/>-hard. The classification has an explicit criterion. This is a culmination of much research on a decade-long classification program for Holant problems, and it uses previous results and techniques from many researchers.  However, as it turned out, the journey to the present theorem has been arduous. Some particularly intriguing concrete functions f6, f8 and their associated families with extraordinary closure properties related to Bell states in quantum information theory play an important role in this proof.  <br/><br/>Based on joint work with Jin-Yi Cai.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-07T04:30:21Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-07T04:30:21Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:38:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5071</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5071" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5071#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5071" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">On the removal of a hideous growth</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">The title of this post is not an allegory. At 10am this morning, I had a previously-scheduled appointment with an oral surgeon to remove a large, hideous, occasionally painful growth on the inside of my lower lip. (I’d delayed getting it looked at for several months because of covid, but I no longer could.) So […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The title of this post is not an allegory.</p>



<p>At 10am this morning, I had a previously-scheduled appointment with an oral surgeon to remove a large, hideous, occasionally painful growth on the inside of my lower lip.  (I’d delayed getting it looked at for several months because of covid, but I no longer could.)</p>



<p>So right now I’m laying in bed at home, with gauze on my lips, dazed, hopped up on painkillers.  I regret that things ever got to the point where this was needed.  I believe, intellectually, that the surgeon executed about as competently as anyone could ask.  But I still wish, if we’re being honest, that there hadn’t been <em>quite</em> this much pain in the surgery or in the recovery from it.</p>



<p>Again intellectually, I know that there’s still lots more pain in the days ahead.  I’m not sure that whatever it was won’t just quickly grow back.  And yet, I couldn’t be feeling more joy through my whole body with every one of these words that I write.  At last I can honestly tell myself: the growth is gone.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-06T19:15:33Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-06T19:15:33Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-11-08T15:51:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/161</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/161" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-161 |  Seed Protecting Extractors | 

	Gil Cohen, 

	Dean Doron, 

	Shahar Samocha</title>
    <summary>We introduce a new type of seeded extractors we dub seed protecting extractors. Informally, a seeded extractor is seed protecting against a class of functions $C$, mappings seeds to seeds, if the seed $Y$ remains close to uniform even after observing the output $\mathrm{Ext}(X,A(Y))$ for every choice of $A \in C$ (or, more generally, observing the outputs corresponding to several adversaries from $C$).

The results of this paper are structural. We establish what we believe to be surprising relations, in fact, equivalences between seed protecting extractors and each of the well-studied strengthenings of seeded extractors: strong extractors, non-malleable extractors (against permutations), and two-source extractors, where each case is classified by a suitable class $C$. Our work put forth a novel approach for constructing nonmalleable extractors against permutations. Indeed, the existing machinery developed for constructing non-malleable extractors focuses on the output and so it is aimed towards breaking correlations. Instead, our work suggests developing techniques for protecting the seed.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-05T20:06:42Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-05T20:06:42Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/04/postdoc-in-algorithms-at-northwestern-university-and-ttic-apply-by-january-1-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/04/postdoc-in-algorithms-at-northwestern-university-and-ttic-apply-by-january-1-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc in Algorithms at Northwestern University and TTIC (apply by January 1, 2021)</title>
    <summary>Northwestern University (NU) &amp; Toyota Technology Institute at Chicago (TTIC) invite applications for postdoc fellowships to conduct research in approx algorithms, beyond-worst-case analysis, high-dimensional data analysis. Postdocs will work with Profs. S. Khuller, K. Makarychev, Y. Makarychev, and A. Vijayaraghavan. Positions are based at NU but postdocs are encouraged to spend some time at TTIC. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Northwestern University (NU) &amp; Toyota Technology Institute at Chicago (TTIC) invite applications for postdoc fellowships to conduct research in approx algorithms, beyond-worst-case analysis, high-dimensional data analysis. Postdocs will work with Profs. S. Khuller, K. Makarychev, Y. Makarychev, and A. Vijayaraghavan. Positions are based at NU but postdocs are encouraged to spend some time at TTIC.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17450">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/17450</a><br/>
Email: nu.cstheory@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-04T19:32:04Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-04T19:32:04Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://dstheory.wordpress.com/?p=69</id>
    <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2020/11/04/monday-nov-09-tal-rabin-from-university-of-pennsylvania/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Monday, Nov 09 — Tal Rabin from University of Pennsylvania</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The next Foundations of Data Science virtual talk will take place on Monday, Nov 09th at 10:00 AM Pacific Time (1:00 pm Eastern Time, 18:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC).  Tal Rabin from UPenn will speak about “You Only Speak Once — Secure MPC with Stateless Ephemeral Roles”. Abstract: The inherent difficulty of maintaining stateful environments<a class="more-link" href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/2020/11/04/monday-nov-09-tal-rabin-from-university-of-pennsylvania/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">"Monday, Nov 09 — Tal Rabin from University of Pennsylvania"</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next Foundations of Data Science virtual talk will take place on Monday, Nov 09th at 10:00 AM Pacific Time (1:00 pm Eastern Time, 18:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC).  <strong>Tal Rabin </strong>from UPenn will speak about “<strong>You Only Speak Once — Secure MPC with Stateless Ephemeral Roles</strong>”.</p>



<p><strong>Abstract</strong>: The inherent difficulty of maintaining stateful environments over long periods of time gave rise to the paradigm of serverless computing, where mostly-stateless components are deployed on demand to handle computation tasks, and are teared down once their task is complete. Serverless architecture could offer the added benefit of improved resistance to targeted denial-of-service attacks. Realizing such protection,<br/>requires that the protocol only uses stateless parties. Perhaps the most famous example of this style of protocols is the Nakamoto consensus protocol used in Bitcoin. We refer to this stateless property as the You-Only-Speak-Once (YOSO) property, and initiate the formal study of it within a new YOSO model. Our model is centered around the notion of roles, which are stateless parties that can only send a single message. Furthermore, we describe several techniques for achieving YOSO MPC; both computational and information theoretic.</p>



<p>The talk will be self contained.</p>



<p>Based on joint works with: Fabrice Benhamouda, Craig Gentry, Sergey Gorbunov, Shai Halevi, Hugo Krawczyk, Chengyu Lin, Bernardo Magri, Jesper Nielsen, Leo Reyzin, Sophia Yakoubov.</p>



<p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/dstheory" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">Please register here to join the virtual talk.</a></p>



<p>The series is supported by the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1934846&amp;HistoricalAwards=false">NSF HDR TRIPODS Grant 1934846</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-04T15:40:16Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-04T15:40:16Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>dstheory</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://dstheory.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://dstheory.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Foundation of Data Science – Virtual Talk Series</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:38:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/04/postdoc-at-ut-san-antonio-apply-by-december-1-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/04/postdoc-at-ut-san-antonio-apply-by-december-1-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at UT San Antonio (apply by December 1, 2020)</title>
    <summary>We have a two year postdoctoral position at UT San Antonio in geometry, probability, optimization, and computing. Applications are on a rolling basis; to be considered in the first round please send your application by 12/01/20 using the mathjobs link. Website: https://www.mathjobs.org/jobs/list/16692 Email: alperen.ergur@utsa.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We have a two year postdoctoral position at UT San Antonio in geometry, probability, optimization, and computing. Applications are on a rolling basis; to be considered in the first round please send your application by 12/01/20 using the mathjobs link.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.mathjobs.org/jobs/list/16692">https://www.mathjobs.org/jobs/list/16692</a><br/>
Email: alperen.ergur@utsa.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-04T14:35:54Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-04T14:35:54Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7875</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/11/03/yet-another-backpropagation-tutorial/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Yet another backpropagation tutorial</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am teaching deep learing this week in Harvard’s CS 182 (Artificial Intelligence) course. As I’m preparing the back-propagation lecture, Preetum Nakkiran told me about Andrej Karpathy’s awesome micrograd package which implements automatic differentiation for scalar variables in very few lines of code. I couldn’t resist using this to show how simple back-propagation and stochastic … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/11/03/yet-another-backpropagation-tutorial/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Yet another backpropagation tutorial</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I am teaching deep learing this week in Harvard’s CS 182 (Artificial Intelligence) course. As I’m preparing the back-propagation lecture, Preetum Nakkiran told me about <a href="https://github.com/karpathy/micrograd">Andrej Karpathy’s awesome micrograd package</a> which implements automatic differentiation for scalar variables in very few lines of code.</p>



<p>I couldn’t resist using this to show how simple back-propagation and stochastic gradient descents are. To make sure we leave nothing “under the hood” we will not import anything from the package but rather only copy paste the few things we need. I hope that the text below is generally accessible to anyone familiar with partial derivatives. See this <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1eLEIMxlGZfAIYPWZMcBCPDLeVJzBMdYf?usp=sharing">colab notebook</a> for all the code in this tutorial. In particular, aside from libraries for plotting and copy pasting a few dozen lines from Karpathy this code uses absolutely no libraries (no numpy, no pytorch, etc..) and can train (slowly..) neural networks using stochastic gradient descent.  (This <a href="https://deepnote.com/publish/f898cdd4-4815-42ad-ba57-ae0b8b733492">notebook</a> builds the code more incrementally.)</p>



<p><strong>Automatic differentiation</strong> is a mechanism that allows you to write a Python functions such as</p>


<pre class="brush: python; gutter: false; title: ; notranslate">def f(x,y): return (x+y)+x**3
</pre>


<p>and enables one to automatically obtain the partial derivatives <img alt="\tfrac{\partial f}{\partial \text{x}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+f%7D%7B%5Cpartial+%5Ctext%7Bx%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{\partial f}{\partial \text{x}}"/> and <img alt="\tfrac{\partial f}{\partial \text{y}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+f%7D%7B%5Cpartial+%5Ctext%7By%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{\partial f}{\partial \text{y}}"/>. Numerically we could do this by choosing some small value <img alt="\delta" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdelta&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\delta"/> and computing both <img alt="\tfrac{f(x+\delta,y)-f(x,y)}{\delta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7Bf%28x%2B%5Cdelta%2Cy%29-f%28x%2Cy%29%7D%7B%5Cdelta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{f(x+\delta,y)-f(x,y)}{\delta}"/> and <img alt="\tfrac{f(x,y+\delta)-f(x,y)}{\delta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7Bf%28x%2Cy%2B%5Cdelta%29-f%28x%2Cy%29%7D%7B%5Cdelta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{f(x,y+\delta)-f(x,y)}{\delta}"/>.<br/>However, if we generalize this approach to <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n"/> variables, we get an algorithm that requires roughly <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n"/> evaluations of <img alt="f" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f"/>. <em>Back-propagation</em> enables computing <em>all</em> of the partial derivatives at only constant overhead over the cost of a single evaluation of <img alt="f" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f"/>.</p>



<h2>Back propagation and the chain rule</h2>



<p>Back-propagation is a direct implication of the <strong>multi-variate chain rule</strong>. Let’s illustrate this for the case of two variables. Suppose that <img alt="v,w: \mathbb{R} \rightarrow \mathbb{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v%2Cw%3A+%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D+%5Crightarrow+%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v,w: \mathbb{R} \rightarrow \mathbb{R}"/> and <img alt="z:\mathbb{R}^2 \rightarrow \mathbb{R}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=z%3A%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D%5E2+%5Crightarrow+%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="z:\mathbb{R}^2 \rightarrow \mathbb{R}"/> are functions, and define</p>



<p><img alt="f(u) = z(v(u),w(u))" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f%28u%29+%3D+z%28v%28u%29%2Cw%28u%29%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f(u) = z(v(u),w(u))"/>.</p>



<p>That is, we have the following situation:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img alt="" src="https://i.imgur.com/KGVphzL.png"/></figure>



<p>where <img alt="f(u)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f%28u%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f(u)"/> is the value <img alt="z=z(v(u),w(u))" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=z%3Dz%28v%28u%29%2Cw%28u%29%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="z=z(v(u),w(u))"/></p>



<p>Then the <strong>chain rule</strong> states that</p>



<p><img alt="\tfrac{\partial f}{\partial u} = ( \tfrac{\partial v}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v} + \tfrac{\partial w}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w} )" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+f%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D+%3D+%28+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+v%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D+%5Ccdot+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+v%7D+%2B+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+w%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D+%5Ccdot+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+w%7D+%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{\partial f}{\partial u} = ( \tfrac{\partial v}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v} + \tfrac{\partial w}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w} )"/></p>



<p>You can take this on faith, but it also has a simple proof. To see the intuition, note that for small <img alt="\delta" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdelta&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\delta"/>, <img alt="v(u+\delta) \approx v(u) + \delta \tfrac{\partial v}{\partial u}(u)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v%28u%2B%5Cdelta%29+%5Capprox+v%28u%29+%2B+%5Cdelta+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+v%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D%28u%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v(u+\delta) \approx v(u) + \delta \tfrac{\partial v}{\partial u}(u)"/> and <img alt="w(u+\delta) \approx w(u) + \delta \tfrac{\partial w}{\partial u}(u)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=w%28u%2B%5Cdelta%29+%5Capprox+w%28u%29+%2B+%5Cdelta+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+w%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D%28u%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="w(u+\delta) \approx w(u) + \delta \tfrac{\partial w}{\partial u}(u)"/>. For small <img alt="\delta_1,\delta_2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdelta_1%2C%5Cdelta_2&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\delta_1,\delta_2"/>, <img alt="z(v+\delta_1,w+\delta_2) \approx z(v,w) + \delta_1 \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v}(z,w) + \delta_2 \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=z%28v%2B%5Cdelta_1%2Cw%2B%5Cdelta_2%29+%5Capprox+z%28v%2Cw%29+%2B+%5Cdelta_1+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+v%7D%28z%2Cw%29+%2B+%5Cdelta_2+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+w%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="z(v+\delta_1,w+\delta_2) \approx z(v,w) + \delta_1 \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v}(z,w) + \delta_2 \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w}"/>. Hence, if we ignore terms with powers of delta two or higher,</p>



<p><img alt="f(u +\delta)= z(w(u+\delta),v(u+\delta)) \approx f(u) + \delta \tfrac{\partial v}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v} + \delta \tfrac{\partial w}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f%28u+%2B%5Cdelta%29%3D+z%28w%28u%2B%5Cdelta%29%2Cv%28u%2B%5Cdelta%29%29+%5Capprox+f%28u%29+%2B+%5Cdelta+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+v%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D+%5Ccdot+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+v%7D+%2B+%5Cdelta+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+w%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D+%5Ccdot+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+w%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f(u +\delta)= z(w(u+\delta),v(u+\delta)) \approx f(u) + \delta \tfrac{\partial v}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v} + \delta \tfrac{\partial w}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w}"/></p>



<p/>



<p>The chain rule generalizes naturally to the case that <img alt="z" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=z&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="z"/> is a function of more variables than <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/>. Generally, if the value <img alt="f(u)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f%28u%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f(u)"/> is obtained by first computing some intermediate values <img alt="v_1,\ldots,v_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v_1%2C%5Cldots%2Cv_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v_1,\ldots,v_k"/> from <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> and then computing <img alt="z" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=z&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="z"/> in some arbitrary way from <img alt="v_1,\ldots,v_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v_1%2C%5Cldots%2Cv_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v_1,\ldots,v_k"/>, then <img alt="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial u} \sum_{i=1}^k \tfrac{\partial v_i}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v_i}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D+%5Csum_%7Bi%3D1%7D%5Ek+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+v_i%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D+%5Ccdot+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+v_i%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial u} \sum_{i=1}^k \tfrac{\partial v_i}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v_i}"/>.</p>



<p>As a corollary, if you already managed to compute the values <img alt="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v_1},\ldots, \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v_k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+v_1%7D%2C%5Cldots%2C+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+v_k%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v_1},\ldots, \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v_k}"/>, and you kept track of the way that <img alt="v_1,\ldots,v_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v_1%2C%5Cldots%2Cv_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v_1,\ldots,v_k"/> were obtained from <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/>, then you can compute <img alt="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial u}"/>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img alt="" src="https://i.imgur.com/35jj2wz.png"/></figure>



<p>This suggests a simple recursive algorithm by which you compute the derivative of the final value <img alt="z" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=z&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="z"/> with respect to an intermediate value <img alt="w" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=w&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="w"/> in the computation using recursive calls to compute the values <img alt="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w'}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+w%27%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w'}"/> for all the values <img alt="w'" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=w%27&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="w'"/> that were directly computed from <img alt="w" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=w&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="w"/>. Back propagation is this algorithm.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/backprop_example.png"><img alt="" class="wp-image-7887" src="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/backprop_example.png?w=1024"/></a>Computing <img alt="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial u},\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v}, \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D%2C%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+v%7D%2C+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+w%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial u},\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial v}, \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w}"/>  for the assignment <img alt="u=5" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u%3D5&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u=5"/> using back propagation</figure>



<h2>Implementing automatic differentiation using back propagation in Python</h2>



<p>We now describe how to do this in Python, following Karpathy’s code. The basic class we use is <code>Value</code>. Every member <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> of <code>Value</code> is a container that holds:</p>



<ol><li>The actual scalar (i.e., floating point) value that <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> holds. We call this <code>data</code>.</li><li>The gradient of <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> with respect to some future unknown value <img alt="f" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f"/> that will use it. We call this <code>grad</code> and it is initialized to zero.</li><li>Pointers to all the values that were used in the computation of <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/>. We call this <code>_prev</code></li><li>The method that adds (using the current value of <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> and other values) the contribution of <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> to the gradient of all its previous values <img alt="v" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v"/> to their gradients. We call this function <code>_backward</code>. Specifically, at the time we call <code>_backward</code> we assume that <code>u.grad</code> already contains <img alt="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial u}"/> where <img alt="z" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=z&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="z"/> is the final value we are interested in. For every value <img alt="v" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v"/> that was used to compute <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/>, we add to <code>v.grad</code> the quantity <img alt="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial u}{\partial v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D+%5Ccdot+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+u%7D%7B%5Cpartial+v%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\tfrac{\partial z}{\partial u} \cdot \tfrac{\partial u}{\partial v}"/>. For the latter quantity we need to keep track of <em>how</em> <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> was computed from <img alt="b" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=b&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="b"/>.</li><li>If we call the method <code>backwards</code> (without an underscore) on a variable <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> then this will compute the derivative of <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> with respect to <img alt="v" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v"/> for all values <img alt="v" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v"/> that were used in the computation of <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/>. We do this by applying <code>_backward</code> to <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> and then recursively (just like in DFS) going over the “children” (values used to compute <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/>), calling <code>_backward</code> on each one and keeping track the ones we visited just like the Depth First Search (DFS) algorithm.</li></ol>



<p>Let’s now describe this in code. We start off with a simple version that only supports addition and multiplication. The constructor for the class is the following:</p>


<pre class="brush: python; gutter: false; title: ; notranslate">class Value:
    """ stores a single scalar value and its gradient """

    def __init__(self, data, _children=()):
        self.data = data
        self.grad = 0
        self._backward = lambda: None
        self._prev = set(_children)
</pre>


<p>which fairly directly matches the description above. This constructor creates a value not using prior ones, which is why the <code>_backward</code> function is empty.<br/>However, we can also create values by adding or multiplying prior ones, by adding the following methods:</p>


<pre class="brush: python; gutter: false; title: ; notranslate">  def __add__(self, other):
        other = other if isinstance(other, Value) else Value(other)
        out = Value(self.data + other.data, (self, other))

        def _backward():
            self.grad += out.grad
            other.grad += out.grad
        out._backward = _backward

        return out

    def __mul__(self, other):
        other = other if isinstance(other, Value) else Value(other)
        out = Value(self.data * other.data, (self, other))

        def _backward():
            self.grad += other.data * out.grad
            other.grad += self.data * out.grad
        out._backward = _backward

        return out
</pre>


<p>That is, if we create <img alt="w" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=w&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="w"/> by adding the values <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> and <img alt="v" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v"/>, then the <code>_backward</code> function of <img alt="w" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=w&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="w"/> works by adding <code>w.grad</code> <img alt="= \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%3D+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+w%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="= \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w}"/> to both <code>u.grad</code> and <code>v.grad</code>.<br/>If we <img alt="w" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=w&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="w"/> is obtain by multiplying <img alt="u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="u"/> and <img alt="v" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=v&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="v"/> then we add <code>w.grad</code> <img alt="\cdot" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ccdot&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\cdot"/> <code>v.data</code> <img alt="= \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w} v" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%3D+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+w%7D+v&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="= \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w} v"/> to <code>u.grad</code> and similarly add <code>w.grad</code> <img alt="\cdot" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ccdot&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\cdot"/> <code>u.data</code> <img alt="= \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w} u" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%3D+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+z%7D%7B%5Cpartial+w%7D+u&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="= \tfrac{\partial z}{\partial w} u"/> to <code>v.grad</code>.</p>



<p>The <code>backward</code> function is obtained by setting the gradient of the current value to <img alt="1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="1"/> and then running <code>_backwards</code> on all other values in reverse topological order:</p>


<pre class="brush: python; gutter: false; title: ; notranslate">def backward(self, visited= None): # slightly shorter code to fit in the blog 
    if visited is None:
        visited= set([self])
        self.grad = 1
    self._backward()
    for child in self._prev:
        if not child in visited:
            visited.add(child)
            child.backward(visited)
</pre>


<p>For example, if we run the following code</p>


<pre class="brush: python; gutter: false; title: ; notranslate">a = Value(5)
print(a.grad)
def f(x): return (x+2)**2 + x**3
f(a).backward()
print(a.grad)
</pre>


<p>then the values printed will be <code>0</code> and <code>89</code> since the derivative of <img alt="(x+2)^2 + x^3 = x^3 + x^2 + 4x + 4" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28x%2B2%29%5E2+%2B+x%5E3+%3D+x%5E3+%2B+x%5E2+%2B+4x+%2B+4&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="(x+2)^2 + x^3 = x^3 + x^2 + 4x + 4"/> equals <img alt="3x^2 + 2x +42" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=3x%5E2+%2B+2x+%2B42&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="3x^2 + 2x +42"/>.</p>



<p>In the <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1eLEIMxlGZfAIYPWZMcBCPDLeVJzBMdYf?usp=sharing#scrollTo=0_nveKyfxXQK">notebook</a> you can see that we implement also the power function, and have some “convenience methods” (division etc..).</p>



<h3>Linear regression using back propagation and stochastic gradient descent</h3>



<p>In <em>stochastic gradient descent</em> we are given some data <img alt="(x_1,y_1),\ldots,(x_n,y_n)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28x_1%2Cy_1%29%2C%5Cldots%2C%28x_n%2Cy_n%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="(x_1,y_1),\ldots,(x_n,y_n)"/> and want to find an hypothesis <img alt="h" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=h&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="h"/> that minimizes the empirical loss <img alt="L(h) = \tfrac{1}{n}\sum_{i=1}^n L(h(x_i),y_i)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%28h%29+%3D+%5Ctfrac%7B1%7D%7Bn%7D%5Csum_%7Bi%3D1%7D%5En+L%28h%28x_i%29%2Cy_i%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L(h) = \tfrac{1}{n}\sum_{i=1}^n L(h(x_i),y_i)"/> where <img alt="L" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L"/> is a <em>loss function</em> mapping two labels <img alt="y, y'" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=y%2C+y%27&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="y, y'"/> to a real number. If we let <img alt="L_i(h)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L_i%28h%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L_i(h)"/> be the <img alt="i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="i"/>-th term of this sum, then, identifying <img alt="h" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=h&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="h"/> with the parameters (i.e., real numbers) that specify it, stochastic gradient descent is the following algorithm:</p>



<ol><li>Set <img alt="h" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=h&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="h"/> to be a random vector. Set <img alt="\eta" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ceta&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\eta"/> to be some small number (e.g., <img alt="\eta = 0.1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Ceta+%3D+0.1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\eta = 0.1"/>)</li><li>For <img alt="t \in {1,\ldots, T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=t+%5Cin+%7B1%2C%5Cldots%2C+T%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="t \in {1,\ldots, T}"/> (where <img alt="T" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=T&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="T"/> is the number of <em>epochs</em>):</li></ol>



<ul><li>For <img alt="i \in {1,\ldots, n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=i+%5Cin+%7B1%2C%5Cldots%2C+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="i \in {1,\ldots, n}"/>: (in random order)<ul><li>Let <img alt="h \leftarrow h - \eta \nabla_h L_i(h)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=h+%5Cleftarrow+h+-+%5Ceta+%5Cnabla_h+L_i%28h%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="h \leftarrow h - \eta \nabla_h L_i(h)"/></li></ul></li></ul>



<p>If <img alt="h" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=h&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="h"/> is specified by the parameters <img alt="h_1,\ldots,h_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=h_1%2C%5Cldots%2Ch_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="h_1,\ldots,h_k"/> <img alt="\nabla_h L_i(h)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cnabla_h+L_i%28h%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\nabla_h L_i(h)"/> is the vector <img alt="( \tfrac{\partial L_i}{\partial h_1}(h), \tfrac{\partial L_i}{\partial h_2}(h),\ldots, \tfrac{\partial L_i}{\partial h_k}(h))" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+L_i%7D%7B%5Cpartial+h_1%7D%28h%29%2C+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+L_i%7D%7B%5Cpartial+h_2%7D%28h%29%2C%5Cldots%2C+%5Ctfrac%7B%5Cpartial+L_i%7D%7B%5Cpartial+h_k%7D%28h%29%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="( \tfrac{\partial L_i}{\partial h_1}(h), \tfrac{\partial L_i}{\partial h_2}(h),\ldots, \tfrac{\partial L_i}{\partial h_k}(h))"/>. This is exactly the vector we can obtain using back propagation.</p>



<p>For example, if we want a linear model, we can use <img alt="(a,b)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28a%2Cb%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="(a,b)"/> as our parameters and the function will be <img alt="x \mapsto a\cdot + b" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x+%5Cmapsto+a%5Ccdot+%2B+b&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="x \mapsto a\cdot + b"/>. We can generate random points <code>X</code>,<code>Y</code> as follows:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img alt="" src="https://i.imgur.com/4Do0KI4.png"/></figure>



<p>Now we can define a linear model as follows:</p>


<pre class="brush: python; gutter: false; title: ; notranslate">class Linear:
  def __init__(self):
    self.a,self.b = Value(random.random()),Value(random.random())
  def __call__(self,x): return self.a*x+self.b

  def zero_grad(self):
    self.a.grad, self.b.grad = 0,0
</pre>


<p>And train it directly by using SGD:</p>


<pre class="brush: python; gutter: false; title: ; notranslate">η = 0.03, epochs = 20
for t in range(epochs):
  for x,y in zip(X,Y):
    model.zero_grad()
    loss = (model(x)-y)**2
    loss.backward()
    model.a , model.b = (model.a - η*model.a.grad  , model.b - η*model.b.grad)
</pre>


<p>Which as you can see works very well:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img alt="" src="https://i.imgur.com/19kDCPM.gif"/></figure>



<h2>From linear classifiers to Neural Networks.</h2>



<p>The above was somewhat of an “overkill” for linear models, but the beautify of automatic differentiation is that we can easily use more complex computation.</p>



<p>We can follow <a href="https://github.com/karpathy/micrograd/blob/master/demo.ipynb">Karpathy’s demo</a> and us the same approach to train a neural network.</p>



<p>We will use a neural network that takes two inputs and has two hidden layers of width 16. A neuron that takes input <img alt="x_1,\ldots,x_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x_1%2C%5Cldots%2Cx_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="x_1,\ldots,x_k"/> will apply the ReLU function (<img alt="max{0,x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=max%7B0%2Cx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="max{0,x}"/>) to <img alt="\sum w_i x_i" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Csum+w_i+x_i&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\sum w_i x_i"/> where <img alt="w_1,\ldots,w_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=w_1%2C%5Cldots%2Cw_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="w_1,\ldots,w_k"/> are its <em>weight</em> parameters. (It’s easy to add support for relu for our <code>Value</code> class. Also we won’t have a bias term in this example.)</p>



<p>The code for this Neural Network is as follows: (when <code>Value() </code>is called without a parameter the value is random number in <img alt="[-1,1]" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5B-1%2C1%5D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="[-1,1]"/>)</p>


<pre class="brush: python; gutter: false; title: ; notranslate">def Neuron(weights,inputs, relu =True):
  # Evaluate neuron with given weights on given inputs
  v =  sum(weights[i]*x for i,x in enumerate(inputs))
  return v.relu() if relu else v


class Net:
  # Depth 3 fully connected neural net with one two inputs and output
  def __init__(self,  N=16):
    self.layer_1 = [[Value(),Value()] for i in range(N)]
    self.layer_2 = [ [Value() for j in range(N)] for i in range(N)]
    self.output =  [ Value() for i in range(N)]
    self.parameters = [v for L in [self.layer_1,self.layer_2,[self.output]] for w in L for v in w]


  def __call__(self,x):
    layer_1_vals = [Neuron(w,x) for w in self.layer_1]
    layer_2_vals = [Neuron(w,layer_1_vals) for w in self.layer_2]
    return Neuron(self.output,layer_2_vals,relu=False) 
    # the last output does not have the ReLU on top

  def zero_grad(self):
    for p in self.parameters:
      p.grad=0
</pre>


<p>We can train it in the same way as above.<br/>We will follow Karpathy and train it to classify the following points:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img alt="" src="https://i.imgur.com/cXv93KU.png"/></figure>



<p>The training code is very similar, with the following differences:</p>



<ul><li>Instead of the square loss, we use the function <img alt="L(y,y')= \max{ 1- y\cdot y', 0 }" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=L%28y%2Cy%27%29%3D+%5Cmax%7B+1-+y%5Ccdot+y%27%2C+0+%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="L(y,y')= \max{ 1- y\cdot y', 0 }"/> which is <img alt="0" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=0&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="0"/> if <img alt="y \cdot y' \geq 1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=y+%5Ccdot+y%27+%5Cgeq+1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="y \cdot y' \geq 1"/>. This makes sense since our data labels will be <img alt="\pm 1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cpm+1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\pm 1"/> and we say we classify correctly if we get the same sign. We get zero loss if we classify correctly all samples with a margin of at least <img alt="1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="1"/>.</li><li>Instead of stochastic gradient descent we will do standard gradient descent, using all the datapoints before taking a gradient step. The optimal for neural networks is actually often something in the middle – <em>batch gradient descent</em> where we take a batch of samples and perform the gradient over them.</li></ul>



<p>The resulting code is the following:</p>


<pre class="brush: python; gutter: false; title: ; notranslate">for t in range(epochs):
  loss = sum([(1+ -y*model(x)).relu() for (x,y) in zip(X,Y)])/len(X)
  model.zero_grad()
  loss.backward()
  for p in model.parameters:
    p.data -= η*p.grad
</pre>


<p>If we use this, we get a decent approximation for this training set (see image below). As Karpathy shows, by adjusting the learning rate and using regularization, one can in fact get 100% accuracy.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img alt="" src="https://i.imgur.com/nbpNZyu.png"/></figure></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-03T23:14:08Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-03T23:14:08Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:56Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/03/postdoc-at-university-of-augsburg-apply-by-november-30-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/03/postdoc-at-university-of-augsburg-apply-by-november-30-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at University of Augsburg (apply by November 30, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The group of Tobias Mömke at University of Augsburg is inviting applications for a three-year Postdoc position, starting at the earliest possible date. The topic of the position is research on Approximation Algorithm. Website: https://www.uni-augsburg.de/en/fakultaet/fai/informatik/prof/raa/hiring/#postdoc Email: moemke@informatik.uni-augsburg.de</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The group of Tobias Mömke at University of Augsburg is inviting applications for a three-year Postdoc position, starting at the earliest possible date. The topic of the position is research on Approximation Algorithm.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.uni-augsburg.de/en/fakultaet/fai/informatik/prof/raa/hiring/#postdoc">https://www.uni-augsburg.de/en/fakultaet/fai/informatik/prof/raa/hiring/#postdoc</a><br/>
Email: moemke@informatik.uni-augsburg.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-03T16:16:06Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-03T16:16:06Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17775</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/03/the-election-night-time-warp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Election Night Time Warp</title>
    <summary>Has Election Night—not just the election—been modeled adequately? The Conversation source Kurt Gödel famously found solutions to Albert Einstein’s equations of general relativity that allow trajectories to loop through time. Today, early on Election Day and a usual time for our posts on Gödel, I talk about the trajectory of counting votes after tomorrow’s polls […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Has Election Night—not just the election—been modeled adequately?</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/03/the-election-night-time-warp/godelinthought/" rel="attachment wp-att-17777"><img alt="" class="alignright size-full wp-image-17777" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/godelinthought.jpg?w=600"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">The Conversation <a href="https://theconversation.com/kurt-godel-from-loopholes-and-dictators-to-the-incompleteness-theorems-72376">source</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Kurt Gödel famously found solutions to Albert Einstein’s equations of general relativity that allow trajectories to loop through time. </p>
<p>
Today, early on Election Day and a usual time for our posts on Gödel, I talk about the trajectory of counting votes after tomorrow’s polls close and time-warp effects that everyone watching the returns will see.</p>
<p>
I am picking up the vein of ethical algorithms in yesterday’s <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/02/the-night-of-the-ethical-algorithm/">post</a>, but with a different take about ethical modeling in novel situations where reliable training data is unavailable. I believe there is a responsibility for running simulations not just of tomorrow’s <em>election</em>, such as FiveThirtyEight <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/2020-election-forecast/">conducts</a>, but also of tomorrow’s <em>count</em> as it may unfold hour by hour and stretch over many following days. </p>
<p>
Gödel also famously believed he had found a logical flaw in the U.S. Constitution that allowed a mechanism for legally instituting a dictatorship, but his argument was never reported. We <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2013/12/06/judging-a-book-by-its-coverage/">discussed</a> this at length in 2013, including noting a 2012 <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2010183">paper</a> by Enrique Guerra-Pujol of the University of Central Florida College of Business, who is a frequent reader of this blog. Guerra-Pujol offers a detailed construction of a mechanism based on self-reference applied to the short <a href="https://www.archives.gov/federal-register/constitution/article-v.html">Article V</a> on amending the Constitution. This topic has been <a href="https://slate.com/technology/2018/08/is-there-a-logical-inconsistency-in-the-constitution.html">addressed</a> <a href="https://harvardlawreview.org/2020/01/pack-the-union-a-proposal-to-admit-new-states-for-the-purpose-of-amending-the-constitution-to-ensure-equal-representation/">several</a> <a href="https://theconversation.com/kurt-godel-from-loopholes-and-dictators-to-the-incompleteness-theorems-72376">times</a> <a href="https://thehill.com/opinion/civil-rights/473613-a-contradiction-at-the-heart-of-the-american-system">since</a>, but what stands out to us is a 2019 <a href="http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-2632/MIREL-19_paper_1.pdf">paper</a> by Valeria Zahoransky and Christoph Benzmüller. This paper attempts to find a proof of Guerra-Pujol’s mechanism by automated logical inference using the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabelle_(proof_assistant)">Isabelle</a>/<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HOL_(proof_assistant)">HOL</a> proof assistant. They found a model that satisfies the argument. </p>
<p/><h2> Election Evolution Over Time </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
My <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2016/11/08/unskewing-the-election/">post</a> on Election Day 2016 contrasted the relatively stable time evolution of polls in 2012 with the gyrations of 2016. That post began by defending Nate Silver of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/">FiveThirtyEight</a> and his 30% likelihood for Donald Trump against those who had Hillary Clinton over 90%. At the time of our 2012 <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2012/11/05/the-election-outcome/">post</a> on Barack Obama versus Mitt Romney, I had thought Silver’s error bars were too wide, but in 2016 they looked right on the basis of last-minute decision making by impulse that my chess model also registers.</p>
<p>
This year, the polls have been even steadier than in 2012, and undecided voters are found to be scarce. Of course, the pandemic has been the greatest factor in the poll numbers, but my first point is that election forecasting uses only the numbers as primary. The algorithms do not have an input that could take values Covid 19, Covid 23, Covid 17… In a normal election, the polling numbers would seem to point to an easier call than in 2012. Silver has, however, expressed <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/im-here-to-remind-you-that-trump-can-still-win/">caution</a> in explaining why his odds stay just short of 90% for Joe Biden as I write at midnight. My first point of further disquiet begins with a simple fact:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> The models have been trained on data from past elections. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
A major difference on our flight path to Election Day is the upsurge in early voting and turnout overall. Texas reports that it has already registered more early votes than total votes cast in 2016. We are not saying this difference has been overlooked—of course, models are being adjusted for it every hour. What we are doubting is the existence of a basis for making those adjustments with high confidence. Before we discuss the major issue of the flight path <em>after</em> the polls close, let me insert an analogy from my current chess work.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> My Own Ethical Interpolation </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
My statistical chess model is trained on millions of moves from games at the hours-long pace of standard in-person chess. The pandemic has led to chess moving online where fast time controls are the norm. For instance, the hallowed US Championships were just held in a format of three games per day at a pace of 25 minutes for the whole game plus 5 seconds for each move played, which equates to G/30 (game in 30 minutes) under a simplification used also <a href="http://universalrating.com/about-us.php">here</a>. The Online Olympiad held in August by the International Chess Federation (FIDE) gave only 15 minutes plus 5 seconds per move, equating to G/20. I have been asked for input on games at paces all the way down to 1-minute “Bullet” chess. </p>
<p>
My solid estimates of how less time affects skill come from the annual FIDE World Rapid and Blitz Championships, which are contested at equivalents of G/25 and G/5, respectively, by hundreds of elite male and female players. For time controls in-between I face twin problems of scant data from in-person chess—basically none for player below master level—and online chess having evident contamination from cheating, as I discussed in a <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/06/07/the-doomsday-argument-in-chess/">post</a> last June. Hence I <em>interpolate</em> to determine model settings for other time controls. </p>
<p>
This <a href="https://cse.buffalo.edu/~regan/chess/RatingTimeCurves.jpg">diagram</a> shows internal evidence supporting the orange curve obtained via <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aitken's_delta-squared_process">Aitken extrapolation</a>, in that inverse polynomial curves based on other reasoning converge to it. The curve has been supported by recent field tests, including a restricted invitational tournament recently run by Chess.com at G/3 and a large junior league in Britain at G/15 equivalent. Still, the <em>ethical</em> status is:</p>
<ol>
<li>
The pandemic has injected me into online fast chess ahead of the year-long timeframe that would be needed to clean the available large data and rebuild my model directly for all the gamut of different time controls. <p/>
</li><li>
So it is ethical for me to give my best estimates, as supported by field tests and <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2019/08/15/predicting-chess-and-horses/">cross-checks</a> in my model, but with caveat of their being “an extrapolation of an interpolation.” <p/>
</li><li>
But in principle there are more-reliable ways to do the modeling.
</li></ol>
<p>
My second point is that this year’s election models are in similar boats: The pandemic forces their cantilevered use in new situations. As with chess the data needed for direct training may not be available. As we’ve said in the <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/02/the-night-of-the-ethical-algorithm/">post</a>, this year’s election <em>task</em> may be “Ethics-Hard.” Now we come to my third and main point about responsibility.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> A Night of Waves and Blue/Red Shifts </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The new dimension of time is the order in which all the following categories of votes will be counted, in the states that variously allow them:</p>
<ol>
<li>
Early votes cast in-person, such as my wife and I did on the first possible <a href="https://buffalonews.com/news/local/government-and-politics/nearly-15-000-turn-out-on-first-day-of-early-voting-in-erie-county/article_f35cc7f0-153b-11eb-bbd6-43fce059203c.html">day</a> in New York. <p/>
</li><li>
Early votes sent by mail. <p/>
</li><li>
In-person votes on Election Day. <p/>
</li><li>
Regular votes by mail in states that vote that way. <p/>
</li><li>
Absentee ballots, which are the only non-Tuesday option in some states.
</li></ol>
<p>
This is approximately the order in which votes will be counted, again with state-by-state differences, which especially may lead to votes in category 2 being counted later. The issue is that the Democratic and Republican shares are expected to vary greatly across the categories, enough to cause large shifts in the perceived leader over real time. </p>
<p>
Geoffrey Skelley of FiveThirtyEight has an <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-pennsylvanias-vote-count-could-change-after-election-night/">article</a> showing how a 5-point win for Biden in Pennsylvania might still present as a <b>16-point</b> lead for President Trump on Election Night, when all in-person votes are counted but only some of the votes by mail. Here are the article’s key graphics, the left one showing actual proportions from Pennsylvania’s June primary.</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/03/the-election-night-time-warp/skelleyblueshiftcombo/" rel="attachment wp-att-17778"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-17778" height="243" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/skelleyblueshiftcombo.png?w=550&amp;h=243" width="550"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">Composite of two figures from FiveThirtyEight Skelley <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-pennsylvanias-vote-count-could-change-after-election-night/">article</a></font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
Other states that allow early tallying of early votes may show an initial Biden lead before a red-shift toward Trump on Election Night, with more of Biden’s vote share remaining to be counted. Still others are less clear. FiveThirtyEight on Saturday posted a useful state-by-state <a href="https://projects.fivethirtyeight.com/election-results-timing/">guide</a>.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Why Important to Model the Count? </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Awareness of the time-shifts is important not only for perception but also for the timing of legal challenges that are expected to arise. For instance, there is a continued specter of <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2020/11/01/texas-drive-thru-votes-harris-county/">invalidating</a> 127,000 early votes already cast by a novel drive-up system in Harris County Texas; despite its <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/live/2020/11/02/us/trump-vs-biden/a-federal-judge-denies-a-bid-to-throw-out-more-than-127000-votes-in-texas-the-republicans-who-sued-have-already-appealed">rejection</a> by a district judge today, it has been appealed higher. There is expectation of legal <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/11/02/us/politics/election-day-ballot-counting.html">battles</a> nationwide over procedures that have been altered by measures to cope with the pandemic.</p>
<p>
Public perception, however, is the most immediate concern. President Trump <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/is totally inappropriate, and I don't believe that's by our laws">stated</a> in a flagged Tweet that we “must have final total on November 3rd” and followed up by saying, “…instead of counting ballots for two weeks, which is totally inappropriate, and I don’t believe that’s by our laws.” Justice Brett Kavanaugh wrote in a formal <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/20pdf/20a66_new_m6io.pdf#page=6">opinion</a> that states “want to avoid the chaos and suspicions of impropriety that can ensue if thousands of absentee ballots flow in after Election Day and potentially flip the results of an election.” Note his phrase “flip the results”—a sure sign that perception is reality.</p>
<p>
Of course many outlets besides FiveThirtyEight are aware of the new election-reporting physics and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/10/27/upshot/election-results-timing.html">have</a> <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/fixgov/2020/10/30/what-to-watch-for-on-election-night-2020/">published</a> <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2020/10/26/timing-election-results/">their</a> <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/will-we-know-who-is-elected-president-on-election-night-a-guide-to-possible-delays-11596629410">own</a> <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/10/30/politics/red-blue-mirage-election-results/index.html">guides</a>. They are adjusting their election-night projection models accordingly. Our main question goes further in terms of responsibility:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Has anyone been running simulations of how Election Night vote-counting may unfold? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
We believe such simulations are just as important as the ones they have run of a timeless election. Showing them is not only important to inform the many who will be watching, it would be a vaccine against pressure that exploits unexpected perception. </p>
<p>
Yet it must be acknowledged that there is neither hard data nor sure knowledge of county-level vote-tallying policies and schedules on which to train such simulations. Nor may there be as many cross-checks as my chess interpolation situation. </p>
<p>
This may be another “Ethics-Hard” problem. But it is one already involved in adjusting the projection models that definitely are being deployed. Aside from the many novel and vital modeling problems from the pandemic, it may be the most important one of our near future. And we are thinking of this less than 48 hours—now less than 24 hours—before the first polls close.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
How do you think Election Night results will unfold, apart from your estimate of the time-independent “ground truth” of the electorate’s intentions?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-03T06:02:38Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-03T06:02:38Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="chess"/>
    <category term="detection"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Constitution"/>
    <category term="data analytics"/>
    <category term="data cleansing"/>
    <category term="Donald Trump"/>
    <category term="Election Day"/>
    <category term="elections"/>
    <category term="Enrique Guerra-Pujol"/>
    <category term="ethical modeling"/>
    <category term="ethics"/>
    <category term="forecasting"/>
    <category term="Geoffrey Skelley"/>
    <category term="Joe Biden"/>
    <category term="Kurt Godel"/>
    <category term="Nate Silver"/>
    <category term="post-normal science"/>
    <category term="social responsibility"/>
    <category term="statistical models"/>
    <category term="statistics"/>
    <author>
      <name>KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5061</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5061" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5061#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5061" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">A Drawing for Singularity Eve</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Lily, my 7-year-old, asked me to share the above on my blog. She says it depicts the US Army luring Trump out of the White House with a hamburger, in order to lock the front door once he’s out—what she proposes should happen if Trump refuses to acknowledge a loss. If you haven’t yet voted, […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/hamburgur2.jpg"><img alt="" src="https://www.scottaaronson.com/hamburgur2-sm.jpg"/></a></figure>



<p>Lily, my 7-year-old, asked me to share the above on my blog.  She says it depicts the US Army luring Trump out of the White House with a hamburger, in order to lock the front door once he’s out—what she proposes should happen if Trump refuses to acknowledge a loss.</p>



<p>If you haven’t yet voted, especially if you live in a contested state, <strong>please do so tomorrow</strong>.  Best wishes to us all!</p>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update (Nov. 3):</span></strong> Even if it comes 4-5 years late, <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/224-key-trumps-appeal/">this 8-minute podcast by Sam Harris</a> gives perhaps the sharpest solution ever articulated to the mystery of how tens of millions of Americans could enthusiastically support an obvious fraud, liar, incompetent, and threat to civilization.  Briefly, it’s not <em>despite</em> his immense failings but <em>because of</em> them—because by flaunting his failings he absolves his supporters for their own, even while the other side serves those same supporters relentless moral condemnation and scorn.  I <em>think</em> I had known this—I even said something similar as the tagline of this blog (“The Far Right is destroying the world, and the Far Left thinks it’s my fault!”).  But Sam Harris expresses it as only he can.  If this analysis is right—and I feel virtually certain it is—then it bodes well that Biden, unlike Hillary Clinton, isn’t seen as especially sanctimonious or judgmental.  Biden’s own gaffes and failings probably help him.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-03T01:41:44Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-03T01:41:44Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-11-08T15:51:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/02/faculty-at-tufts-university-apply-by-december-15-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/02/faculty-at-tufts-university-apply-by-december-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty at Tufts University (apply by December 15, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Tufts Computer Science seeks Assistant/Associate Professor with research in Quantum Computation and Information, and a strong background in theoretical computer science whose research connects with current faculty in quantum information and beyond. Candidates should demonstrate attention to diversity and inclusion as related to teaching, research, and engagement. Tufts is an EO/AA employer. Website: https://apply.interfolio.com/78094 Email: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Tufts Computer Science seeks Assistant/Associate Professor with research in Quantum Computation and Information, and a strong background in theoretical computer science whose research connects with current faculty in quantum information and beyond. Candidates should demonstrate attention to diversity and inclusion as related to teaching, research, and engagement. Tufts is an EO/AA employer.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://apply.interfolio.com/78094">https://apply.interfolio.com/78094</a><br/>
Email: ttsearch@cs.tufts.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-02T22:19:18Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-02T22:19:18Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/02/constant-width-involutes</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/02/constant-width-involutes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Constant width from involutes of pseudotriangles</title>
    <summary>In his online collection of fun stuff, Jeff Edmonds recently posted a method of constructing curves of constant width by spinning a pencil on a flat surface, with a varying axis, and tracking the movement of its ends. It is pretty similar to the classical method of crossed lines described by Martin Gardner in The Unexpected Hanging, in which one constructs an arrangement of lines in the plane, sorts them in circular order by slope, and builds a curve out of circular arcs centered at the crossing points of consecutive lines in this sorted order. However, it grows the curve at both ends simultaneously, rather than only at one end, and chooses the lines dynamically rather than in advance. Regardless, the result is the same: a piecewise-circular constant-width curve.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In his <a href="https://www.eecs.yorku.ca/~jeff/courses/fun/">online collection of fun stuff</a>, Jeff Edmonds recently posted <a href="https://www.eecs.yorku.ca/~jeff/courses/fun/Equal_Distance.docx">a method of constructing curves of constant width</a> by spinning a pencil on a flat surface, with a varying axis, and tracking the movement of its ends. It is pretty similar to the classical method of crossed lines described by Martin Gardner in <em>The Unexpected Hanging</em>, in which one constructs an arrangement of lines in the plane, sorts them in circular order by slope, and builds a curve out of circular arcs centered at the crossing points of consecutive lines in this sorted order. However, it grows the curve at both ends simultaneously, rather than only at one end, and chooses the lines dynamically rather than in advance. Regardless, the result is the same: a piecewise-circular constant-width curve.</p>

<p>This got me wondering how we might go about constructing curves of constant width that are not piecewise-circular. Instead of a finite set of lines, we could use a continuous family of lines, one of each slope, but that’s a little difficult to visualize. Instead, there’s a simpler method that works more like Jeff’s spinning pencil, which Robinson (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1112/blms/16.3.264">“Smooth curves of constant width and transnormality”, <em>Bull. LMS</em> 1984</a>) attributes to Euler (<a href="https://scholarlycommons.pacific.edu/euler-works/513/">“De curvis triangularibus”, 1778</a>):</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Draw a closed curve in the plane that has only one tangent line of each slope.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Rotate a “long enough” tangent line segment of some fixed length around this curve without sliding it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Trace the paths of the endpoints of the line segment.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The first step may already seem a little confusing. Don’t curves usually have at least two tangent lines of each slope, their support lines from opposite sides? Well, yes, for convex curves. But for a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudotriangle">pseudotriangle</a>, a curve whose boundary is concave everywhere except at three extreme points, there might only be one tangent line of each slope. A standard example of such a curve is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deltoid_curve">deltoid</a>, and the following animation stolen from the <a href="https://mathcurve.com/courbes2d.gb/deltoid/deltoid.shtml">mathcurve.com page on deltoids</a> shows a tangent line segment (black) rotating around a deltoid (blue) and tracing out a curve of constant width (red).</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Animation of a tangent line segment rolling around a deltoid, with its endpoints tracing out a curve of constant width, from https://mathcurve.com/courbes2d.gb/deltoid/deltoid.shtml" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/involute-deltoid.gif"/></p>

<p>The traced curve is always perpendicular to the rotating line segment, so locally at least this segment behaves like the width of the curve in each given direction. And since we don’t change the length of the segment while it rotates, the width stays constant. The same deltoid, the same curve of constant width, and two positions of its tangent line segment can also be seen in the illustration below from a 1954 mathematics paper, <a href="https://doi.org/10.2307/2307215">“Rotors within rotors” by Michael Goldberg in the <em>Amer. Math. Monthly</em></a>. I’ve overlaid a red Reuleaux triangle to show that, like <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/08/30/linkage.html">so</a> <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/07/05/shape-wankel-rotor.html">many</a> <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/06/30/linkage.html">other</a> <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2018/06/24/la-maddalena-non-reuleaux.html">curvy</a> <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2018/04/17/mythical-reuleaux-manhole.html">triangles</a>, this is not a Reuleaux triangle, even though it has constant width. Although its corners are drawn to look kind of pointy, they should actually be smooth, and the rest of the curve bulges farther out from its sides than a Reuleaux triangle would.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="The involute of deltoid, as depicted by Goldberg in &quot;Rotors within rotors&quot;, with an overlaid Reuleaux triangle" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/rotors-within-rotors.png"/></p>

<p>More formally, this process of rotating and tracing tangent line segments produces a curve called the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Involute">involute</a> of the deltoid. An involute of a curve is more typically described as what you get when you fix one end of a length of string at a point on the curve, wrap it tightly around the curve, and then unwrap it while keeping it taut, tracing a curve with the other end of the string as you do. The two ends of the rotating tangent line segment can both be thought of as being formed in the same way from two strings, with one of them unwrapping the deltoid from one direction while the other wraps it back up in the other direction. In the deltoid example the segment was the same length as the sides of the deltoid, which were all equal, but it also works with unequal sides or longer segments, as long as the rotating segment is long enough to reach all three cusps.</p>

<p>You might worry whether the segment always comes back to its starting position after each rotation, and this does require a little care in the initial choice of length and placement of the line segment. If the length of the rotating segment and eventual width of the traced curve are \(w\), the pseudotriangle sides have lengths \(a\), \(b\), and \(c\), and the segment starts with \(x\) units of extra length extending past the cusp prior to side \(a\) in its rotation, then it will have \(w-a-x\) units of extra length at the next cusp, \(w-b-(w-a-x)=x+a-b\) units at the third cusp, and \(w-c-(x+a-b)=w-x-a+b-c\) units at the last cusp. To make a curve of constant width we need the amount of extra length at the start and end to be equal, which happens when we set this length to be \(x=(w-a+b-c)/2\).</p>

<p>If the pseudotriangle that the tangent segment rotates around includes a line segment, there will be a discontinuity in its rotating movement as the axis of rotation shifts from one end of the segment to the other, much like the changes of axis described by Edmonds, but the same process still works.  If the pseudotriangle has a point where its slope changes discontinuously (for instance, if it is a polygon rather than a smooth curve), then the rotating segment will rotate around this point, with its ends tracing circular arcs, as it continuously moves between the same slopes; this can happen either at the three convex points of the pseudotriangle or along the concave curves between them. In particular, if your pseudotriangle is actually an equilateral triangle and the rotating segment has the same length as its sides, you get a Reuleaux triangle.</p>

<p>It’s also possible to form closed curves with only one tangent line of each slope that are not pseudotriangles. An example is the standard pentagram (whose involute is the Reuleaux pentagon), or a cuspy and irregular pentagram like the one below (whose involute is another curve of constant width without circular arcs). The same process works for these, with a slightly more complicated calculation of how to place a rotating segment of a given length for a given starting curve, involving alternating sums of side lengths.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="A curved five-point star with one tangent line in each direction" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/cuspy-star.svg"/></p>

<p>What happens when the rotating line segment is too short, so that it doesn’t reach one or more of the cusps? I’m not sure in general, but for the deltoid the result can be the same deltoid (for which the rotating line segment is one possibility for Goldberg’s “rotor within a rotor”, although the rotor he describes is larger) or another similar but smaller deltoid inside it. See the mathcurve link for details.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105144037558097550">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-02T17:26:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-02T17:26:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-11-03T21:15:52Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-9123933489422342245</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/9123933489422342245/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/i-polled-my-class-about-election.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/9123933489422342245" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/9123933489422342245" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/i-polled-my-class-about-election.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>I polled my class about the election</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> In 2016 I had the Sophomore discrete math class do a poll of who they wanted for president.</p><p>In 2020 I had the  both my  Senior Crypto class and Clyde's Sophomore algorithms course do a poll of who they wanted for president.</p><p>All of these polls were anonymous. One big difference- in 2016 it was paper, they could check offwho they wanted or put in a write in, whereas in 2020 it was on elms without a mechanism for a write in--- so no votes for Bernie or Bill or Kruskal (not sure if they were voting for the man or the algorithm) were possible. In all cases I included everyone who was on the Maryland Ballot (so Libertarian and Green votes were possible). </p><p><br/></p><p>Discrete Math 2016: 428 students took the poll. Write ins allowed. </p><p>Clinton- 305 which is 71%</p><p>Trump- 44 which is  10%</p><p>Johnson (Libertarian)- 21 which is 5%</p><p>Stein (Green)-  11which is 3%</p><p>Sanders-6 which is 1%</p><p>Silly answers: 41 which is 10%</p><p>I was NOT surprised that Trump got 44 votes- every year I do this and every year the </p><p>republican gets between 10 and 20 percent. Romney go 17% in 2012 (see <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2012/11/random-thoughts-on-election.html">here</a>). </p><p><br/></p><p>Algorithms, 2020, 161 students took the poll</p><p>Biden: 127 (79%)</p><p>Trump: 25 (16%)</p><p>Hawkins (Green): 4 (2%)</p><p>Jorgenson (Libertarian): 4 (2%)</p><p>Segal (Bread and Roses Party) 1 (1%)</p><p><br/></p><p>Cryptography in 2020: </p><p>Biden- 40 which is 78%</p><p>Trump-6 which is 12%</p><p>Hawkins (Green ) 3 which is 6%</p><p>Jorgenson (Libertarian) 2 which is 4%</p><p>Segal (Bread and Roses) 0 which is 0%</p><p><br/></p><p>I have no idea what these numbers mean. College students tend to be liberal- we knew that. That Trump went from 10% to 16% would be interesting if it was a larger sample size. I wonder if forcing them to NOT have a write-in had an effect. </p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-02T15:41:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-02T15:41:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T08:19:03Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/160</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/160" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-160 |  Non-adaptive vs Adaptive Queries in the Dense Graph Testing Model | 

	Oded Goldreich, 

	Avi Wigderson</title>
    <summary>We study the relation between the query complexity of adaptive and non-adaptive testers in the dense graph model. 
It has been known for a couple of decades that the query complexity of non-adaptive testers is at most quadratic in the query complexity of adaptive testers. 
We show that this general result is essentially tight; that is, there exist graph properties for which any non-adaptive tester must have query complexity that is almost quadratic in the query complexity of the best general (i.e., adaptive) tester. 

More generally, for every $q:\N\to\N$ such that $q(n)\leq{\sqrt n}$ and constant $c\in[1,2]$, we show a graph property that is testable in $\Theta(q(n))$ queries, but its non-adaptive query complexity is $\Theta(q(n)^c)$, omitting $\poly(\log n)$ factors and ignoring the effect of the proximity parameter $\epsilon$. Furthermore, the upper bounds hold for one-sided error testers,
and are at most quadratic in $1/\epsilon$. 

These results are obtained through the use of general reductions that transport properties of ordered structured (like bit strings) to those of unordered structures (like unlabeled graphs). 
The main features of these reductions are query-efficiency and preservation of distance to the properties.
This method was initiated in our prior work ({\em ECCC}, TR20-149), and we significantly extend it here.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-02T15:24:24Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-02T15:24:24Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/159</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/159" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-159 |  Relating existing powerful proof systems for QBF | 

	Leroy Chew</title>
    <summary>We advance the theory of QBF proof systems by showing the first simulation of the universal checking format QRAT by a theory-friendly system. We show that the sequent system G fully p-simulates QRAT, including the Extended Universal Reduction (EUR) rule which was recently used to show QRAT does not have strategy extraction. Because EUR heavily uses resolution paths our technique also brings resolution path dependency and sequent systems closer together. 
	While we do not recommend G for practical applications this work can potentially show what features are needed for a new QBF checking format stronger than QRAT.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-02T09:48:39Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-02T09:48:39Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17765</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/02/the-night-of-the-ethical-algorithm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Night of the Ethical Algorithm</title>
    <summary>Algorithms for the Election Michael Kearns and Aaron Roth are the authors of the book Ethical Algorithms and the The Science of Socially Aware Algorithm Design. It has earned strong reviews including this one in Nature—impressive. Michael is a long-time friend who is a leader in machine learning, artificial intelligence, and much more. He also […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Algorithms for the Election</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/kearnsroth.png"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-17767" height="110" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/kearnsroth.png?w=142&amp;h=110" width="142"/></a></p>
<p>
Michael Kearns and Aaron Roth are the authors of the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Ethical-Algorithm-Science-Socially-Design/dp/0190948205">book</a> <em>Ethical Algorithms and the The Science of Socially Aware Algorithm Design</em>. It has earned strong reviews including this <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41567-019-0768-1.epdf?shared_access_token=PLLHPNTn5pByQUPaJ-n_KdRgN0jAjWel9jnR3ZoTv0OmI9hygrW1-UKQon3ZVGlMNsZowBl_5psAIvdU-Dic4gtf_j0e7S_897lCTN3vdbqv3cbSQwUtbHG78r5ycJNB2VKFndoPOT_8w0OYjS-pjQ%3D%3D">one</a> in <i>Nature</i>—impressive.</p>
<p>
Michael is a long-time friend who is a leader in machine learning, artificial intelligence, and much <a href="https://www.cis.upenn.edu/~mkearns/">more</a>. He also overlapped with Ken at Oxford while visiting Les Valiant there in the mid-1980s. He is at the University of Pennsylvania in computer science along with his co-author Roth. Cynthia Dwork and Roth wrote an earlier <a href="https://www.cis.upenn.edu/~aaroth/privacybook.html">book</a> on the related issue of Differential Privacy.</p>
<p>
Today we will talk about making algorithms ethical.</p>
<p>
Tuesday is the 2020 US national election for President, for Congress, and for state and local offices. Every four years we have a national election, and we cannot imagine a better motivation for making sure that algorithms are ethical. </p>
<p>
The word “algorithm” appears 157 times in their book. Two words used hand-in-hand with it are “data” (132 times) and “model” (103 times), both spread through all of the book’s 232 pages. Models of electorates, trained on data from past elections, inform the algorithms used by news agencies to make election-night projections. These carry more responsibilities than election-eve forecasts. There have been infamous mistakes, most notably the premature calls of Florida both ways in the 2000 election. </p>
<p>
We believe that Tuesday’s election in our novel pandemic situation requires attention to ethics from first principles. We will discuss why this is important. What it means to be ethical here? And how one can make an algorithm ethical? </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Issue </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Algorithms have been around forever. Euclid devised his <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euclidean_algorithm">gcd</a> algorithm in 300 BCE. In the first half of the last century, the central issue was how to define that an algorithm is <b>effective</b>. This led to showing that some problems are <em>uncomputable</em>, so that algorithms for them are impossible.</p>
<p>
In the second half, the emphasis shifted to whether algorithms are <b>efficient</b>. This led to classifying problems as <em>feasible</em> or (contingently) <em>hard</em>. Although many algorithms for feasible problems have been improved in ways that redouble the effect of faster and cheaper hardware, the study of complexity classes such as <img alt="{\mathsf{NP}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cmathsf%7BNP%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\mathsf{NP}}"/> has given reasons why algorithms for hard problems may never be improvable.</p>
<p>
The new territory, that of Kearns and Roth, is whether algorithms are <b>ethical</b>. Current ones that they and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weapons_of_Math_Destruction">others</a> have critqued as unethical accompany models for the likes of mortgages, small-business loans, parole decisions, and college admissions. The training data for these models often bakes in past biases. Besides problems of racial and gender bias and concerns of societal values, the raw fact is that past biases cause the models to miss the mark for today’s applications. For algorithms with such direct application to society, ethical design is critical. </p>
<p>
But this requirement is further reaching that one might initially imagine, so that as with computability and complexity, the factors can be ingrained in the <em>problems</em>. </p>
<p>
Consider a simple problem: We given a collection of pairs of numbers <img alt="{(x,y)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x%2Cy%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{(x,y)}"/>. We are to predict whether this number pair has the property </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x + y \ge 0. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x+%2B+y+%5Cge+0.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x + y \ge 0. "/></p>
<p>This is pretty easy if we can use both <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{x}"/> and <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{y}"/>. But imagine a world where <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{x}"/> is allowed to be viewed but <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{y}"/> is secret. Perhaps the law requires that we cannot use <img alt="{y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{y}"/>—it is illegal. Now we might do as poorly as <img alt="{50\%}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B50%5C%25%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{50\%}"/>. Suppose that the data consists of </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  (1,-1), (1,1), (2,-2), (2,2) \dots " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%281%2C-1%29%2C+%281%2C1%29%2C+%282%2C-2%29%2C+%282%2C2%29+%5Cdots+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  (1,-1), (1,1), (2,-2), (2,2) \dots "/></p>
<p>Then seeing only <img alt="{x}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{x}"/> gives no advantage, while giving both is perfect. Thus what in these simplified terms counts as an ethical algorithm is a poor predictor, whereas an unethical one is perfect. </p>
<p>
The blurb for the Kearns-Roth book says that they “…explain how we can better embed human principles into machine code—without halting the advance of data-driven scientific exploration.” While we agree their approach is vital, we suspect that as with complexity there will be indelibly ethically hard tasks. We wonder whether election modeling has already become one of them. </p>
<p>
Ken and I have two separate takes on this. We will do the first and then the other in a second post.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Red/Blue Leakage, Bias, and Ethics </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
One question on everyone’s minds is whether we will see a repeat of the forecasting misses from 2016. Let us remind that our own Election Day 2016 <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2016/11/08/unskewing-the-election/">post</a> started by defending Nate Silver of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/">FiveThirtyEight</a> for giving Donald Trump as much as a 30% chance to defeat Hillary Clinton. He had been attacked by representatives of many news and opinion agencies whose models had Clinton well over 90%. </p>
<p>
We wonder whether these models were affected by the kind of biases highlighted in the book by Kearns and Roth. We must say right away that we are neither alleging conscious biases nor questioning the desire for prediction accuracy. One issue in ethical modeling (for parole, loans, admissions) is the divergence between algorithm outcomes that are most <em>predictive</em> versus those that are best for society. Here we agree that accurate prediction—and accurate projections as results come in after the polls close—is paramount. However, the algorithms used for the latter projections (which were not at fault in 2016 but have been wrong previously) may be even more subject to what we as computer scientists with crypto background see as a “leakage” issue.</p>
<p>
Here is the point. Ideally, models using polling data and algorithms reading the Election Night returns should read the numbers as if they did not have ‘R’ and ‘D’ attached to them. Their own workings should be invariant under transformations that interchange Joe Biden and Donald Trump, or whoever are opposed in a local race. However, a crucial element in the projection models in particular is knowledge of voting geography. They must use data on the general voting preferences of regions where much of the vote is still extant. Thus they cannot avoid intimate knowledge of who is ‘R’ and who is ‘D.’ There is no double-blind or zero-knowledge approach to the subjects being projected.</p>
<p>
There is also the question of error bars. A main point of our 2016 post (and of Silver’s analysis) was the high uncertainty factor that could be read from how the Clinton-Trump race unfolded. Underestimating uncertainty causes overconfidence in models. This can result from “groupthink” of the kind we perceive in newsrooms of many of the same outlets that are doing the projections. The algorithms ought to be isolated from opinions of those in the organization, but again there is reason from the last election to wonder about leakage.</p>
<p>
Unlike cases addressed by Kearns and Roth, we do not see a solution to suggest. As in our simple <img alt="{x+y}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%2By%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{x+y}"/> example, prior knowledge of the data in full may be needed for prediction. This may just be an “Ethics-Hard” problem. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>
The word “election” does <i>not</i> appear in Kearns and Roth’s book.  What further application of their standpoint to elections would you make?</p>
<p>Ken sees a larger question of ethical modeling decisions given the unprecedented circumstances of the current election.  This comes not from spatial geography distorted by the pandemic but rather from the dimension of time injected by massive early voting and late counting of many mailed ballots.  He will address this next.</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-02T05:10:12Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-02T05:10:12Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Aaron Roth"/>
    <category term="Algorithms"/>
    <category term="bias"/>
    <category term="election"/>
    <category term="ethics"/>
    <category term="fairness"/>
    <category term="Michael Kearns"/>
    <category term="prediction"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-10-31-ebb-and-flow-protocols-a-resolution-of-the-availability-finality-dilemma/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-10-31-ebb-and-flow-protocols-a-resolution-of-the-availability-finality-dilemma/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Resolving the Availability-Finality Dilemma</title>
    <summary>Guest post by Joachim Neu, Ertem Nusret Tas, and David Tse DLS and Nakamoto: Where to Go From Synchrony? An earlier blog post has explained classical models of the consensus literature from the 1980s, synchrony, asynchrony and partial synchrony. To recapitulate, the most basic network/adversary model is synchrony, where it...</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-01T05:16:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-01T05:16:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-11-08T22:50:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/10/31/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/10/31/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage for a trick-or-treat-less Halloween</title>
    <summary>3d flythrough of a near-optimal TSP tour through a dataset of nearly 221 stars (\(\mathbb{M}\), via). I found the “full view of tour” a lot easier to navigate than the mini-view on the main page.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.math.uwaterloo.ca/tsp/star/gaia1.html">3d flythrough of a near-optimal TSP tour through a dataset of nearly 221 stars</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105048388019149239">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24807080">via</a>). I found the “full view of tour” a lot easier to navigate than the mini-view on the main page.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://lightherder.blogspot.com/">The light herder</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105056854067105557">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://boingboing.net/2020/10/18/amazing-in-camera-patterns-with-a-video-feedback-kinetic-sculpture.html">via</a>). Dave Blair makes dynamic fractals from old-school video feedback.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.siam.org/conferences/cm/program/accepted-papers/soda21-accepted-papers">Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA 2021) accepted papers</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105062503320962361">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Lots of interesting looking titles there, but you’ll have to search online for links to the corresponding papers.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://tomlehrersongs.com/">Tom Lehrer has made his song lyrics public domain, or as close to it as one can legally get</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105076781151866254">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24833683">via</a>, <a href="https://boingboing.net/2020/10/20/brilliant-satirist-tom-lehrers-catalog-now-in-the-public-domain.html">via2</a>). But you have to download them within four years because his domain may go away after that. In honor of which, here’s a link to an (audio-only) version of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IL4vWJbwmqM">a little ditty about plagiarism</a> (only be sure always to call it please research).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://dev.scottdarby.com/chaos-ink/">Chaos ink</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105082966399876773">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://boingboing.net/2020/10/18/chaos-ink-disturb-a-tank-of-virtual-liquid-metal.html">via</a>). It’s rendered to look like waves in liquid metal, but I think it’s actually some kind of reaction-diffusion equation, in which you can move your mouse around to try to control where the reactions are centered.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://nebusresearch.wordpress.com/2020/10/21/my-all-2020-mathematics-a-to-z-statistics/">2020 Mathematics A to Z: Statistics</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@nebusj/105085756046257623">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). On the differences between statistics and mathematics, historical connections between statistics and eugenics, and new connections to algorithmic fairness.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/bad-math-day-spring-2020/home">Bay Area Discrete Math Day, November 21</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105091339250415859">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). This year, it’s a day of online discrete math talks, so you don’t actually need to be in the SF Bay Area to participate.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://liorpachter.wordpress.com/2020/09/10/sexual-harassment-case-number-1052/">Lior Pachter reports on confirmed sexual harassment within the computational geometry community, at SoCG 2016 in Boston, by Adrian Dumitrescu</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105097516664950105">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). According to the victim, <a href="https://twitter.com/RupeiXu/status/1302069912286957571">SoCG organizers told her they would try to bar Dumitrescu from future events, but told Dumitrescu he could not be barred</a> (see also <a href="https://twitter.com/RupeiXu/status/1310211818716049409">this update</a>). She says <a href="https://twitter.com/RupeiXu/status/1303309158427615234">there was also a second victim, whose academic career was “ruined” as a result</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/wepa2020">Fourth International Workshop on Enumeration Problems and Applications</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105102101211362136">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). I haven’t participated in previous instances but this year I’m on the program committee. Submission deadline November 8; online workshop December 7–10.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://igorpak.wordpress.com/2020/10/26/the-guest-publishing-scam/">Igor Pak hates journal special issues</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105116591625994062">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). The underlying problem appears to be loss of quality control compared to regular papers. He suggests handling festschrifts as books instead, and publishing surveys and reminiscences instead of research papers in them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://atlas.gregas.eu/graphs/31">The 84-vertex cubic symmetric graph</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105121991976224491">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>) is drawn nicely on <a href="http://www.mathpuzzle.com/">mathpuzzle.com</a> (update of June 27) using its structure as a <a href="https://www.abstract-polytopes.com/atlas/504/156/3.html">36-heptagon symmetric tiling of a non-orientable surface of Euler characteristic \(-6\)</a>. The Petrie dual of this tiling is <a href="https://www.abstract-polytopes.com/atlas/504/156/9.html">another symmetric tiling of the same graph with 28 nonagons on a higher-genus surface</a>. Does anyone know of other sources on these tilings? Or nice 3d embeddings of their surfaces?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://plus.maths.org/content/prize-young-mathematicians"><em>Plus</em> magazine on Cambridge’s Whitehead Prize winners</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105128113002070698">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):  A nice general-audience explainer of</p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Maria Bruna’s derivation of macro-level models from micro-level behavior, applied to vacuum cleaner design</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Holly Krieger’s connections between prime factors in integer sequences and special points on the Mandelbrot set</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Henry Wilton on the impossibility of determining whether infinite symmetry groups have finite quotients</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.iflscience.com/technology/ai-camera-ruins-soccar-game-for-fans-after-mistaking-referees-bald-head-for-ball/">Silly computer news of the day: automatically aimed soccer game video camera follows bald referee’s head instead of the ball, causing fans to miss key plays</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105131999819480420">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24955651">via</a>).</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-10-31T22:59:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-10-31T22:59:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-11-03T21:15:52Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4974</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4974" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4974#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4974" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">The Complete Idiot’s Guide to the Independence of the Continuum Hypothesis: Part 1 of</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">A global pandemic, apocalyptic fires, and the possible descent of the US into violent anarchy three days from now can do strange things to the soul. Bertrand Russell—and if he’d done nothing else in his long life, I’d love him forever for it—once wrote that “in adolescence, I hated life and was continually on the […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A global pandemic, apocalyptic fires, and the possible descent of the US into violent anarchy three days from now can do strange things to the soul.</p>



<p>Bertrand Russell—and if he’d done nothing else in his long life, I’d love him forever for it—once wrote that “in adolescence, I hated life and was continually on the verge of suicide, from which, however, I was restrained by the desire to know more mathematics.”  This summer, unable to bear the bleakness of 2020, I obsessively read up on the celebrated proof of the unsolvability of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuum_hypothesis">Continuum Hypothesis</a> (CH) from the standard foundation of mathematics, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zermelo%E2%80%93Fraenkel_set_theory">Zermelo-Fraenkel axioms</a> of set theory.  (In this post, I’ll typically refer to “ZFC,” which means Zermelo-Fraenkel plus the famous <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Axiom_of_choice">Axiom of Choice</a>.)</p>



<p>For those tuning in from home, the Continuum Hypothesis was formulated by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georg_Cantor">Georg Cantor</a>, shortly after his epochal discovery that there are different orders of infinity: so for example, the infinity of real numbers (denoted C for continuum, or \( 2^{\aleph_0} \)) is strictly greater than the infinity of integers (denoted ℵ<sub>0</sub>, or “Aleph-zero”).  CH is simply the statement that there’s no infinity <em>intermediate</em> between ℵ<sub>0</sub> and C: that anything greater than the first is at least the second.  Cantor tried in vain for decades to prove or disprove CH; the quest is believed to have contributed to his mental breakdown.  When David Hilbert presented his <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilbert%27s_problems">famous list</a> of 23 unsolved math problems in 1900, CH was at the very top.</p>



<p>Halfway between Hilbert’s speech and today, the question of CH was finally “answered,” with the solution earning the only <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fields_Medal">Fields Medal</a> that’s ever been awarded for work in set theory and logic.  But unlike with any previous yes-or-no question in the history of mathematics, the answer was that there provably <em>is</em> no answer from the accepted axioms of set theory!  You can either have intermediate infinities or not; neither possibility can create a contradiction.  And if you <em>do</em> have intermediate infinities, it’s up to you how many: 1, 5, 17, ∞, etc.</p>



<p>The easier half, the consistency of CH with set theory, was proved by incompleteness dude <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt_G%C3%B6del">Kurt Gödel</a> in 1940; the harder half, the consistency of not(CH), by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Cohen">Paul Cohen</a> in 1963.  Cohen’s work introduced the method of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forcing_(mathematics)">forcing</a>, which was so fruitful in proving set-theoretic questions unsolvable that it quickly took over the whole subject of set theory.  Learning Gödel and Cohen’s proofs had been a dream of mine since teenagerhood, but one I constantly put off.</p>



<p>This time around I started with <a href="https://projecteuclid.org/download/pdf_1/euclid.rmjm/1181070010">Cohen’s retrospective essay</a>, as well as Timothy Chow’s <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/sci.math.research/c/pQdPHJYML0E/m/ZrvqIxpd1sIJ?pli=1">Forcing for Dummies</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0712.1320">A Beginner’s Guide to Forcing</a>.  I worked through Cohen’s own <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Theory-Continuum-Hypothesis-Dover-Mathematics/dp/0486469212">Set Theory and the Continuum Hypothesis</a>, and Ken Kunen’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-Independence-Studies-Foundations-Mathematics/dp/0444868399">Set Theory: An Introduction to Independence Proofs</a>, and <a href="https://www2.karlin.mff.cuni.cz/~krajicek/scott67.pdf">Dana Scott’s 1967 paper</a> reformulating Cohen’s proof.  I emailed questions to Timothy Chow, who was ridiculously generous with his time.  When Tim and I couldn’t answer something, we tried <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_M._Solovay">Bob Solovay</a> (one of the world’s great set theorists, who later worked in computational complexity and quantum computing), or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andreas_Blass">Andreas Blass</a> or <a href="http://karagila.org/">Asaf Karagila</a>.  At some point mathematician and friend-of-the-blog <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greg_Kuperberg">Greg Kuperberg</a> joined my quest for understanding.  I thank all of them, but needless to say take sole responsibility for all the errors that surely remain in these posts.</p>



<p>On the one hand, the proof of the independence of CH would seem to stand with general relativity, the wheel, and the chocolate bar as a triumph of the human intellect.  It represents a culmination of Cantor’s quest to know the basic rules of infinity—all the more amazing if the answer turns out to be that, in some sense, we <em>can’t</em> know them.</p>



<p>On the other hand, perhaps no other scientific discovery of equally broad interest remains so sparsely popularized, not even (say) quantum field theory or the proof of Fermat’s Last Theorem.  I found barely any attempts to explain how forcing works to non-set-theorists, let alone to non-mathematicians.  One notable exception was Timothy Chow’s <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0712.1320">Beginner’s Guide to Forcing</a>, mentioned earlier—but Chow himself, near the beginning of his essay, calls forcing an “open exposition problem,” and admits that he hasn’t solved it.  My modest goal, in this post and the following ones, is to make a further advance on the exposition problem.</p>



<p>OK, but why a doofus computer scientist like me?  Why not, y’know, an actual expert?  I won’t put forward my ignorance as a qualification, although I <em>have</em> often found that the better I learn a topic, the more completely I forget what initially confused me, and so the less able I become to explain things to beginners.</p>



<p>Still, there is <em>one</em> thing I know well that turns out to be intimately related to Cohen’s forcing method, and that made me feel like I had a small “in” for this subject.  This is the construction of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oracle_machine">oracles</a> in computational complexity theory.  In CS, we like to construct hypothetical universes where P=NP or P≠NP, or P≠BQP, or the polynomial hierarchy is infinite, etc.  To do so, we, by fiat, insert a new function—an <em>oracle</em>—into the universe of computational problems, carefully chosen to make the desired statement hold.  Often the oracle needs to satisfy an infinite list of conditions, so we handle them one by one, taking care that when we satisfy a new condition we don’t invalidate the previous conditions.</p>



<p>All this, I kept reading, is <em>profoundly</em> analogous to what the set theorists do when they create a mathematical universe where the Axiom of Choice is true but CH is false, or vice versa, or any of a thousand more exotic possibilities.  They insert new sets into their models of set theory, sets that are carefully constructed to “force” infinite lists of conditions to hold.  In fact, some of the exact same people—such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_M._Solovay">Solovay</a>—who helped pioneer forcing in the 1960s, later went on to pioneer oracles in computational complexity.  We’ll say more about this connection in a future post.</p>



<p><strong>How Could It Be?</strong></p>



<p>How do you study a well-defined math problem, and return the answer that, as far as the accepted axioms of math can say, there <em>is</em> no answer?  I mean: even supposing it’s <em>true</em> that there’s no answer, how do you <em>prove</em> such a thing?</p>



<p>Arguably, not even <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6del%27s_incompleteness_theorems">Gödel’s Incompleteness Theorem</a> achieved such a feat.  Recall, the Incompleteness Theorem says loosely that, for every formal system F that could possibly serve as a useful foundation for mathematics, there exist statements even of elementary arithmetic that are true but unprovable in F—and Con(F), a statement that encodes F’s own consistency, is an example of one.  But the very statement that Con(F) is unprovable is equivalent to Con(F)’s being <em>true</em> (since an inconsistent system could prove anything, including Con(F)).  In other words, if the Incompleteness Theorem as applied to F holds any interest, then that’s only because F <em>is, in fact</em>,<em> consistent</em>; it’s just that resources beyond F are needed to prove this.</p>



<p>Yes, there’s a “self-hating theory,” F+Not(Con(F)), which believes in its own inconsistency.  And yes, by Gödel, this self-hating theory is <em>consistent</em> if F itself is.  This means that it has a <strong>model</strong>—involving “nonstandard integers,” formal artifacts that effectively promise a proof of F’s inconsistency without ever actually delivering it.  We’ll have much, <em>much</em> more to say about models later on, but for now, they’re just collections of objects, along with relationships between the objects, that satisfy all the axioms of a theory (thus, a model of the axioms of group theory is simply … any group!).</p>



<p>In any case, though, the self-hating theory F+Not(Con(F)) can’t be <em>arithmetically sound</em>: I mean, just look at it!  It’s either unsound because F is consistent, or else it’s unsound because F is inconsistent.  In general, this is one of the most fundamental points in logic: <strong>consistency does not imply soundness</strong>.  If I believe that the moon is made of cheese, that might be <em>consistent</em> with all my other beliefs about the moon (for example, that Neil Armstrong ate delicious chunks of it), but that doesn’t mean my belief is <em>true</em>.  Like the classic conspiracy theorist, who thinks that any apparent evidence against their hypothesis was planted by George Soros or the CIA, I might simply believe a self-consistent collection of absurdities.  Consistency is purely a syntactic condition—it just means that I can never prove both a statement and its opposite—but soundness goes further, asserting that whatever I can prove is actually the case, a <em>relationship</em> between what’s inside my head and what’s outside it.</p>



<p>So again, assuming we had any business using F in the first place, the Incompleteness Theorem gives us two <em>consistent</em> ways to extend F (by adding Con(F) or by adding Not(Con(F))), but only one <em>sound</em> way (by adding Con(F)).  But the independence of CH from the ZFC axioms of set theory is of a fundamentally different kind.  It will give us models of ZFC+CH, and models of ZFC+Not(CH), that are <em>both</em> at least somewhat plausible as “sketches of mathematical reality”—and that both even have defenders.  The question of which is right, or whether it’s possible to decide at all, will be punted to the future: to the discovery (or not) of some intuitively compelling foundation for mathematics that, as Gödel hoped, answers the question by going beyond ZFC.</p>



<p><strong>Four Levels to Unpack</strong></p>



<p>While experts might consider this too obvious to spell out, Gödel’s and Cohen’s analyses of CH aren’t so much about infinity, as they are about our ability to <em>reason </em>about infinity using finite sequences of symbols.  The game is about building self-contained mathematical universes to order—universes where all the accepted axioms about infinite sets hold true, and yet that, in some cases, seem to mock what those axioms were supposed to <em>mean</em>, by containing vastly fewer objects than the mathematical universe was “meant” to have.</p>



<p>In understanding these proofs, the central hurdle, I think, is that there are at least four different “levels of description” that need to be kept in mind simultaneously.</p>



<p>At the first level, Gödel’s and Cohen’s proofs, like all mathematical proofs, are finite sequences of symbols.  Not only that, they’re proofs that can be formalized in elementary arithmetic (!).  In other words, even though they’re <em>about</em> the axioms of set theory, they don’t themselves <em>require</em> those axioms.  Again, this is possible because, at the end of the day, Gödel’s and Cohen’s proofs won’t be talking about infinite sets, but “only” about finite sequences of symbols that make statements about infinite sets.</p>



<p>At the second level, the proofs are making an “unbounded” but perfectly clear claim.  They’re claiming that, if someone showed you a proof of either CH or Not(CH), from the ZFC axioms of set theory, then no matter how long the proof or what its details, you could convert it into a proof that <em>ZFC itself</em> was inconsistent.  In symbols, they’re proving the “relative consistency statements”</p>



<p>Con(ZFC) ⇒ Con(ZFC+CH),<br/>Con(ZFC) ⇒ Con(ZFC+Not(CH)),</p>



<p>and they’re proving these as theorems of <em>elementary arithmetic</em>.  (Note that there’s no hope of proving Con(ZF+CH) or Con(ZFC+Not(CH)) <em>outright</em> within ZFC, since by Gödel, ZFC can’t even prove its own consistency.)</p>



<p>This translation is completely explicit; the independence proofs even yield <em>algorithms</em> to convert proofs of inconsistencies in ZFC+CH or ZFC+Not(CH), supposing that they existed, into proofs of inconsistencies in ZFC itself.</p>



<p>Having said that, as Cohen himself often pointed out, thinking about the independence proofs in terms of algorithms to manipulate sequences of symbols is hopeless: to have any chance of understanding these proofs, let alone coming up with them, at some point you need to think about what the symbols <em>refer</em> to.</p>



<p>This brings us to the third level: the symbols refer to <em>models of set theory</em>, which could also be called “mathematical universes.”  Crucially, we always can and often will take these models to be only <em>countably</em> infinite: that is, to contain an infinity of sets, but “merely” ℵ<sub>0</sub> of them, the infinity of integers or of finite strings, and no more.</p>



<p>The fourth level of description is from within the models themselves: each model imagines itself to have an <em>uncountable</em> infinity of sets.  As far as the model’s concerned, it comprises the entire mathematical universe, even though “looking in from outside,” we can see that that’s not true.  In particular, each model of ZFC <em>thinks</em> it has uncountably many sets, many themselves of uncountable cardinality, even if “from the outside” the model is countable.</p>



<p>Say what?  The models are <em>mistaken</em> about something as basic as their own size, about how many sets they have?  Yes.  The models will be like <em>The Matrix</em> (the movie, not the mathematical object), or <em>The Truman Show</em>.  They’re self-contained little universes whose inhabitants can never discover that they’re living a lie—that they’re missing sets that we, from the outside, know to exist.  The poor denizens of the Matrix will never even be able to learn that their universe—what<em> </em>they mistakenly think of as <em>the</em> universe—is secretly countable!  And no <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morpheus_(The_Matrix)">Morpheus</a> will ever arrive to enlighten them, although—and this is crucial to Cohen’s proof in particular—the inhabitants will be able to reason more-or-less intelligibly about what would happen if a Morpheus <em>did</em> arrive.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%B6wenheim%E2%80%93Skolem_theorem">Löwenheim-Skolem Theorem</a>, from the early 1920s, says that <em>any</em> countable list of first-order axioms that has any model at all (i.e., that’s consistent), must have a model with at most countably many elements.  And ZFC is a countable list of first-order axioms, so Löwenheim-Skolem applies to it—even though ZFC implies the existence of an uncountable infinity of sets!  Before taking the plunge, we’ll need to not merely grudgingly accept but love and internalize this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skolem%27s_paradox">“paradox,”</a> because pretty much the entire proof of the independence of CH is built on top of it.</p>



<p>Incidentally, once we realize that it’s possible to build self-consistent yet “fake” mathematical universes, we can ask the question that, incredibly, the <em>Matrix</em> movies never ask.  Namely, how do we know that our own, larger universe isn’t similarly a lie?  The answer is that we don’t!  As an example—I hope you’re sitting down for this—even though Cantor proved that there are uncountably many real numbers, that only means there are uncountably many reals <em>for us</em>.  We can’t rule out the possibly that God, looking down on our universe, would see countably many reals.</p>



<p><strong>Cantor’s Proof Revisited</strong></p>



<p>To back up: the whole story of CH starts, of course, with Cantor’s epochal discovery of the different orders of infinity, that for example, there are more subsets of positive integers (or equivalently real numbers, or equivalently infinite binary sequences) than there are positive integers.  The devout Cantor thought his discovery illuminated the nature of God; it’s never been entirely obvious to me that he was wrong.</p>



<p>Recall how Cantor’s proof works: we suppose by contradiction that we have an enumeration of all infinite binary sequences: for example,</p>



<p>s(0) = <strong>0</strong>0000000…<br/>s(1) = 0<strong>1</strong>010101…<br/>s(2) = 11<strong>0</strong>01010….<br/>s(3) = 100<strong>0</strong>0000….</p>



<p>We then produce a new infinite binary sequence that’s not on the list, by going down the diagonal and flipping each bit, which in the example above would produce 1011…</p>



<p>But look more carefully.  What Cantor really shows is only that, <em>within our mathematical universe</em>, there can’t be an enumeration of all the reals of our universe.  For if there were, we could use it to define a new real that was in the universe but not in the enumeration.  The proof doesn’t rule out the possibility that <em>God</em> could enumerate the reals of our universe!  It only shows that, if so, there would need to be additional, heavenly reals that were missing from even God’s enumeration (for example, the one produced by diagonalizing against <em>that</em> enumeration).</p>



<p>Which reals could possibly be “missing” from our universe?  Every real you can name—42, π, √e, even uncomputable reals like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaitin%27s_constant">Chaitin’s Ω</a>—has to be there, right?  Yes, and there’s the rub: <em>every real you can name</em>.  Each name is a finite string of symbols, so whatever your naming system, you can only ever name countably many reals, leaving 100% of the reals nameless.</p>



<p>Or did you think of only the <em>rationals</em> or <em>algebraic numbers</em> as forming a countable dust of discrete points, with numbers like π and e filling in the solid “continuum” between them?  If so, then I hope you’re sitting down for this: <em>every real number you’ve ever heard of</em> belongs to the countable dust!  The entire concept of “the continuum” is only needed for reals that don’t have names and never will.</p>



<p><strong>From ℵ<sub>0</sub> Feet</strong></p>



<p>Gödel and Cohen’s achievement was to show that, without creating any contradictions in set theory, we can adjust size of this elusive “continuum,” put more reals into it or fewer.  How does one even start to begin to prove such a statement?</p>



<p>From a distance of ℵ<sub>0</sub> feet, Gödel proves the consistency of CH by building minimalist mathematical universes: one where “the only sets that exist, are the ones <em>required</em> to exist by the ZFC axioms.”  (These universes can, however, differ from each other in how “tall” they are: that is, in how many <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ordinal_number">ordinals</a> they have, and hence how many sets overall.  More about that in a future post!)  Gödel proves that, <em>if</em> the axioms of set theory are consistent—that is, if they describe any universes at all—then they also describe these minimalist universes.  He then proves that, in any of these minimalist universes, from the standpoint of someone <em>within</em> that universe, there are exactly ℵ<sub>1</sub> real numbers, and hence CH holds.</p>



<p>At an equally stratospheric level, Cohen proves the consistency of not(CH) by building … well, <em>non</em>-minimalist mathematical universes!  A simple way is to start with Gödel’s minimalist universe—or rather, an even more minimalist universe than his, one that’s been cut down to have only countably many sets—and then to stick in a bunch of <em>new real numbers</em> that weren’t in that universe before.  We choose the new real numbers to ensure two things: first, we still have a model of ZFC, and second, that we make CH false.  The details of how to do that will, of course, concern us later.</p>



<p><strong>My Biggest Confusion</strong></p>



<p>In subsequent posts, I’ll say more about the character of the ZFC axioms and how one builds models of them to order.  Just as a teaser, though, to conclude this post I’d like to clear up a fundamental misconception I had about this subject, from roughly the age of 16 until a couple months ago.</p>



<p>I thought: the way Gödel proves the consistency of CH, must be by examining all the sets in his minimalist universe, and checking that each one has either at most ℵ<sub>0</sub> elements or else at least C of them.  Likewise, the way Cohen proves the consistency of not(CH), must be by “forcing in” some extra sets, which have more than ℵ<sub>0</sub> elements but fewer than C elements.</p>



<p>Except, it turns out that’s not how it works.  Firstly, to prove CH in his universe, Gödel is not going to check each set to make sure it doesn’t have intermediate cardinality; instead, he’s simply going to count all the reals to make sure that there are only ℵ<sub>1</sub> of them—where <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleph_number#Aleph-one">ℵ<sub>1</sub></a> is the next infinite cardinality after ℵ<sub>0</sub>.  This will imply that C=ℵ<sub>1</sub>, which is another way to state CH.</p>



<p>More importantly, to build a universe where CH is false, Cohen is going to start with a universe where C=ℵ<sub>1</sub>, like Gödel’s universe, and then <em>add in more reals:</em> say, ℵ<sub>2</sub> of them.  The ℵ<sub>1</sub> “original” reals will then supply our set of intermediate cardinality between the ℵ<sub>0</sub> integers and the ℵ<sub>2</sub> “new” reals.</p>



<p>Looking back, the core of my confusion was this.  I had thought: I can visualize what ℵ<sub>0</sub> means; that’s just the infinity of integers.  I can <em>also</em> visualize what \( C=2^{\aleph_0} \) means; that’s the infinity of points on a line.  Those, therefore, are the two bedrocks of clarity in this discussion.  By contrast, I <em>can’t</em> visualize a set of intermediate cardinality between ℵ<sub>0</sub> and C.  The intermediate infinity, being weird and ghostlike, is the one that shouldn’t exist unless we deliberately “force” it to.</p>



<p>Turns out I had things backwards.  For starters, I <em>can’t</em> visualize the uncountable infinity of real numbers.  I might <em>think</em> I’m visualizing the real line—it’s solid, it’s black, it’s got little points everywhere—but how can I be sure that I’m not merely visualizing the ℵ<sub>0</sub> rationals, or (say) the computable or definable reals, which include all the ones that arise in ordinary math?</p>



<p>The continuum C is <em>not at all</em> the bedrock of clarity that I’d thought it was.  Unlike its junior partner ℵ<sub>0</sub>, the continuum is adjustable, changeable—and we <em>will</em> change it when we build different models of ZFC.  What’s (relatively) more “fixed” in this game is something that I, like many non-experts, had always given short shrift to: Cantor’s sequence of Alephs ℵ<sub>0</sub>, ℵ<sub>1</sub>, ℵ<sub>2</sub>, etc.</p>



<p>Cantor, who was a very great man, didn’t merely discover that C&gt;ℵ<sub>0</sub>; he also discovered that the infinite cardinalities form a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Well-order">well-ordered</a> sequence, with no infinite descending chains.  Thus, after ℵ<sub>0</sub>,  there’s a next greater infinity that we call ℵ<sub>1</sub>; after ℵ<sub>1</sub> comes  ℵ<sub>2</sub>; after the entire infinite sequence ℵ<sub>0</sub>,ℵ<sub>1</sub>,ℵ<sub>2</sub>,ℵ<sub>3</sub>,… comes ℵ<sub>ω</sub>; after ℵ<sub>ω</sub> comes ℵ<sub>ω+1</sub>; and so on.  These infinities will always be there in any universe of set theory, and always in the same order.</p>



<p>Our job, as engineers of the mathematical universe, will include pegging the continuum C to one of the Alephs.  If we stick in a bare minimum of reals, we’ll get C=ℵ<sub>1</sub>, if we stick in more we can get C=ℵ<sub>2</sub> or C=ℵ<sub>3</sub>, etc.  We can’t make C equal to ℵ<sub>0</sub>—that’s Cantor’s Theorem—and we <em>also</em> can’t make C equal to ℵ<sub>ω</sub>, by an important <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K%C3%B6nig%27s_theorem_(set_theory)">theorem of König</a> that we’ll discuss later (yes, this is an umlaut-heavy field).  But it will turn out that we can make C equal to just about any other Aleph: in particular, to any infinity other than ℵ<sub>0</sub> that’s not the supremum of a countable list of smaller infinities.</p>



<p>In some sense, this is the whole journey that we need to undertake in this subject: from seeing the cardinality of the continuum as a metaphysical mystery, which we might contemplate by staring really hard at a black line on white paper, to seeing the cardinality of the continuum <em>as an engineering problem</em>.</p>



<p>Stay tuned!  Next installment coming after the civilizational Singularity in three days, assuming there’s still power and Internet and food and so forth.</p>



<p>Oh, and happy Halloween.  Ghostly sets of intermediate cardinality … spoooooky!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-10-31T19:51:21Z</updated>
    <published>2020-10-31T19:51:21Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Metaphysical Spouting"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-11-08T15:51:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7857</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/10/30/digging-into-election-models/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Digging into election models</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With election on my mind, and constantly looking at polls and predictions, I thought I would look a little more into how election models are made. (Disclaimer: I am not an expert statistician / pollster and this is based on me trying to read their methodological description as well as looking into results of simulations … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/10/30/digging-into-election-models/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Digging into election models</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>With election on my mind, and constantly looking at polls and predictions, I thought I would look a little more into how election models are made. (<strong>Disclaimer:</strong> I am not an expert statistician / pollster and this is based on me trying to read their methodological description as well as looking into results of simulations in Python. However, there is a <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1GaoBn71PwIk_uAisNWzp2Naqev9JHW0I?usp=sharing">colab notebook</a> so you can try this on your own!)</p>



<p>If polls were 100% accurate, then we would not need election models – we will know that the person polling at more than 50% in a given state will win, and we can just sum up the electoral votes. However, polls have various sources of errors:</p>



<ol><li><strong>Statistical sample error</strong> –  this is simply the deviation between the fraction of people that would say “I will vote for X” at time T in the population, and the empirical fraction reported by the poll based on their sample. As battleground states get polled frequently with large samples, this error is likely to be negligible.</li><li><strong>Sampling bias</strong> – this is the bias incurred by the fact that we cannot actually sample a random subset of the population and get them to answer our questions – the probability that people will pick up their phone may be correlated with their vote. Pollsters hope that these correlations all disappear once you condition on certain demographic variables (race, education, etc..) and so try to ensure the sample is balanced according to these metrics. I believe this was part of the reason that polls were off in 2016, since they didn’t explicitly adjust for levels of education (which were not strongly correlated with party before) and ended up under-representing white voters without college degrees.</li><li><strong>Lying responses or “shy” voters</strong> – Some people suggest that voters lie to pollsters because their choice is considered “socially undesirable”. There is <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/trump-supporters-arent-shy-but-polls-could-still-be-missing-some-of-them/">not much support</a> that this is a statistically significant effect. In particular <a href="https://morningconsult.com/form/shy-trump-2020/">one study</a> showed there was no statistically significant difference between responders’ responses in online and live calling. Also in  2016 polls equally under-estimated the votes for Trump and Republican senators (which presumably didn’t have the same “social stigma” to them).</li><li><strong>Turnout estimates</strong> – Estimating the probability that a person supporting candidate X will actually show up to vote (or mail it in) is a bit of a dark art, and account for the gap in polls representing registered voters (which make no such estimates) and polls representing likely voters (which do). Since traditionally the Republican electorate is older and more well off, they tend to vote more reliably and hence likely voter estimates are typically better for republicans. The effect seems not to be very strong this year. Turnout might be particularly hard to predict this year, though it seems likely to be historically high.</li><li><strong>Voters changing their mind</strong> –  The poll is done at a given point in time and does not necessarily reflect voters views in election day. For example in 2016 it seems that many undecided voters broke for Trump. In this cycle the effect might be less pronounced since there are few undecided voters and “election day” is smoothed over a 2-4 week period due to early and mail-in voting.</li></ol>



<p>To a first approximation, a poll-based election model does the following:<br/><br/>1. Aggregates polls into national and state-wise predictions </p>



<p>2. Computes a probability distribution over the correlated error vectors (i.e. the vector <img alt="\vec{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cvec%7Be%7D&amp;bg=eeeeee&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\vec{e}"/>  with coordinate for each jurisdiction containing the deviation from the prediction)</p>



<p>3. Samples from the probability distribution over vectors to obtain probabilities over outcomes.</p>



<p>From a skim of <a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-fivethirtyeights-2020-presidential-forecast-works-and-whats-different-because-of-covid-19/">538’s methodology</a> it seems that they do the following:</p>



<ol><li>Aggregate polls (weighing by quality, timeliness, adjusting for house effects, etc..). Earlier in the election cycle they also mix in “fundamentals” such as state of the economy etc.. though their weight decreases with time.</li><li>Estimate magnitude of national error (i.e., sample a value <img alt="E \in \mathbb{R}_+" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=E+%5Cin+%5Cmathbb%7BR%7D_%2B&amp;bg=eeeeee&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="E \in \mathbb{R}_+"/> according to some distribution that reflects the amount of national uncertainty.</li><li>(This is where I may be understanding wrong.) Sample a vector <img alt="\vec{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cvec%7Be%7D&amp;bg=eeeeee&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\vec{e}"/> whose entries sum up to <img alt="E" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=E&amp;bg=eeeeee&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="E"/> according to a correlated distribution, where the correlations between states depends on demographic, location, and other  factors. For each particular choice of $E$, because the sum is fixed, if a state has $E+X$ bias then on average the other states will need to compensate for this $-X$ bias, and hence this can create <a href="https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2020/10/24/reverse-engineering-the-problematic-tail-behavior-of-the-fivethirtyeight-presidential-election-forecast/">negative correlations</a> between states. (It is not clear that negative correlations are unreasonable – one could imagine policies that are deeply popular with population A and deeply unpopular with population B)</li></ol>



<p>From a skim of the <a href="https://projects.economist.com/us-2020-forecast/president/how-this-works">Economist’s methodology</a> it seems that they do the following:</p>



<ol><li>They start again with some estimate on the national popular vote, based on polls and fundamentals, and then assume it is distributed according to some probability distribution to account for errors.</li><li>They then compute some prior on “partisan lean” (difference between state and national popular vote) for each state. If we knew the popular vote and partisan lean perfectly then we would know the result. Again like good Bayesians they assume that the lean is distributed according to some probability distribution.</li><li>They update the prior based on state polls and other information</li><li>They sample from an error distribution <img alt="\vec{e}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cvec%7Be%7D&amp;bg=eeeeee&amp;fg=666666&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\vec{e}"/> according to some explicit pairwise correlation matrix that has only non-negative entries (and hence you don’t get negative correlations in their model).</li></ol>



<p>So, given all of the above, how much do these models differ? Perhaps surprisingy, the answer is “not by much”.  To understand how they differ, I plotted for both models the following: </p>



<ol><li>The histogram of Biden’s popular vote margin</li><li>The probability of Biden to win conditioned on a particular margin</li></ol>



<p>Much of the methodological difference, including the issue of pairwise correlations, should manifest in 2, but eyeballing it, they don’t seem to differ that much. It seems that conditioned on a particular margin, both models give Biden similar probability to win. (In particular both models think that 3% margin is about 50/50, while 4% margin gives Biden about 80/20 chance). The main difference is actually in the first part of estimating the popular vote margin – 538 is more “conservative” and has fatter tails.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2020/10/election_models.png"><img alt="" class="wp-image-7867" src="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2020/10/election_models.png?w=993"/></a></figure>



<p>If you want to check my data, see if I have a bug, or try your own analysis, you can use this <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1GaoBn71PwIk_uAisNWzp2Naqev9JHW0I?usp=sharing">colab notebook</a>.</p>



<h2>“Make your own needle”</h2>



<p>Another applications for such models is to help us adjust the priors as new information comes in. For example, it’s possible that Florida, North Carolina and Texas will report results early. If Biden loses one of these states, should we adjust our estimate of win probability significantly? It turns out that the answer depends on by how much he loses.</p>



<p>The following graphs show the updated win probability conditioned on a particular margin in a state. We see that winning or losing Florida, North Carolina, and Texas on their own doesn’t make much difference to the probability – it’s all about the margin. In contrast, losing Pennsylvania’s 20 electoral votes will make a significant difference to Biden’s chances.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2020/10/predict_states.png"><img alt="" class="wp-image-7869" src="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2020/10/predict_states.png?w=1024"/></a></figure>



<p>(The non monotonicity is simply a side effect of having a finite number of simulation runs and would disappear in the limit.)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-10-30T16:16:57Z</updated>
    <published>2020-10-30T16:16:57Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:56Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7851</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/10/30/im-with-her-but-4-years-too-late/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>I’m with her (but 4 years too late)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In May 2016, after Donald Trump was elected as the republican nominee for president, I wrote the following blog post. I ended up not publishing it – this has always been a technical blog (and also more of a group blog, at the time). While the damage of a Donald Trump presidency was hypothetical at … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/10/30/im-with-her-but-4-years-too-late/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">I’m with her (but 4 years too late)</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In May 2016, after Donald Trump was elected as the republican nominee for president, I wrote the following blog post. I ended up not publishing it – this has always been a technical blog (and also more of a group blog, at the time).  While the damage of a Donald Trump presidency was hypothetical at the time, it is now very real and in a second term the stakes are only higher. I once again hope American readers of this blog would do what they can to support Joe Biden.<br/></p>



<p>Note: this is not an invitation for a debate on who to vote for in the comments. At this point, if you are educated and following the news (as I imagine all readers of this blog are) then if you are not already convinced that Donald Trump is a danger to this country and the world, nothing I will say will change your mind. Similarly, nothing you will say will change mine. Hence this is just a call for those readers who already support Joe Biden to make sure they vote and think of how they can help with their money or time in other ways.</p>



<h2>I’m with Her</h2>



<p><strong>Boaz Barak / May 3, 2016</strong><br/><br/>The republican electorate, in their infinite wisdom, have just (essentially) finalized the election of Donald Trump as their nominee for the position of the president of the United States.</p>



<p>While I have my political views, I don’t consider myself a very political person, and have not (as far as I remember) ever written about politics in this blog. However, extreme times call for extreme measures. It is tempting to be fatalist or cynical about this process, and believe that whether Donald Trump or Hillary Clinton is elected doesn’t make much of a difference. Some people believe that the presidency shapes the person more than the other way around, and others feel that all politicians are anyway corrupt or that Hillary is not much better than trump since she voted for the Iraq war and gave paid speeches for Wall Street firms. I think the last two presidencies of George W. Bush and Barack Obama demonstrated that the identity of the president makes a huge difference. All evidence points out that with Trump this difference will be entirely in the negative direction.</p>



<p>While his chances might not be great, this is not a bet I’m comfortable taking. I plan to support Hillary Clinton as much as I can, and hope that other American readers of this blog will do the same</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-10-30T14:20:47Z</updated>
    <published>2020-10-30T14:20:47Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:56Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/10/29/postdoc-in-causal-inference-ml-theory-at-university-of-chicago-and-carnegie-mellon-university-apply-by-january-30-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/10/29/postdoc-in-causal-inference-ml-theory-at-university-of-chicago-and-carnegie-mellon-university-apply-by-january-30-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc in Causal Inference / ML Theory at University of Chicago and Carnegie Mellon University (apply by January 30, 2021)</title>
    <summary>Applications are invited for a postdoctoral researcher working on problems in causal inference and graphical models. The candidate will be given the opportunity to pursue a broad research agenda at the intersection of theoretical statistics, machine learning, and causal inference. This is part of a collaborative project between Bryon Aragam (UChicago), Pradeep Ravikumar (CMU), and […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Applications are invited for a postdoctoral researcher working on problems in causal inference and graphical models. The candidate will be given the opportunity to pursue a broad research agenda at the intersection of theoretical statistics, machine learning, and causal inference. This is part of a collaborative project between Bryon Aragam (UChicago), Pradeep Ravikumar (CMU), and Eric Xing (CMU).</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://bryonaragam.com/uchicago_cmu_postdoc_announcement.pdf">http://bryonaragam.com/uchicago_cmu_postdoc_announcement.pdf</a><br/>
Email: bryon@chicagobooth.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-10-29T22:03:53Z</updated>
    <published>2020-10-29T22:03:53Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:37:39Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=505</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2020/10/29/tcs-talk-wednesday-november-4-shalev-ben-david-university-of-waterloo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, November 4 — Shalev Ben-David, University of Waterloo</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, November 4th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). Shalev Ben-David from University of Waterloo will speak about “Forecasting Algorithms, Minimax Theorems, and Randomized Lower Bounds” (abstract below). You can reserve a spot as an individual or a […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, November 4th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). <strong>Shalev Ben-David</strong> from University of Waterloo will speak about “<em>Forecasting Algorithms, Minimax Theorems, and Randomized Lower Bounds</em>” (abstract below).</p>



<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk/live-seat-reservation">the online form</a>. Due to security concerns, <em>registration is required</em> to attend the interactive talk. (The link to the YouTube livestream will also be posted <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk">on our  website</a> on the day of the talk, so people who did not sign up will still be able to  watch the talk live.) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/">the website</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-quote">Abstract: I will present a new approach to randomized lower bounds, particularly in the setting where we wish to give a fine-grained analysis of randomized algorithms that achieve small bias. The approach is as follows: instead of considering ordinary randomized algorithms which give an output in <img alt="\{0,1\}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%7B0%2C1%5C%7D&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\{0,1\}"/> and may err, we switch models to look at “forecasting” randomized algorithms which output a confidence in <img alt="[0,1]" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5B0%2C1%5D&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="[0,1]"/> for whether they think the answer is 1. When scored by a proper scoring rule, the performance of the best forecasting algorithm is closely related to the bias of the best (ordinary) randomized algorithm, but is more amenable to analysis. <br/>As an application, I’ll present a new minimax theorem for randomized algorithms, which can be viewed as a strengthening of Yao’s minimax theorem. Yao’s minimax theorem guarantees the existence of a hard distribution for a function <img alt="f" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f"/> such that solving <img alt="f" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f"/> against this distribution (to a desired error level) is as hard as solving <img alt="f" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f"/> in the worst case (to that same error level). However, the hard distribution provided by Yao’s theorem depends on the chosen error level. Our minimax theorem removes this dependence, giving a distribution which certifies the hardness of <img alt="f" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=f&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="f"/> against all bias levels at once. In recent work, we used this minimax theorem to give a tight composition theorem for randomized query complexity. <br/><br/>Based on joint work with Eric Blais.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-10-29T19:35:16Z</updated>
    <published>2020-10-29T19:35:16Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T13:38:13Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6849296165197348032</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6849296165197348032/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/10/2020-fall-jobs-post.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6849296165197348032" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6849296165197348032" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/10/2020-fall-jobs-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>2020 Fall Jobs Post</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">My annual fall jobs posts, giving advice to PhDs looking for faculty positions, were getting repetitive. See <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2019/10/2019-fall-jobs-post.html">last year's post</a> for the usual stuff and feel free to post opportunities in the comments on this post. This year let's talk about what's changed.<div><br/></div><div>First something you might have missed--the latest <a href="https://cra.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/2019-Taulbee-Survey.pdf">Taulbee Survey</a> shows a small drop in the number of new undergraduate CS majors in 2019 after years of massive growth. Is it a simple blip or have we hit the saturation point? We may never know because of the change you definitely didn't miss seeing.</div><div><br/></div><div>So let's talk about the effect of COVID. We're seeing a large drop in new international students who are having a hard time getting visas or just avoiding the US like the plague (literally). Not sure those numbers will fully come back given other alternatives and a changing international relationship particularly with China. Many undergrads have delayed college and some may never attend. </div><div><br/></div><div>On the other hand, COVID has accelerated digitizing the economy, from videoconferencing to in-home entertainment and games to remote access to work environments. The post-COVID economy could create even a larger demand for computer scientists. </div><div><br/></div><div>Many universities curtailed hiring last year worried and may do so in the spring given the uncertain budget situation due to the virus. Others continue to hire in computing, some to make up for last year. I just can't make a prediction for the upcoming year but I wouldn't rush to the job market if you have the option to wait. Last year the CRA reinstated the <a href="https://cifellows2020.org/">CIFellows</a>, postdocs to help those in a tight job market, and may do so again next year. The CRA will also repeat its <a href="https://cra.org/cras-cv-database-initiative-turns-two/">CV database</a>.</div><div><br/></div><div>Late spring interviews in 2020 went virtual and will likely go virtual again in 2021. Nevertheless take the zoom meetings seriously. Make sure your interview talk is still a discussion--answer questions people give in the chat. Still do your research to have strong conversations with everyone you talk to, especially the non-theorists. And still dress nicely, at least from the waist up. Putting on a sports coat is not a bad idea. </div><div><div><br/></div><div>Though most places continue to focus on data science/ML, cybersecurity and to some degree quantum, Rutgers is <a href="https://www.cs.rutgers.edu/about/employment/details/tenure-track-assistant-professor-position-2">specifically looking</a> for a hire in computational complexity. Don't see that everyday. </div></div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-10-28T22:27:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-10-28T22:27:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-11-09T08:19:03Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
