<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2021-10-06T04:39:58Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1576</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2021/10/news-for-september-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for September 2021</title>
    <summary>A nice array of papers for this month, ranging from distribution testing, dense graph property testing, sublinear graph algorithms, and various mixtures of them. Let us now sample our spread! A Lower Bound on the Complexity of Testing Grained Distributions by Oded Goldreich and Dana Ron (ECCC). A discrete distribution is called \(m\)-grained if all […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p id="block-79f77829-3f22-4392-8cc9-3f466129d855">A nice array of papers for this month, ranging from distribution testing, dense graph property testing, sublinear graph algorithms, and various mixtures of them. Let us now sample our spread!</p>



<p id="block-db4c65bf-46c4-4c3e-ad70-d3348de84ff3"><strong>A Lower Bound on the Complexity of Testing Grained Distributions</strong> by Oded Goldreich and Dana Ron (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/129/">ECCC</a>). A discrete distribution is called \(m\)-grained if all probabilities are integer multiples of \(1/m\). This paper studies the complexity of testing this property of distributions. For simplicity, consider the property of being \(n/2\)-grained, where the support size is \(n\). The classic lower bound for testing uniformity shows that \(\Omega(\sqrt{n})\) samples are required to distinguish the uniform distribution from a distribution uniform on \(n/2\) elements. Thus, we get a lower bound of \(\Omega(\sqrt{n})\) for testing \(n/2\)-grainedness (if I am permitted to use that word). This paper proves a lower bound of \(\Omega(n^c)\), for all constant \(c &lt; 1\). It is conjectured that the lower bound is actually \(\Omega(n/\log n)\), which would match the upper bound (for any label-invariant property).</p>



<p><strong>Testing Distributions of Huge Objects</strong> by Oded Goldreich and Dana Ron (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/133/">ECCC</a>). This paper introduced a new model that marries distribution testing with property testing on strings. The “object” of interest is a distribution \(\mathcal{D}\) over strings of length \(n\). We wish to test if \(\mathcal{D}\) possesses some property. The tester can get a random string \(x\) from the distribution, and can query any desired index of \(x\). The distance between distributions is defined using the earthmover distance (where we use the Hamming distance between strings). This model is called the DoHO (Distributions of Huge Objects) model. There are many questions posed and connections drawn to classical property testing and distribution testing. What I find interesting is a compelling application: the distribution \(\mathcal{D}\) may represent noisy or perturbed versions of a single object. The DoHO model gives a natural generalization of standard property testing to noisy objects. This paper considers problems such as testing if \(\mathcal{D}\) is: a random perturbation of a string, or a random cyclic shift, or a random isomorphism of a graph. </p>



<p><strong>Sublinear Time and Space Algorithms for Correlation Clustering via Sparse-Dense Decompositions</strong> by Sepehr Assadi and Chen Wang (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.14528.pdf">arXiv</a>). Correlation clustering is a classic problem where edges in a graph are labeled ‘+’ or ‘-‘, denoting whether these edges should be uncut or cut. The aim is to cluster the graph minimizing the total “disagreements” (cut ‘+’ edges or uncut ‘-‘ edges). This paper gives an \(O(1)\)-approximation algorithm that runs in \(O(n\log^2n)\) time; this is the first sublinear time approximation algorithm for this problem. Correlation clustering has seen results for the property testing/sublinear algorithms community, first by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1312.5105">Bonchi, Garcia Soriano, and Kutzkov</a>. But previous results were essentially on the dense graph model, giving \(O(\epsilon n^2)\) error assuming adjacency matrix input. This paper considers access to the adjacency list of ‘+’ edges. Interestingly (from a technical standpoint), the key tool is a new <em>sparse-dense</em> decomposition. Such decompositions emerged from the seminal work of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1807.08886">Assadi-Chen-Khanna</a> for sublinear \((\Delta+1)\)-colorings, and it is great to see applications beyond coloring.</p>



<p><strong>Sublinear-Time Computation in the Presence of Online Erasures</strong> by Iden Kalemaj, Sofya Raskhodnikova, and Nithin Varma (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.08745">arXiv</a>). Can property testing be done when portions of the input are hidden? This question was first raised by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1607.05786">Dixit-Raskhodnikova-Thakurta-Varma</a>, who gave a model of <em>erasure-resilient testing.</em> There is an adversary who hides (erases) part of the input function; queries to those parts just yield a dummy symbol. This paper defines an online version of this model. There is an erasure parameter \(t\). On each query by the property tester, the adversary can erase \(t\) values of the function. Consider the property of classic linearity of functions \(f:\{0,1\}^d \rightarrow \{0,1\}\). The BLR tester queries triples of pairs \((x,y, x \oplus y)\). Observe how this tester is easily defeated by our adversary, by erasing the value \(f(x\oplus y)\). One of the main results of this paper is a \(O(1/\varepsilon)\)-query tester for linearity, that works for any constant erasure parameter \(t\). Note that this matches the bound for the standard setting. There are a number of results for other classic properties, such as monotonicity (sortedness) and Lipschitz.</p>



<p>S<strong>ublinear Time Eigenvalue Approximation via Random Sampling</strong> by Rajarshi Bhattacharjee, Cameron Musco, and Archan Ray (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.07647">arXiv</a>). Consider the problem of estimating all the eigenvalues of a real, symmetric \(n \times n\) matrix \(M\) with bounded entries, in sublinear time. The main result shows that the eigenvalues of a uniform random \(O(\epsilon^{-4}\log n)\) principal submatrix can be used to approximate all eigenvalues of \(M\) up to additive error \(\epsilon n\). One can think of this as a sort of concentration inequality for eigenvalues. This result follows (and builds upon) work of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.06441">Bakshi-Chepurko-Jayaram</a> on property testing semidefiniteness. The key idea is that eigenvectors corresponding to large eigenvalues have small infinity norm: intuitively, since all entries in \(M\) are bounded, such an eigenvector must have its mass spread out among many coordinates. Hence, we can get information about it by randomly sampling a few coordinates. The paper also shows that approach of taking principal submatrices requires taking \(\Omega(\epsilon^{-2})\) columns/rows.</p>



<p><strong>Deterministic Graph Coloring in the Streaming Model</strong> by Sepehr Assadi, Andrew Chen, and Glenn Sun (arXiv). This is technically not a sublinear algorithms paper<em> (well ok, streaming is sublinear, but we tend not to cover the streaming literature. Maybe we should? – Ed.)</em> But, I think that the connections are of interest to our community of readers. The main tool of sublinear \((\Delta+1)\)-coloring algorithm of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1807.08886">Assadi-Chen-Khanna</a> is the palette sparsification lemma (\(\Delta\) is the maximum degree). This lemma shows that vertices can randomly shorten their ”palette” of colors, after which all colorings from these palettes lead to very few monochromatic edges. This is an immensely powerful tool, since one can get immediately sublinear complexity algorithms in many models: adjacency list, streaming, distributed. Is the randomness necessary? Note that these algorithms run in \(\Omega(n)\) time/space, so it is conceivable that deterministic sublinear algorithms exists. This paper shows that randomization is necessary in the semi-streaming model (space \(O(n poly(\log n))\)). Indeed, there exist no deterministic semi-streaming algorithms that can achieve even \(\exp(\Delta^{o(1)})\) colorings.</p>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-06T04:31:45Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-06T04:31:45Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Seshadhri</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:39:30Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=573</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2021/10/05/tcs-talk-wednesday-october-13-nutan-limaye-it-university-of-copenhagen/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TCS+ talk: Wednesday, October 13 — Nutan Limaye, IT University of Copenhagen</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place next Wednesday, October 13th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC: check your time zone!). Nutan Limaye from IT University of Copenhagen will speak about “Superpolynomial Lower Bounds Against Low-Depth Algebraic Circuits” (abstract below). You can reserve a spot as […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk will take place next Wednesday, October 13th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 17:00 UTC: <a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/worldclock/converter.html?iso=20211013T170000&amp;p1=tz_pt&amp;p2=tz_et&amp;p3=tz_cest&amp;p4=1440">check your time zone!</a>). <a href="https://www.cse.iitb.ac.in/~nutan/"><strong>Nutan Limaye</strong></a> from IT University of Copenhagen will speak about “<em>Superpolynomial Lower Bounds Against Low-Depth Algebraic Circuits</em>” (abstract below).</p>
<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/next-tcs-talk">the online form</a>. Registration is <em>not</em> required to attend the interactive talk, and the link will be posted on the website the day prior to the talk; however, by registering in the form, you will receive a reminder, along with the link. (The recorded talk will also be posted <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/past-talks">on our website</a> afterwards) As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/welcome/suggest-a-talk">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/tcsplus/">the website</a>.</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>Abstract: Every multivariate polynomial P(X) can be written as a sum of monomials, i.e. a sum of products of variables and field constants. In general, the size of such an expression is the number of monomials that have a non-zero coefficient in P.</p>
<p>What happens if we add another layer of complexity, and consider sums of products of sums (of variables and field constants) expressions? Now, it becomes unclear how to prove that a given polynomial P(X) does not have small expressions. In this result, we solve exactly this problem.</p>
<p>More precisely, we prove that certain explicit polynomials have no polynomial-sized “Sigma-Pi-Sigma” (sums of products of sums) representations. We can also show similar results for Sigma-Pi-Sigma-Pi, Sigma-Pi-Sigma-Pi-Sigma and so on for all “constant-depth” expressions.</p>
<p>The talk is based on a joint work of Nutan Limaye, Srikanth Srinivasan, and Sébastien Tavenas.</p></blockquote></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-05T21:34:49Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-05T21:34:49Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:38:59Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4554</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2021/10/05/hasselmann-manabe-and-parisi-win-2021-physics-nobel-prize/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hasselmann, Manabe and Parisi win 2021 Physics Nobel Prize</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Today the Italian academic community, along with lots of other people, was delighted to hear that Giorgio Parisi is one of the three recipients of the 2021 Nobel Prize for Physics. Perhaps Parisi’s most influential contribution has been his “replica … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2021/10/05/hasselmann-manabe-and-parisi-win-2021-physics-nobel-prize/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img alt="itscomingrome-lorenza-parisi" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4558" src="https://lucatrevisan.files.wordpress.com/2021/10/itscomingrome-lorenza-parisi-1.jpeg?w=584"/></p>
<p>Today the Italian academic community, along with lots of other people, was delighted to hear that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_Parisi">Giorgio Parisi</a> is one of the three recipients of the 2021 Nobel Prize for Physics.</p>
<p>Perhaps Parisi’s most influential contribution has been his “replica method” for the analysis of the Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model. His ideas have led to several breakthroughs in statistical physics by Parisi and his collaborators, and they have also found applications in computer science: to tight analyses on a number of questions about combinatorial optimization on random graphs, to results on random constraint satisfaction problems (including the famous connection with random k-SAT analyzed by Mezard, Parisi and Zecchina) and random error correcting codes, and to understanding the solution landscape in optimization problems arising from machine learning. Furthermore these ideas have also led to the development and analysis of algorithms.</p>
<p>The news was particularly well received at Bocconi, where most of the faculty of the future CS department has done work that involved the replica method, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.05648">including me</a>!</p>
<p>Mezard and Montanari have written a <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~montanar/RESEARCH/book.html">book-length treatment</a> on the interplay between ideas from statistical physics, algorithms, optimization, information theory and coding theory that arise from this tradition. Readers of <em>in theory</em> looking for a shorter exposition aimed at theoretical computer scientists will enjoy these <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2021/08/11/replica-method-for-the-machine-learning-theorist-part-1-of-2/">notes posted by Boaz Barak</a>, or <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/03/14/statistical-physics-dictionary/">this even shorter post by Boaz</a>.</p>
<p>In this post, I will try to give a sense to the reader of what the replica method for the Sherrington-Kirkpatrick model looks like when applied to the average-case analysis of optimization problems, stripped of all the physics. Of course, without the physics, nothing makes any sense, and the interested reader should look at Boaz’s posts (and to references that he provides) for an introduction to the context. I did not have time to check too carefully what I wrote, so be aware that several details could be wrong.</p>
<p>What is the typical value of the max cut in a <img alt="{G_{n,\frac 12}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG_%7Bn%2C%5Cfrac+12%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> random graph with <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> vertices?</p>
<p>Working out an upper bound using union bounds and Chernoff bound, and a lower bound by thinking about a greedy algorithm, we can quickly convince ourselves that the answer is <img alt="{\frac {n^2}{4} + \Theta(n^{1.5})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac+%7Bn%5E2%7D%7B4%7D+%2B+%5CTheta%28n%5E%7B1.5%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. Great, but <em>what is the constant in front of the <img alt="{n^{1.5}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7B1.5%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>?</em> This question is answered by the <em>Parisi formula</em>, though this fact was not rigorously established by Parisi. (Guerra proved that the formula gives an upper bound, Talagrand proved that it gives a tight bound.)</p>
<p>Some manipulations can reduce the question above to the following question: suppose that I pick a random <img alt="{n\times n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5Ctimes+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> symmetric matrix <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, say with zero diagonal, and such that (up to the symmetry requirement) the entries are mutually independent and each entry is equally likely to be <img alt="{+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> or <img alt="{-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, or perhaps each entry is distributed according to a standard normal distribution (the two versions can be proved to be equivalent), what is the typical value of</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \max _{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } \ \ \frac 1{n^{1.5}} x^T M x " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cmax+_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+%5C+%5C+%5Cfrac+1%7Bn%5E%7B1.5%7D%7D+x%5ET+M+x+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>up to <img alt="{o_n(1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bo_n%281%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> additive terms,?</p>
<p>As a first step, we could replace the maximum with a “soft-max,” and note that, for every choice of <img alt="{\beta&gt;0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta%3E0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, we have</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \max _{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } \ \ x^T M x \leq \frac 1 \beta \log \sum_{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } e^{\beta x^T Mx} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cmax+_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+%5C+%5C+x%5ET+M+x+%5Cleq+%5Cfrac+1+%5Cbeta+%5Clog+%5Csum_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+e%5E%7B%5Cbeta+x%5ET+Mx%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>The above upper bound gets tighter and tighter for larger <img alt="{\beta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, so if we were able to estimate</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \mathop{\mathbb E} \log \sum_{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } e^{\beta x^T Mx} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+%5Clog+%5Csum_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+e%5E%7B%5Cbeta+x%5ET+Mx%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>for every <img alt="{\beta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> (where the expectation is over the randomness of <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>) then we would be in good shape.</p>
<p>We could definitely use convexity and write</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \mathop{\mathbb E} \max _{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } \ \ x^T M x \leq \frac 1 \beta \mathop{\mathbb E} \log \sum_{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } e^{\beta x^T Mx} \leq \frac 1 \beta \log \mathop{\mathbb E} \sum_{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } e^{\beta x^T Mx} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+%5Cmax+_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+%5C+%5C+x%5ET+M+x+%5Cleq+%5Cfrac+1+%5Cbeta+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+%5Clog+%5Csum_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+e%5E%7B%5Cbeta+x%5ET+Mx%7D+%5Cleq+%5Cfrac+1+%5Cbeta+%5Clog+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+%5Csum_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+e%5E%7B%5Cbeta+x%5ET+Mx%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>and then use linearity of expectation and independence of the entries of <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> to get to</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \leq \frac 1 \beta \log \sum_{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } \prod_{1\leq i &lt; j\leq n} \mathop{\mathbb E} e^{2\beta M_{i,j} x_i x_j } " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cleq+%5Cfrac+1+%5Cbeta+%5Clog+%5Csum_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+%5Cprod_%7B1%5Cleq+i+%3C+j%5Cleq+n%7D+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+e%5E%7B2%5Cbeta+M_%7Bi%2Cj%7D+x_i+x_j+%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>Now things simplify quite a bit, because for all <img alt="{i&lt;j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bi%3Cj%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> the expression <img alt="{M_{i,j} x_i x_j}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM_%7Bi%2Cj%7D+x_i+x_j%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, in the Rademacher setting, is equally likely to be <img alt="{+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> or <img alt="{-1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B-1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, so that, for <img alt="{\beta = o(1)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta+%3D+o%281%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, we have</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \mathop{\mathbb E} e^{2\beta M_{i,j} x_i x_j } = cosh (2\beta) \leq 1 + O(\beta^2) \leq e^{O(\beta^2)} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+e%5E%7B2%5Cbeta+M_%7Bi%2Cj%7D+x_i+x_j+%7D+%3D+cosh+%282%5Cbeta%29+%5Cleq+1+%2B+O%28%5Cbeta%5E2%29+%5Cleq+e%5E%7BO%28%5Cbeta%5E2%29%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>and</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \sum_{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } \prod_{1\leq i &lt; j\leq n} \mathop{\mathbb E} e^{2\beta M_{i,j} x_i x_j } \leq 2^n \cdot e^{O(\beta^2 n^2)} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Csum_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+%5Cprod_%7B1%5Cleq+i+%3C+j%5Cleq+n%7D+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+e%5E%7B2%5Cbeta+M_%7Bi%2Cj%7D+x_i+x_j+%7D+%5Cleq+2%5En+%5Ccdot+e%5E%7BO%28%5Cbeta%5E2+n%5E2%29%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>so that</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \frac 1 \beta \log \sum_{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } \prod_{1\leq i &lt; j\leq n} \mathop{\mathbb E} e^{2\beta M_{i,j} x_i x_j } \leq \frac n{\beta} + O(\beta n^2) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cfrac+1+%5Cbeta+%5Clog+%5Csum_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+%5Cprod_%7B1%5Cleq+i+%3C+j%5Cleq+n%7D+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+e%5E%7B2%5Cbeta+M_%7Bi%2Cj%7D+x_i+x_j+%7D+%5Cleq+%5Cfrac+n%7B%5Cbeta%7D+%2B+O%28%5Cbeta+n%5E2%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>which, choosing <img alt="{\beta = 1/\sqrt n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta+%3D+1%2F%5Csqrt+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, gives an <img alt="{O(n^{1.5})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E%7B1.5%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> upper bound which is in the right ballpark. Note that this is exactly the same calculations coming out of a Chernoff bound and union bound. If we optimize the choice of <img alt="{\beta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> we unfortunately do not get the right constant in front of <img alt="{n^{1.5}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7B1.5%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.</p>
<p>So, if we call</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle F := \sum_{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } e^{\beta x^T Mx} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+F+%3A%3D+%5Csum_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+e%5E%7B%5Cbeta+x%5ET+Mx%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>we see that we lose too much if we do the step</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \mathop{\mathbb E} \log F \leq \log \mathop{\mathbb E} F " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+%5Clog+F+%5Cleq+%5Clog+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+F+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>But what else can we do to get rid of the logarithm and to reduce to an expression in which we take expectations of products of independent quantities (if we are not able to exploit the assumption that <img alt="{M}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> has mutually independent entries, we will not be able to make progress)?</p>
<p>The idea is that if <img alt="{k&gt;0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%3E0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is small enough quantity (something much smaller than <img alt="{1/\log F}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%2F%5Clog+F%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>), then <img alt="{F^k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BF%5Ek%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is close to 1 and we have the approximation</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \log F^k \approx F^k-1 " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Clog+F%5Ek+%5Capprox+F%5Ek-1+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>and we obviously have</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \log F^k = k \log F " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Clog+F%5Ek+%3D+k+%5Clog+F+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>so we can use the approximation</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \log F \approx \frac 1k (F^k - 1) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Clog+F+%5Capprox+%5Cfrac+1k+%28F%5Ek+-+1%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>and</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \mathop{\mathbb E} \log F \approx \frac 1k (\mathop{\mathbb E} F^k - 1) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+%5Clog+F+%5Capprox+%5Cfrac+1k+%28%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+F%5Ek+-+1%29+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>Let’s forget for a moment that we want <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> to be a very small parameter. If <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> was an integer, we would have</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle \mathop{\mathbb E} F^k = \mathop{\mathbb E} \left( \sum_{x \in \{+1,1\}^n } e^{\beta x^T Mx} \right)^k = \sum_{x^{(1)},\ldots x^{(k)} \in \{+1,-1\}^n} \mathop{\mathbb E} e^{\beta \cdot ( x^{(1) T} M x^{(1)} + \cdots + x^{(k)T} M x^{(k)}) } " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+F%5Ek+%3D+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+%5Cleft%28+%5Csum_%7Bx+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C1%5C%7D%5En+%7D+e%5E%7B%5Cbeta+x%5ET+Mx%7D+%5Cright%29%5Ek+%3D+%5Csum_%7Bx%5E%7B%281%29%7D%2C%5Cldots+x%5E%7B%28k%29%7D+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C-1%5C%7D%5En%7D+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+e%5E%7B%5Cbeta+%5Ccdot+%28+x%5E%7B%281%29+T%7D+M+x%5E%7B%281%29%7D+%2B+%5Ccdots+%2B+x%5E%7B%28k%29T%7D+M+x%5E%7B%28k%29%7D%29+%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle = \sum_{x^{(1)},\ldots x^{(k)} \in \{+1,-1\}^n} \ \ \prod_{i&lt; j} \ \mathop{\mathbb E} e^{2\beta M_{i,j} \cdot ( x^{(1)}_i x^{(1)}_j + \cdots + x^{(k)}_i x^{(k)}_j )} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle+%3D+%5Csum_%7Bx%5E%7B%281%29%7D%2C%5Cldots+x%5E%7B%28k%29%7D+%5Cin+%5C%7B%2B1%2C-1%5C%7D%5En%7D+%5C+%5C+%5Cprod_%7Bi%3C+j%7D+%5C+%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+e%5E%7B2%5Cbeta+M_%7Bi%2Cj%7D+%5Ccdot+%28+x%5E%7B%281%29%7D_i+x%5E%7B%281%29%7D_j+%2B+%5Ccdots+%2B+x%5E%7B%28k%29%7D_i+x%5E%7B%28k%29%7D_j+%29%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>Note that the above expression involves choices of <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-tuples of feasible solutions of our maximization problem. These are the “replicas” in “replica method.”</p>
<p>The above expression does not look too bad, and note how we were fully able to use the independence assumption and “simplify” the expression. Unfortunately, it is actually still very bad. In this case it is preferable to continue assuming the <img alt="{M_{i,j}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BM_%7Bi%2Cj%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> to be Gaussian, write the expectation as an integral, do a change of variable and some tricks so that we reduce to computing the maximum of a certain function, let’s call it <img alt="{G(z)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%28z%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, and then we have to guess what is an input of maximum value for this function.</p>
<p>After all this, we get an expression for <img alt="{(\mathop{\mathbb E} F^k - 1)/k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28%5Cmathop%7B%5Cmathbb+E%7D+F%5Ek+-+1%29%2Fk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for every integer <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, as a function of <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. What next? Remember how we wanted <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> to be a tiny real number and not an integer? Well, we take the expression and we set <img alt="{k=0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%3D0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>!</p>
<p>(Foto credit: Lorenza Parisi via facebook.com)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-05T20:53:23Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-05T20:53:23Z</published>
    <category term="science"/>
    <category term="Giorgio Parisi"/>
    <category term="things that are excellent"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:37:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/10/05/tenure-track-faculty-positions-at-portland-state-university-apply-by-november-1-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/10/05/tenure-track-faculty-positions-at-portland-state-university-apply-by-november-1-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>tenure-track faculty positions at Portland State University (apply by November 1, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Computer Science department at Portland State University has multiple Faculty openings this year. Theory is a top interest area. One position is part of a cluster hire in computational science, which also welcomes theory folks if their research intersects with big data analysis, scalable ML, scientific computing etc. Website: https://www.pdx.edu/computer-science/open-faculty-positions Email: cssearch@pdx.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Computer Science department at Portland State University has multiple Faculty openings this year. Theory is a top interest area. One position is part of a cluster hire in computational science, which also welcomes theory folks if their research intersects with big data analysis, scalable ML, scientific computing etc.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.pdx.edu/computer-science/open-faculty-positions">https://www.pdx.edu/computer-science/open-faculty-positions</a><br/>
Email: cssearch@pdx.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-05T20:16:35Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-05T20:16:35Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:38:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5859</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5859" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5859#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5859" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">The Physics Nobel, Gaussian BosonSampling, and Dorian Abbot</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">1. Huge congratulations to the winners of this year’s Nobel Prize in Physics: Syukuro Manabe and Klaus Hasselmann for climate modelling, and separately, Giorgio Parisi for statistical physics. While I don’t know the others, I had the great honor to get to know Parisi three years ago, when he was chair of the committee that […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>1. Huge congratulations to the <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/2021/summary/">winners</a> of this year’s Nobel Prize in Physics: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syukuro_Manabe">Syukuro Manabe</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klaus_Hasselmann">Klaus Hasselmann</a> for climate modelling, and separately, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_Parisi">Giorgio Parisi</a> for statistical physics.  While I don’t know the others, I had the great honor to get to know Parisi three years ago, when he was chair of the committee that awarded me the <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=3955">Tomassoni-Chisesi Prize in Physics</a>, and when I visited Parisi’s department at Sapienza University of Rome to give the prize lecture and collect the award.  I remember Parisi’s kindness, a lot of good food, and a lot of discussion of the interplay between theoretical computer science and physics.  Note that, while much of Parisi’s work is beyond my competence to comment on, in computer science he’s very well-known for applying statistical physics methods to the analysis of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/cs/0212002">survey propagation</a>—an algorithm that revolutionized the study of random 3SAT when it was introduced two decades ago.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>2. Two weeks ago, a group at Google <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.11525">put out a paper</a> with a new efficient classical algorithm to simulate the recent Gaussian BosonSampling experiments from USTC in China.  They argued that this algorithm called into question USTC’s claim of BosonSampling-based quantum supremacy.  Since then, I’ve been in contact with Sergio Boixo from Google, Chaoyang Lu from USTC, and Jelmer Renema, a Dutch BosonSampling expert and friend of the blog, to try to get to the bottom of this.  Very briefly, the situation seems to be that Google’s new algorithm outperforms the USTC experiment on one particular metric: namely, <em>total variation distance from the ideal marginal distribution, if (crucially) you look at only a subset of the optical modes</em>, <em>say 14 modes out of 144 total</em>.  Meanwhile, though, if you look at the k<sup>th</sup>-order correlations for large values of k, then the USTC experiment continues to win.  With the experiment, the correlations fall off exponentially with k but still have a meaningful, detectable signal even for (say) k=19, whereas with Google’s spoofing algorithm, you choose the k that you want to spoof (say, 2 or 3), and then the correlations become nonsense for larger k.</p>



<p>Now, given that you were only ever <em>supposed</em> to see a quantum advantage from BosonSampling if you looked at the k<sup>th</sup>-order correlations for large values of k, and given that we already knew, from the work of Leonid Gurvits, that <em>very</em> small marginals in BosonSampling experiments would be easy to reproduce on a classical computer, my inclination is to say that USTC’s claim of BosonSampling-based quantum supremacy still stands.  On the other hand, it’s true that, with BosonSampling especially, more so than with qubit-based random circuit sampling, we currently lack an adequate theoretical understanding of what the <em>target</em> should be.  That is, which numerical metric should an experiment aim to maximize, and how well does it have to score on that metric before it’s plausibly outperforming any fast classical algorithm?  One thing I feel confident about is that, whichever metric is chosen—Linear Cross-Entropy or whatever else—it needs to capture the k<sup>th</sup>-order correlations for large values of k.  No metric that’s insensitive to those correlations is good enough.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p>3. Like many others, I was outraged and depressed that MIT <a href="https://bariweiss.substack.com/p/mit-abandons-its-mission-and-me">uninvited Dorian Abbot</a> (see also <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/mit-cancels-geophysicists-lecture-after-activists-outrage-over-his-views-diversity-1635371">here</a>), a geophysicist at the University of Chicago, who was slated to give the Carlson Lecture in the Department of Earth, Atmospheric, and Planetary Sciences about the atmospheres of extrasolar planets.  The reason for the cancellation was that, totally unrelatedly to his scheduled lecture, Abbot had <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/diversity-problem-campus-opinion-1618419">argued in <em>Newsweek</em></a> and elsewhere that Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion initiatives should aim for equality for opportunity rather than equality of outcomes, a Twitter-mob decided to go after him in retaliation, and they succeeded.  It should go without saying that it’s perfectly reasonable to <strong>disagree</strong> with Abbot’s stance, to <strong>counterargue</strong>—if those very concepts haven’t gone the way of floppy disks.  It should also go without saying that the MIT EAPS department chair is <em>free</em> to bow to social-media pressure, as he did, rather than standing on principle … just like I’m <em>free</em> to criticize him for it.  To my mind, though, cancelling a scientific talk because of the speaker’s centrist (!) political views completely, 100% validates the right’s narrative about academia, that it’s become a fanatically intolerant echo chamber.  To my fellow progressive academics, I beseech thee in the bowels of Bertrand Russell: <em>why would you commit such an unforced error?</em></p>



<p>Yes, one can <em>imagine</em> views (e.g., open Nazism) so hateful that they might justify the cancellation of unrelated scientific lectures by people who hold those views, as many physicists after WWII refused to speak to Werner Heisenberg.  But it seems obvious to me—as it would’ve been obvious to everyone else not long ago—that no matter where a reasonable person draws the line, Abbot’s views as he expressed them in <em>Newsweek</em> don’t come within a hundred miles of it.  To be more explicit still: if Abbot’s views justify deplatforming him as a planetary scientist, then <strong>all my quantum computing and theoretical computer science lectures deserve to be cancelled too</strong>, for the many attempts I’ve made on this blog over the past 16 years to share my honest thoughts and life experiences, to write like a vulnerable human being rather than like a university press office.  While I’m sure some sneerers gleefully embrace that implication, I ask everyone else to consider how deeply they believe in the idea of academic freedom at all—keeping in mind that such a commitment <em>only ever gets tested</em> when there’s a chance someone might denounce you for it.</p>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update:</span></strong> Princeton’s James Madison Program has <a href="https://jmp.princeton.edu/events/climate-and-potential-life-other-planets">volunteered</a> to host Abbot’s Zoom talk in place of MIT.  The talk is entitled “Climate and the Potential for Life on Other Planets.”  Like probably hundreds of others who heard about this only because of the attempted cancellation, I plan to attend!</p>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Unrelated Bonus Update:</span></strong> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=934eLObPLmM">Here’s a neat YouTube video</a> put together by the ACM about me as well as David Silver of AlphaGo and AlphaZero, on the occasion of our ACM Prizes in Computing.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-05T19:23:45Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-05T19:23:45Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Complexity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Obviously I'm Not Defending Aaronson"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T20:54:12Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01231</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01231" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An impossible utopia in distance geometry</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Abud:Germano.html">Germano Abud</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Alencar:Jorge.html">Jorge Alencar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lavor:Carlile.html">Carlile Lavor</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liberti:Leo.html">Leo Liberti</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mucherino:Antonio.html">Antonio Mucherino</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01231">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Distance Geometry Problem asks for a realization of a given weighted
graph in $\mathbb{R}^K$. Two variants of this problem, both originating from
protein conformation, are based on a given vertex order (which abstracts the
protein backbone). Both variants involve an element of discrete decision in the
realization of the next vertex in the order using $K$ preceding (already
realized) vertices. The difference between these variants is that one requires
the $K$ preceding vertices to be contiguous. The presence of this constraint
allows one to prove, via a combinatorial counting of the number of solutions,
that the realization algorithm is fixed-parameter tractable. Its absence, on
the other hand, makes it possible to efficiently construct the vertex order
directly from the graph. Deriving a combinatorial counting method without using
the contiguity requirement would therefore be desirable. In this paper we prove
that, unfortunately, such a counting method cannot be devised in general.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T23:07:28Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01213</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01213" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Clique percolation method: memory efficient almost exact communities</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Baudin:Alexis.html">Alexis Baudin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Danisch:Maximilien.html">Maximilien Danisch</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kirgizov:Sergey.html">Sergey Kirgizov</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Magnien:Cl=eacute=mence.html">Clémence Magnien</a>, Marwan Ghanem <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01213">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Automatic detection of relevant groups of nodes in large real-world graphs,
i.e. community detection, has applications in many fields and has received a
lot of attention in the last twenty years. The most popular method designed to
find overlapping communities (where a node can belong to several communities)
is perhaps the clique percolation method (CPM). This method formalizes the
notion of community as a maximal union of $k$-cliques that can be reached from
each other through a series of adjacent $k$-cliques, where two cliques are
adjacent if and only if they overlap on $k-1$ nodes. Despite much effort CPM
has not been scalable to large graphs for medium values of $k$.
</p>
<p>Recent work has shown that it is possible to efficiently list all $k$-cliques
in very large real-world graphs for medium values of $k$. We build on top of
this work and scale up CPM. In cases where this first algorithm faces memory
limitations, we propose another algorithm, CPMZ, that provides a solution close
to the exact one, using more time but less memory.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T23:05:52Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01181</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01181" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>FM-Indexing Grammars Induced by Suffix Sorting for Long Patterns</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Jin Jie Deng, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hon:Wing=Kai.html">Wing-Kai Hon</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/K=ouml=ppl:Dominik.html">Dominik Köppl</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sadakane:Kunihiko.html">Kunihiko Sadakane</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01181">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The run-length compressed Burrows-Wheeler transform (RLBWT) used in
conjunction with the backward search introduced in the FM index is the
centerpiece of most compressed indexes working on highly-repetitive data sets
like biological sequences. Compared to grammar indexes, the size of the RLBWT
is often much bigger, but queries like counting the occurrences of long
patterns can be done much faster than on any existing grammar index so far. In
this paper, we combine the virtues of a grammar with the RLBWT by building the
RLBWT on top of a special grammar based on induced suffix sorting. Our
experiments reveal that our hybrid approach outperforms the classic RLBWT with
respect to the index sizes, and with respect to query times on biological data
sets for sufficiently long patterns.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T23:02:27Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01173</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01173" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Bipartite 3-Regular Counting Problems with Mixed Signs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cai:Jin=Yi.html">Jin-Yi Cai</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fan:Austen_Z=.html">Austen Z. Fan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Yin.html">Yin Liu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01173">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We prove a complexity dichotomy for a class of counting problems expressible
as bipartite 3-regular Holant problems. For every problem of the form
$\operatorname{Holant}\left(f\mid =_3 \right)$, where $f$ is any integer-valued
ternary symmetric constraint function on Boolean variables, we prove that it is
either P-time computable or #P-hard, depending on an explicit criterion of $f$.
The constraint function can take both positive and negative values, allowing
for cancellations. The dichotomy extends easily to rational valued functions of
the same type. In addition, we discover a new phenomenon: there is a set
$\mathcal{F}$ with the property that for every $f \in \mathcal{F}$ the problem
$\operatorname{Holant}\left(f\mid =_3 \right)$ is planar P-time computable but
#P-hard in general, yet its planar tractability is by a combination of a
holographic transformation by $\left[\begin{smallmatrix} 1 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; -1
\end{smallmatrix}\right]$ to FKT together with an independent global argument.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:42:50Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01111</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01111" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Is this the simplest (and most surprising) sorting algorithm ever?</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fung:Stanley_P=_Y=.html">Stanley P. Y. Fung</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01111">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present an extremely simple sorting algorithm. It may look like it is
obviously wrong, but we prove that it is in fact correct. We compare it with
other simple sorting algorithms, and analyse some of its curious properties.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:55:14Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01096</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01096" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fast algorithm to identify cluster synchrony through fibration symmetries in large information-processing networks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Higor S. Monteiro, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Leifer:Ian.html">Ian Leifer</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Reis:Saulo_D=_S=.html">Saulo D. S. Reis</a>, José S. Andrade, Jr., Hernan A. Makse <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01096">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Recent studies revealed an important interplay between the detailed structure
of fibration symmetric circuits and the functionality of biological and
non-biological networks within which they have be identified. The presence of
these circuits in complex networks are directed related to the phenomenon of
cluster synchronization, which produces patterns of synchronized group of
nodes. Here we present a fast, and memory efficient, algorithm to identify
fibration symmetries over information-processing networks. This algorithm is
specially suitable for large and sparse networks since it has runtime of
complexity $O(M\log N)$ and requires $O(M+N)$ of memory resources, where $N$
and $M$ are the number of nodes and edges in the network, respectively. We
propose a modification on the so-called refinement paradigm to identify
circuits symmetrical to information flow (i.e., fibers) by finding the coarsest
refinement partition over the network. Finally, we show that the presented
algorithm provides an optimal procedure for identifying fibers, overcoming the
current approaches used in the literature.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:40:10Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01093</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01093" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TSP on manifolds</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>David Zisselman <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01093">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we present a new approach of creating PTAS to the TSP problems
by defining a bounded-curvature surface embedded spaces. Using this definition
we prove: - A bounded-curvature surface embedded spaces TSP admits to a PTAS. -
Every bounded doubling dimension space can be embedded into a bounded-curvature
surface. - Every uniform metric space can be embedded into a bounded-curvature
surface.
</p>
<p>Thus, the algorithm generalizes <a href="http://export.arxiv.org/abs/1112.0699">arXiv:1112.0699</a> (and therefore [7] and [8] as
well, w.r.t PTAS of TSP). But, the algorithm is much broader as uniform metric
spaces aren't bounded doubling dimension spaces. It should be mentioned that
our definition of a surface is derived from Riemannian geometry, but doesn't
match it exactly. therefore, our definitions and basic geometry algorithm is
given here in full.
</p>
<p>[7] Sanjeev Arora. 1998. Polynomial time approximation schemes for Euclidean
traveling salesman and other geometric problems. J. ACM 45, 5 (September 1998),
753-782. DOI=<a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/29&lt;a href=">this http URL</a>
</p>
<p>[8] Joseph S. B. Mitchell. Guillotine subdivisions approximate polygonal
subdivisions: A simple polynomial time approximation scheme for geometric TSP,
k- MST, and related problems. SIAM J. Comput., 28(4):1298-1309, 1999.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T23:07:11Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01070</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01070" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Graph Generation: A New Approach to Solving Expanded Linear Programming Relaxations</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yarkony:Julian.html">Julian Yarkony</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Haghani:Naveed.html">Naveed Haghani</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Regan:Amelia.html">Amelia Regan</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01070">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this article we introduce Graph Generation, an enhanced Column Generation
(CG) algorithm for solving expanded linear programming relaxations of mixed
integer linear programs. To apply Graph Generation, we must be able to map any
given column to a small directed acyclic graph for which any path from source
to sink describes a feasible column. This structure is easily satisfied for
vehicle routing and crew scheduling problems; and other such problems where
pricing is a resource constrained shortest path problem. Such graphs are then
added to the restricted master problem (RMP) when the corresponding column is
generated during pricing. The use of Graph Generation does not weaken the
linear programming relaxation being solved. At any given iteration of CG
enhanced by Graph Generation; the technique permits the RMP to express a much
wider set of columns than those generated during pricing, leading to faster
convergence of CG. Graph Generation does not change the structure of the CG
pricing problem. We show how the method can be applied in a general way, and
then demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach on the classical Capacitated
Vehicle Routing Problem.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:49:17Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01069</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01069" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hinged Trouchet tiling fractals</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>H Verrill <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01069">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This article describes a new method of producing space filling fractal dragon
curves based on a hinged tiling procedure. The fractals produced can be
generated by a simple L-system. The construction as a hinged tiling has the
advantage of automatically implying that the fractiles produced tessellate, and
that the Heighway fractal dragon curve, and the other curves constructed by
this method, do not cross themselves. This also gives a new limiting procedure
to apply to certain Trouchet tilings. I include the computation of the fractal
dimension of the boundary of one of the curves, and describe an algorithm for
computing the sim value of the fractal boundary of these curves. The curves
produced are well known. The hinged tiling approach is new, as is the algorithm
for computing the sim value.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T23:07:08Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01030</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01030" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Recursive Algorithm for Solving Simple Stochastic Games</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Montjoye:Xavier_Badin_de.html">Xavier Badin de Montjoye</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01030">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present two recursive strategy improvement algorithms for solving simple
stochastic games. First we present an algorithm for solving SSGs of degree $d$
that uses at most $O\left(\left\lfloor(d+1)^2/2\right\rfloor^{n/2}\right)$
iterations, with $n$ the number of MAX vertices. Then, we focus on binary SSG
and propose an algorithm that has complexity $O\left(\varphi^nPoly(N)\right)$
where $\varphi = (1 + \sqrt{5})/2$ is the golden ratio. To the best of our
knowledge, this is the first deterministic strategy improvement algorithm that
visits $2^{cn}$ strategies with $c &lt; 1$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:55:07Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00958</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00958" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fingerprint Matching using the Onion Peeling Approach and Turning Function</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Padkan:Nazanin.html">Nazanin Padkan</a>, B. Sadeghi Bigham, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Faraji:Mohammad_Reza.html">Mohammad Reza Faraji</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00958">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Fingerprint, as one of the most popular and robust biometric traits, can be
used in automatic identification and verification systems to identify
individuals. Fingerprint matching is a vital and challenging issue in
fingerprint recognition systems. Most fingerprint matching algorithms are
minutiae-based. The minutiae in fingerprints can be determined by their
discontinuity. Ridge ending and ridge bifurcation are two frequently used
minutiae in most fingerprint-based matching algorithms.
</p>
<p>This paper presents a new minutiae-based fingerprint matching using the onion
peeling approach. In the proposed method, fingerprints are aligned to find the
matched minutiae points. Then, the nested convex polygons of matched minutiae
points are constructed and the comparison between peer-to-peer polygons is
performed by the turning function distance. Simplicity, accuracy, and low time
complexity of the Onion peeling approach are three important factors that make
it a standard method for fingerprint matching purposes. The performance of the
proposed algorithm is evaluated on the database $FVC2002$. The results show
that fingerprints of the same fingers have higher scores than different
fingers. Since the fingerprints that the difference between the number of their
layers is more than $2$ and the minutiae matching score lower than 0.15 are
ignored, the better results are obtained.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T23:07:13Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00900</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00900" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The isomorphism problem for plain groups is in $\Sigma_3^{\mathsf{P}}$</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dietrich:Heiko.html">Heiko Dietrich</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Elder:Murray.html">Murray Elder</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Piggott:Adam.html">Adam Piggott</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/q/Qiao:Youming.html">Youming Qiao</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wei=szlig=:Armin.html">Armin Weiß</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00900">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Testing isomorphism of infinite groups is a classical topic, but from the
complexity theory viewpoint, few results are known. S\'enizergues and Wei\ss
(ICALP2018) proved that the isomorphism problem for virtually free groups is
decidable in $\mathsf{PSPACE}$ when the input is given in terms of so-called
virtually free presentations. Here we consider the isomorphism problem for the
class of \emph{plain groups}, that is, groups that are isomorphic to a free
product of finitely many finite groups and finitely many copies of the infinite
cyclic group. Every plain group is naturally and efficiently presented via an
inverse-closed finite convergent length-reducing rewriting system. We prove
that the isomorphism problem for plain groups given in this form lies in the
polynomial time hierarchy, more precisely, in $\Sigma_3^{\mathsf{P}}$. This
result is achieved by combining new geometric and algebraic characterisations
of groups presented by inverse-closed finite convergent length-reducing
rewriting systems developed in recent work of Elder and Piggott (2021) with
classical finite group isomorphism results of Babai and Szemer\'edi (1984).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:41:43Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00839</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00839" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tiling Rectangles and the Plane using Squares of Integral Sides</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bigham:Bahram_Sadeghi.html">Bahram Sadeghi Bigham</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Davoodi:Mansoor.html">Mansoor Davoodi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mazaheri:Samaneh.html">Samaneh Mazaheri</a>, Jalal Kheyrabadi <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00839">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the problem of perfect tiling in the plane and exploring the
possibility of tiling a rectangle using integral distinct squares. Assume a set
of distinguishable squares (or equivalently a set of distinct natural numbers)
is given, and one has to decide whether it can tile the plane or a rectangle or
not. Previously, it has been proved that tiling the plane is not feasible using
a set of odd numbers or an infinite sequence of natural numbers including
exactly two odd numbers. The problem is open for different situations in which
the number of odd numbers is arbitrary. In addition to providing a solution to
this special case, we discuss some open problems to tile the plane and
rectangles in this paper.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T23:11:27Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00827</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00827" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Deterministic Algorithms for the Hidden Subgroup Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Ye:Zekun.html">Zekun Ye</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Lvzhou.html">Lvzhou Li</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00827">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider deterministic algorithms for the well-known hidden subgroup
problem ($\mathsf{HSP}$): for a finite group $G$ and a finite set $X$, given a
function $f:G \to X$ and the promise that for any $g_1, g_2 \in G, f(g_1) =
f(g_2)$ iff $g_1H=g_2H$ for a subgroup $H \le G$, the goal of the decision
version is to determine whether $H$ is trivial or not, and the goal of the
identification version is to identify $H$. An algorithm for the problem should
query $f(g)$ for $g\in G$ at least as possible. Nayak \cite{Nayak2021} asked
whether there exist deterministic algorithms with $O(\sqrt{\frac{|G|}{|H|}})$
query complexity for $\mathsf{HSP}$. We answer this problem by proving the
following results, which also extend the main results of Ref. [30], since here
the algorithms do not rely on any prior knowledge of $H$. (i)When $G$ is a
general finite Abelian group, there exist an algorithm with
$O(\sqrt{\frac{|G|}{|H|}})$ queries to decide the triviality of $H$ and an
algorithm to identify $H$ with $O(\sqrt{\frac{|G|}{|H|}\log |H|}+\log |H|)$
queries. (ii)In general there is no deterministic algorithm for the
identification version of $\mathsf{HSP}$ with query complexity of
$O(\sqrt{\frac{|G|}{|H|}})$, since there exists an instance of $\mathsf{HSP}$
that needs $\omega(\sqrt{\frac{|G|}{|H|}})$ queries to identify
$H$.\footnote{$f(x)$ is said to be $\omega(g(x))$ if for every positive
constant $C$, there exists a positive constant $N$ such that for $x&gt;N$,
$f(x)\ge C\cdot g(x)$, which means $g$ is a strict lower bound for $f$.} On the
other hand, there exist instances of $\mathsf{HSP}$ with query complexity far
smaller than $O(\sqrt{\frac{|G|}{|H|}})$, whose query complexity is $O(\log
\frac{|G|}{|H|})$ and even $O(1)$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T23:02:07Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00776</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00776" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Minimizing LR(1) State Machines is NP-Hard</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yang:Wuu.html">Wuu Yang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00776">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>LR(1) parsing was a focus of extensive research in the past 50 years. Though
most fundamental mysteries have been resolved, a few remain hidden in the dark
corners. The one we bumped into is the minimization of the LR(1) state
machines, which we prove is NP-hard. It is the node-coloring problem that is
reduced to the minimization puzzle. The reduction makes use of two technique:
indirect reduction and incremental construction. Indirect reduction means the
graph to be colored is not reduced to an LR(1) state machine directly. Instead,
it is reduced to a context-free grammar from which an LR(1) state machine is
derived. Furthermore, by considering the nodes in the graph to be colored one
at a time, the context-free grammar is incrementally extended from a template
context-free grammar that is for a two-node graph. The extension is done by
adding new grammar symbols and rules. A minimized LR(1) machine can be used to
recover a minimum coloring of the original graph.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:40:34Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00744</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00744" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Random Subgraph Detection Using Queries</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Huleihel:Wasim.html">Wasim Huleihel</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mazumdar:Arya.html">Arya Mazumdar</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pal:Soumyabrata.html">Soumyabrata Pal</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00744">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The planted densest subgraph detection problem refers to the task of testing
whether in a given (random) graph there is a subgraph that is unusually dense.
Specifically, we observe an undirected and unweighted graph on $n$ nodes. Under
the null hypothesis, the graph is a realization of an Erd\H{o}s-R\'{e}nyi graph
with edge probability (or, density) $q$. Under the alternative, there is a
subgraph on $k$ vertices with edge probability $p&gt;q$. The statistical as well
as the computational barriers of this problem are well-understood for a wide
range of the edge parameters $p$ and $q$. In this paper, we consider a natural
variant of the above problem, where one can only observe a small part of the
graph using adaptive edge queries.
</p>
<p>For this model, we determine the number of queries necessary and sufficient
for detecting the presence of the planted subgraph. Specifically, we show that
any (possibly randomized) algorithm must make $\mathsf{Q} =
\Omega(\frac{n^2}{k^2\chi^4(p||q)}\log^2n)$ adaptive queries (on expectation)
to the adjacency matrix of the graph to detect the planted subgraph with
probability more than $1/2$, where $\chi^2(p||q)$ is the Chi-Square distance.
On the other hand, we devise a quasi-polynomial-time algorithm that finds the
planted subgraph with high probability by making $\mathsf{Q} =
O(\frac{n^2}{k^2\chi^4(p||q)}\log^2n)$ adaptive queries. We then propose a
polynomial-time algorithm which is able to detect the planted subgraph using
$\mathsf{Q} = O(\frac{n^4}{k^4\chi^2(p||q)}\log n)$ queries. We conjecture that
in the leftover regime, where $\frac{n^2}{k^2}\ll\mathsf{Q}\ll
\frac{n^4}{k^4}$, no polynomial-time algorithms exist; we give an evidence for
this hypothesis using the planted clique conjecture. Our results resolve three
questions posed in \cite{racz2020finding}, where the special case of adaptive
detection and recovery of a planted clique was considered.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:47:18Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00734</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00734" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Capacity Expansion in the College Admission Problem</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bobbio:Federico.html">Federico Bobbio</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Carvalho:Margarida.html">Margarida Carvalho</a>, Andrea Lodi, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Torrico:Alfredo.html">Alfredo Torrico</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00734">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The college admission problem plays a fundamental role in several real-world
allocation mechanisms such as school choice and supply chain stability. The
classical framework assumes that the capacity of each college is known and
fixed in advance. However, increasing the quota of even a single college would
improve the overall cost of the students. In this work, we study the problem of
finding the college capacity expansion that achieves the best cost of the
students, subject to a cardinality constraint. First, we show that this problem
is NP-hard to solve, even under complete and strict preference lists. We
provide an integer quadratically constrained programming formulation and study
its linear reformulation. We also propose two natural heuristics: A greedy
algorithm and an LP-based method. We empirically evaluate the performance of
our approaches in a detailed computational study. We observe the practical
superiority of the linearized model in comparison with its quadratic
counterpart and we outline their computational limits. In terms of solution
quality, we note that the allocation of a few extra spots can significantly
impact the overall student satisfaction.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:40:49Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00692</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00692" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Decomposing a graph into subgraphs with small components</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jiang:Rain.html">Rain Jiang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jiang:Kai.html">Kai Jiang</a>, Minghui Jiang <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00692">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The component size of a graph is the maximum number of edges in any connected
component of the graph. Given a graph $G$ and two integers $k$ and $c$,
$(k,c)$-Decomposition is the problem of deciding whether $G$ admits an edge
partition into $k$ subgraphs with component size at most $c$. We prove that for
any fixed $k \ge 2$ and $c \ge 2$, $(k,c)$-Decomposition is NP-complete in
bipartite graphs. Also, when both $k$ and $c$ are part of the input,
$(k,c)$-Decomposition is NP-complete even in trees. Moreover,
$(k,c)$-Decomposition in trees is W[1]-hard with parameter $k$, and is FPT with
parameter $c$. In addition, we present approximation algorithms for decomposing
a tree either into the minimum number of subgraphs with component size at most
$c$, or into $k$ subgraphs minimizing the maximum component size. En route to
these results, we also obtain a fixed-parameter algorithm for Bin Packing with
the bin capacity as parameter.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00671</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00671" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fast and Exact Convex Hull Simplification</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Klimenko:Georgiy.html">Georgiy Klimenko</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Raichel:Benjamin.html">Benjamin Raichel</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00671">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a point set $P$ in the plane, we seek a subset $Q\subseteq P$, whose
convex hull gives a smaller and thus simpler representation of the convex hull
of $P$. Specifically, let $cost(Q,P)$ denote the Hausdorff distance between the
convex hulls $\mathcal{CH}(Q)$ and $\mathcal{CH}(P)$. Then given a value
$\varepsilon&gt;0$ we seek the smallest subset $Q\subseteq P$ such that
$cost(Q,P)\leq \varepsilon$. We also consider the dual version, where given an
integer $k$, we seek the subset $Q\subseteq P$ which minimizes $cost(Q,P)$,
such that $|Q|\leq k$. For these problems, when $P$ is in convex position, we
respectively give an $O(n\log^2 n)$ time algorithm and an $O(n\log^3 n)$ time
algorithm, where the latter running time holds with high probability. When
there is no restriction on $P$, we show the problem can be reduced to APSP in
an unweighted directed graph, yielding an $O(n^{2.5302})$ time algorithm when
minimizing $k$ and an $O(\min\{n^{2.5302}, kn^{2.376}\})$ time algorithm when
minimizing $\varepsilon$, using prior results for APSP. Finally, we show our
near linear algorithms for convex position give 2-approximations for the
general case.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T23:11:06Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00633</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00633" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Uniform Bounds for Scheduling with Job Size Estimates</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Scully:Ziv.html">Ziv Scully</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Grosof:Isaac.html">Isaac Grosof</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mitzenmacher:Michael.html">Michael Mitzenmacher</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00633">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the problem of scheduling to minimize mean response time in M/G/1
queues where only estimated job sizes (processing times) are known to the
scheduler, where a job of true size $s$ has estimated size in the interval
$[\beta s, \alpha s]$ for some $\alpha \geq \beta &gt; 0$. We evaluate each
scheduling policy by its approximation ratio, which we define to be the ratio
between its mean response time and that of Shortest Remaining Processing Time
(SRPT), the optimal policy when true sizes are known. Our question: is there a
scheduling policy that (a) has approximation ratio near 1 when $\alpha$ and
$\beta$ are near 1, (b) has approximation ratio bounded by some function of
$\alpha$ and $\beta$ even when they are far from 1, and (c) can be implemented
without knowledge of $\alpha$ and $\beta$?
</p>
<p>We first show that naively running SRPT using estimated sizes in place of
true sizes is not such a policy: its approximation ratio can be arbitrarily
large for any fixed $\beta &lt; 1$. We then provide a simple variant of SRPT for
estimated sizes that satisfies criteria (a), (b), and (c). In particular, we
prove its approximation ratio approaches 1 uniformly as $\alpha$ and $\beta$
approach 1. This is the first result showing this type of convergence for M/G/1
scheduling.
</p>
<p>We also study the Preemptive Shortest Job First (PSJF) policy, a cousin of
SRPT. We show that, unlike SRPT, naively running PSJF using estimated sizes in
place of true sizes satisfies criteria (b) and (c), as well as a weaker version
of (a).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:55:27Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00627</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.00627" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the complexity of the optimal transport problem with graph-structured cost</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Fan:Jiaojiao.html">Jiaojiao Fan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Haasler:Isabel.html">Isabel Haasler</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Karlsson:Johan.html">Johan Karlsson</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Yongxin.html">Yongxin Chen</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.00627">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Multi-marginal optimal transport (MOT) is a generalization of optimal
transport to multiple marginals. Optimal transport has evolved into an
important tool in many machine learning applications, and its multi-marginal
extension opens up for addressing new challenges in the field of machine
learning. However, the usage of MOT has been largely impeded by its
computational complexity which scales exponentially in the number of marginals.
Fortunately, in many applications, such as barycenter or interpolation
problems, the cost function adheres to structures, which has recently been
exploited for developing efficient computational methods. In this work we
derive computational bounds for these methods. With $m$ marginal distributions
supported on $n$ points, we provide a $ \mathcal{\tilde O}(d(G)m
n^2\epsilon^{-2})$ bound for a $\epsilon$-accuracy when the problem is
associated with a tree with diameter $d(G)$. For the special case of the
Wasserstein barycenter problem, which corresponds to a star-shaped tree, our
bound is in alignment with the existing complexity bound for it.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:37:35Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2106.05423</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2106.05423" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A New Notion of Individually Fair Clustering: $\alpha$-Equitable $k$-Center</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1633392000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chakrabarti:Darshan.html">Darshan Chakrabarti</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dickerson:John_P=.html">John P. Dickerson</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/e/Esmaeili:Seyed_A=.html">Seyed A. Esmaeili</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Srinivasan:Aravind.html">Aravind Srinivasan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tsepenekas:Leonidas.html">Leonidas Tsepenekas</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2106.05423">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Clustering is a fundamental problem in unsupervised machine learning, and
fair variants of it have recently received significant attention due to its
societal implications. In this work we introduce a novel definition of
individual fairness for clustering problems. Specifically, in our model, each
point $j$ has a set of other points $\mathcal{S}_j$ that it perceives as
similar to itself, and it feels that it is fairly treated if the quality of
service it receives in the solution is $\alpha$-close (in a multiplicative
sense, for a given $\alpha \geq 1$) to that of the points in $\mathcal{S}_j$.
We begin our study by answering questions regarding the structure of the
problem, namely for what values of $\alpha$ the problem is well-defined, and
what the behavior of the \emph{Price of Fairness (PoF)} for it is. For the
well-defined region of $\alpha$, we provide efficient and easily-implementable
approximation algorithms for the $k$-center objective, which in certain cases
enjoy bounded-PoF guarantees. We finally complement our analysis by an
extensive suite of experiments that validates the effectiveness of our
theoretical results.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2021-10-05T22:49:48Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?p=123</id>
    <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/2021/10/04/focs-2021-best-paper-awards/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>FOCS 2021 Best Paper Awards</title>
    <summary>On behalf of the FOCS 2021 PC, I am delighted to announce the Best Paper Awards. Best paper: Nutan Limaye, Srikanth Srinivasan and Sébastien Tavenas. Superpolynomial Lower Bounds Against Low-Depth Algebraic Circuits This paper makes a fundamental advance by proving super-polynomial lower bounds against algebraic circuits of arbitrary constant depth. Paper: https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/081/ Machtey Award for Best […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>On behalf of the FOCS 2021 PC, I am delighted to announce the Best Paper Awards.</p>



<p><strong>Best paper: </strong></p>



<p>Nutan Limaye, Srikanth Srinivasan and Sébastien Tavenas. <em>Superpolynomial Lower Bounds Against Low-Depth Algebraic Circuits</em></p>



<p/>



<p>This paper makes a fundamental advance by proving super-polynomial lower bounds against algebraic circuits of arbitrary constant depth. </p>



<p>Paper: <a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/081/" rel="nofollow">https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/081/</a></p>



<p/>



<p><strong>Machtey Award for Best Student Paper:</strong></p>



<p>Xiao Mao. <em>Breaking the Cubic Barrier for (Unweighted) Tree Edit Distance</em><a href="https://twitter.com/NisheethVishnoi"><br/></a><br/>This paper shows how, unlike the weighted case, the unweighted tree edit distance problem has a sub-cubic time algorithm. </p>



<p>Paper: <a href="https://t.co/G8yw1EZwuR?amp=1" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.02026</a></p>



<p/>



<p>Congratulations to the winners and see you all in Denver from Feb 7-10, 2022!<a href="https://twitter.com/NisheethVishnoi/status/1445099200274960390/photo/1"/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-04T18:58:20Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-04T18:58:20Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>nisheethvishnoi</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Algorithms, Nature, and Society</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:39:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/10/04/five-tenure-track-faculty-positions-in-cs-at-the-university-of-virginia-at-university-of-virginia-apply-by-december-1-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/10/04/five-tenure-track-faculty-positions-in-cs-at-the-university-of-virginia-at-university-of-virginia-apply-by-december-1-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Five Tenure-Track Faculty Positions in CS at the University of Virginia at University of Virginia  (apply by December 1, 2021)</title>
    <summary>Computer Science Department at the University of Virginia seeks 5 tenured or tenure-track faculty at all ranks, with Theory as one of our core targeted areas. Review of applications begins 12/1/2021. Website: https://uva.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/UVAJobs/job/Charlottesville-VA/Open-Rank-Faculty-Position-in-Computer-Science_R0028993 Email: selbaum@virginia.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Computer Science Department at the University of Virginia seeks 5 tenured or tenure-track faculty at all ranks, with Theory as one of our core targeted areas. Review of applications begins 12/1/2021.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://uva.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/UVAJobs/job/Charlottesville-VA/Open-Rank-Faculty-Position-in-Computer-Science_R0028993">https://uva.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/UVAJobs/job/Charlottesville-VA/Open-Rank-Faculty-Position-in-Computer-Science_R0028993</a><br/>
Email: selbaum@virginia.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-04T18:40:21Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-04T18:40:21Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:38:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2021-10-04-crusader-agreement-with-dollars-slash-leq-1-slash-3$-error-is-impossible-for-$n-slash-leq-3f$-if-the-adversary-can-simulate/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2021-10-04-crusader-agreement-with-dollars-slash-leq-1-slash-3$-error-is-impossible-for-$n-slash-leq-3f$-if-the-adversary-can-simulate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Crusader Agreement with $\leq 1/3$ Error is Impossible for $n\leq 3f$ if the Adversary can Simulate</title>
    <summary>The classic FLM lower bound says that in Synchrony, Byzantine Agreement is impossible when $n \leq 3f$. We discussed this important bound in a previous post. In this post we strengthen the FLM lower bound in two important ways: Maybe randomization allows circumventing the FLM lower bound? No! Even allowing...</summary>
    <updated>2021-10-04T14:46:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-04T14:46:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T23:14:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-989853369577969981</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/989853369577969981/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/10/how-have-computers-changed-society.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/989853369577969981" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/989853369577969981" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/10/how-have-computers-changed-society.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>How have computers changed society? Harry Lewis (with co-authors) have a book out on that.</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> (Disclosure - Harry Lewis was my PhD advisor.)</p><p><br/></p><p>It seems like just a few weeks ago I I blogged about a book of Harry Lewis's that was recently available (see <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/08/what-are-most-important-46-papers-in.html">here</a>).  And now I am blogging about another one. Writing two books in two years seems hard! I can only think of one other computer scientist who has done that recently (see <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mathematical-Muffin-Morsels-Problem-Mathematics-ebook/dp/B08BJ4G2Z1/ref=sr_1_2?dchild=1&amp;keywords=gasarch&amp;qid=1626492618&amp;sr=8-2">here</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Problems-Point-Exploring-Computer-Science/dp/9813279729/ref=sr_1_2?dchild=1&amp;keywords=gasarch+point&amp;qid=1626492655&amp;sr=8-2">here</a>).</p><p><br/></p><p>In 2008 Abelson, Ledeen, and Lewis wrote </p><p><i>Blown to Bits: Your Life, Liberty, and Happiness after the Digital Explosion</i></p><p>which I reviewed in SIGACT news, see <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/users/gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/bitsbook.pdf">here</a></p><p><br/></p><p>Both computers and society have changed since 2008. Hence an update was needed. </p><p>In 2021 Adelson, Ledeen, Lewis, and Seltzer wrote a second edition.</p><p><br/></p><p>Should you buy the new version if you bought the old version? </p><p>1) Not my problem- I got them both for free since I reviewed them. </p><p>2) Not your problem- The second edition is available free-on-line <a href="https://www.bitsbook.com/thebook/">here</a>. Is that a link to some dark corner of the dark web? No, its the formal webpage about the book. So the book is available free-on-line legally, if you care (and even if you don't care). </p><p>3) If you like paper, the book is on amazon. (If you don't like paper, the book is still on amazon). </p><p><br/></p><p>I reviewed it in SIGACT news. A non-paywalled link: <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/b2bits2.pdf">here</a> (is that link legal? I have no idea.) </p><p>In this post I'll just mention two things that changed since the last book</p><p>1) Shared Music and pirating were an issue back in 2008.  It does not seem to be anymore since there is now a variety of services that seem to make pirating not worth it: itunes, streaming services, and some bands give it away for free and ask you to pay what its worth. Movies are still struggling with this issue. </p><p>2) AI systems that reinforce existing bias is a new problem.</p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-04T04:19:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-04T04:19:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T14:58:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/10/02/generating-fibbinary-numbers</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/10/02/generating-fibbinary-numbers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Generating fibbinary numbers, three ways</title>
    <summary>I just added to Wikipedia two articles on the Jordan–Pólya numbers and fibbinary numbers, two integer sequences used in my recent paper on Egyptian fractions. Jordan–Pólya numbers are the products of factorials, while the fibbinary numbers are the ones with binary representations having no two consecutive 1’s. The OEIS page on the fibbinary numbers, A003714, lists many ways of generating this sequence algorithmically, of which most are boring or slow (generate all binary numbers and test which ones belong to the sequence; you can test if a variable x is fibbinary by checking that x&amp;(x&gt;&gt;1) is zero). I thought it might be interesting to highlight two of those methods that are a little more clever and generate these numbers in small numbers of operations.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I just added to Wikipedia two articles on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jordan%E2%80%93P%C3%B3lya_number">Jordan–Pólya numbers</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fibbinary_number">fibbinary numbers</a>, two integer sequences used in <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/09/24/which-integer-sequences.html">my recent paper on Egyptian fractions</a>. Jordan–Pólya numbers are the products of factorials, while the fibbinary numbers are the ones with binary representations having no two consecutive 1’s. The OEIS page on the fibbinary numbers, <a href="https://oeis.org/A003714">A003714</a>, lists many ways of generating this sequence algorithmically, of which most are boring or slow (generate all binary numbers and test which ones belong to the sequence; you can test if a variable <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> is fibbinary by checking that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x&amp;(x&gt;&gt;1)</code> is zero). I thought it might be interesting to highlight two of those methods that are a little more clever and generate these numbers in small numbers of operations.</p>

<p>Some functional languages, and in part Python even though it’s mostly not functional, have a notion of a stream, a potentially infinite sequence of values generated by a coroutine. In Python, you can program these using <a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0255/">simple generators</a> and the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">yield</code> keyword. I wrote here long ago about <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2011/10/02/generating-permutations-with.html">methods for using generators recursively</a>: a generator can call itself, manipulate the resulting sequence of values, and pass them on to its output. It’s actually a very old idea, used for instance to generate <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regular_number">regular numbers</a> by Dijkstra <a href="http://web.cecs.pdx.edu/~black/AdvancedProgramming/Lectures/Smalltalk%20II/Dijkstra%20on%20Hamming%27s%20Problem.pdf">in his 1976 book <em>A Discipline of Programming</em></a>. Reinhard Zumkeller used the same idea to generate the fibbinary numbers in Haskell, based on the observation that the sequence of positive fibbinary numbers can be generated, starting from the number 1, by two operations, doubling smaller values or replacing a smaller value \(x\) with \(4x+1\). Here is is, translated into Python:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python"><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">heapq</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">merge</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">affine</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">stream</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">b</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">stream</span><span class="p">:</span>
        <span class="k">yield</span> <span class="n">x</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">b</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">fibbinary</span><span class="p">():</span>
    <span class="k">yield</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">merge</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">affine</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fibbinary</span><span class="p">(),</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">),</span><span class="n">affine</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fibbinary</span><span class="p">(),</span><span class="mi">4</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)):</span>
        <span class="k">yield</span> <span class="n">x</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>It’s elegant, but has a couple of minor flaws. First, it omits the number \(0\), and while it can be modified to include \(0\), the modifications make the code messier. But second, it takes more than a constant amount of time per element to generate each sequence element. A fibbinary number \(x\) has to be generated from a sequence of smaller elements by repeated doubling and quadrupling, and that takes \(\log x\) steps per element. Even if we assume those steps to take constant time each, generating the first \(n\) elements in this way takes time \(\Theta(n\log n)\). It’s better than the \(\Theta(n^{\log_\varphi 2})\approx n^{1.44}\) that you would get from generate-and-test, but still not as good as we might hope for. One way to fix this would be to memoize the generator, so that the recursive calls look at a stored copy of the sequence generated by the outer call rather than generating the same sequence redundantly, but this again makes the code messier and also takes more storage than necessary.</p>

<p>Instead, Jörg Arndt observed that you can generate each fibbinary number directly from the previous one by a process closely resembling binary addition. Adding one to a binary number sets the first available bit from zero to one, and zeros out all the smaller bits; here, a bit is available if it is already zero. Finding the next fibbinary number does the same thing, but with a different definition of availability: a bit is available if both it and the next larger bit are zero. We can find the available bit using binary addition on a modified word that fills in bits whose neighbor is nonzero. Using this idea, we can generate the fibbinary numbers in a constant number of bitwise binary word-level operations per number. Here it is again in Python, translated from Arndt’s C++ and simplified based on <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@efroach76/107037399683569338">a comment by efroach76</a>:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">fibbinary</span><span class="p">():</span>
    <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
    <span class="k">while</span> <span class="bp">True</span><span class="p">:</span>
        <span class="k">yield</span> <span class="n">x</span>
        <span class="n">y</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">~</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
        <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">y</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span> <span class="n">y</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>It’s even possible to use the same idea to generate the fibbinary numbers in a constant amortized number of bit-level operations per number, although this ends up being a little less efficient in practice because high-level languages end up translating all these bit operations into word operations anyway.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">fibbinary</span><span class="p">():</span>
    <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span>
    <span class="k">while</span> <span class="bp">True</span><span class="p">:</span>
        <span class="k">yield</span> <span class="n">x</span>
        <span class="n">y</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
        <span class="k">while</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">y</span> <span class="o">|</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">y</span><span class="o">&lt;&lt;</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="o">!=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">:</span>
            <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">&amp;=~</span> <span class="n">y</span>
            <span class="n">y</span> <span class="o">&lt;&lt;=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
        <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">|=</span> <span class="n">y</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>The inner loop ends immediately at fibbinary numbers whose successor is odd (at positions given by the ones of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fibonacci_word">Fibonacci word</a>), whose fraction of the total is \(1-1/\varphi\approx 0.382\), where \(\varphi\) is the golden ratio. It ends in two steps for the remaining values when their next bit is odd, in the same proportion, and so on. So the average number of steps for the inner loop adds in a geometric series to \(O(1)\).</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107034017632258123">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-02T13:53:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-02T13:53:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2021-10-03T20:00:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/10/02/postdoc-at-irif-paris-france-apply-by-november-1-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/10/02/postdoc-at-irif-paris-france-apply-by-november-1-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at IRIF, Paris, France (apply by November 1, 2021)</title>
    <summary>IRIF, Paris, France, is seeking excellent candidates for postdoctoral positions in all areas of the Foundations of Computer Science. IRIF is a joint laboratory of the CNRS (French National Center for Scientific Research) and Université de Paris; see https://www.irif.fr/en/informations/presentation . Knowledge of French is not required; applications can be sent either in French or in […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>IRIF, Paris, France, is seeking excellent candidates for postdoctoral positions in all areas of the Foundations of Computer Science.</p>
<p>IRIF is a joint laboratory of the CNRS (French National Center for Scientific Research) and Université de Paris; see <a href="https://www.irif.fr/en/informations/presentation">https://www.irif.fr/en/informations/presentation</a> .</p>
<p>Knowledge of French is not required; applications can be sent either in French or in English.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.irif.fr/postes/postdoc">https://www.irif.fr/postes/postdoc</a><br/>
Email: postdoc-advice@irif.fr</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-02T07:50:27Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-02T07:50:27Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:38:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/142</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/142" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-142 |  Mixing of 3-term progressions in Quasirandom Groups  | 

	Amey Bhangale, 

	Prahladh Harsha, 

	Sourya Roy</title>
    <summary>In this note, we show the mixing of three-term progressions $(x, xg, xg^2)$ in every finite quasirandom group, fully answering a question of Gowers. More precisely, we show that for any $D$-quasirandom group $G$ and any three sets $A_1, A_2, A_3 \subset G$, we have
\[ \left|\Pr_{x,y\sim G}\left[ x \in A_1, xy \in A_2, xy^2 \in A_3\right] - \prod_{i=1}^3 \Pr_{x\sim G}\left[x \in A_i\right] \right| \leq \left(\frac{2}{\sqrt{D}}\right)^{\frac14}.\] 
Prior to this, Tao answered this question when the underlying quasirandom group is $\mathrm{SL}_{d}(\mathbb{F}_q)$. Subsequently, Peluse extended the result to all nonabelian finite simple groups. In this work, we show that a slight modification of Peluse's argument is sufficient to fully resolve Gower's quasirandom conjecture for 3-term progressions. Surprisingly, unlike the proofs of Tao and Peluse, our proof is elementary and only uses basic facts from nonabelian Fourier analysis.</summary>
    <updated>2021-10-01T16:38:04Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-01T16:38:04Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/?p=595</id>
    <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2021/09/theory-at-the-institute-and-beyond-september-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Theory at the Institute and Beyond, September 2021</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">by Prasad Raghavendra (Simons Institute) Being in one of the talks in the Simons Institute auditorium, witnessing live and lively interaction with the speaker, feels like the closest thing to normal since the start of the pandemic. There is a sense … <a href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2021/09/theory-at-the-institute-and-beyond-september-2021/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>by <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/people/prasad-raghavendra">Prasad Raghavendra</a> (Simons Institute)</p>



<p><img alt="" src="https://simons.berkeley.edu/sites/default/files/news/_prasad_and_algebraic_circuit_complexity_v4.png" style="margin: 5px; float: right; width: 328px; height: 219px;"/>Being in one of the talks in the Simons Institute auditorium, witnessing live and lively interaction with the speaker, feels like the closest thing to normal since the start of the pandemic. There is a sense of tangible joy among the participants just to be sharing the same physical space, let alone the fantastic environs of the Institute. The renewed energy is all there to witness in the programs this semester on <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/programs/si2021"><u>Computational Complexity of Statistical Inference</u></a> (CCSI) and <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/programs/gmos2021"><u>Geometric Methods in Optimization and Sampling</u></a> (GMOS), both of which are now in full swing. Although masking is maintained, it doesn’t seem to change the quintessential Simons program experience even a little bit. I am referring, of course, to the constant feeling of missing out on all the incredibly interesting activities going on, much of which one is unable to fit into their schedule.</p>



<p>At least some of the palpable energy can be attributed to over 40 postdocs and research fellows who have arrived at the Institute this semester, many of whom will stay on for a year or two. This extraordinary group of young researchers covers the whole gamut of topics, ranging from cryptography, quantum computing, and fairness to machine learning, data structures, algorithms, and complexity theory. Each of these postdocs and fellows gave a 10-minute presentation at the “Meet the Fellows’’ welcome event that the Institute held on September 8 and 9. Check out their <a href="https://simons.berkeley.edu/events/meet-fellows-welcome-event-wednesday-schedule"><u>talks</u></a> for glimpses of the cutting edge in all these subfields of theory.</p>



<p><strong>An advance in algebraic circuit complexity</strong><br/>
	This time around, there is some good news from the front lines on circuit complexity, one of the most challenging arenas within theoretical computer science.</p>



<p>An algebraic circuit consists of gates, each of which carries out either addition or multiplication over some field, say real numbers. The depth of the circuit is the length of the longest path from the output to one of its inputs. Naturally, an algebraic circuit computes a polynomial over its inputs.</p>



<p>In the world of Boolean circuits with AND/OR/NOT gates, lower bounds against constant depth circuits, aka AC0 circuit lower bounds, have been known since the 1980s and are one of the most influential results in complexity theory. For general algebraic circuits over a large field (say reals), even superpolynomial lower bounds for depth three circuits had remained elusive. In a <a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/081/">remarkable paper</a>, Nutan Limaye, Srikanth Srinivasan, and Sébastien Tavenas have obtained the first superpolynomial lower bounds against general algebraic circuits of all constant depths over fields of characteristic zero (say reals). Furthermore, the lower-bound result is shown for a simple polynomial known as “iterated matrix multiplication” whose input consists of \(d\) matrices \(X_1,\ldots,X_d\) of dimension \(n \times n\), and the goal is to compute a fixed entry of their product \(X_1 \cdot X_2 \cdots X_d\). The same work also obtains a depth hierarchy theorem for algebraic circuits showing that for every depth <em>D</em>, there is an explicit polynomial that can be computed by a depth <em>D</em> circuit of size <em>s</em>, but requires circuits of size superpolynomial in <em>s</em> if the depth is <em>D</em>-1.</p>



<p><strong>Remarkable work of Matthew Brennan</strong><br/> The theory community suffered a terrible loss this year with the tragic and untimely passing of one of our rising stars, Matthew Brennan. While still a graduate student at MIT, Matthew almost single-handedly pushed forward an ambitious research program at the intersection of computational complexity and statistics. Here we will try to give a glimpse of Matthew’s extensive body of research.</p>



<span id="more-595"/>



<p/>



<p>To set the context, traditionally the field of computational complexity has been concerned with characterizing how much memory or computational power is needed, while statistics sheds light on how much data are needed. The interplay between computational and statistical resources and their underlying trade-offs is only recently coming into focus.</p>



<p>Many statistical estimation tasks exhibit information-computation gaps wherein the accuracy obtained by efficient algorithms is strictly worse than the estimate that one could in principle extract from the data if there were no computational limitations. In other problems, there is an apparent trade-off between the number of samples needed for an estimation task and the computational power of the estimation algorithm.</p>



<p>Identifying and rigorously establishing the presence of these information-computation trade-offs is a fundamental challenge that has drawn much interest in theoretical computer science and statistics. To rigorously establish an information-computation gap, one would need to prove lower bounds against efficient algorithms for statistical estimation problems.</p>



<p>Here on, there are two routes that one could take. First, one can prove limitations for specific classes of algorithms like MCMC, spectral methods, semidefinite programming, statistical queries, and so on. This approach has been highly successful, yielding precise lower bounds in many models and numerous relations discovered between the models.</p>



<p>Alternatively, one can take the grander route: assume the intractability of a well-studied computational problem and use <em>reductions</em> to establish hardness of the statistical estimation problem at hand. In a seminal work, Berthet and Rigollet showed a reduction from the planted clique problem to the sparse principal component analysis (sparse PCA), thereby establishing the presence of an information-computation gap for a version of sparse PCA.</p>



<p>In its most canonical setup, the input to the sparse PCA problem consists of samples from a \(d\)-dimensional Gaussian with covariance \(\Sigma = I_d + \theta vv^T\), where \(v\) is a \(k\)-sparse unit vector and \(\theta\) denotes the signal strength. A simple hypothesis testing variant of the problem asks to distinguish \(n\) samples drawn from this spiked covariance matrix and \(n\) samples drawn from the standard Gaussian distribution.</p>



<p>Notice that statistical estimation problems like sparse PCA are most interesting when their inputs are drawn from some natural distribution like the Gaussian distribution. Therefore, a reduction from a hard problem <em>A</em> to a statistical estimation problem <em>B</em> will not only have to map instances of <em>A</em> to instances of <em>B</em>, but also have to produce the right distribution over instances of <em>B</em>. For example, ideally a reduction from planted clique to sparse PCA must map instances of planted clique (random graphs with cliques) to random vectors drawn from an appropriate Gaussian measure. How could a reduction ever do this, one might ask.</p>



<p>In fact, this is why one might decide not to take the grand route of using reductions to understand the complexity of statistical problems. While reductions have been exceptionally successful in establishing tight hardness results for <em>NP</em>-complete optimization problems, building a similar web of reductions for statistical problems like sparse PCA seemed hopeless to me. Not for Matthew, who courageously took this challenge head-on and succeeded!</p>



<p>Despite efforts following the seminal work of Berthet and Rigollet, showing a tight hardness result for sparse PCA in its most canonical Gaussian setup seemed out of reach. In a series of works, Matthew and coauthors developed a set of simple reduction tools that when put together led to a tight characterization of the complexity of the sparse PCA problem in its most canonical setup, over the entire range of parameters!</p>



<p>More recently, Matthew and his advisor, Guy Bresler, proposed a generalized planted clique conjecture referred to as “secret leakage planted clique” that can serve as a starting point for a web of reductions encompassing a variety of problems such as tensor PCA, robust sparse mean estimation, and semirandom community recovery. Not only have these works developed a set of useful reduction techniques for statistical problems, but most importantly, they have demonstrated that reductions can indeed be harnessed toward tight hardness results for statistical problems. Matthew was a recipient of the best student paper award at the Conference on Learning Theory (COLT) on two separate occasions for this line of work.</p>



<p>Matthew’s work is one of the central themes of this semester’s program on Computational Complexity of Statistical Inference. His work has laid the foundations of a theory of reductions for statistical problems, something for us to build on over the coming years. While his ideas are ever present this semester, his presence at the program is sorely missed.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-10-01T03:00:37Z</updated>
    <published>2021-10-01T03:00:37Z</published>
    <category term="General"/>
    <author>
      <name>1737780</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu</id>
      <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>What's New at the Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing.</subtitle>
      <title>Calvin Café: The Simons Institute Blog</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:38:57Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/09/30/phd-student-at-university-of-bergen-norway-apply-by-november-14-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/09/30/phd-student-at-university-of-bergen-norway-apply-by-november-14-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>PhD Student at University of Bergen (Norway) (apply by November 14, 2021)</title>
    <summary>3-year PhD student position in the field of Symbolic Algorithms (extension to 4 years if teaching). Salary: 491,200 NOK per year (approx 48,000 EUR per year) before taxes. Applicants should have a MSc. degree (or obtain a MSc. degree before 31/01/2022) and a strong background in some relevant subfield of TCS, such as algorithms, graph […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>3-year PhD student position in the field of Symbolic Algorithms (extension to 4 years if teaching). Salary: 491,200 NOK per year (approx 48,000 EUR per year) before taxes. Applicants should have a MSc. degree (or obtain a MSc. degree before 31/01/2022) and a strong background in some relevant subfield of TCS, such as algorithms, graph theory, combinatorics, automata theory, type theory, etc.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.jobbnorge.no/en/available-jobs/job/212570/phd-research-fellow-in-informatics-symbolic-algorithms">https://www.jobbnorge.no/en/available-jobs/job/212570/phd-research-fellow-in-informatics-symbolic-algorithms</a><br/>
Email: mateus.oliveira@uib.no</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-09-30T21:59:57Z</updated>
    <published>2021-09-30T21:59:57Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:38:03Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/09/30/postdoc-at-university-of-bergen-norway-apply-by-november-14-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/09/30/postdoc-at-university-of-bergen-norway-apply-by-november-14-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at University of Bergen (Norway) (apply by November 14, 2021)</title>
    <summary>3-year postdoc position in the field of Symbolic Algorithms. Salary: 535,500 NOK per year (approx. 52,500 EUR per year) before taxes. Applicants should have a Ph.D. degree (or obtain a Ph.D. degree before 31/01/2022) and a strong publication record in some relevant subfield of TCS, such as algorithms, graph theory, combinatorics, automata theory, type theory, […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>3-year postdoc position in the field of Symbolic Algorithms. Salary: 535,500 NOK per year (approx. 52,500 EUR per year) before taxes. Applicants should have a Ph.D. degree (or obtain a Ph.D. degree before 31/01/2022) and a strong publication record in some relevant subfield of TCS, such as algorithms, graph theory, combinatorics, automata theory, type theory, etc.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.jobbnorge.no/en/available-jobs/job/212553/postdoctoral-research-fellow-position-within-informatics-symbolic-algorithms">https://www.jobbnorge.no/en/available-jobs/job/212553/postdoctoral-research-fellow-position-within-informatics-symbolic-algorithms</a><br/>
Email: mateus.oliveira@uib.no</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-09-30T21:44:57Z</updated>
    <published>2021-09-30T21:44:57Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2021-10-06T04:38:02Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8844632344201187395</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/8844632344201187395/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/09/being-chair.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8844632344201187395" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8844632344201187395" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/09/being-chair.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Being the Chair</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>If you have Netflix and interested in the academic world, I recommend <a href="https://www.netflix.com/title/81206259">The Chair</a>, a six-episode dramatic series starring Sandra Oh as a new English department chair at a "lower tier ivy league university". The series takes many artistic liberties and compresses much in a short time period but gets much about academics right such as the tension between faculty and the administration with the chair caught in the middle, the need to create majors that attract students, faculty past their prime teaching the same courses in the same way for decades, faculty who get themselves in a hole and keep digging, alumni donors controlling academic decisions, pressure to build a diverse faculty, faculty feeling under appreciated and getting outside offers, and a wonderful exposition of how the field has changed over the past thirty years given to someone who had dropped out before finishing their PhD to take on a different career.</p><p>When I served as department chair at Georgia Tech, I dealt with most if not all of these issues above, though not at the same time. I had some challenges that today's English department doesn't face: how to handle enrollments that more than doubled while barely able to hire more faculty than were departing, not that I would trade in a second for the existential crisis that English departments are going through. </p><p>When I left Georgia Tech after seven years, I had outlasted every other current chair in the Colleges of Computing, Science and Engineering. Not sure what this says about me or about Georgia Tech.</p><p>Being chair is the most challenging job in academia. The faculty technically report to you but you aren't their boss in any traditional sense--they came to academia because of the freedom to work on what they want and they won't give it up. It's virtually impossible to fire anyone with tenure. The joke goes that a chair needs two umbrellas, one to block stuff coming from the administration going to the faculty and the other to block the stuff from the faculty from going to the administration. Since I left it has gotten much uglier in the University System of Georgia which has no mask or vaccine mandates and glad I'm not the chair to deal with that.</p><p>This all sounds like I'm discouraging of becoming a department chair and it certainly isn't a job for anyone but it can be a very rewarding job. You can help shape the future of the department by the faculty you hire and the vision you set and create an environment that helps your faculty and students succeed. </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-09-30T14:29:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-09-30T14:29:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T14:58:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/09/30/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/09/30/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>Textbook company Pearson sues Chegg for copyright infringement, for selling solutions to textbook homework problems (\(\mathbb{M}\)). On the one hand, for-profit cheater-enablers like Chegg are a cancer on higher education. On the other, the solution to a problem is generally a concept, not a text, and should not be something that can be locked up under copyright. So I don’t know who to root for?</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2021/09/15/pearson-sues-former-partner-chegg-copyright-infringement">Textbook company Pearson sues Chegg for copyright infringement, for selling solutions to textbook homework problems</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106945803113477254">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). On the one hand, for-profit cheater-enablers like Chegg are a cancer on higher education. On the other, the solution to a problem is generally a concept, not a text, and should not be something that can be locked up under copyright. So I don’t know who to root for?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2021/09/13/future-academic-conference"><em>Inside Higher Ed</em> on the future of academic conferences</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106951348197294218">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). A significant fraction of academics surveyed said that they still felt unsafe going to physical conferences, and with the carbon footprint and reduced expenses of virtual but greater interactivity of physical meetings, some mix of both seems likely going forward. However, trying to mix both in one conference (especially for conferences with many parallel small talks or panels) seems difficult and expensive.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.kennethmoreland.com/color-advice/">Color map advice for scientific visualization</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106955479284414863">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28579720">via</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Three sets of talk slides from recent talks (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106962519567502209">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p><a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pubs/Epp-WG-21-slides.pdf">The graphs of stably matchable pairs, <em>WG 2021</em></a></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pubs/Epp-WADS-21-slides.pdf">A stronger lower bound on parametric minimum spanning trees, <em>WADS 2021</em></a></p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p><a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pubs/Epp-GD-21-slides.pdf">Limitations on realistic hyperbolic graph drawing, <em>GD 2021</em></a></p>
      </li>
    </ul>

    <p>Unfortunately I don’t have links to recordings of the talks.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I thought for sure I had posted before about <a href="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/2017/09/bold-new-geometric-cake-designs-by-dinara-kasko/">Dinara Kasko’s 3d-printed geometric food designs</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106968564827718278">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://culturainquieta.com/es/arte/diseno/item/12643-la-reposteria-matematica-de-la-arquitecta-dinara-kasko.html">see also</a>, <a href="https://dinarakasko.com/">home page</a>), but grep tells me that if I ever did, it wasn’t with her name.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The <a href="https://zbmath.org/">zbMATH</a> mathematics review database was broken for a day (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106971763813682368">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), unable to show the old scans of printed reviews, but fortunately it got better.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-p7C5FrgAzU">Twelve threads</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/106982013693223792">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Vi Hart’s latest video mixes up discussions of the nature of social media, the philosophy of mathematical creativity, an exploration of symmetry, and an investigation of the spot patterns of 8-sided dice (which turn out not to all be the same) and how to visualize them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@mathcination/106905943747555880">Visualization of Poncelet’s porism</a>, calculated with difficulty by mathcination from Cayley’s criteria. It would have been easier to calculate a regular hendecagram and then perturb it by a projective transformation, but that wasn’t the point.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I recently saw a link to <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/MathML3/chapter1.html">Chapter 1 of the MathML 3.0 spec</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107002528612296323">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), using as an example the quadratic formula in both layout markup and content markup. Its totally unwieldy non-human-readable expansion obscures the fact that the MathML authors didn’t even get the math right: their content markup silently replaces the plus-minus sign, by which the correct formula represents both solutions, with an addition operation, giving only one of the two. Time to re-link my old <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2015/08/04/mathml-considered-harmful.html">anti-MathML rant</a>?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/2021/09/hacer-origami-sculptures/">Giant origami animals in Midtown Manhattan</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107007549470942566">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). But now I want to know if they were really each fabricated from a single uncut square sheet of steel. And if so, how did they get the corners so crisp?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.getty.edu/publications/virtuallibrary/pdf/9780892363353.pdf"><em>The Topkapı Scroll – Geometry and Ornament in Islamic Architecture</em>, by Harvard professor Gülru Necipoğlu</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107017227413204703">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> One of many beautiful art books free for download from the <a href="https://www.getty.edu/publications/virtuallibrary/">Getty Virtual Library</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.formulas.it/formulog/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/sierpinski-aplimat.pdf">Sierpiński triangles in stone, on medieval floors in Rome</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107021612310283993">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), Elisa Conversano and Laura Tedeschini Lalli. See also Kim Williams, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1007%2Fbf03024339">The pavements of the Cosmati</a>”. The <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Sierpi%C5%84ski_triangles_in_Cosmatesque_pavements">collection of images of these on Wikimedia commons</a> is a little sad — Conversano and Tedeschini Lalli, and Williams, have a lot more.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Every invertible function computable both ways in polynomial time has polynomial-size reversible logic circuits, using extra “dummy” values that are zero on both input and output (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107024956502298623">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>): See Jacopini, Mentrasti, &amp; Sontacchi, “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/0403020">Reversible turing machines and polynomial time reversibly computable functions</a>”, SIAM J. Disc. Math. 1990.</p>

    <p><em>Theorem:</em> No circuit of reversible gates of arity less than \(n\), without dummy values, can compute \(n\)-bit 2’s-complement negation.</p>

    <p><em>Proof:</em> Each gate performs an even permutation on the \(2^n\) inputs, but negation is an odd permutation. \(\Box\)</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-09-30T11:57:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-09-30T11:57:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2021-10-03T20:00:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2021-09-30-distributed-consensus-made-simple-for-real-this-time/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2021-09-30-distributed-consensus-made-simple-for-real-this-time/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Distributed consensus made simple (for real this time!)</title>
    <summary>Multi-Paxos is the de facto solution for deciding a log of commands to execute on a replicated state machine, yet it’s famously difficult to understand, motivating the switch to ‘simpler’ consensus protocols such as Raft. The conventional wisdom is that the best way to use Paxos (aka Synod, or single-shot...</summary>
    <updated>2021-09-30T07:39:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-09-30T07:39:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2021-10-05T23:14:55Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
