<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-09-01T22:21:47Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4407</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/09/01/time-flies-when-the-world-is-falling-apart/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Time Flies When the World is Falling Apart</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been exactly one year since I moved to Italy. Coming here a year ago, I expected that I would face some challenges and that there would be major life changes. Obviously, I did not know the half of … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/09/01/time-flies-when-the-world-is-falling-apart/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>It has been exactly one year since I moved to Italy.</p>
<p>Coming here a year ago, I expected that I would face some challenges and that there would be major life changes. Obviously, I did not know the half of it.</p>
<p><span id="more-4407"/></p>
<p>In March and April, being in the hottest hot spot of a global pandemic was not ideal. Something rather unexpected, however, has happened. Italy is not known for very effective governance and Italians are not known as a rule-following people. Yet the government implemented a strict lockdown, and held it long enough that the “reopening” took place with a safely low circulation of the virus. People have been mostly following the rules after the reopening, and for most of the summer Italy has been doing quite well. (There has been a recent surge of new cases  in the last few weeks, so it may be too soon to declare victory, but the numbers of intensive care hospitalizations and of deaths are still low).</p>
<p>Meanwhile, there have been “second waves” in several other European countries and the situation in the United States, as the President memorably said, is what it is.</p>
<p>This picture by Noah Berger for AP has been circulating as the perfect description of what is going on in Northern California this summer</p>
<p><img alt="IMG_0077" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4409" src="https://lucatrevisan.files.wordpress.com/2020/09/img_0077.jpeg?w=584"/></p>
<p>This New York Times headline also does a good job of packing at least five things that are wrong in California right now (the spread of covid-19, the overcrowding of prisons because of excessive sentencing, the budget cuts affecting firefighting efforts, the exploitation of prisoners for underpaid work, and the spread of wildfires) in a single sentence:</p>
<p><img alt="california-inmates" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4410" src="https://lucatrevisan.files.wordpress.com/2020/09/california-inmates.png?w=584"/></p>
<p>At the cost of resorting to banalities and cliches, Italians often do badly when confronted with good opportunities and lucky breaks, that are often wasted, but we do unexpectedly well in times of crisis. This can even be seen in the national football team, that is known for epic come-from-behind victories and for missing penalty kicks. The American spirit is to be ambitious and optimistic, and to pursue high-risk high-reward opportunities when they present themselves. The flip side is that adversity is often met in America with either despair or anger, typically counterproductively. All things considered, I am happy that I am getting to spend 2020 in Italy. Earlier this summer, the president and the rector of Bocconi announced the new long-term strategic plan for the university, which involves creating a new computer science department. If/when such plans come to fruition, there will be several faculty positions in computer science, at internationally competitive salaries, with advantageous taxation for people moving to Italy from other countries, and with English as the language of instructions, so maybe you too will consider such a move.</p>
<p>Bocconi is preparing to restart in-person teaching in a couple of weeks. The plan is to record and post lectures, to allow students to attend lectures remotely if they prefer, and to use classrooms at most at half capacity. If a class has to be scheduled in a classroom whose capacity is less than twice the class enrollment, students will be split in two groups. Each group will (be allowed to) physically attend in alternating weeks, and will (be required to) attend online at other times.</p>
<p>The space between campus buildings has been marked with well-spaced walking paths, and there are even pedestrian roundabouts.</p>
<p><img alt="IMG_0122" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-4412" src="https://lucatrevisan.files.wordpress.com/2020/09/img_0122.jpeg?w=584"/></p>
<p>Are we heading for a second-wave disaster? Will students really follow the rules? On Sunday we were in Rome and we took a bus to the city center. Every other seat in the bus was marked with a “do not sit” sign to create distancing between sitting people. All marked seats were empty even as the bus was filling up and several people were standing. Then a group of German tourists got in, and they sat in all the forbidden seats. This is the upside-down world of 2020, all bets are off.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-09-01T17:36:01Z</updated>
    <published>2020-09-01T17:36:01Z</published>
    <category term="Bocconi"/>
    <category term="Italy"/>
    <category term="philosophy"/>
    <category term="politics"/>
    <category term="things that are terrible"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:20:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-4647242799583898034</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/4647242799583898034/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/09/a-well-known-theorem-that-has-not-been.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/4647242799583898034" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/4647242799583898034" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/09/a-well-known-theorem-that-has-not-been.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A well known theorem that has not been written down- so I wrote it down- CLIQ is #P-complete</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>(The two proofs that CLIQ is #P-complete that I discuss in this blog are written up by Lance and myself and are <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/users/gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/sharpclique.pdf">here</a>. I think both are well known but I have not been able to find a writeup,so Lance and I did one.)</p><p><br/></p><p> I have been looking at #P (see my last blog on it it, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/08/sharp-p-and-issue-of-natural-problems.html">here</a>, for a refresher on this topic) since I will be teaching this topic in Spring 2021.  Recall</p><p>#SAT(\phi) = the number of satisfying assignments for phi</p><p>#CLIQ((G,k))= the number of cliques of size \ge k of G</p><p>#SAT is #P-complete by a cursory look at the proof of the Cook-Levin theorem.</p><p>A function is #P-complete if everything else in #P is Turing-Poly red to it. To show for some set A </p><p>in NP, #A is #P-complete one usually uses pars reductions. </p><p>I wanted a proof that #CLIQ is #P-complete, so I wanted a parsimonious reduction from SAT to CLIQ (Thats a reduction f: SAT--&gt; CLIQ such that the number of satisfying assignments of phi equals the number of cliques of size \ge k of G.)</p><p>I was sure there is such a reduction and that it was well known and would be on the web someplace. So I tried to find it.</p><p>ONE:</p><p>I tracked some references to a paper by Janos Simon (<a href="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007%2F3-540-08342-1_37.pdf">see here</a>)  where he claims that the reduction of SAT to CLIQ  by Karp <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/{http://cgi.di.uoa.gr/~sgk/teaching/grad/handouts/karp.pdf">(see here)</a> was pars.  I had already considered that and decided that Karps reduction was NOT pars.  I looked at both Simon's paper and Karp's paper to make sure I wasn't missing something (e.g., I misunderstood what Simon Says or what Karp ... darn, I can't think of anything as good as `Simon Says'). It seemed to me that Simon was incorrect. If I am wrong let me know.</p><p>TWO</p><p>Someone told me that it was in Valiant's  paper (see <a href="https://epubs.siam.org/doi/10.1137/0208032">here</a>). Nope. Valiant's paper shows that counting the number of maximal cliques is #P-complete. Same Deal Here- if I am wrong let me know. One can modify Valiant's argument to get CLIQ #P-complete, and I do so in the write up. The proof is a string of reductions and starts with PERM is #P-complete. This does prove that CLIQ is  #P-complete, but is rather complicated. Also, the reduction is not pars.</p><p>THREE <br/>Lance told me an easy pars reduction that is similar to Karp's non-pars reduction, but it really is NOT Karp's reduction. Its in my write up. I think it is well known since I recall hearing it about 10 years ago. From Lance. Hmmm, maybe its just well known to Lance.</p><p><br/></p><p>But here is my question: I am surprised I didn't find it on the web. If someone can point to a place on the web where it is, please let me know. In any case, its on the web NOW (my write up) so hopefully in the future someone else looking for it can find it.</p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-09-01T15:29:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-09-01T15:29:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T19:51:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/09/01/quics-hartree-postdoctoral-fellowships-at-joint-center-for-quantum-information-and-computer-science-apply-by-december-1-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/09/01/quics-hartree-postdoctoral-fellowships-at-joint-center-for-quantum-information-and-computer-science-apply-by-december-1-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>QuICS Hartree Postdoctoral Fellowships at Joint Center for Quantum Information and Computer Science (apply by December 1, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Joint Center for Quantum Information and Computer Science (QuICS, http://quics.umd.edu) is seeking exceptional candidates for the QuICS Hartree Postdoctoral Fellowships in Quantum Information and Computer Science. Applications should be submitted through AcademicJobsOnline at https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/16778. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/16778 Email: quics-coordinator@umiacs.umd.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Joint Center for Quantum Information and Computer Science (QuICS, <a href="http://quics.umd.edu">http://quics.umd.edu</a>) is seeking exceptional candidates for the QuICS Hartree Postdoctoral Fellowships in Quantum Information and Computer Science.<br/>
Applications should be submitted through AcademicJobsOnline at <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/16778.">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/16778.</a></p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/16778">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/16778</a><br/>
Email: quics-coordinator@umiacs.umd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-09-01T14:39:18Z</updated>
    <published>2020-09-01T14:39:18Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-25562705.post-7958692547156288391</id>
    <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/feeds/7958692547156288391/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=25562705&amp;postID=7958692547156288391" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default/7958692547156288391" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default/7958692547156288391" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/2020/07/the-existence-of-no-regret-learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>No Regret Algorithms from the Min Max Theorem</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The existence of no-regret learning algorithms can be used to prove <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimax_theorem">Von-Neumann's min-max theorem</a>. This argument is originally due to <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~schapire/papers/FreundScYY.pdf">Freund and Schapire</a>, and I <a href="https://www.cis.upenn.edu/~aaroth/courses/slides/agt20/lect08.pdf">teach it to my undergraduates </a>in my algorithmic game theory class. The min-max theorem also can be used to prove the existence of no-regret learning algorithms. Here is a constructive version of the argument (Constructive in that in the resulting algorithm, you only need to solve polynomially sized zero-sum games, so you can do it via linear programming).<div><br/></div><div>Recall the setting. Play proceeds in rounds $t \in \{1,\ldots,T\}$. At each day $t$, the learner chooses one of $k$ actions $i_t \in \{1,\ldots,k\}$, and the adversary chooses a loss vector $\ell^t \in [0,1]^k$. The learner incurs loss $\ell^t_{i_t}$, corresponding to the action he chose. At the end of the interaction, the regret of the learner is defined to be the difference between the cumulative loss he incurred and the cumulative loss of the best fixed action (played consistently)  in hindsight:</div><div>$$\textrm{Regret}_T = \max_j \left(\sum_{t=1}^T \ell^t_{i_t} - \ell^t_j\right)$$ </div><div>A classical and remarkable result is that there exist algorithms that can guarantee that regret grows only sublinearly with time: $\textrm{Regret}_T = O(\sqrt{T})$. Lets prove this. </div><div><br/></div><div><br/></div><div>Define the non-negative portion of our cumulative regret with respect to action $j$ up until day $d$ as:</div><div>$$V_d^j = \left(\sum_{t=1}^d\left(\ell^t_{i_t} - \ell^t_j\right)\right)^+$$</div><div>and our additional regret at day $d+1$ with respect to action $j$ as:</div><div>$$r_{j}^{d+1} = \ell_{i_{d+1}}^{d+1} - \ell^{d+1}_j$$</div><div>Observe that if $V_{d}^j \geq 1$  then $V_{d+1}^j = V_d^j + r_j^{d+1}$. </div><div><br/></div><div><br/></div><div>Define a surrogate loss function as our squared cumulative regrets, summed over all actions: </div><div>$$L_d = \sum_{j=1}^k (V_d^j)^2$$</div><div>Observe that we can write the expected gain in our loss on day $d+1$, conditioned on the history thus far:</div><div>$$\mathbb{E}[L_{d+1} - L_d] \leq \sum_{j : V_d^j \geq 1} \mathbb{E}[(V_d^j+r_j^{d+1})^2 - (V_d^j)^2) ] + 3k$$</div><div>$$= \sum_{j : V_d^j \geq 1} \left(2V_d^j \mathbb{E}[r_{j}^{d+1}] + \mathbb{E}[(r_{j}^{d+1})^2]\right) + 3k $$</div><div>$$\leq \sum_{j=1}^k \left(2V_d^j \mathbb{E}[r_{j}^{d+1}]\right) + 4k$$</div><div>where the expectations are taken over the randomness of both the learner and the adversary in round $d+1$. </div><div><br/></div><div>Now consider a zero-sum game played between the learner and the adversary in which the learner is the minimization player, the adversary is the maximization player, and the utility function is $$u(i_{d+1}, \ell^{d+1}) = \sum_{j=1}^k \left(2V_d^j \mathbb{E}[r_{j}^{d+1}]\right)$$ The min-max theorem says that the learner can guarantee the same payoff for herself in the following two scenarios:</div><div><br/></div><div><ol style="text-align: left;"><li>The learner first has to commit to playing a distribution $p_{d+1}$ over actions $i$, and then the adversary gets to best respond by picking the worst possible loss vectors, or</li><li>The adversary has to first commit to a distribution over loss vectors $\ell$ and then the learner gets the benefit of picking the best action $i_{d+1}$ to respond with. </li></ol>Scenario 1) is the scenario our learner finds herself in, when playing against an adaptive adversary. But 2) is much easier to analyze. If the adversary first commits to a distribution over loss vectors $\ell^{d+1}$, the learner can always choose action $i_{d+1} = \arg\min_j \mathbb{E}[\ell^{d+1}_j]$, which guarantees that $\mathbb{E}[r_{j}^{d+1}] \leq 0$, which in turn guarantees that the value of the game $ \sum_{j=1}^k \left(2V_d^j \mathbb{E}[r_{j}^{d+1}]\right) \leq 0$.  Hence, the min-max theorem tells us that the learner always has a distribution over actions $p_{d+1}$ that guarantees that $\mathbb{E}[L_{d+1} - L_d] \leq 4k$, <i>even in the worst case over loss functions</i>. If the learner always plays according to this distribution, then by a telescoping sum, we have that:</div><div>$$\mathbb{E}[L_T] \leq 4kT$$.</div><div>We therefore have by Jensen's inequality that:</div><div>$$\mathbb{E}[\max_j (V^j_T)] \leq \sqrt{\mathbb{E}[\max_j (V^j_T)^2]}\leq \sqrt{\mathbb{E}[\sum_{j=1}^T (V_j^T)^2]} \leq 2\sqrt{kT}$$.</div></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-09-01T14:16:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-09-01T14:16:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Aaron</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/09952936358739421126</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-25562705</id>
      <category term="game theory"/>
      <category term="news"/>
      <author>
        <name>Aaron</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/09952936358739421126</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/25562705/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <title>Adventures in Computation</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T14:42:08Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/09/01/postdoc-at-tu-hamburg-apply-by-september-30-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/09/01/postdoc-at-tu-hamburg-apply-by-september-30-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at TU Hamburg (apply by September 30, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Institute for Algorithms and Complexity at TUHH: Hamburg University of Technology invites applications for a 5-year postdoc position (attached to DASHH: Data Science in Hamburg). The focus is on algorithms, applied to combinatorial optimization, operations research, and discrete mathematics in the natural sciences, particularly on big data obtained at Germany’s largest particle accelerator. Website: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Institute for Algorithms and Complexity at TUHH: Hamburg University of Technology invites applications for a 5-year postdoc position (attached to DASHH: Data Science in Hamburg). The focus is on algorithms, applied to combinatorial optimization, operations research, and discrete mathematics in the natural sciences, particularly on big data obtained at Germany’s largest particle accelerator.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.tuhh.de/algo/jobs.html">https://www.tuhh.de/algo/jobs.html</a><br/>
Email: matthias.mnich@tuhh.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-09-01T08:46:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-09-01T08:46:00Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13735</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13735" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Estimating Rank-One Spikes from Heavy-Tailed Noise via Self-Avoiding Walks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Jingqiu Ding, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hopkins:Samuel_B=.html">Samuel B. Hopkins</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Steurer:David.html">David Steurer</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.13735">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study symmetric spiked matrix models with respect to a general class of
noise distributions. Given a rank-1 deformation of a random noise matrix, whose
entries are independently distributed with zero mean and unit variance, the
goal is to estimate the rank-1 part. For the case of Gaussian noise, the top
eigenvector of the given matrix is a widely-studied estimator known to achieve
optimal statistical guarantees, e.g., in the sense of the celebrated BBP phase
transition. However, this estimator can fail completely for heavy-tailed noise.
In this work, we exhibit an estimator that works for heavy-tailed noise up to
the BBP threshold that is optimal even for Gaussian noise. We give a
non-asymptotic analysis of our estimator which relies only on the variance of
each entry remaining constant as the size of the matrix grows: higher moments
may grow arbitrarily fast or even fail to exist. Previously, it was only known
how to achieve these guarantees if higher-order moments of the noises are
bounded by a constant independent of the size of the matrix. Our estimator can
be evaluated in polynomial time by counting self-avoiding walks via a color
-coding technique. Moreover, we extend our estimator to spiked tensor models
and establish analogous results.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13729</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13729" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Online Search With a Hint</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Spyros Angelopoulos <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.13729">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The linear search problem, informally known as the cow path problem, is one
of the fundamental problems in search theory. In this problem, an immobile
target is hidden at some unknown position on an unbounded line, and a mobile
searcher, initially positioned at some specific point of the line called the
root, must traverse the line so as to locate the target. The objective is to
minimize the worst-case ratio of the distance traversed by the searcher to the
distance of the target from the root, which is known as the competitive ratio
of the search.
</p>
<p>In this work we study this problem in a setting in which the searcher has a
hint concerning the target. We consider three settings in regards to the nature
of the hint: i) the hint suggests the exact position of the target on the line;
ii) the hint suggests the direction of the optimal search (i.e., to the left or
the right of the root); and iii) the hint is a general k-bit string that
encodes some information concerning the target. Our objective is to study the
Pareto-efficiency of strategies in this model. Namely, we seek optimal, or
near-optimal tradeoffs between the searcher's performance if the hint is
correct (i.e., provided by a trusted source) and if the hint is incorrect
(i.e., provided by an adversary).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13697</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13697" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Topology and Neural Networks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hajij:Mustafa.html">Mustafa Hajij</a>, Kyle Istvan <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.13697">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We utilize classical facts from topology to show that the classification
problem in machine learning is always solvable under very mild conditions.
Furthermore, given a training dataset, we show how topological formalism can be
used to suggest the appropriate architectural choices for neural networks
designed to be trained as classifiers on the data. Finally, we show how the
architecture of a neural network cannot be chosen independently from the shape
of the underlying data. To demonstrate these results, we provide example
datasets and show how they are acted upon by neural nets, from this topological
perspective.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13648</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13648" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Edmonds' problem and the membership problem for orbit semigroups of quiver representations</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chindris:Calin.html">Calin Chindris</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kline:Daniel.html">Daniel Kline</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.13648">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A central problem in algebraic complexity, posed by J. Edmonds, asks to
decide if the span of a given $l$-tuple $\V=(\V_1, \ldots, \V_l)$ of $N \times
N$ complex matrices contains a non-singular matrix.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we provide a quiver invariant theoretic approach to this
problem. Viewing $\V$ as a representation of the $l$-Kronecker quiver $\K_l$,
Edmonds' problem can be rephrased as asking to decide if there exists a
semi-invariant on the representation space $(\CC^{N\times N})^l$ of weight
$(1,-1)$ that does not vanish at $\V$. In other words, Edmonds' problem is
asking to decide if the weight $(1,-1)$ belongs to the orbit semigroup of $\V$.
</p>
<p>Let $Q$ be an arbitrary acyclic quiver and $\V$ a representation of $Q$. We
study the membership problem for the orbit semi-group of $\V$ by focusing on
the so-called $\V$-saturated weights. We first show that for any given
$\V$-saturated weight $\sigma$, checking if $\sigma$ belongs to the orbit
semigroup of $\V$ can be done in deterministic polynomial time.
</p>
<p>Next, let $(Q, \R)$ be an acyclic bound quiver with bound quiver algebra
$A=KQ/\langle \R \rangle$ and assume that $\V$ satisfies the relations in $\R$.
We show that if $A/\Ann_A(\V)$ is a tame algebra then any weight $\sigma$ in
the weight semigroup of $\V$ is $\V$-saturated.
</p>
<p>Our results provide a systematic way of producing families of tuples of
matrices for which Edmonds' problem can be solved effectively.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13640</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13640" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Sorting by Prefix Block-Interchanges</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Labarre:Anthony.html">Anthony Labarre</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.13640">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We initiate the study of sorting permutations using prefix
block-interchanges, which exchange any prefix of a permutation with another
non-intersecting interval. The goal is to transform a given permutation into
the identity permutation using as few such operations as possible. We give a
2-approximation algorithm for this problem, show how to obtain improved lower
and upper bounds on the corresponding distance, and determine the largest
possible value for that distance.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13556</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13556" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Zoomless Maps: External Labeling Methods for the Interactive Exploration of Dense Point Sets at a Fixed Map Scale</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Sven Gedicke, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bonerath:Annika.html">Annika Bonerath</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Niedermann:Benjamin.html">Benjamin Niedermann</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Haunert:Jan=Henrik.html">Jan-Henrik Haunert</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.13556">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Visualizing spatial data on small-screen devices such as smartphones and
smartwatches poses new challenges in computational cartography. The current
interfaces for map exploration require their users to zoom in and out
frequently. Indeed, zooming and panning are tools suitable for choosing the map
extent corresponding to an area of interest. They are not as suitable, however,
for resolving the graphical clutter caused by a high feature density since
zooming in to a large map scale leads to a loss of context. Therefore we
present new external labeling methods that allow navigating through dense sets
of points of interest while keeping the current map extent fixed. We provide a
unified model, in which labels are placed at the boundary of the map and
visually associated with the corresponding features via connecting lines, which
are called leaders. Since the screen space is limited, labeling all features at
the same time is impractical. Therefore, at any time, we label a subset of the
features. We offer interaction techniques to change the current selection of
features systematically and, thus, give the user access to all features. We
distinguish three methods, which allow the user either to slide the labels
along the bottom side of the map or to browse the labels based on pages or
stacks. We present a generic algorithmic framework that provides us with the
possibility of expressing the different variants of interaction techniques as
optimization problems in a unified way. We propose both exact algorithms and
fast and simple heuristics that solve the optimization problems taking into
account different criteria such as the ranking of the labels, the total leader
length and the distance between leaders. We experimentally evaluate these
algorithms and discuss the three variants with respect to their strengths and
weaknesses proving the flexibility of the presented algorithmic framework.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13491</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13491" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Semipaired Domination in Some Subclasses of Chordal Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Henning:Michael_A=.html">Michael A. Henning</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pandey:Arti.html">Arti Pandey</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tripathi:Vikash.html">Vikash Tripathi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.13491">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A dominating set $D$ of a graph $G$ without isolated vertices is called
semipaired dominating set if $D$ can be partitioned into $2$-element subsets
such that the vertices in each set are at distance at most $2$. The semipaired
domination number, denoted by $\gamma_{pr2}(G)$ is the minimum cardinality of a
semipaired dominating set of $G$. Given a graph $G$ with no isolated vertices,
the \textsc{Minimum Semipaired Domination} problem is to find a semipaired
dominating set of $G$ of cardinality $\gamma_{pr2}(G)$. The decision version of
the \textsc{Minimum Semipaired Domination} problem is already known to be
NP-complete for chordal graphs, an important graph class. In this paper, we
show that the decision version of the \textsc{Minimum Semipaired Domination}
problem remains NP-complete for split graphs, a subclass of chordal graphs. On
the positive side, we propose a linear-time algorithm to compute a minimum
cardinality semipaired dominating set of block graphs. In addition, we prove
that the \textsc{Minimum Semipaired Domination} problem is APX-complete for
graphs with maximum degree $3$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T01:24:13Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13292</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13292" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Low-Depth Parallel Algorithms for the Binary-Forking Model without Atomics</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Ahmad:Zafar.html">Zafar Ahmad</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chowdhury:Rezaul.html">Rezaul Chowdhury</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Das:Rathish.html">Rathish Das</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Ganapathi:Pramod.html">Pramod Ganapathi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gregory:Aaron.html">Aaron Gregory</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Javanmard:Mohammad_Mahdi.html">Mohammad Mahdi Javanmard</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.13292">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The binary-forking model is a parallel computation model, formally defined by
Blelloch et al. very recently, in which a thread can fork a concurrent child
thread, recursively and asynchronously. The model incurs a cost of $\Theta(\log
n)$ to spawn or synchronize $n$ tasks or threads. The binary-forking model
realistically captures the performance of parallel algorithms implemented using
modern multithreaded programming languages on multicore shared-memory machines.
In contrast, the widely studied theoretical PRAM model does not consider the
cost of spawning and synchronizing threads, and as a result, algorithms
achieving optimal performance bounds in the PRAM model may not be optimal in
the binary-forking model. Often, algorithms need to be redesigned to achieve
optimal performance bounds in the binary-forking model and the non-constant
synchronization cost makes the task challenging.
</p>
<p>Though the binary-forking model allows the use of atomic {\em test-and-set}
(TS) instructions to reduce some synchronization overhead, assuming the
availability of such instructions puts a stronger requirement on the hardware
and may limit the portability of the algorithms using them. In this paper, we
avoid the use of locks and atomic instructions in our algorithms except
possibly inside the join operation which is implemented by the runtime system.
</p>
<p>In this paper, we design efficient parallel algorithms in the binary-forking
model without atomics for three fundamental problems: Strassen's (and
Strassen-like) matrix multiplication (MM), comparison-based sorting, and the
Fast Fourier Transform (FFT). All our results improve over known results for
the corresponding problem in the binary-forking model both with and without
atomics.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13209</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.13209" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tight Bound for the Number of Distinct Palindromes in a Tree</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Paweł Gawrychowski, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kociumaka:Tomasz.html">Tomasz Kociumaka</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rytter:Wojciech.html">Wojciech Rytter</a>, Tomasz Waleń <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.13209">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>For an undirected tree with $n$ edges labelled by single letters, we consider
its substrings, which are labels of the simple paths between pairs of nodes. We
prove that there are $O(n^{1.5})$ different palindromic substrings. This solves
an open problem of Brlek, Lafreni\`ere, and Proven\c{c}al (DLT 2015), who gave
a matching lower-bound construction. Hence, we settle the tight bound of
$\Theta(n^{1.5})$ for the maximum palindromic complexity of trees. For standard
strings, i.e., for paths, the palindromic complexity is $n+1$.
</p>
<p>We also propose $O(n^{1.5} \log{n})$-time algorithm for reporting all
distinct palindromes in an undirected tree with $n$ edges.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:44Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12928</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12928" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Double Exponential Runtime is Tight for 2-Stage Stochastic ILPs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jansen:Klaus.html">Klaus Jansen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Klein:Kim=Manuel.html">Kim-Manuel Klein</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lassota:Alexandra.html">Alexandra Lassota</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12928">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider fundamental algorithmic number theoretic problems and their
relation to a class of block structured Integer Linear Programs (ILPs) called
$2$-stage stochastic. A $2$-stage stochastic ILP is an integer program of the
form $\min \{w^T x \mid \mathcal{A} x = b, L \leq x \leq U, x \in \mathbb{Z}^{s
+ nt} \}$ where the constraint matrix $\mathcal{A} \in \mathbb{Z}^{r n \times s
+nt}$ consists of $n$ repetitions of a block matrix $A \in \mathbb{Z}^{r \times
s}$ on the vertical line and $n$ repetitions of a matrix $B \in \mathbb{Z}^{r
\times t}$ on the diagonal line aside.
</p>
<p>In this paper we show an advanced hardness result for a number theoretic
problem called Quadratic Congruences where the objective is to compute a number
$z \leq \gamma$ satisfying $z^2 \equiv \alpha \bmod \beta$ for given $\alpha,
\beta, \gamma \in \mathbb{Z}$. As an implication of our hardness result for the
Quadratic Congruences problem we prove a lower bound of $2^{2^{\delta(r+t)}}
|I|^{O(1)}$ for some $\delta &gt; 0$ for the running time of any algorithm solving
$2$-stage stochastic ILPs where $|I|$ is the encoding length of the instance.
This result even holds if $s$, $||b||_{\infty}$ and the largest absolute value
$\Delta$ in the constraint matrix $\mathcal{A}$ are constant. This shows that
the recent algorithm developed by Klein is nearly optimal. The lower bound is
based on the Exponential Time Hypothesis (ETH).
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T01:20:26Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12905</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12905" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Batching and Matching for Food Delivery in Dynamic Road Networks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Manas Joshi, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Singh:Arshdeep.html">Arshdeep Singh</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ranu:Sayan.html">Sayan Ranu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bagchi:Amitabha.html">Amitabha Bagchi</a>, Priyank Karia, Puneet Kala <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12905">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a stream of food orders and available delivery vehicles, how should
orders be assigned to vehicles so that the delivery time is minimized? Several
decisions have to be made: (1) assignment of orders to vehicles, (2) grouping
orders into batches to cope with limited vehicle availability, and (3) adapting
to dynamic positions of delivery vehicles. We show that the minimization
problem is not only NP-hard but inapproximable in polynomial time. To mitigate
this computational bottleneck, we develop an algorithm called FoodMatch, which
maps the vehicle assignment problem to that of minimum weight perfect matching
on a bipartite graph. To further reduce the quadratic construction cost of the
bipartite graph, we deploy best-first search to only compute a subgraph that is
highly likely to contain the minimum matching. The solution quality is further
enhanced by reducing batching to a graph clustering problem and anticipating
dynamic positions of vehicles through angular distance. Extensive experiments
on food-delivery data from large metropolitan cities establish that FoodMatch
is substantially better than baseline strategies on a number of metrics, while
being efficient enough to handle real-world workloads.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12895</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12895" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Efficient Routing Protocol for Secured Communication in Cognitive Radio Sensor Networks</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Akter:Sharmin.html">Sharmin Akter</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Rahman:Mohammad_Shahriar.html">Mohammad Shahriar Rahman</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mansoor:Nafees.html">Nafees Mansoor</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12895">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper introduces an efficient reactive routing protocol considering the
mobility and the reliability of a node in Cognitive Radio Sensor Networks
(CRSNs). The proposed protocol accommodates the dynamic behavior of the
spectrum availability and selects a stable transmission path from a source node
to the destination. Outlined as a weighted graph problem, the proposed protocol
measures the weight for an edge the measuring the mobility patterns of the
nodes and channel availability. Furthermore, the mobility pattern of a node is
defined in the proposed routing protocol from the viewpoint of distance, speed,
direction, and node's reliability. Besides, the spectrum awareness in the
proposed protocol is measured over the number of shared common channels and the
channel quality. It is anticipated that the proposed protocol shows efficient
routing performance by selecting stable and secured paths from source to
destination. Simulation is carried out to assess the performance of the
protocol where it is witnessed that the proposed routing protocol outperforms
existing ones.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12825</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12825" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Is the space complexity of planted clique recovery the same as that of detection?</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598918400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mardia:Jay.html">Jay Mardia</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12825">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the planted clique problem in which a clique of size k is planted in
an Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi graph G(n, 1/2), and one is interested in either detecting
or recovering this planted clique. This problem is interesting because it is
widely believed to show a statistical-computational gap at clique size
k=sqrt{n}, and has emerged as the prototypical problem with such a gap from
which average-case hardness of other statistical problems can be deduced. It
also displays a tight computational connection between the detection and
recovery variants, unlike other problems of a similar nature. This wide
investigation into the computational complexity of the planted clique problem
has, however, mostly focused on its time complexity. In this work, we ask-
</p>
<p>Do the statistical-computational phenomena that make the planted clique an
interesting problem also hold when we use `space efficiency' as our notion of
computational efficiency?
</p>
<p>It is relatively easy to show that a positive answer to this question depends
on the existence of a O(log n) space algorithm that can recover planted cliques
of size k = Omega(sqrt{n}). Our main result comes very close to designing such
an algorithm. We show that for k=Omega(sqrt{n}), the recovery problem can be
solved in O((log*{n}-log*{k/sqrt{n}}) log n) bits of space.
</p>
<p>1. If k = omega(sqrt{n}log^{(l)}n) for any constant integer l &gt; 0, the space
usage is O(log n) bits.
</p>
<p>2.If k = Theta(sqrt{n}), the space usage is O(log*{n} log n) bits.
</p>
<p>Our result suggests that there does exist an O(log n) space algorithm to
recover cliques of size k = Omega(sqrt{n}), since we come very close to
achieving such parameters. This provides evidence that the
statistical-computational phenomena that (conjecturally) hold for planted
clique time complexity also (conjecturally) hold for space complexity.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://differentialprivacy.org/icml2020/</id>
    <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/icml2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Conference Digest - ICML 2020</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020">ICML 2020</a> is one of the premiere venues in machine learning, and generally features a lot of great work in differentially private machine learning.
This year is no exception: the relevant papers are listed below to the best of our ability, including links to the full versions of papers, as well as the conference pages (which contain slides and 15 minute videos for each paper).
As always, please inform us if we overlooked any papers on differential privacy.</p>

<h2 id="papers">Papers</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.12732">Alleviating Privacy Attacks via Causal Learning</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6346">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/shtople/">Shruti Tople</a>, <a href="http://www.amitsharma.in/">Amit Sharma</a>, <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/adityan/">Aditya Nori</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1805.10341">An end-to-end Differentially Private Latent Dirichlet Allocation Using a Spectral Algorithm</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6240">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://github.com/dpeng817">Chris DeCarolis</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/exsidius">Mukul Ram</a>, <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/people/sesmaeil">Seyed Esmaeili</a>, <a href="https://sites.cs.ucsb.edu/~yuxiangw/">Yu-Xiang Wang</a>, <a href="http://furong-huang.com/">Furong Huang</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.09697">Bayesian Differential Privacy for Machine Learning</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6547">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=BCWx7iQAAAAJ">Aleksei Triastcyn</a>, <a href="https://people.epfl.ch/boi.faltings">Boi Faltings</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.03030">Certified Data Removal from Machine Learning Models</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/5895">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://sites.google.com/view/chuanguo">Chuan Guo</a>, <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~tomg/">Tom Goldstein</a>, <a href="https://awnihannun.com/">Awni Hannun</a>, <a href="https://lvdmaaten.github.io/">Laurens van der Maaten</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.00038">Context Aware Local Differential Privacy</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/5775">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://people.ece.cornell.edu/acharya/">Jayadev Acharya</a>, <a href="https://research.google/people/105175/">Kallista Bonawitz</a>, <a href="https://kairouzp.github.io/">Peter Kairouz</a>, <a href="https://research.google/people/106777/">Daniel Ramage</a>, <a href="http://www.zitengsun.com/">Ziteng Sun</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.12813">Data-Dependent Differentially Private Parameter Learning for Directed Graphical Models</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6262">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=lWWAZ4YAAAAJ">Amrita Roy Chowdhury</a>, <a href="http://pages.cs.wisc.edu/~thodrek/">Theodoros Rekatsinas</a>, <a href="http://pages.cs.wisc.edu/~jha/">Somesh Jha</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09745">Differentially Private Set Union</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6541">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/sigopi/">Sivakanth Gopi</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pankajgulhane/">Pankaj Gulhane</a>, <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/jakul/">Janardhan Kulkarni</a>, <a href="https://heyyjudes.github.io/">Judy Hanwen Shen</a>, <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/milads/">Milad Shokouhi</a>, <a href="http://www.yekhanin.org/">Sergey Yekhanin</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.11651">Fair Learning with Private Demographic Data</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6499">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://husseinmozannar.github.io/">Hussein Mozannar</a>, <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/mesrob/home/">Mesrob Ohannessian</a>, <a href="https://ttic.uchicago.edu/~nati/">Nathan Srebro</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.15744">Fast and Private Submodular and $k$-Submodular Functions Maximization with Matroid Constraint</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6365">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://dblp.org/pid/166/1694.html">Akbar Rafiey</a>, <a href="http://research.nii.ac.jp/~yyoshida/">Yuichi Yoshida</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2006.00706">(Locally) Differentially Private Combinatorial Semi-Bandits</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6315">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=sioumZAAAAAJ">Xiaoyu Chen</a>, <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Bw-WdyUAAAAJ">Kai Zheng</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/zixinjackzhou">Zixin Zhou</a>, <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=m8m9nD0AAAAJ">Yunchang Yang</a>, <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/weic/">Wei Chan</a>, <a href="http://www.liweiwang-pku.com/">Liwei Wang</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.05453">New Oracle-Efficient Algorithms for Private Synthetic Data Release</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/5814">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://sites.google.com/umn.edu/giuseppe-vietri/home">Giuseppe Vietri</a>, <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=dDVIyEQAAAAJ">Grace Tian</a>, <a href="https://cs-people.bu.edu/mbun/">Mark Bun</a>, <a href="http://www.thomas-steinke.net/">Thomas Steinke</a>, <a href="https://zstevenwu.com/">Zhiwei Steven Wu</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://proceedings.icml.cc/static/paper_files/icml/2020/1190-Paper.pdf">On Differentially Private Stochastic Convex Optimization with Heavy-tailed Data</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/5948">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="http://www.acsu.buffalo.edu/~dwang45/">Di Wang</a>, <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=e3ZhEDEAAAAJ">Hanshen Xiao</a>, <a href="https://people.csail.mit.edu/devadas/">Srinivas Devadas</a>, <a href="https://cse.buffalo.edu/~jinhui/">Jinhui Xu</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.13830">Optimal Differential Privacy Composition for Exponential Mechanisms</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6687">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://www.math.upenn.edu/~jinshuo/">Jinshuo Dong</a>, <a href="https://dblp.org/pid/155/9794.html">David Durfee</a>, <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=jr7gGB4AAAAJ">Ryan Rogers</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.01783">Oracle Efficient Private Non-Convex Optimization</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/5815">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://sethneel.com/">Seth Neel</a>, <a href="https://www.cis.upenn.edu/~aaroth/">Aaron Roth</a>, <a href="https://sites.google.com/umn.edu/giuseppe-vietri/home">Giuseppe Vietri</a>, <a href="https://zstevenwu.com/">Zhiwei Steven Wu</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://proceedings.icml.cc/static/paper_files/icml/2020/2341-Paper.pdf">Private Counting from Anonymous Messages: Near-Optimal Accuracy with Vanishing Communication Overhead</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6134">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://sites.google.com/view/badihghazi/home">Badih Ghazi</a>, <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/ravik53/">Ravi Kumar</a>, <a href="https://pasin30055.github.io/">Pasin Manurangsi</a>, <a href="https://www.itu.dk/people/pagh/">Rasmus Pagh</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://proceedings.icml.cc/static/paper_files/icml/2020/6298-Paper.pdf">Private Outsourced Bayesian Optimization</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6783">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=7_2XTQ8AAAAJ">Dmitrii Kharkovskii</a>, <a href="https://daizhongxiang.github.io/">Zhongxiang Dai</a>, <a href="https://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/~lowkh/research.html">Bryan Kian Hsiang Low</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.10941">Private Query Release Assisted by Public Data</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6329">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://sites.google.com/view/rbassily">Raef Bassily</a>, <a href="https://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/albertcheu/">Albert Cheu</a>, <a href="http://www.cs.technion.ac.il/~shaymrn/">Shay Moran</a>, <a href="http://www.cs.toronto.edu/~anikolov/">Aleksandar Nikolov</a>, <a href="https://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/jullman/">Jonathan Ullman</a>, <a href="https://zstevenwu.com/">Zhiwei Steven Wu</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://proceedings.icml.cc/static/paper_files/icml/2020/2453-Paper.pdf">Private Reinforcement Learning with PAC and Regret Guarantees</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6152">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://sites.google.com/umn.edu/giuseppe-vietri/home">Giuseppe Vietri</a>, <a href="https://borjaballe.github.io/">Borja Balle</a>, <a href="https://people.cs.umass.edu/~akshay/">Akshay Krishnamurthy</a>, <a href="https://zstevenwu.com/">Zhiwei Steven Wu</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.01327">Privately Detecting Changes in Unknown Distributions</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/5854">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://sites.gatech.edu/rachel-cummings/">Rachel Cummings</a>, <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/skrehbiel/home">Sara Krehbiel</a>, <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=ayasb_wAAAAJ">Yuliia Lut</a>, <a href="https://wanrongz.github.io/">Wanrong Zhang</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09463">Privately Learning Markov Random Fields</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/5776">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://huanyuzhang.github.io/">Huanyu Zhang</a>, <a href="http://www.gautamkamath.com/">Gautam Kamath</a>, <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/jakul/">Janardhan Kulkarni</a>, <a href="https://zstevenwu.com/">Zhiwei Steven Wu</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.09822">Scalable Differential Privacy with Certified Robustness in Adversarial Learning</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6401">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://sites.google.com/site/ihaiphan/">NhatHai Phan</a>, <a href="https://www.cise.ufl.edu/~mythai/">My T. Thai</a>, <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=OgXtPDIAAAAJ">Han Hu</a>, <a href="http://www.cs.kent.edu/~jin/">Ruoming Jin</a>, <a href="https://research.adobe.com/person/tong-sun/">Tong Sun</a>, <a href="https://ix.cs.uoregon.edu/~dou/">Dejing Dou</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04493">Sharp Composition Bounds for Gaussian Differential Privacy via Edgeworth Expansion</a> (<a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/poster/6734">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://enosair.github.io/">Qinqing Zheng</a>, <a href="https://www.math.upenn.edu/~jinshuo/">Jinshuo Dong</a>, <a href="https://www.med.upenn.edu/apps/faculty/index.php/g275/p8939931">Qi Long</a>, <a href="http://www-stat.wharton.upenn.edu/~suw/">Weijie J. Su</a></p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-31T18:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-31T18:00:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam Kamath</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://differentialprivacy.org</id>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Website for the differential privacy research community</subtitle>
      <title>Differential Privacy</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T23:53:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17496</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/31/mea-culpa/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Mea Culpa</title>
    <summary>Plus more on the separating word problem Mea Culpa is not someone we introduced on the blog before. She does not come from the same world as Lofa Polir or Neil L. As in the French movie poster at right, the meaning is “my fault.” Today we apologize for some oversights and hasty omissions regarding […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Plus more on the separating word problem</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/31/mea-culpa/mea/" rel="attachment wp-att-17499"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-17499" height="147" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/mea.jpg?w=110&amp;h=147" width="110"/></a></p>
<p>
Mea Culpa is not someone we introduced on the blog before. She does not come from the same world as Lofa Polir or Neil L. As in the French <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mea_Culpa_(film)">movie</a> poster at right, the meaning is “my fault.”</p>
<p/><p>
Today we apologize for some oversights and hasty omissions regarding the last <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/29/20000-comments-and-more/">post</a>. Then we will explain Dick’s “laws with errors”.</p>
<p>
Let’s be clear. The paper we discussed in the last post claiming an order <img alt="{\log n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log n}"/> upper bound is wrong. The best upper bound is still due to Zachary Chase and is order <img alt="{n^{1/3}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7B1%2F3%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n^{1/3}}"/>, with some log’s. </p>
<p>
At GLL we try to be fair and upbeat, especially with proof attempts. We know how hard it is to put yourself out there when you claim a new result. Whether for a famous open problem or not, it is always difficult. Mistakes are possible, miss understandings are possible. </p>
<p>
But perhaps this time we have gone too far, and for that we apologize. We just love the SWP, and want to reiterate the idea the post was supposed to be (only) about, an approach to SWP. </p>
<p>
There is also Nostra Culpa—“our fault,” Ken says too.  Not only is there a short <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt8513100/">film</a> with that title, there is a 2013 one-singer <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t2paj1mrCQI">opera</a> of that title with libretto drawn from a 2012 Twitter <a href="https://news.err.ee/106193/nostra-culpa-an-interview-with-the-writers-of-a-financial-opera">feud</a> between the economist Paul Krugman and the president of Estonia. At least our issue did not break out on Twitter. We were instead contacted privately by some friends who knew more about the erroneous paper highlighted in our post. We could have contacted them first—that was our omission.</p>
<p>
Again sorry for any confusion we created. Let’s turn to the approach we want to share about SWP.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Laws with Errors </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I think there is hope that positive laws must be large, especially if we extend what it mean by a law. Consider a positive law 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  U = V, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++U+%3D+V%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  U = V, "/></p>
<p>where <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> and <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{V}"/> are words over the letters <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> and <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/>. Recall we can tell if <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> and <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{V}"/> are different provided there is a finite group <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> so that for some <img alt="{A,B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%2CB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A,B}"/> in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> the value of <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> and <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{V}"/> are different. This can be computed by a FSA with at most order <img alt="{|G|}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%7C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{|G|}"/> states. So the smaller <img alt="{|G|}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%7C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{|G|}"/> is the better. </p>
<p>
The trouble is it does not seem to the case that strong enough lower bounds are known for positive laws. This suggest that we make it harder for a law to work. </p>
<p>
The idea is to use a FST, that is a finite state transducer. This is a finite state device that reads a symbol, updates its state, and outputs one or more symbols. If <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> is the FST and <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> is a string, let <img alt="{T(U)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%28U%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T(U)}"/> be the result of applying <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/>. For example, suppose that <img alt="{ABBBAB}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BABBBAB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{ABBBAB}"/> is an input <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/>. Let the transducer add a <img alt="{C}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{C}"/> after each <img alt="{AB}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BAB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{AB}"/>. Thus <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> maps to: 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  ABCBBABC. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++ABCBBABC.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  ABCBBABC. "/></p>
<p>	 Then the following is true: </p>
<blockquote><p><b>Lemma 1</b> <em> Let <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> be group and let <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> be a transducer with <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S}"/> states. Then we can separate <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> from <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{V}"/> by a FSA with order <img alt="{|G| \cdot S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%7C+%5Ccdot+S%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{|G| \cdot S}"/> states provided 	</em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  T(U) = T(V) " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++T%28U%29+%3D+T%28V%29+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  T(U) = T(V) "/></p>
</em><p><em>is not a law in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
<em>Proof:</em>  The key is to simulate <img alt="{T}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T}"/> as we read the input, and at the same time update the group element. This can be done by a FSA with the product <img alt="{|G|}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%7CG%7C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{|G|}"/> and <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S}"/> states. <img alt="\Box" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5CBox&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\Box"/></p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The hope is that having a law that is invariant for all FST, even only those with few states, is difficult. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <b>A conjecture</b>: Positive laws that can handle all FST transducers with <img alt="{n^{\epsilon}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7B%5Cepsilon%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n^{\epsilon}}"/> states must be large. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>That is are large enough to advance our best bounds on SWP. What do you think?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-31T13:41:04Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-31T13:41:04Z</published>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="claims"/>
    <category term="mistake"/>
    <category term="open problem"/>
    <category term="separate words"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:20:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?p=99</id>
    <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/2020/08/31/algorithms-for-convex-optimization-book/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Algorithms for Convex Optimization Book</title>
    <summary>I am excited to announce that a pre-publication draft of my book Algorithms for Convex Optimization (to be published by Cambridge University Press) is now available for download here: Algorithms for Convex Optimization Book The goal of this book is to enable a reader to gain an in-depth understanding of algorithms for convex optimization. The emphasis is […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I am excited to announce that a pre-publication draft of my book <strong>Algorithms for Convex Optimization</strong> (to be published by Cambridge University Press) is now available for download here:</p>
<p><a href="https://convex-optimization.github.io/">Algorithms for Convex Optimization Book</a></p>
<p>The goal of this book is to enable a reader to gain an in-depth understanding of algorithms for convex optimization. The emphasis is to derive key algorithms for convex optimization from first principles and to establish precise running time bounds in terms of the input length.</p>
<p>The intended audience includes advanced undergraduate students, graduate students and researches from theoretical computer science, discrete optimization, and machine learning.</p>
<div class="page" title="Page 8">
<div class="layoutArea">
<div class="column">
<p>The book has four parts:</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<ol>
<li class="p1">Chapters 3,4, and 5: Introduction to convexity, models of computation and notions of efficiency in convex optimization, Lagrangian duality, Legendre-Fenchel duality, and KKT conditions.</li>
<li class="p1">Chapters 6,7, and 8: First-order methods such as gradient descent, mirror descent and the multiplicative weights update method, and accelerated gradient descent.</li>
<li class="p1">Chapters 9,10, and 11: Newton’s method, path-following interior point methods for linear programming, and self-concordant barrier functions.</li>
<li class="p1">Chapter 11 and 12: Cutting plane methods such as the ellipsoid method for linear and general convex programs.</li>
</ol>
<p class="p1">Chapter 1 summarizes the book via a brief history of the interplay between continuous and discrete optimization: how the search for fast algorithms for discrete problems is leading to improvements in algorithms for convex optimization.</p>
<p class="p1">Many chapters contain applications ranging from finding maximum flows, minimum cuts, and perfect matchings in graphs, to linear optimization over 0-1-polytopes, to submodular function minimization, to computing maximum entropy distributions over combinatorial polytopes.</p>
<p class="p1">The book is self-contained and starts with a review of calculus, linear algebra, geometry, dynamical systems, and graph theory in Chapter 2. Exercises posed in this book not only play an important role in checking one’s understanding, but sometimes important methods and concepts are introduced and developed entirely through them. Examples include the Frank-Wolfe method, coordinate descent, stochastic gradient descent, online convex optimization, the min-max theorem for zero-sum games, the Winnow algorithm for classification, the conjugate gradient method, primal-dual interior point method, and matrix scaling.</p>
<p>Feedback, corrections, and comments are welcome.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-31T13:30:40Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-31T13:30:40Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>nisheethvishnoi</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://nisheethvishnoi.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Algorithms, Nature, and Society</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:21:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/31/postdoc-at-epfl-apply-by-september-13-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/31/postdoc-at-epfl-apply-by-september-13-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at EPFL (apply by September 13, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Applications are solicited for postdoctoral positions in all aspects of Theoretical Computer Science at EPFL. Each position will be for a period of up to two years and comes with a competitive salary and generous travel support. Website: https://theory.epfl.ch/postdoc.html Email: tcs-postdoc@groupes.epfl.ch</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Applications are solicited for postdoctoral positions in all aspects of Theoretical Computer Science at EPFL. Each position will be for a period of up to two years and comes with a competitive salary and generous travel support.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://theory.epfl.ch/postdoc.html">https://theory.epfl.ch/postdoc.html</a><br/>
Email: tcs-postdoc@groupes.epfl.ch</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-31T08:29:08Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-31T08:29:08Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12776</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12776" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Efficiently Solving MDPs with Stochastic Mirror Descent</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598832000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jin:Yujia.html">Yujia Jin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sidford:Aaron.html">Aaron Sidford</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12776">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We present a unified framework based on primal-dual stochastic mirror descent
for approximately solving infinite-horizon Markov decision processes (MDPs)
given a generative model. When applied to an average-reward MDP with $A_{tot}$
total state-action pairs and mixing time bound $t_{mix}$ our method computes an
$\epsilon$-optimal policy with an expected $\widetilde{O}(t_{mix}^2 A_{tot}
\epsilon^{-2})$ samples from the state-transition matrix, removing the
ergodicity dependence of prior art. When applied to a $\gamma$-discounted MDP
with $A_{tot}$ total state-action pairs our method computes an
$\epsilon$-optimal policy with an expected $\widetilde{O}((1-\gamma)^{-4}
A_{tot} \epsilon^{-2})$ samples, matching the previous state-of-the-art up to a
$(1-\gamma)^{-1}$ factor. Both methods are model-free, update state values and
policies simultaneously, and run in time linear in the number of samples taken.
We achieve these results through a more general stochastic mirror descent
framework for solving bilinear saddle-point problems with simplex and box
domains and we demonstrate the flexibility of this framework by providing
further applications to constrained MDPs.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12727</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12727" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Recoverable Robust Representatives Selection Problems with Discrete Budgeted Uncertainty</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598832000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Goerigk:Marc.html">Marc Goerigk</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lendl:Stefan.html">Stefan Lendl</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wulf:Lasse.html">Lasse Wulf</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12727">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Recoverable robust optimization is a multi-stage approach, where it is
possible to adjust a first-stage solution after the uncertain cost scenario is
revealed. We analyze this approach for a class of selection problems. The aim
is to choose a fixed number of items from several disjoint sets, such that the
worst-case costs after taking a recovery action are as small as possible. The
uncertainty is modeled as a discrete budgeted set, where the adversary can
increase the costs of a fixed number of items. While special cases of this
problem have been studied before, its complexity has remained open. In this
work we make several contributions towards closing this gap. We show that the
problem is NP-hard and identify a special case that remains solvable in
polynomial time. We provide a compact mixed-integer programming formulation and
two additional extended formulations. Finally, computational results are
provided that compare the efficiency of different exact solution approaches.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-31T23:20:26Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12567</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12567" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Topological Similarity Measure between Multi-Field Data using Multi-Resolution Reeb Spaces</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598832000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Agarwal:Tripti.html">Tripti Agarwal</a>, Yashwanth Ramamurthi, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chattopadhyay:Amit.html">Amit Chattopadhyay</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12567">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Searching topological similarity between a pair of shapes or data is an
important problem in data analysis and visualization. The problem of computing
similarity measures using scalar topology has been studied extensively and
proven useful in shape and data matching. Even though multi-field (or
multivariate) topology-based techniques reveal richer topological features,
research on computing similarity measures using multi-field topology is still
in its infancy. In the current paper, we propose a novel similarity measure
between two piecewise-linear multi-fields based on their multi-resolution Reeb
spaces - a newly developed data-structure that captures the topology of a
multi-field. Overall, our method consists of two steps: (i) building a
multi-resolution Reeb space corresponding to each of the multi-fields and (ii)
proposing a similarity measure for a list of matching pairs (of nodes),
obtained by comparing the multi-resolution Reeb spaces. We demonstrate an
application of the proposed similarity measure by detecting the nuclear
scission point in a time-varying multi-field data from computational physics.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12516</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12516" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Work-Efficient Parallel Algorithms for Predicate Detection</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598832000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Rohan Garg <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12516">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Recently, the predicate detection problem was shown to be in the parallel
complexity class NC. In this paper, we give some more work efficient parallel
algorithms to solve the predicate detection problem on a distributed
computation with $n$ processes and at most $m$ states per process. The previous
best known parallel predicate detection algorithm, ParallelCut, had work
complexity $O(m^3n^3\log mn)$. We give two algorithms, a deterministic
algorithm with work complexity $O(m^2n^2)$ and a randomized algorithm with work
complexity $\tilde{O}(m^2n^2)$. Furthermore, our algorithms have a space
complexity of $O(mn^2)$ whereas ParallelCut had a space complexity of
$O(m^2n^2)$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12388</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12388" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Differentially Private Clustering via Maximum Coverage</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598832000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jones:Matthew.html">Matthew Jones</a>, Huy Lê Nguyen, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nguyen:Thy.html">Thy Nguyen</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12388">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper studies the problem of clustering in metric spaces while
preserving the privacy of individual data. Specifically, we examine
differentially private variants of the k-medians and Euclidean k-means
problems. We present polynomial algorithms with constant multiplicative error
and lower additive error than the previous state-of-the-art for each problem.
Additionally, our algorithms use a clustering algorithm without differential
privacy as a black-box. This allows practitioners to control the trade-off
between runtime and approximation factor by choosing a suitable clustering
algorithm to use.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12386</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.12386" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Polynomial-time trace reconstruction in the smoothed complexity model</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1598832000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Chen:Xi.html">Xi Chen</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/De:Anindya.html">Anindya De</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lee:Chin_Ho.html">Chin Ho Lee</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Servedio:Rocco_A=.html">Rocco A. Servedio</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sinha:Sandip.html">Sandip Sinha</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.12386">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the \emph{trace reconstruction problem}, an unknown source string $x \in
\{0,1\}^n$ is sent through a probabilistic \emph{deletion channel} which
independently deletes each bit with probability $\delta$ and concatenates the
surviving bits, yielding a \emph{trace} of $x$. The problem is to reconstruct
$x$ given independent traces. This problem has received much attention in
recent years both in the worst-case setting where $x$ may be an arbitrary
string in $\{0,1\}^n$ \cite{DOS17,NazarovPeres17,HHP18,HL18,Chase19} and in the
average-case setting where $x$ is drawn uniformly at random from $\{0,1\}^n$
\cite{PeresZhai17,HPP18,HL18,Chase19}.
</p>
<p>This paper studies trace reconstruction in the \emph{smoothed analysis}
setting, in which a ``worst-case'' string $x^{\worst}$ is chosen arbitrarily
from $\{0,1\}^n$, and then a perturbed version $\bx$ of $x^{\worst}$ is formed
by independently replacing each coordinate by a uniform random bit with
probability $\sigma$. The problem is to reconstruct $\bx$ given independent
traces from it.
</p>
<p>Our main result is an algorithm which, for any constant perturbation rate
$0&lt;\sigma &lt; 1$ and any constant deletion rate $0 &lt; \delta &lt; 1$, uses $\poly(n)$
running time and traces and succeeds with high probability in reconstructing
the string $\bx$. This stands in contrast with the worst-case version of the
problem, for which $\text{exp}(O(n^{1/3}))$ is the best known time and sample
complexity \cite{DOS17,NazarovPeres17}.
</p>
<p>Our approach is based on reconstructing $\bx$ from the multiset of its short
subwords and is quite different from previous algorithms for either the
worst-case or average-case versions of the problem. The heart of our work is a
new $\poly(n)$-time procedure for reconstructing the multiset of all $O(\log
n)$-length subwords of any source string $x\in \{0,1\}^n$ given access to
traces of $x$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-31T23:20:27Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4942</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4942" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4942#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=4942" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">My new motto</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Update (Sep 1): Thanks for the comments, everyone! As you can see, I further revised this blog’s header based on the feedback and on further reflection. The Right could only kill me and everyone I know.The Left is scarier; it could convince me that it was my fault! (In case you missed it on the […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update (Sep 1):</span></strong> Thanks for the comments, everyone!  As you can see, I further revised this blog’s header based on the feedback and on further reflection.<br/><br/><strong>The Right could only kill me and everyone I know.<br/>The Left is scarier; it could convince me that it was my fault</strong>!</p>



<p>(In case you missed it on the blog’s revised header, right below “Quantum computers aren’t just nondeterministic Turing machines” and “Hold the November US election by mail.”  I added an exclamation point at the end to suggest a <em>slightly</em> comic delivery.)</p>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update:</span></strong> A friend expressed concern that, because my new motto appears to “blame both sides,” it might generate confusion about my sympathies or what I want to happen in November.  So to eliminate all ambiguity: I hereby announce that I will match all reader donations made in the next 72 hours to either the <a href="https://secure.actblue.com/donate/duforjoe">Biden-Harris campaign</a> or the <a href="https://lincolnproject.us/donate/">Lincoln Project</a>, up to a limit of $2,000.  Honor system; just tell me in the comments what you donated.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-30T23:21:02Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-30T23:21:02Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Embarrassing Myself"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Obviously I'm Not Defending Aaronson"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Self-Referential"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T14:14:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/08/30/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/08/30/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>The evolution of mathematical word processing (\(\mathbb{M}\)). “Developments in computing over the last 30 years have not done as much as one might have thought to make writing mathematics easier.”</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://sinews.siam.org/Details-Page/the-evolution-of-mathematical-word-processing">The evolution of mathematical word processing</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104701998974894412">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). “Developments in computing over the last 30 years have not done as much as one might have thought to make writing mathematics easier.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://prideout.net/blog/svg_wireframes/">3D Wireframes in SVG, via Python</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104707509485635530">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://github.com/prideout/svg3d">code repository</a>). Once you generate the model, it does the rest. Its depth-ordering heuristics aren’t perfect (and will fail when the depth order is cyclic), but generally work pretty well. For example, here’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jessen%27s_icosahedron">Jessen’s icosahedron</a> in a simple partially-transparent style without fancy shading (<a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/jessen.py">Python code</a>). To get it to look right I had to edit the resulting svg and manually reorder the faces.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Jessen's icosahedron" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/jessen.svg"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2020/08/17/ip-grab-youngstown-state">Intellectual property grab at Youngstown State</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104714502717608284">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). In negotiations with the faculty union, the university wants to replace the tradition of faculty holding copyright to research articles, textbooks, syllabi and lectures, etc by instead taking ownership of “all nonpatentable faculty work” as work-for-hire. They claim that they aren’t changing their policies and are merely doing this “to be consistent with the law” but this comes across as unlikely and disingenuous.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://digital.lib.washington.edu/researchworks/bitstream/handle/1773/15700/Lost%20Mathematics.pdf?fterence=1">Lectures on lost mathematics</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104718951109084030">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). In this 79-page pdf from 1975, Branko Grünbaum discusses mathematical questions studied by non-mathematicians but snubbed by pure mathematicians, including which polygons tile, the girth of infinitely-repeating cubic spatial graphs, the classification of vertex-transitive polyhedral manifolds in space, generalization of Kempe universality to surfaces, flexible polyhedra, and tensegrity.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://xkcd.com/2348/">A recent xkcd on river crossing puzzles</a> particularly amused me (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104726172352360084">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="xkcd comic &quot;Boat Puzzle&quot;, https://xkcd.com/2348/" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/xkcd-2348.png" width="80%"/></p>

    <p>It’s too bad xkcd uses an -NC clause in its CC license; if it didn’t, we could use it or its first frame to replace <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/River_crossing_puzzle">the Wikipedia article’s illustration</a>, which is undergoing a long slow <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Commons:Deletion_requests/File:Vovk_koza_kapusta.png">deletion discussion because copied from a 1954 Soviet book</a>. If you know something useful about the copyright status of 1954 Soviet books, please add your knowledge to that discussion.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.flyingcoloursmaths.co.uk/eye-to-eye/">Eye to eye</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104731872882549290">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Let \(C\) and \(C'\) be circles with centers outside the other circle, and draw tangent rays from each center to the other circle. These rays cut their circles in chords of equal length. But I wonder: when only one circle has its center outside the other, its chord is still well defined, but the same length can’t be a chord of the other circle because it exceeds the diameter. But it should still have a geometric meaning with respect to the other circle: what is it?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://petapixel.com/2020/08/20/lightroom-app-update-wipes-users-photos-and-presets-adobe-says-they-are-not-recoverable/">Lightroom App update irrecoverably loses users’ photos</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104742916488291004">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=24229864">via</a>). My choice to continue using an oldish powerbook with dubiously-reliable keyboard, to avoid giving up my paid-for non-subscription Adobe apps which won’t run on newer Macs, has an unexpected benefit: my files haven’t been auto-deleted. Also, let this be a reminder to do your backups, and make sure that they include a local non-cloud backup of your files.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://github.andrewt.net/mines/">Minesweeper where forced guesses are always safe, but unforced guesses always explode</a> (<a href="https://mastodon.technology/@andrewt/104701318997810776">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Scotland/comments/ig9jia/ive_discovered_that_almost_every_single_article/">“The Scots language version of Wikipedia is legendarily bad” — turns out because it was mostly written by an American teenager</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104751072546716749">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://www.metafilter.com/188374/The-problem-is-that-this-person-cannot-speak-Scots">via</a>). See <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Wikipedia_Signpost/2020-08-30/News_and_notes">the <em>Signpost</em> article</a> for an update.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Today’s mini-episode of “not the Reuleaux triangle” (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104757581337870450">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>): the logo of Polish football club Ruch Chorzów, which a supporter tried to add to the Wikipedia article. Unlike many non-Reuleaux round triangles, it appears to use circular arcs, but not centered at the corners and with non-equilateral corners. The arc across the bottom is longer than the two sides, and it is wider than it is tall. Image from <a href="http://kubamalicki.com/portfolio_page/ruch-chorzow-100-years-anniversary/">an article on a recent redesign of the official logo</a>.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Geometric analysis of the Ruch Chorz&#xF3;w logo showing that it is not a Reuleaux triangle" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/ruch-logo.png" width="80%"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@jsiehler/104763100825420197">J. Siehler asks for unsolved problems in mathematics whose statements are understandable by elementary school students, other than in number theory </a>. Examples given so far include <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inscribed_square_problem">square pegs</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bellman%27s_lost_in_a_forest_problem">lost in a forest</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moving_sofa_problem">sofa-moving</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moser%27s_worm_problem">Moser’s worm</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Net_(polyhedron)#Existence_and_uniqueness">Dürer’s nets</a>, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tur%C3%A1n%27s_brick_factory_problem">brick factory</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lonely_runner_conjecture">lonely runners</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.rayawolfsun.com/2015/02/06/the-romance-of-al-asturlabiya/">Concerning “Mariam” Al-Asturlabiya</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104771298687510642">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). A warning about how romanticizing past figures (in this case <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mariam_al-Asturlabi">the only woman astrolabist known from the medieval Islamic world</a>) can result in creating biographical details for them out of thin air.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://prideout.net/knotgl/">Interactive 3d knot table</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104779316951663485">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). One of many interesting visualizations on “<a href="https://prideout.net/">the little grasshopper</a>”, by Philip Rideout (author of the svg3d Python library linked above).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://gd2020.cs.ubc.ca/program-no-links/">The Graph Drawing 2020 program is online</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/104781215682863021">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). It is September 16-18, from 8AM to noon Pacific daylight time (the time in Vancouver, where the conference was originally to be held). The format has talk videos available pre-conference, with sessions consisting of 1-minute reminders of each talk and 5 minutes of live questions per talk. Jeff Erickson and Sheelagh Carpendale will give live invited talks. It’s free but requires registration, with deadline September 10.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-30T17:47:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-30T17:47:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T01:37:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17466</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/29/20000-comments-and-more/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>20,000 Comments and More</title>
    <summary>With more about the Separating Words Problem I.I.T. Madras page Anoop S K M is a PhD student in the theory group of I.I.T. Madras in Chennai, India. His comment two weeks ago Monday was the 20,000th reader comment (including trackbacks) on this blog. Today we thank Anoop and all our readers and say more […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>With more about the Separating Words Problem</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/anoopskm-1.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-17474" height="150" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/anoopskm-1.jpg?w=128&amp;h=150" width="128"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">I.I.T. Madras <a href="http://www.cse.iitm.ac.in/~theory/memberdetails.php?memberid=512">page</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Anoop S K M is a PhD student in the theory group of I.I.T. Madras in Chennai, India. His <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/03/cleverer-automata-exist/#comment-111947">comment</a> two weeks ago Monday was the <font color="green"><b>20,000</b></font>th reader comment (including trackbacks) on this blog.</p>
<p>
Today we thank Anoop and all our readers and say more about the subject of his comment.</p>
<p>
Anoop’s advisor is Jayalal Sarma, who has a further connection to me (Ken). Sarma has <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1002.1496">co-authored</a> <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00224-013-9519-3">three</a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0912.2565">papers</a> with my PhD graduate Maurice Jansen, whose work we have <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2011/04/20/could-euler-have-solved-this/">also</a> featured <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2011/04/28/succinct-constant-depth-arithmetic-circuits-are-weak/">here</a>. </p>
<p>
The comment was Anoop’s first and thus far only one on the blog. In passing we note that after one’s first comment is moderated through, subsequent ones appear freely and immediately. Thus one can say that Anoop had only a 0.005% chance of hitting the milestone. </p>
<p>
Dick and I would also like to give a warm shout out to someone else who in another sense had almost a 56% chance of hitting it: Jon Awbrey, who writes the blog <a href="https://inquiryintoinquiry.com/">Inquiry Into Inquiry</a> and also <a href="https://ncatlab.org/nlab/show/Jon+Awbrey">contributes</a> to the <a href="https://ncatlab.org/nlab/show/About">nLab</a> Project.</p>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/jon_awbrey.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-17470" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/jon_awbrey.jpg?w=128&amp;h=150"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright">
<font size="-2"><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jon_Awbrey">src</a><br/>
</font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>As we were twenty-seven comments into our third myriad at the time of drafting this post, we note that most of his 15-of-27 comments are trackback citations of our previous <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/19/logical-complexity-of-proofs/">post</a> on proof complexity, but he wrote <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/19/logical-complexity-of-proofs/#comment-112175">two</a> long <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/19/logical-complexity-of-proofs/#comment-112189">comments</a> as well. We have not had time to act on them; for my part, chess cheating has found ways to mutate into new kinds of cases even as I see hope for stemming the main online outbreak of it. But comments can also be resources for others, especially students who may be emboldened to take a swing at progress from where we’ve left off.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Anoop’s Comment and SWP Ideas </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Anoop’s comment was in our recent <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/08/03/cleverer-automata-exist/">post</a> on the Separating Word Problem (SWP). He asked about a technical <a href="http://invenio.nusl.cz/record/251413/files/content.csg.pdf">report</a> by Jiří Wiedermann claiming a clean best-possible <img alt="{O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(\log n)}"/> bound on the SWP over alphabet <img alt="{\{0,1\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%7B0%2C1%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\{0,1\}}"/>. </p>
<p>
Wiedermann’s idea is simple to state—maybe too simple: Consider finite state automata (FSAs) <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> whose <img alt="{2m}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2m%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{2m}"/> states form two <img alt="{m}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bm%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{m}"/>-cycle “tracks”: </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  q_0 \rightarrow q_1 \rightarrow \cdots \rightarrow q_{m-1} \rightarrow q_0; \qquad q'_0 \rightarrow q'_1 \rightarrow \cdots \rightarrow q'_{m-1} \rightarrow q'_0 " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++q_0+%5Crightarrow+q_1+%5Crightarrow+%5Ccdots+%5Crightarrow+q_%7Bm-1%7D+%5Crightarrow+q_0%3B+%5Cqquad+q%27_0+%5Crightarrow+q%27_1+%5Crightarrow+%5Ccdots+%5Crightarrow+q%27_%7Bm-1%7D+%5Crightarrow+q%27_0+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  q_0 \rightarrow q_1 \rightarrow \cdots \rightarrow q_{m-1} \rightarrow q_0; \qquad q'_0 \rightarrow q'_1 \rightarrow \cdots \rightarrow q'_{m-1} \rightarrow q'_0 "/></p>
<p>Each edge goes to the next state on the same track on both <img alt="{0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{0}"/> and <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/> <em>unless</em> we place a “crossover” so that the edges switch tracks on <img alt="{1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{1}"/>. The primed track has accepting states. It does not matter whether the start state is <img alt="{q_0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq_0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q_0}"/> or <img alt="{q'_0}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%27_0%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q'_0}"/>, but it is the same for any pair of strings <img alt="{u,v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%2Cv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u,v}"/> of length <img alt="{n \gg m}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn+%5Cgg+m%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n \gg m}"/> that we wish to distinguish.</p>
<p>
Let <img alt="{S \subseteq [n]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS+%5Csubseteq+%5Bn%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S \subseteq [n]}"/> be the set of places where <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> and <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> differ. Now suppose we have <img alt="{b \in [m]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb+%5Cin+%5Bm%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b \in [m]}"/> such that the intersection of <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S}"/> with the residue class <img alt="{R_{m,b} = \{am + b : a \in \mathbb{N}\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BR_%7Bm%2Cb%7D+%3D+%5C%7Bam+%2B+b+%3A+a+%5Cin+%5Cmathbb%7BN%7D%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{R_{m,b} = \{am + b : a \in \mathbb{N}\}}"/> is odd. Make <img alt="{A = A_{m,b}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA+%3D+A_%7Bm%2Cb%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A = A_{m,b}}"/> by placing one “crossover” at point <img alt="{b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b}"/> on the tracks; that is, make the transitions for <img alt="{q_b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq_b%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q_b}"/> and <img alt="{q'_b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bq%27_b%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{q'_b}"/> be </p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  (q_b,0,q_{b+1}),~(q_b,1,q'_{b+1}),~(q'_b,0,q'_{b+1}),~(q'_b,1,q_{b+1}), " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%28q_b%2C0%2Cq_%7Bb%2B1%7D%29%2C%7E%28q_b%2C1%2Cq%27_%7Bb%2B1%7D%29%2C%7E%28q%27_b%2C0%2Cq%27_%7Bb%2B1%7D%29%2C%7E%28q%27_b%2C1%2Cq_%7Bb%2B1%7D%29%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  (q_b,0,q_{b+1}),~(q_b,1,q'_{b+1}),~(q'_b,0,q'_{b+1}),~(q'_b,1,q_{b+1}), "/></p>
<p>where the addition is modulo <img alt="{m}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bm%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{m}"/>. Then whenever a place where <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> and <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> differ enters the crossover, the strings flip their status of being on the same track or different tracks. Since this happens an odd number of times, <img alt="{A_{m,b}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA_%7Bm%2Cb%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A_{m,b}}"/> accepts <img alt="{u}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u}"/> and rejects <img alt="{v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{v}"/> or vice-versa.</p>
<p>
If for every <img alt="{S \subseteq [n]}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS+%5Csubseteq+%5Bn%5D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S \subseteq [n]}"/> we could find such <img alt="{m}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bm%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{m}"/> and <img alt="{b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b}"/> with <img alt="{m = O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bm+%3D+O%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{m = O(\log n)}"/> then SWP would fall with the best possible logarithmic size, nullifying anything like Zachary Chase’s improvement from <img alt="{m = \tilde{O}(n^{2/5})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bm+%3D+%5Ctilde%7BO%7D%28n%5E%7B2%2F5%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{m = \tilde{O}(n^{2/5})}"/> to <img alt="{m = \tilde{O}(n^{1/3})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bm+%3D+%5Ctilde%7BO%7D%28n%5E%7B1%2F3%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{m = \tilde{O}(n^{1/3})}"/>. The “<img alt="{m = O(\log n)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bm+%3D+O%28%5Clog+n%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{m = O(\log n)}"/>” is not hiding any <img alt="{\log n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log n}"/> factors with a tilde—it is just a bare <img alt="{\log n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Clog+n%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\log n}"/> factor. The report claims this complete resolution, but it makes and then unmakes a point in a way we don’t follow. The point is that the idea of focusing on subsets <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S}"/> is not only independent of particular strings <img alt="{u,v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%2Cv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u,v}"/> but also independent of the lengths <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> of the string, except insofar as the maximum index in <img alt="{S}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S}"/> constrains the smallest <img alt="{m}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bm%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{m}"/> that works. But then the report states a theorem that invests <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> itself with significance that contradicts said point, so it just appears wrong.</p>
<p>
The report anyway does not appear either on Wiedermann’s publications page or his DBLP page. Its conclusion references a 2015 <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2015/09/03/open-problems-that-might-be-easy/">post</a> on this blog in which SWP was included, but we had not heard of this until Anoop’s comment. So it goes in our mistake file. We have been grappling all week with the subject of claims and mistakes on a much larger scale with complicated papers and techniques. In the old days, ideas and errors would be threshed out in-person at conferences and workshops and only the finished product would be visible to those outside the loop. Now we not only have Internet connectivity but also the pandemic has curtailed the “in-person” aspect. Thus we are not averse to promoting the threshing and wonder how best to extract the useful novelty from new attempts that likely have errors.</p>
<p>
The <img alt="{A_{m,b}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA_%7Bm%2Cb%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A_{m,b}}"/> construction is neat but has a weakness that can be framed as motivation for Dick’s idea in the rest of this post.  Adding more crossovers for a fixed <img alt="{m}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bm%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{m}"/> does not help separate any more strings: If <img alt="{S \cap R_{m,b}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS+%5Ccap+R_%7Bm%2Cb%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S \cap R_{m,b}}"/> and <img alt="{S \cap R_{m,c}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS+%5Ccap+R_%7Bm%2Cc%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S \cap R_{m,c}}"/> both have even cardinality then adding <em>two</em> crossovers at <img alt="{b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{b}"/> and <img alt="{c}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bc%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{c}"/> has no effect.  Intuitively speaking, all crossovers behave merely as the same non-unit element of the two-element group.  In particular, they commute with each other.  The idea moving forward is, can we get more interesting behavior from <em>non</em>-commutative groups that still yield small automata <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> separating given pairs of strings? </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Laws on Finite Groups </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Let’s start to explain a connection of SWP with finite groups. A <b>law</b> for a group <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> is 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  U = V, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++U+%3D+V%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  U = V, "/></p>
<p>where <img alt="{U,V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%2CV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U,V}"/> are words over <img alt="{\{ A,B \}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%7B+A%2CB+%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\{ A,B \}}"/>. We will think of <img alt="{U,V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%2CV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U,V}"/> as embeddings within the group of the binary strings <img alt="{u,v}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bu%2Cv%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{u,v}"/> we want to separate. The law says that <img alt="{U=V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%3DV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U=V}"/> for all substitutions of <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> and <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> as elements in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/>. Thus 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  AB = BA " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++AB+%3D+BA+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  AB = BA "/></p>
<p>is a law that holds in abelian groups. Every finite group <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> satisfies the law 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  A^{n} = 1, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++A%5E%7Bn%7D+%3D+1%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  A^{n} = 1, "/></p>
<p>where <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> is the size of the group. </p>
<p>
There has been quite a bit of research on laws for groups. </p>
<ul>
<li>
Some are on the complexity of checking if they hold. It is a famous result that with randomness one can check to see if <img alt="{AB=BA}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BAB%3DBA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{AB=BA}"/> with few tests. <p/>
</li><li>
Some are on the structure of laws. <p/>
</li><li>
Most relevant to SWP is the interest in the smallest size law that holds for all groups of <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> or less elements. The size of a law is the maximum of the length of the words <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> and <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{V}"/>.
</li></ul>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Laws and SWP </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Suppose that we wish to construct a FSA that can tell <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> from <img alt="{\beta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\beta}"/>. We assume that <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> and <img alt="{\beta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\beta}"/> are distinct <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> long strings over <img alt="{A,B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%2CB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A,B}"/>. Pick a finite group <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/>. The key is two observations: </p>
<ol>
<li>
If <img alt="{\alpha = \beta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha+%3D+%5Cbeta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha = \beta}"/> is <b>not</b> a law over <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/>, then we can set <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> and <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> to elements in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> so that 	<p/>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \alpha \neq \beta. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Calpha+%5Cneq+%5Cbeta.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \alpha \neq \beta. "/></p>
</li><li>
There is a FSA that can compute the values of <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> and <img alt="{\beta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\beta}"/> as elements in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> with order <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> states.
</li></ol>
<p>This then proves that we can separate the words <img alt="{A,B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%2CB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A,B}"/> with order the size of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{G}"/> states. </p>
<p>
<i>Warning</i> It is important that the FSA operates on <img alt="{\alpha}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Calpha%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\alpha}"/> and <img alt="{\beta}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cbeta%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\beta}"/> independently. Moreover, the FSA must run the same computation on these strings—the output must be different. </p>
<p>
I liked this approach since I hoped there would be useful results on laws in groups. There is quite a bit known. It would have been neat if there was a paper that proved: No law of length <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/> holds in all finite groups of size at most <img alt="{n^{1/4}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%5E%7B1%2F4%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n^{1/4}}"/>. Alas this is not true. Well not exactly. Our laws are of the form 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  U = V. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++U+%3D+V.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  U = V. "/></p>
<p>Since there are no inverses allowed in <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> and <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{V}"/> these are called <i>positive laws</i>. If we drop that restriction, then short laws do exist. There are laws of size <img alt="{O(n^{2/3})}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BO%28n%5E%7B2%2F3%7D%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{O(n^{2/3})}"/> that hold for all groups of order <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{n}"/>. But I believe it is still open whether positive laws can be small.</p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/f2_cayley_graph.png"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-17454" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/f2_cayley_graph.png?w=600"/></a></p>
<p/><h2> Positive Laws </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I (Dick) started to search the web about laws in groups. I quickly found a <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1609.03199.pdf">paper</a> by Andrei Bulatov, Olga Karpova, Arseny Shur, Konstantin Startsev on exactly this approach, titled “Lower Bounds on Words Separation: Are There Short Identities in Transformation Semigroups?” They study the problem, prove some results, and do some computer searches. They say: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> It is known that the shortest positive identity in the symmetric group on <img alt="{3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B3%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{3}"/> objects <img alt="{S_{3}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS_%7B3%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S_{3}}"/> is <img alt="{x^{2}y^{2} = y^{2}x^{2}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%5E%7B2%7Dy%5E%7B2%7D+%3D+y%5E%7B2%7Dx%5E%7B2%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{x^{2}y^{2} = y^{2}x^{2}}"/>. The shortest such identity in <img alt="{S_{4}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BS_%7B4%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{S_{4}}"/> has length <img alt="{11}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B11%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{11}"/>: 	</em></p><em>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x^{6}y^{2}xy^{2} = y^{2}xy^{2}x^{6}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x%5E%7B6%7Dy%5E%7B2%7Dxy%5E%7B2%7D+%3D+y%5E%7B2%7Dxy%5E%7B2%7Dx%5E%7B6%7D.+&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  x^{6}y^{2}xy^{2} = y^{2}xy^{2}x^{6}. "/></p>
</em><p><em/>
</p></blockquote>
<p>They also note that:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> The problem is to find upper bounds on the function <img alt="{Sep}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BSep%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{Sep}"/>. This problem is inverse to finding the asymptotics of the length of the shortest identity in full transformation semigroups <img alt="{T_{k}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BT_%7Bk%7D%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{T_{k}}"/>. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
I believe the last part of their statement is true, but perhaps misleading. I would argue that laws are related to SWP with a twist. The hope is that this twist is enough to make progress. Let me explain. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Laws with Errors </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I think there is hope that positive laws must be large, if we extend what it mean by a law. Suppose that we have a law 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  U_{1} \cdots U_{n} = V_{1} \cdots V_{n}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++U_%7B1%7D+%5Ccdots+U_%7Bn%7D+%3D+V_%7B1%7D+%5Ccdots+V_%7Bn%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  U_{1} \cdots U_{n} = V_{1} \cdots V_{n}. "/></p>
<p>Where <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> and <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{V}"/> are as before words over <img alt="{\{A,B\}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5C%7BA%2CB%5C%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{\{A,B\}}"/>. Assume that for all small groups this is always true when we set <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> and <img alt="{B}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BB%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{B}"/> to elements. </p>
<p>
We note however we can have the FSA do more than just substitutions. We could have it modify the <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> and <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{V}"/>. We can have the FSA make some changes to <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> and <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{V}"/>: Of course the FSA must do the same to <img alt="{U}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U}"/> and <img alt="{V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{V}"/>, and it must keep the number of states down. </p>
<p>
This means that the law <img alt="{U=V}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BU%3DV%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{U=V}"/> must be robust to modifications that can be done with few states. As examples, the FSA could: </p>
<ol>
<li>
The FSA could map <img alt="{A^{2} \rightarrow A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%5E%7B2%7D+%5Crightarrow+A%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A^{2} \rightarrow A}"/> and leave all others the same. <p/>
</li><li>
The FSA could map <img alt="{ABBBA}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BABBBA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{ABBBA}"/> to <img alt="{A}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BA%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{A}"/> when ever it sees this. <p/>
</li><li>
The FSA could delete the even letters. Thus <p/>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}   A^{6}B^{2}AB^{2} &amp;=&amp; B^{2}AB^{2}A^{6} \\  AAAAAA BB A BB &amp;=&amp; BB A BB AAAAAA \\  A~ A~ A~ B~ A ~ B &amp;=&amp; B~ A~ B ~ A~ A~ A \\  AAABA &amp;=&amp; BABAAA. \end{array} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++%5Cbegin%7Barray%7D%7Brcl%7D++%09A%5E%7B6%7DB%5E%7B2%7DAB%5E%7B2%7D+%26%3D%26+B%5E%7B2%7DAB%5E%7B2%7DA%5E%7B6%7D+%5C%5C+%09AAAAAA+BB+A+BB+%26%3D%26+BB+A+BB+AAAAAA+%5C%5C+%09A%7E+A%7E+A%7E+B%7E+A+%7E+B+%26%3D%26+B%7E+A%7E+B+%7E+A%7E+A%7E+A+%5C%5C+%09AAABA+%26%3D%26+BABAAA.+%5Cend%7Barray%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  \begin{array}{rcl}   A^{6}B^{2}AB^{2} &amp;=&amp; B^{2}AB^{2}A^{6} \\  AAAAAA BB A BB &amp;=&amp; BB A BB AAAAAA \\  A~ A~ A~ B~ A ~ B &amp;=&amp; B~ A~ B ~ A~ A~ A \\  AAABA &amp;=&amp; BABAAA. \end{array} "/></p>
</li></ol>
<p>Note the FSA could even add new letters. Thus it could 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  AB \rightarrow ACB, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++AB+%5Crightarrow+ACB%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  AB \rightarrow ACB, "/></p>
<p>where <img alt="{C}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="{C}"/> is a new letter. Thus 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  AAAAAA BB A BB = BB A BB AAAAAA " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++AAAAAA+BB+A+BB+%3D+BB+A+BB+AAAAAA+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  AAAAAA BB A BB = BB A BB AAAAAA "/></p>
<p>becomes 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  AAAAAA CBB A CBB = BB A C BB AAAAAA. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++AAAAAA+CBB+A+CBB+%3D+BB+A+C+BB+AAAAAA.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0" title="\displaystyle  AAAAAA CBB A CBB = BB A C BB AAAAAA. "/></p>
<p>And so on. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Can we get better lower bounds on positive laws if we require them to be resilient to such modifications? Ones that can be done by a small state FSA. What do you think?</p>
<p>
Again we thank Anoop and all our readers for stimulating comments.</p>
<p/><p><br/>
[changed wording in section 2 and improved transition to the rest]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-29T21:54:23Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-29T21:54:23Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Anoop SKM"/>
    <category term="blog milestone"/>
    <category term="comments"/>
    <category term="finite automata"/>
    <category term="groups"/>
    <category term="readers"/>
    <category term="separating words problem"/>
    <category term="SWP"/>
    <category term="thanks"/>
    <category term="upper bounds"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:20:42Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/28/full-time-position-at-universidad-catolica-de-chile-apply-by-october-7-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/28/full-time-position-at-universidad-catolica-de-chile-apply-by-october-7-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Full-time Position at Universidad Católica de Chile (apply by October 7, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Universidad Católica de Chile (UC) is offering one or more full-time positions at the assistant (tenure-track) or associate level. We invite applications from highly qualified candidates in Data Science, Machine Learning, Optimization, Statistics and Stochastics, although other areas from Computational Science and Engineering, Optimization and Applied Mathematics will also be considered. Website: http://imc.uc.cl/index.php/noticias/183-open-position-at-the-institute-for-mathematical-and-computational-engineering-uc Email: vacancysearch.imc@uc.cl</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Universidad Católica de Chile (UC) is offering one or more full-time positions at the assistant (tenure-track) or associate level. We invite applications from highly qualified candidates in Data Science, Machine Learning, Optimization, Statistics and Stochastics, although other areas from Computational Science and Engineering, Optimization and Applied Mathematics will also be considered.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://imc.uc.cl/index.php/noticias/183-open-position-at-the-institute-for-mathematical-and-computational-engineering-uc">http://imc.uc.cl/index.php/noticias/183-open-position-at-the-institute-for-mathematical-and-computational-engineering-uc</a><br/>
Email: vacancysearch.imc@uc.cl</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-28T18:02:24Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-28T18:02:24Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-08-28-what-is-a-cryptographic-hash-function/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-08-28-what-is-a-cryptographic-hash-function/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What is a Cryptographic Hash Function?</title>
    <summary>If you ever tried to understand Bitcoin, you’ve probably banged your head against the wall trying to understand what is a cryptographic hash function? The goal of this post is to: Give you a very simple mental model for how hash functions work, called the random oracle model Give you...</summary>
    <updated>2020-08-28T17:05:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-28T17:05:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T23:53:22Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/?p=276</id>
    <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2020/08/lattice-blog-reduction-part-iii-self-dual-bkz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Lattice Blog Reduction – Part III: Self-Dual BKZ</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is the third and last entry in a series of posts about lattice block reduction. See here and here for the first and second part, resp. In this post I will assume you have read the other parts. In … <a href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2020/08/lattice-blog-reduction-part-iii-self-dual-bkz/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This is the third and last entry in a series of posts about lattice block reduction. See <a class="uri" href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2020/04/lattice-blog-reduction-part-i-bkz/">here</a> and <a class="uri" href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/2020/05/lattice-blog-reduction-part-ii-slide-reduction/">here</a> for the first and second part, resp. In this post I will assume you have read the other parts.</p>
<p>In the first two parts we looked at BKZ and Slide reduction, the former being the oldest and most useful in practice, while the latter achieves the best provable bounds and has the cleaner analysis. While BKZ is a natural generalization of LLL, we have seen that the analysis of LLL does not generalize well to BKZ. One can view Slide reduction as a different generalization of LLL with the goal of also naturally generalizing its analysis. As we mentioned in the first part, there is another analysis technique based on dynamical systems, introduced in [HPS11]. Unfortunately, as applied to BKZ, there are some cumbersome technicalities and the resulting bounds on the output quality are not as tight as we would like them to be (i.e. as for Slide reduction). One can view the algorithm we are considering today – SDBKZ [MW16] – as a generalization of LLL that lends itself much easier to this dynamical systems analysis: it is simpler, cleaner and yields better results. Since part of the goal of today’s post is to demonstrate this very useful analysis technique, SDBKZ is a natural candidate.</p>
<h1 id="sec:sdbkz">SDBKZ</h1>
<p>Recall the two tools we’ve been relying on in the first two algorithms, SVP and DSVP reduction of projected subblocks:</p>



<div class="wp-block-group"><div class="wp-block-group__inner-container">
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-156" src="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/svp.png"/>Effect of a call to the DSVP oracle. GSO log norms of the input in black, of the output in blue. Note that the sum of the GSO log norms is a constant, so increasing the length of the last vector, decreases the (average of the) remaining vectors.</figure></div>
</div></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-262" src="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/dsvp.png"/>Effect of a call to the DSVP oracle. GSO log norms  of the input in black, of the output in blue. Note that the sum of the GSO log norms is a constant, so increasing the length of the last vector, decreases the (average of the) remaining vectors.</figure></div>



<p>We will use both of them again today. Like BKZ, a tour of SDBKZ starts by calling the SVP oracle on successive blocks of our basis. However, when we reach the end of the basis, we will not decrease the size of the window, since this is actually quite inconvenient for the analysis. Instead, we will keep the size of the window constant but switch to DSVP reduction, i.e. at the end of the BKZ tour we DSVP reduce the last block. This will locally maximize the last GSO vector in the basis, just as the first SVP call locally minimized the first vector of the basis. Then we will move the window successively backwards, mirroring a BKZ tour, but using DSVP reduction, until we reach the beginning of the basis again. At this point, we switch back to SVP reduction and move the window forward, etc. So SDBKZ runs in forward and backward tours.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-283" src="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/sdbkz-1024x825.png"/>SDBKZ in one picture: apply the SVP oracle to the projected blocks from start to finish and when you reach the end, apply the DSVP oracle to from finish to start. Repeat.</figure>



<p>A nice observation here is that the backward tour can be viewed equivalently as: 1) compute the reversed dual basis (i.e. the dual basis with reversed columns), 2) run a forward tour, 3) compute the primal basis again. The first of these two steps is self-inverse: computing the reversed dual basis of the reversed dual basis yields the original primal basis. This means step 3) is actually the same as step 1). So in effect, one can view SDBKZ as simply repeating the following two steps: 1) run a forward tour, 2) compute the reversed dual basis. So it doesn’t matter if we use the primal or the dual basis as input, the operations of the algorithm are the same. This is why it is called <em>Self-Dual</em> BKZ.</p>
<p>There is one caveat with this algorithm: it is not clear, when one should terminate. In BKZ and Slide reduction one can formulate clear criteria, when the algorithm makes no more progress anymore. In SDBKZ this is not the case, but the analysis will show that we can bound the number of required tours ahead of time.</p>
<h4 id="the-analysis">The Analysis</h4>
<p>We will start by analyzing the effect of a forward tour. Let <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}\)</span> be our input basis. The first call to the SVP oracle in a forward tour replaces <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{b}}_1\)</span> with the shortest vector in <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}_{[1,k]}\)</span>. This means that the new basis <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}’\)</span> satifies <span class="math inline">\(\| {\mathbf{b}}_1′ \| \leq \sqrt{\gamma_k} (\prod_{i=1}^k \|{\mathbf{b}}_i^* \|)^{1/k}\)</span> by Minkowski’s bound. Equivalently, this can be written as <span class="math display">\[\log \| {\mathbf{b}}_1′ \|
  \leq \log \sqrt{\gamma_k} + \frac1k (\sum_{i=1}^k \log \|{\mathbf{b}}_i^* \|).\]</span> So if we consider the <span class="math inline">\(\log \|{\mathbf{b}}_i^*\|\)</span> as variables, it seems like linear algebra could be useful here. So far, so good. The second step is more tricky though. We know that the next basis <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}”\)</span>, i.e. after the call to the SVP oracle on <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}’_{[2,k+1]}\)</span>, satisfies <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{b}}_1” = {\mathbf{b}}_1’\)</span> and <span class="math inline">\(\| ({\mathbf{b}}_2”)^* \| \leq \sqrt{\gamma_k} (\prod_{i=2}^{k+1} \|({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \|)^{1/k}\)</span>. Unfortunately, we have no control over <span class="math inline">\(\|({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \|\)</span> for <span class="math inline">\(i \in {2,\dots,k} \)</span>, since we do not know how the SVP oracle in the first call changed these vector. However, we do know that the lattice <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}_{[1,k+1]}\)</span> did not change in that call. So we can write <span class="math display">\[\prod_{i=2}^{k+1} \|({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \| = \frac{\prod_{i=1}^{k+1} \|{\mathbf{b}}_i^* \|}{\| {\mathbf{b}}’_1 \|}\]</span> and thus we obtain <span class="math display">\[\log \| ({\mathbf{b}}_2′)^* \|
  \leq \log \sqrt{\gamma_k} + \frac1k (\sum_{i=1}^{k+1} \log \|{\mathbf{b}}_i^* \| – \log \|{\mathbf{b}}’_1 \|).\]</span> Again, this looks fairly “linear algebraicy”, so it could be useful. But there is another issue now: in order to get an inequality purely in the input basis <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}\)</span>, we would like to use our inequality for <span class="math inline">\(\log \|{\mathbf{b}}_1′ \|\)</span> in the one for <span class="math inline">\(\log \| ({\mathbf{b}}_2′)^* \|\)</span>. But the coefficient of <span class="math inline">\(\log \|{\mathbf{b}}_1′ \|\)</span> is negative, so we would need a lower bound for <span class="math inline">\(\log \|{\mathbf{b}}_1′ \|\)</span>. Furthermore, we would like to use upper bounds for our variables later, since the analysis of a tour will result in upper bounds and we would like to apply it iteratively. For this, negative coefficients are a problem. So, we need one more modification: we will use a change of variable to fix this. Instead of considering the variables <span class="math inline">\(\log \| {\mathbf{b}}_i^* \|\)</span>, we let the input variables to our forward tour be <span class="math inline">\(x_i = \sum_{j &lt; k+i} \log \|{\mathbf{b}}^*_i \|\)</span> and the output variables <span class="math inline">\(y_i = \sum_{j \leq i} \log \|({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \|\)</span> for <span class="math inline">\(i \in [1,\dots,n-k]\)</span>. Clearly, we can now write our upper bound on <span class="math inline">\(\log \|({\mathbf{b}}’_1)^*\|\)</span> as <span class="math display">\[y_1 \leq \log \sqrt{\gamma_k} + \frac{x_1}{k}.\]</span> More generally, we have <span class="math display">\[\|({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \| \leq \sqrt{\gamma_k} \left(\frac{\prod_{j=1}^{i+k-1} \|{\mathbf{b}}_j^* \|}{\prod_{j=1}^{i-1} \|({\mathbf{b}}’_j)^* \|} \right)^{\frac1k}\]</span> which means for our variables <span class="math inline">\(x_i\)</span> and <span class="math inline">\(y_i\)</span> that <span class="math display">\[y_i = y_{i-1} + \log \| ({\mathbf{b}}’_i)^* \|
  \leq y_{i-1} + \log \sqrt{\gamma_k} + \frac{x_i – y_{i-1}}{k}
  = (1-\frac1k) y_{i-1} + \frac1k x_i + \log \sqrt{\gamma_k}.\]</span></p>
<p>Note that we can write each <span class="math inline">\(y_i\)</span> in terms of <span class="math inline">\(x_i\)</span> and the previous <span class="math inline">\(y_i\)</span> with only positive coefficients. So now we can apply induction to write each <span class="math inline">\(y_i\)</span> only in terms of the <span class="math inline">\(x_i\)</span>’s, which shows that <span class="math display">\[y_i = \frac1k \sum_{j=1}^i \omega^{i-j} x_j + (1-\omega)^i k \alpha\]</span> where we simplified notation a little by defining <span class="math inline">\(\alpha = \log \sqrt{\gamma_k}\)</span> and <span class="math inline">\(\omega = 1-\frac1k\)</span>. By collecting the <span class="math inline">\(x_i\)</span>’s and <span class="math inline">\(y_i\)</span>’s in a vector each, we have the vectorial inequality <span class="math display">\[{\mathbf{y}} \leq {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}} + {\mathbf{b}}\]</span> where <span class="math display">\[{\mathbf{b}} = \alpha k \left[
\begin{array}{c}
1 – \omega \\ 
\vdots \\
1 – \omega^{n-k} 
\end{array}\right]
\qquad\qquad
{\mathbf{A}} = \frac1k 
\left[
\begin{array}{cccc}
  1 &amp; &amp; &amp; \\
  \omega &amp; 1 &amp; &amp; \\
   \vdots &amp; \ddots &amp; \ddots &amp; \\
   \omega^{n-k-1} &amp; \cdots &amp; \omega &amp; 1
\end{array}
\right].\]</span></p>
<p>Now recall that after a forward tour, SDBKZ computes the reversed dual basis. Given the close relationship between the primal and the dual basis and their GSO, one can show that simply reversing the vector <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{y}}\)</span> will yield the right variables <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}’_i\)</span> to start the next “forward tour” (which is actually a backward tour, but on the dual). I.e. after reversing <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{y}}\)</span>, the variables represent the logarithm of the corresponding subdeterminants of the dual basis. (For this we assume for convenience and w.l.o.g. that the lattice has determinant 1; otherwise, there would be a scaling factor involved in this transformation.)</p>
<p>In summary, the effect on the vector <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}\)</span> of executing once the two steps, 1) forward tour and 2) computing the reversed dual basis, can be described as <span class="math display">\[{\mathbf{x}}’ \leq {\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}} + {\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{b}}\]</span> where <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{R}}\)</span> is the reversed identity matrix (i.e. the identity matrix with reversed columns). Iterating the two steps simply means we will be iterating the vectorial inequality above. So analyzing the affine dynamical system <span class="math display">\[{\mathbf{x}} \mapsto {\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}} + {\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{b}}\]</span> will allow us to deduce information about the basis after a certain number of iterations.</p>
<h4 id="small-digression-affine-dynamical-systems">Small Digression: Affine Dynamical Systems</h4>
<p>Consider some dynamical system <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}} \mapsto {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}} + {\mathbf{b}} \)</span> and assume it has exactly one fixed point, i.e. <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}^*\)</span> such that <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}}^* + {\mathbf{b}} = {\mathbf{x}}^* \)</span>. We can write any input <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}’\)</span> as <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}’ = {\mathbf{x}}^* + {\mathbf{e}}\)</span> for some “error vector” <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{e}}\)</span>. When applying the system to it, we get <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}’ \mapsto {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{x}}’ + {\mathbf{b}} = {\mathbf{x}}^* + {\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{e}}\)</span>. So the error vector <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{e}}\)</span> is mapped to <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{A}} {\mathbf{e}}\)</span>. Applying this <span class="math inline">\(t\)</span> times maps <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{e}}\)</span> to <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{A}}^t {\mathbf{e}}\)</span>, which means after <span class="math inline">\(t\)</span> iterations the error vector has norm <span class="math inline">\(\|{\mathbf{A}}^t {\mathbf{e}} \|_{p} \leq \|{\mathbf{A}}^t \|_{p} \| {\mathbf{e}} \|_{p} \)</span> (where <span class="math inline">\(\| \cdot \|_{p}\)</span> is the matrix norm induced by the vector <span class="math inline">\(p\)</span>-norm). If we can show that <span class="math inline">\(\|{\mathbf{A}} \|_p \leq 1 – \epsilon\)</span>, then <span class="math inline">\(\|{\mathbf{A}}^t \|_p \leq \|A \|^t \leq (1-\epsilon)^t \leq e^{-\epsilon t}\)</span>, so the error vector will decay exponentially in <span class="math inline">\(t\)</span> with base <span class="math inline">\(e^{-\epsilon}\)</span> and the algorithm converges to the fixed point <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}^*\)</span>.</p>
<p>Back to our concrete system above. As we just saw, we can analyze its output quality by computing its fixed point and its running time by computing <span class="math inline">\(\|{\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{A}} \|_p\)</span> for some induced matrix <span class="math inline">\(p\)</span>-norm. Since this has been a lenghty post already, I hope you’ll trust me that our system above has a fixed point <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{x}}^*\)</span>, which can be written out explicitely in closed form. As a teaser, its first coordinate is <span class="math display">\[x^*_1 = \frac{(n-k)k}{k-1} \alpha.\]</span> This means that if the algorithm converges, it will converge to a basis such that <span class="math inline">\(\sum_{j \leq k}\log \| {\mathbf{b}}_j^*\| \leq \frac{(n-k)k}{k-1} \log \sqrt{\gamma_k}\)</span>. Applying Minkowski’s Theorem to the first block <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{B}}_{[1,k]}\)</span> now shows that the shortest vector in this block satisfies <span class="math inline">\(\lambda_1({\mathbf{B}}_{[1,k]}) \leq \sqrt{\gamma_k}^{\frac{n-1}{k-1}}\)</span>. Note that the next forward tour will find a vector of such length. Recall that we assumed that our lattice has determinant 1, so this is exactly the Hermite factor achieved by Slide reduction, but for arbitrary block size (we do not need to assume that <span class="math inline">\(k\)</span> divides <span class="math inline">\(n\)</span>) and better than what we can achieve for BKZ (even using the same technique). Moreover, the fixed point actually gives us more information: the other coordinates (that I have ommited here) allow us control over all but <span class="math inline">\(k\)</span> GSO vectors and by terminating the algorithm at different positions, it allows us to choose which vectors we want control over.</p>
<p>It remains to show that the algorithm actually converges and figure out how fast. It is fairly straight-forward to show that <span class="math display">\[\|{\mathbf{R}} {\mathbf{A}}\|_{\infty} = \|{\mathbf{A}}\|_{\infty} = 1 – \omega^{n-k} \approx e^{-\frac{n-k}{k}}.\]</span> (Consider the last row of <span class="math inline">\({\mathbf{A}}\)</span>.) This is always smaller than 1, so the algorithm does indeed converge. For <span class="math inline">\(k = \Omega(n)\)</span> this is bounded far enough from 1 such that the system will converge to the fixed point up to an arbitrary constant in a number of SVP calls that is polynomial in <span class="math inline">\(n\)</span>. Using another change of variable [N16] or considering the relative error instead of the absolute error [MW15], one can show that this also holds for smaller <span class="math inline">\(k\)</span>.</p>
<p>As mentioned before, this type of analysis was introduced in [HPS11] and has inspired new ideas even in the heuristic analysis of BKZ. In particular, one can predict the behavior of BKZ by simply running such a dynamical system on typical inputs (and making some heuristic assumptions). This idea has been and is being used extensively in cryptanalysis and in optimizing parameters of state-of-the-art algorithms.</p>
<p>Finally, a few last words on SDBKZ: we have seen that it achieves a good Hermite factor, but what can we say about the approximation factor? I actually do not know if the algorithm achieves a good approximation factor and also do not see a good way to analyze it. However, there is a reduction [L86] from achieving approximation factor <span class="math inline">\(\alpha\)</span> to achieving Hermite factor <span class="math inline">\(\sqrt{\alpha}\)</span>. So SDBKZ can be used to achieve approximation factor <span class="math inline">\(\gamma_k^{\frac{n-1}{k-1}}\)</span>. This is a little unsatisfactory in two ways: 1) the reduction results in a different algorithm, and 2) the bound is a little worse than the factor achieved by slide reduction, which is <span class="math inline">\(\gamma_k^{\frac{n-k}{k-1}}\)</span>. On a positive note, a recent work [ALNS20] has shown that, due to the strong bound on the Hermite factor, SDBKZ can be used to generalize Slide reduction to arbitrary block size <span class="math inline">\(k\)</span> in a way to achieve the approximation factor <span class="math inline">\(\gamma_k^{\frac{n-k}{k-1}}\)</span>. Another recent work [ABFKSW20] exploited the fact that SDBKZ allows to heuristically predict large parts of the basis to achieve better bounds on the running time of the SVP oracle.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Lov<span>á</span>sz. An Algorithmic Theory of Numbers, Graphs and Convexity. 1986</p></li>
<li><p>Hanrot, Pujol, Stehlé. Analyzing blockwise lattice algorithms using dynamical systems. CRYPTO 2011</p></li>
<li><p>Micciancio, Walter. Practical, predictable lattice basis reduction – Full Version. <a class="uri" href="http://eprint.iacr.org/2015/1123">http://eprint.iacr.org/2015/1123</a></p></li>
<li><p>Micciancio, Walter. Practical, predictable lattice basis reduction. EUROCRYPT 2016</p></li>
<li><p>Neumaier. Bounding basis reduction properties. Designs, Codes and Cryptography 2016</p></li>
<li><p>Aggarwal, Li, Nguyen, Stephens-Davidowitz. Slide Reduction, Revisited—Filling the Gaps in SVP Approximation. CRYPTO 2020</p></li>
<li><p>Albrecht, Bai, Fouque, Kirchner, Stehlé, Wen. Faster Enumeration-based Lattice Reduction: Root Hermite Factor <span class="math inline">\(k^{(1/(2k))}\)</span> in Time <span class="math inline">\(k^{(k/8 + o(k))}\)</span>. CRYPTO 2020</p></li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-28T11:56:55Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-28T11:56:55Z</published>
    <category term="General"/>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Walter</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu</id>
      <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>What's New at the Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing.</subtitle>
      <title>Calvin Café: The Simons Institute Blog</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T23:52:19Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/26/postdoc-at-uc-berkeley-apply-by-september-10-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/26/postdoc-at-uc-berkeley-apply-by-september-10-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at UC Berkeley (apply by September 10, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Please send a cover letter, CV, and research statement to the email below. In CV please list at least 3 references. In cover letter please identify faculty of interest. Also, have references submit letters to the e-mail below, with your name in the subject line. Multiple opportunities available; earliest deadline requires nomination by September 10th. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Please send a cover letter, CV, and research statement to the email below. In CV please list at least 3 references. In cover letter please identify faculty of interest. Also, have references submit letters to the e-mail below, with your name in the subject line. Multiple opportunities available; earliest deadline requires nomination by<br/>
September 10th.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="http://theory.cs.berkeley.edu/postdoc.html">http://theory.cs.berkeley.edu/postdoc.html</a><br/>
Email: tcs-postdoc-inquiries@lists.eecs.berkeley.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-26T04:54:53Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-26T04:54:53Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=790</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2020/08/25/my-monitor-setup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>My monitor setup</title>
    <summary>In the not-distant future there will be a single monitor that gets you the best of both worlds. For the contemporaneous, I maintain that the above is the best monitor setup available to us in 2020. I use the tiny E-ink monitor as much as possible, including now, for my blitz matches on chess.com, and […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img alt="" class="wp-image-792" src="https://emanueleviola.files.wordpress.com/2020/08/webcam-toy-photo7.jpg?w=800"/></figure>

<p>In the not-distant future there will be a single monitor that gets you the best of both worlds. For the contemporaneous, I maintain that the above is the best monitor setup available to us in 2020. I use the tiny E-ink monitor as much as possible, including now, for my blitz matches on chess.com, and of course for writing and sometimes reviewing papers. But as I mentioned earlier unfortunately for certain bureaucratic tasks that not all of us can skip altogether you just need a bigger monitor with color. So I push a button on the hdmi switch, and the image blasts open on the 30-inch screen, <em>m’illumino d’immenso</em>, and suddenly the mouse feels like the interface from <em>Minority Reports</em>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-25T19:35:48Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-25T19:35:48Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="health"/>
    <category term="tech"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:21:04Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://differentialprivacy.org/colt2020/</id>
    <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/colt2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Conference Digest - COLT 2020</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/">COLT 2020</a> was held online in July, and featured nine papers on differential privacy, as well as a keynote talk by Salil Vadhan.
While differential privacy has always had a home in the COLT community, it seems like this year was truly exceptional in terms of the number of results.
We link all the content below, including pointers to the papers, videos on Youtube, and the page on the conference website. 
Please let us know if we missed any papers on differential privacy, either in the comments below or by email.</p>

<h2 id="keynote">Keynote</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/speaker_1.html">The Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4bpFDpT1t7I">video</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://salil.seas.harvard.edu/">Salil Vadhan</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="papers">Papers</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.08743">Domain Compression and its Application to Randomness-Optimal Distributed Goodness-of-Fit</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dgGdARyU6oY">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_96.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://people.ece.cornell.edu/acharya/">Jayadev Acharya</a>, <a href="http://www.cs.columbia.edu/~ccanonne/">Clément L. Canonne</a>, <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~yjhan/">Yanjun Han</a>, <a href="http://www.zitengsun.com/">Ziteng Sun</a>, <a href="https://ece.iisc.ac.in/~htyagi/">Himanshu Tyagi</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2003.04509">Closure Properties for Private Classification and Online Prediction</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U9hqJH6sEyY">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_320.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://web.math.princeton.edu/~nalon/">Noga Alon</a>, <a href="https://www.cs.bgu.ac.il/~beimel/">Amos Beimel</a>, <a href="http://www.cs.technion.ac.il/~shaymrn/">Shay Moran</a>, <a href="https://www.uri.co.il/">Uri Stemmer</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01452">Pan-Private Uniformity Testing</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yMXAjEGDXdI">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_141.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="http://amin.kareemx.com/">Kareem Amin</a>, <a href="https://www.majos.net/">Matthew Joseph</a>, <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/jieming-mao">Jieming Mao</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.01100">Efficient, Noise-Tolerant, and Private Learning via Boosting</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xCh7oZKcINs">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_304.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://cs-people.bu.edu/mbun/">Mark Bun</a>, <a href="https://marco.ntime.org/">Marco L. Carmosino</a>, <a href="http://cseweb.ucsd.edu/~jlsorrel/">Jessica Sorrell</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.10541">PAC Learning with Stable and Private Predictions</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jZlgmBUQ4nU">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_37.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://yuvaldagan.wordpress.com/">Yuval Dagan</a>, <a href="http://vtaly.net/">Vitaly Feldman</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09465">Locally Private Hypothesis Selection</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MGeBYQ7lJYw">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_5.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/sigopi/">Sivakanth Gopi</a>, <a href="http://www.gautamkamath.com/">Gautam Kamath</a>, <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/people/jakul/">Janardhan D. Kulkarni</a>, <a href="http://www.cs.toronto.edu/~anikolov/">Aleksandar Nikolov</a>, <a href="https://zstevenwu.com/">Zhiwei Steven Wu</a>, <a href="https://huanyuzhang.github.io/">Huanyu Zhang</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2002.09464">Private Mean Estimation of Heavy-Tailed Distributions</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6NVuAZqxrSE">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_6.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="http://www.gautamkamath.com/">Gautam Kamath</a>, <a href="http://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/vikrantsinghal/">Vikrant Singhal</a>, <a href="https://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/jullman/">Jonathan Ullman</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.10137">Privately Learning Thresholds: Closing the Exponential Gap</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uGTfJsJAkh0">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_219.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="http://www.cs.tau.ac.il/~haimk/">Haim Kaplan</a>, <a href="https://www.cs.huji.ac.il/~katrina/">Katrina Ligett</a>, <a href="https://www.tau.ac.il/~mansour/">Yishay Mansour</a>, <a href="http://www.wisdom.weizmann.ac.il/~naor/">Moni Naor</a>, <a href="https://www.uri.co.il/">Uri Stemmer</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.09122">Reasoning About Generalization via Conditional Mutual Information</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c5fzeqiTwWk">video</a>, <a href="https://www.learningtheory.org/colt2020/virtual/papers/paper_98.html">page</a>)<br/>
<a href="http://www.thomas-steinke.net/">Thomas Steinke</a>, <a href="http://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/lydiazak/">Lydia Zakynthinou</a></p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-25T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-25T14:00:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Gautam Kamath</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://differentialprivacy.org</id>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Website for the differential privacy research community</subtitle>
      <title>Differential Privacy</title>
      <updated>2020-08-31T23:53:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/25/assistant-professor-tenure-track-and-professor-positions-in-computer-science-at-institute-of-science-and-technology-austria-apply-by-october-30-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/08/25/assistant-professor-tenure-track-and-professor-positions-in-computer-science-at-institute-of-science-and-technology-austria-apply-by-october-30-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor (tenure-track) and Professor positions in Computer Science at Institute of Science and Technology Austria (apply by October 30, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Institute of Science and Technology Austria (IST Austria) invites applications for several open positions in all areas of computer science. IST Austria values diversity and is committed to equal opportunity. We strive for increasing the number of women, particularly in fields where they are underrepresented, and therefore we strongly encourage female researchers to apply. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Institute of Science and Technology Austria (IST Austria) invites applications for several open positions in all areas of computer science.</p>
<p>IST Austria values diversity and is committed to equal opportunity. We strive for increasing the number of women, particularly in fields where they are underrepresented, and therefore we strongly encourage female researchers to apply.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://ist.ac.at/en/jobs/faculty/">https://ist.ac.at/en/jobs/faculty/</a><br/>
Email: faculty.recruiting@ist.ac.at</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-25T13:23:45Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-25T13:23:45Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:20:45Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7790</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/08/24/highlights-of-algorithms-halg-free-aug-31-sep-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Highlights of Algorithms (HALG) -free – Aug 31- Sep 2</title>
    <summary>[Guest post by Yossi Azar] The 5th Highlights of Algorithms conference (HALG 2020) will take place Aug 31- Sep 2, 2020. http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/ The Highlights of Algorithms conference is a forum for presenting the highlights of recent developments in algorithms and for discussing potential further advances in this area. The conference will provide a broad picture […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><em>[Guest post by Yossi Azar]</em></p>



<p>The 5th <strong>Highlights of Algorithms conference (HALG 2020)</strong> will take place Aug 31- Sep 2, 2020. <a href="http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/</a></p>



<p>The Highlights of Algorithms conference is a forum for presenting the highlights of recent developments in algorithms and for discussing potential further advances in this area. The conference will provide a broad picture of the latest research in algorithms through a series of invited talks, as well as short talks. <br/>Invited talks includes top algorithmic surveys and papers from FOCS/STOC/SODA/COLT/PODC/SPAA/ITCS/PODS (2019-20)</p>



<p><br/>PROGRAM<br/>The conference will take place online on Mon, Aug 31-Wed, Sep 2 from 12:00 noon until 19:30 CEST (Europe time) <a href="http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/programme" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/programme</a></p>



<p>The short contributed talk are on Sep 1-2, 9:45-11:30 CEST <a href="http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/shorttalks" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">http://highlightsofalgorithms.org/shorttalks</a></p>



<p>REGISTRATION<br/>Registration is free but mandatory<br/>Please register on our webpage: <a href="https://highlightsofalgorithms2020.ethz.ch/registration" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://highlightsofalgorithms2020.ethz.ch/registration</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-08-24T19:17:23Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-24T19:17:23Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:20:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2020/08/24/ideal-special-quarter-theory-of-deep-learning/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2020/08/24/ideal-special-quarter-theory-of-deep-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>IDEAL Special Quarter (Theory of Deep Learning)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">September 21 – December 12, 2020 Online (https://www.ideal.northwestern.edu/special-quarters/fall-2020/) https://www.ideal.northwestern.edu/special-quarters/fall-2020/registration There will be a Special Quarter on Theory of Deep Learning this Fall as a part of IDEAL – The Institute for Data, Econometrics, Algorithms, and Learning, runs jointly with TTIC and the University of Chicago. The Special Quarter will be entirely online, and take place … <a class="more-link" href="https://cstheory-events.org/2020/08/24/ideal-special-quarter-theory-of-deep-learning/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">IDEAL Special Quarter (Theory of Deep Learning)</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-08-24T16:02:27Z</updated>
    <published>2020-08-24T16:02:27Z</published>
    <category term="other"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2020-09-01T22:21:14Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
