<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2022-01-05T02:38:51Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info/?p=1612</id>
    <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/2022/01/news-for-december-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>News for December 2021</title>
    <summary>Happy 2022 everyone! We now cover the last papers of 2021. Our readers have pointed out a number of papers from previous months that we missed (sorry). To adequately cover (and publicize) these papers, we’ve decided to just incorporate those papers on this post rather than update previous posts. We have a breakthrough on Locally […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Happy 2022 everyone! We now cover the last papers of 2021. Our readers have pointed out a number of papers from previous months that we missed (sorry). To adequately cover (and publicize) these papers, we’ve decided to just incorporate those papers on this post rather than update previous posts. </p>



<p>We have a breakthrough on Locally Testable Codes, sublinear algorithms for testing pattern freeness, new thoughts on convexity testing, and a perspective on sampling community structure. And here’s the final list for 2021.</p>



<p><strong>Locally Testable Codes with constant rate, distance, and locality</strong> by Irit Dinur, Shai Evra, Ron Livne, Alexander Lubotzky, and Shahar Mozes (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/151/">ECCC</a>, posted Nov 2021). A Locally Testable Code (LTC) is one where the set of codewords has a property tester. The study of LTCs started with the PCP theorem, but blossomed into a deep research agenda. The holy grail is a \(c^3\)-LTC: one with constant rate, constant distance, and constant query property tester. Just to recall, the rate \(r \in (0,1)\) is the ratio of the message length to the encoding length. The distance \(\delta \in (0,1)\) is the (normalized) Hamming distance between codewords (we typically expect this to be constant for an error correcting code). And, most familiar to us, \(q\) is the number of queries required to property test codewords. The aim is to get all these parameters to be constants independent of the message length. The classic linearity test of BLR basically proves that the Hadamard code is 3-query testable. But the Hadamard code has poor (exponentially small) rate. Low-degree tests prove that Reed-Muller codes are constant-query testable, but they have inverse polynomial rate. Further work constructed LTCs with inverse polylogarithmic rate, meaning that the encoding has length \(n\cdot poly(\log n)\) for message length \(n\). There was even some belief that any LTC must have a rate going to zero. This paper invalidates that belief, and gives a truly \(c^3\)-construction. The construction is based on a 2-dimensional simplicial complex based on Cayley graphs. This is basically a graph with hyperedges corresponding to “squares” of vertices. Concurrent and independent work of <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2012.09271.pdf">Breuckmann-Ebedhardt</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03654">Panteleev-Kalachev</a> also have similar constructions, though their perspective is of quantum codes.</p>



<p><strong>On the Locally Testable Code of Dinur et al. (2021)</strong> by Oded Goldreich (<a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/175/">ECCC</a>). As the title says, this short paper gives a high level discussion of the previous result. It abstracts out some of the graph theoretic aspects, to explain connections to more combinatorial constructions. The construction and analysis is based on expander codes. These codes (e.g. low-density parity check, LDPC codes) have constant rate and distance, but we do not know how to test them. A string far from a codeword might only fail on (say) one parity check constraint. Interpreting the Dinur et al as an expander code, we essentially get a collection of correlated parity constraints. Hence, a string that is far from a codeword violates many constraints, leading to a tester. (Of course, this is an extremely watered down version of the analysis idea.) The construction takes two Cayley graphs on a non-Abelian group (which form the vertices). Specific 4-cycles in this graph (together with a constant sized tensor code) are used to make the final codewords.</p>



<p><strong>Strongly Sublinear Algorithms for Testing Pattern Freeness</strong> by Ilan Newman and Nithin Varma (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.04856">arXiv</a>, posted Jun 2021). Pattern freeness is a major generalization of monotonicity testing. The input is (query access to) a function \(f: [n] \mapsto \mathbb{R}\). Let \(\pi: [k] \mapsto [k]\) be a permutation. The input is \(pi\)-free if no restriction of \(f\) to \(k\) elements induces the permutation \(pi\). <a href="http://cs.haifa.ac.il/~ilan/online-papers/permutations.pdf">Newman-Rabinovich-Rajendraprasad-Sohler</a> introduced this problem. When \(k=2\), this property is precisely monotonicity, for which (many) \(O(\varepsilon^{-1} \log n)\) property testers are known. Is such a bound achievable for \(k \geq 3\)? Interestingly, for non-adaptive algorithms, an optimal bound of \(\Theta(n^{1-1/(k-1)})\) (ignoring, \(\varepsilon, k\) dependencies) was achieved by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.10660">Ben-Eliezer and Canonne</a>. This papers shows that there is an adaptive algorithm that makes \(n^{o(1)}\) queries, thereby proving a separation between adaptive and non-adaptive algorithms. A key idea is to visualize the input as a set of points in the plane, and construct a coarse grid that partitions the points. There is a highly non-trivial case analysis on top of this that leads to a \(O(\sqrt{n})\)-query algorithm (this already beats the non-adaptive lower bound).</p>



<p><strong>Parameterized Convexity Testing</strong> by Abhiruk Lahiri, Ilan Newman, and Nithin Varma (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.13012">arXiv</a>, posted Oct 2021). Given a function \(f:[n] \mapsto \mathbb{R}\), the property of interest is (discrete) convexity. The discrete derivatives should be monotonically non-decreasing. It is known that there is a \(O(\varepsilon^{-1}\log n)\) query non-adaptive tester for this property. This paper studies this problem from the perspective of parameterized property testing, where the range is restricted. The main result is that if the number of distinct discrete derivates is at most \(s\), there is a \(O(\varepsilon^{-1} \log s)\) query non-adaptive tester. Moreover, this bound is optimal even for adaptive algorithms. This picture parallels that of monotonicity. Interestingly, when there are only two distinct discrete derivatives, the tester can be made deterministic.</p>



<p><strong>Modularity and edge sampling</strong> by Colin McDiarmid and Fiona Skerman (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.13190">arXiv</a>). Not your typical sublinear algorithms paper, but certainly of interest to us. The main problem is to understand when a random samples of edges in a graph can reveal information about the “community structure”. The modularity of a graph is a measure of this structure. Essentially, a partition has low modularity if the number of edges crossing the partition is close to that of a random graph with the same degree distribution. A partition of high modularity has significant fewer edges, and is thus a valid “clustering” of the graph. The modularity of the graph is obtained by maximizing over partitions. (The normalization of modularity is chosen so that the partition generally has a constant number of sets.) This paper proves a concentration inequality for the modularity of a constant sample of uniform random edges. The modularity of a sample of \(\Theta(\varepsilon^{-5})\) edges is an additive \(\varepsilon\)-approximation of the overall modularity, whp.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-04T23:42:02Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-04T23:42:02Z</published>
    <category term="Monthly digest"/>
    <author>
      <name>Seshadhri</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://ptreview.sublinear.info</id>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://ptreview.sublinear.info" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>The latest in property testing and sublinear time algorithms</subtitle>
      <title>Property Testing Review</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T00:21:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/04/faculty-positions-in-human-centered-design-at-the-uc-san-diego-design-lab-assistant-and-associate-professor-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-18-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/04/faculty-positions-in-human-centered-design-at-the-uc-san-diego-design-lab-assistant-and-associate-professor-at-university-of-california-san-diego-apply-by-january-18-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty Positions in Human-Centered Design at the UC San Diego Design Lab (Assistant and Associate Professor) at University of California – San Diego (apply by January 18, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Design Lab at UC San Diego seeks candidates for tenure-track Assistant Professor and tenured Associate Professor faculty positions across multiple disciplines to begin July 1, 2022. We especially seek scholars who engage major societal issues at the intersections of Blackness, Indigeneity, race, migration, gender, sexuality, disability, class and other manifestations of power and difference. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Design Lab at UC San Diego seeks candidates for tenure-track Assistant Professor and tenured Associate Professor faculty positions across multiple disciplines to begin July 1, 2022. We especially seek scholars who engage major societal issues at the intersections of Blackness, Indigeneity, race, migration, gender, sexuality, disability, class and other manifestations of power and difference.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://cse.ucsd.edu/index.php/administration/human-resources/recruitment/faculty-position/assistant-and-associate-professor">https://cse.ucsd.edu/index.php/administration/human-resources/recruitment/faculty-position/assistant-and-associate-professor</a><br/>
Email: nherrera@eng.ucsd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-04T19:58:43Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-04T19:58:43Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/003</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/003" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-003 |  On Semi-Algebraic Proofs and Algorithms | 

	Robert Robere, 

	Noah Fleming, 

	Mika Göös, 

	Stefan Grosser</title>
    <summary>We give a new characterization of the Sherali-Adams proof system, showing that there is a degree-$d$ Sherali-Adams refutation of an unsatisfiable CNF formula $C$ if and only if there is an $\varepsilon &gt; 0$ and a degree-$d$ conical junta $J$ such that $viol_C(x) - \varepsilon = J$, where $viol_C(x)$ counts the number of falsified clauses of $C$ on an input $x$. Using this result we show that the linear separation complexity, a complexity measure recently studied by Hrubeš (and independently by de Oliveira Oliveira and Pudlák under the name of weak monotone linear programming gates), monotone feasibly interpolates Sherali-Adams proofs; this sharpens a recent feasible interpolation result due to Hakoniemi.

We then investigate separation results for $viol_C(x) - \varepsilon$. In particular, we give a family of unsatisfiable CNF formulas $C$ which have polynomial-size and small-width resolution proofs, but for which any representation of $viol_C(x) - 1$ by a conical junta requires degree $\Omega(n)$; this resolves an open question of Filmus, Mahajan, Sood, and Vinyals. Since Sherali-Adams can simulate resolution, this separates the non-negative degree of $viol_C(x) - 1$ and $viol_C(x) - \varepsilon$ for arbitrarily small $\varepsilon &gt; 0$. Finally, by applying lifting theorems, we translate this lower bound into new separation results between extension complexity and monotone circuit complexity.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T18:55:39Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-04T18:55:39Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/04/postdoc-at-centre-for-quantum-technologies-apply-by-march-31-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/04/postdoc-at-centre-for-quantum-technologies-apply-by-march-31-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at Centre for Quantum Technologies (apply by March 31, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Centre for Quantum Technologies at the National University of Singapore invites applications for Postdoctoral Research Fellowships in its Computer Science Group. The applications are accepted any time of the year. There is no application deadline. Website: https://cs.quantumlah.org/postdocposter.pdf Email: dcsdiva@nus.edu.sg</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Centre for Quantum Technologies at the National University of Singapore invites applications for Postdoctoral Research Fellowships in its Computer<br/>
Science Group. The applications are accepted any time of the year. There is no application deadline.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://cs.quantumlah.org/postdocposter.pdf">https://cs.quantumlah.org/postdocposter.pdf</a><br/>
Email: dcsdiva@nus.edu.sg</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-04T15:47:27Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-04T15:47:27Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/04/postdocs-at-universite-de-lyon-ens-lyon-apply-by-january-11-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/04/postdocs-at-universite-de-lyon-ens-lyon-apply-by-january-11-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdocs at Université de Lyon / ENS Lyon (apply by January 11, 2022)</title>
    <summary>Two postdoctoral positions in mathematics, computer science and their interactions are open for the period 2022-2024. The previous deadline of January 4 has just been postponed by one week. Website: https://milyon.universite-lyon.fr/postdoctoral-positions-2022-2024-130160.kjsp?RH=1571748911317 Email: [guillaume.hanrot,nicolas.trotignon]@ens-lyon.fr</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Two postdoctoral positions in mathematics, computer science and their interactions are open for the period 2022-2024. The previous deadline of January 4 has just been postponed by one week.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://milyon.universite-lyon.fr/postdoctoral-positions-2022-2024-130160.kjsp?RH=1571748911317">https://milyon.universite-lyon.fr/postdoctoral-positions-2022-2024-130160.kjsp?RH=1571748911317</a><br/>
Email: [guillaume.hanrot,nicolas.trotignon]@ens-lyon.fr</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-04T09:04:14Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-04T09:04:14Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00724</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00724" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Submodular Maximization with Limited Function Access</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Andrew Downie, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gharesifard:Bahman.html">Bahman Gharesifard</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Smith:Stephen_L=.html">Stephen L. Smith</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00724">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider a class of submodular maximization problems in which
decision-makers have limited access to the objective function. We explore
scenarios where the decision-maker can observe only pairwise information, i.e.,
can evaluate the objective function on sets of size two. We begin with a
negative result that no algorithm using only $k$-wise information can guarantee
performance better than $k/n$. We present two algorithms that utilize only
pairwise information about the function and characterize their performance
relative to the optimal, which depends on the curvature of the submodular
function. Additionally, if the submodular function possess a property called
supermodularity of conditioning, then we can provide a method to bound the
performance based purely on pairwise information. The proposed algorithms offer
significant computational speedups over a traditional greedy strategy. A
by-product of our study is the introduction of two new notions of curvature,
the $k$-Marginal Curvature and the $k$-Cardinality Curvature. Finally, we
present experiments highlighting the performance of our proposed algorithms in
terms of approximation and time complexity.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:42:40Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00613</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00613" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Squeeze: Efficient Compact Fractals for Tensor Core GPUs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/q/Quezada:Felipe_A=.html">Felipe A. Quezada</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Navarro:Crist=oacute=bal_A=.html">Cristóbal A. Navarro</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hitschfeld:Nancy.html">Nancy Hitschfeld</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bustos:Benjamin.html">Benjamin Bustos</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00613">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This work presents Squeeze, an efficient compact fractal processing scheme
for tensor core GPUs. By combining discrete-space transformations between
compact and expanded forms, one can do data-parallel computation on a fractal
with neighborhood access without needing to expand the fractal in memory. The
space transformations are formulated as two GPU tensor-core accelerated thread
maps, $\lambda(\omega)$ and $\nu(\omega)$, which act as compact-to-expanded and
expanded-to-compact space functions, respectively. The cost of the maps is
$\mathcal{O}(\log_2 \log_s(n))$ time, with $n$ being the side of a $n \times n$
embedding for the fractal in its expanded form, and $s$ the linear scaling
factor. The proposed approach works for any fractal that belongs to the
Non-overlapping-Bounding-Boxes (NBB) class of discrete fractals, and can be
extended to three dimensions as well. Experimental results using a discrete
Sierpinski Triangle as a case study shows up to $\sim12\times$ of speedup and a
memory reduction factor of up to $\sim 315\times$ with respect to a GPU-based
expanded-space bounding box approach. These results show that the proposed
compact approach will allow the scientific community to efficiently tackle
problems that up to now could not fit into GPU memory.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:49:31Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00592</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00592" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Line Clipping in E3 with Expected Complexity O(1)</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Vaclav Skala <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00592">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A new line clipping algorithm against convex polyhedron in E3 with an
expected complexity O(1) is presented. The suggested approach is based on two
orthogonal projections to E2 co-ordinate system and on pre-processing of the
given polyhedron. The pre-processing enables to speed up solution
significantly. The proposed method is convenient for those applications when
many lines are clipped against constant convex polyhedron. Theoretical
considerations and experimental results are also presented.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:51:04Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00590</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00590" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Two New Algorithms for Line Clipping in E2 and Their Comparison</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Vaclav Skala, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bui:Duc_Huy.html">Duc Huy Bui</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00590">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Many algorithms for clipping a line by a rectangular area or a convex polygon
in E2 or by a non-convex or convex polyhedron in E3 have been published. The
line segment clipping by the rectangular window in E2 is often restricted to
the use of the Cohen-Sutherland (CS) algorithm or its modifications based on
some presumptions like small clipping window or more sophisticated coding
technique, etc. The line clipping problem solution is a bottleneck of many
packages and applications and, therefore, it would be desirable to use the
fastest algorithm even though it is more complex.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:50:38Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00587</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00587" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A New Algorithm for Pyramidal Clipping of Line Segments in E3</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Vaclav Skala, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bui:Duc_Huy.html">Duc Huy Bui</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00587">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A new algorithm for clipping a line segment against a pyramid in E3 is
presented. This algorithm avoids computation of intersection points which are
not end-points of the output line segment. It also allows solving all cases
more effectively. The performance of this algorithm is shown to be consistently
better than existing algorithms, including the Cohen-Sutherland, Liang-Barsky
and Cyrus-Beck algorithms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:52:46Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00549</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00549" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Efficient enumeration algorithms for annotated grammars</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Amarilli:Antoine.html">Antoine Amarilli</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jachiet:Louis.html">Louis Jachiet</a>, Martín Muñoz, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Riveros:Cristian.html">Cristian Riveros</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00549">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We introduce annotated grammars, an extension of context-free grammars which
allows annotations on terminals. Our model extends the standard notion of
regular spanners, and has the same expressiveness as the extraction grammars
recently introduced by Peterfreund. We study the enumeration problem for
annotated grammars: fixing a grammar, and given a string as input, enumerate
all annotations of the string that form a word derivable from the grammar. Our
first result is an algorithm for unambiguous annotated grammars, which
preprocesses the input string in cubic time and enumerates all annotations with
output-linear delay. This improves over Peterfreund's result, which needs
quintic time preprocessing to achieve this delay bound. We then study how we
can reduce the preprocessing time while keeping the same delay bound, by making
additional assumptions on the grammar. Specifically, we present a class of
grammars which only have one derivation shape for all outputs, for which we can
enumerate with quadratic time preprocessing. We also give classes generalizing
regular spanners for which linear time preprocessing suffices.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:43:07Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00539</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00539" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Mechanization of Incidence Projective Geometry in Higher Dimensions, a Combinatorial Approach</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Schreck:Pascal.html">Pascal Schreck</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Magaud:Nicolas.html">Nicolas Magaud</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Braun:David.html">David Braun</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00539">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Several tools have been developed to enhance automation of theorem proving in
the 2D plane. However, in 3D, only a few approaches have been studied, and to
our knowledge, nothing has been done in higher dimensions. In this paper, we
present a few examples of incidence geometry theorems in dimensions 3, 4, and
5. We then prove them with the help of a combinatorial prover based on matroid
theory applied to geometry.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:52:54Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00536</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00536" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A New Modeling of Classical Folds in Computational Origami</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Ida:Tetsuo.html">Tetsuo Ida</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Takahashi:Hidekazu.html">Hidekazu Takahashi</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00536">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper shows a cut along a crease on an origami sheet makes simple
modeling of popular traditional basic folds such as a squash fold in
computational origami. The cut operation can be applied to other classical
folds and significantly simplify their modeling and subsequent implementation
in the context of computational origami.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00535</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00535" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Maximizing the Sum of the Distances between Four Points on the Unit Hemisphere</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zeng:Zhenbing.html">Zhenbing Zeng</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lu:Jian.html">Jian Lu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/x/Xu:Yaochen.html">Yaochen Xu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wang:Yuzheng.html">Yuzheng Wang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00535">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In this paper, we prove a geometrical inequality which states that for any
four points on a hemisphere with the unit radius, the largest sum of distances
between the points is 4+4*sqrt(2). In our method, we have constructed a
rectangular neighborhood of the local maximum point in the feasible set, which
size is explicitly determined, and proved that (1): the objective function is
bounded by a quadratic polynomial which takes the local maximum point as the
unique critical point in the neighborhood, and (2): the rest part of the
feasible set can be partitioned into a finite union of a large number of very
small cubes so that on each small cube the conjecture can be verified by
estimating the objective function with exact numerical computation.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:51:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00534</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00534" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On Automating Triangle Constructions in Absolute and Hyperbolic Geometry</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Vesna Marinković, Tijana Šukilović, Filip Marić <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00534">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We describe first steps towards a system for automated triangle constructions
in absolute and hyperbolic geometry. We discuss key differences between
constructions in Euclidean, absolute and hyperbolic geometry, compile a list of
primitive constructions and lemmas used for constructions in absolute and
hyperbolic geometry, build an automated system for solving construction
problems and test it on a corpus of triangle-construction problems. We also
provide an online compendium containing construction descriptions and
illustrations.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:51:30Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00533</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00533" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Realizations of Rigid Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Koutschan:Christoph.html">Christoph Koutschan</a>, Linz, Austria) <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00533">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A minimally rigid graph, also called Laman graph, models a planar framework
which is rigid for a general choice of distances between its vertices. In other
words, there are finitely many ways, up to isometries, to realize such a graph
in the plane. Using ideas from algebraic and tropical geometry, we derive a
recursive formula for the number of such realizations. Combining computational
results with the construction of new rigid graphs via gluing techniques, we can
give a new lower bound on the maximal possible number of realizations for
graphs with a given number of vertices.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:50:46Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00430</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00430" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Classifying Subset Feedback Vertex Set for $H$-Free Graphs</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Paesani:Giacomo.html">Giacomo Paesani</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Paulusma:Dani=euml=l.html">Daniël Paulusma</a>, Paweł Rzążewski <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00430">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>In the Feedback Vertex Set problem, we aim to find a small set $S$ of
vertices in a graph intersecting every cycle. The Subset Feedback Vertex Set
problem requires $S$ to intersect only those cycles that include a vertex of
some specified set $T$. We also consider the Weighted Subset Feedback Vertex
Set problem, where each vertex $u$ has weight $w(u)&gt;0$ and we ask that $S$ has
small weight. By combining known NP-hardness results with new polynomial-time
results we prove full complexity dichotomies for Subset Feedback Vertex Set and
Weighted Subset Feedback Vertex Set for $H$-free graphs, that is, graphs that
do not contain a graph $H$ as an induced subgraph.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00408</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00408" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Optimal Vertex Connectivity Oracles</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Pettie:Seth.html">Seth Pettie</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Saranurak:Thatchaphol.html">Thatchaphol Saranurak</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yin:Longhui.html">Longhui Yin</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00408">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A $k$-vertex connectivity oracle for undirected $G$ is a data structure that,
given $u,v\in V(G)$, reports $\min\{k,\kappa(u,v)\}$, where $\kappa(u,v)$ is
the pairwise vertex connectivity between $u,v$. There are three main measures
of efficiency: construction time, query time, and space. Prior work of Izsak
and Nutov shows that a data structure of total size $\tilde{O}(kn)$ can even be
encoded as a $\tilde{O}(k)$-bit labeling scheme so that vertex-connectivity
queries can be answered in $\tilde{O}(k)$ time. The construction time is
polynomial, but unspecified.
</p>
<p>In this paper we address the top three complexity measures: Space, Query
Time, and Construction Time. We give an $\Omega(kn)$-bit lower bound on any
vertex connectivity oracle. We construct an optimal-space connectivity oracle
in max-flow time that answers queries in $O(\log n)$ time, independent of $k$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:44:42Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00311</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00311" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Rough analysis of computation trees</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Moshkov:Mikhail.html">Mikhail Moshkov</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00311">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper deals with computation trees over an arbitrary structure
consisting of a set along with collections of functions and predicates that are
defined on it. It is devoted to the comparative analysis of three parameters of
problems with $n$ input variables over this structure: the complexity of a
problem description, the minimum complexity of a computation tree solving this
problem deterministically, and the minimum complexity of a computation tree
solving this problem nondeterministically. Rough classification of
relationships among these parameters is considered and all possible seven types
of these relations are enumerated. The changes of relation types with the
growth of the number $n$ of input variables are studied.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:37:22Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00234</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00234" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Asymptotic Experiments with Data Structures: Bipartite Graph Matchings and Covers</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Eason Li, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Brglez:Franc.html">Franc Brglez</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00234">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider instances of bipartite graphs and a number of asymptotic
performance experiments in three projects: (1) top movie lists, given databases
of movies and viewers, (2) maximum matchings, and (3) minimum set covers.
Experiments are designed to measure the asymptotic runtime performance of
abstract data types (ADTs) in three programming languages: Java, R, and C++.
The outcomes of these experiments may be surprising. In project (1), the best
ADT in R consistently outperforms all ADTs in public domain Java libraries,
including the library from Google. The largest movie list has $2^{20}$ titles.
In project (2), the Ford-Fulkerson algorithm implementation in R significantly
outperforms Java. The hardest instance has 88452 rows and 729 columns. In
project (3), a stochastic version of a greedy algorithm in R can significantly
outperform a state-of-the-art stochastic solver in C++ on instances with
$num\_rows \ge 300$ and $num\_columns \ge 3000$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:42:24Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00228</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00228" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dynamic Least-Squares Regression</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/j/Jiang:Shunhua.html">Shunhua Jiang</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Peng:Binghui.html">Binghui Peng</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Weinstein:Omri.html">Omri Weinstein</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00228">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A common challenge in large-scale supervised learning, is how to exploit new
incremental data to a pre-trained model, without re-training the model from
scratch. Motivated by this problem, we revisit the canonical problem of dynamic
least-squares regression (LSR), where the goal is to learn a linear model over
incremental training data. In this setup, data and labels $(\mathbf{A}^{(t)},
\mathbf{b}^{(t)}) \in \mathbb{R}^{t \times d}\times \mathbb{R}^t$ evolve in an
online fashion ($t\gg d$), and the goal is to efficiently maintain an
(approximate) solution to $\min_{\mathbf{x}^{(t)}} \| \mathbf{A}^{(t)}
\mathbf{x}^{(t)} - \mathbf{b}^{(t)} \|_2$ for all $t\in [T]$. Our main result
is a dynamic data structure which maintains an arbitrarily small constant
approximate solution to dynamic LSR with amortized update time $O(d^{1+o(1)})$,
almost matching the running time of the static (sketching-based) solution. By
contrast, for exact (or even $1/\mathrm{poly}(n)$-accuracy) solutions, we show
a separation between the static and dynamic settings, namely, that dynamic LSR
requires $\Omega(d^{2-o(1)})$ amortized update time under the OMv Conjecture
(Henzinger et al., STOC'15). Our data structure is conceptually simple, easy to
implement, and fast both in theory and practice, as corroborated by experiments
over both synthetic and real-world datasets.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:44:10Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00135</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.00135" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Geometric Complexity Theory -- Lie Algebraic Methods for Projective Limits of Stable Points</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1641254400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Adsul:Bharat.html">Bharat Adsul</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Sohoni:Milind.html">Milind Sohoni</a>, K V Subrahmanyam <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.00135">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Let $G$ be a connected reductive group acting on a complex vector space $V$
and projective space ${\mathbb P}V$. Let $x\in V$ and ${\cal H}\subseteq {\cal
G}$ be the Lie algebra of its stabilizer. Our objective is to understand points
$[y]$, and their stabilizers which occur in the vicinity of $[x]$. We construct
an explicit ${\cal G}$-action on a suitable neighbourhood of $x$, which we call
the local model at $x$. We show that Lie algebras of stabilizers of points in
the vicinity of $x$ are parameterized by subspaces of ${\cal H}$. When ${\cal
H}$ is reductive these are Lie subalgebras of ${\cal H}$. If the orbit of $x$
is closed this also follows from Luna's theorem. Our construction involves a
map connected to the local curvature form at $x$. We apply the local model to
forms, when the form $g$ is obtained from the form $f$ as the leading term of a
one parameter family acting on $f$. We show that there is a flattening ${\cal
K}_0$ of ${\cal K}$, the stabilizer of $f$ which sits as a subalgebra of ${\cal
H}$, the stabilizer $g$. We specialize to the case of forms $f$ whose
$SL(X)$-orbits are affine, and the orbit of $g$ is of co-dimension $1$. We show
that (i) either ${\cal H}$ has a very simple structure, or (ii) conjugates of
the elements of ${\cal K}$ also stabilize $g$ and the tangent of exit. Next, we
apply this to the adjoint action. We show that for a general matrix $X$, the
signatures of nilpotent matrices in its projective orbit closure (under
conjugation) are determined by the multiplicity data of the spectrum of $X$.
Finally, we formulate the path problem of finding paths with specific
properties from $y$ to its limit points $x$ as an optimization problem using
local differential geometry. Our study is motivated by Geometric Complexity
Theory proposed by the second author and Ketan Mulmuley.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-04T22:38:19Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8283</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/01/03/itc-2022-call-for-papers-guest-post-by-benny-applebaum/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>ITC 2022: Call for papers (guest post by Benny Applebaum)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Deal friends, We are happy to announce the third edition of the conference on Information-Theoretic Cryptography (ITC). Information-theoretic cryptography studies security in the presence of computationally unbounded adversaries and covers a wide array of topics at the intersection of cryptography, coding theory, information theory and theory of computation. Notable examples include randomness extraction and privacy … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/01/03/itc-2022-call-for-papers-guest-post-by-benny-applebaum/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">ITC 2022: Call for papers (guest post by Benny Applebaum)</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Deal friends,</p>



<p><br/>We are happy to announce the third edition of the conference on Information-Theoretic Cryptography (ITC). Information-theoretic cryptography studies security in the presence of computationally unbounded adversaries and covers a wide array of topics at the intersection of cryptography, coding theory, information theory and theory of computation. Notable examples include randomness extraction and privacy amplification, secret sharing,  secure multiparty computation and proof systems, private-information retrieval and locally decodable codes, authentication codes and non-malleable codes, differential privacy, quantum information processing, and information-theoretic foundations of physical-layer security.</p>



<p><br/>See <a href="https://itcrypto.github.io/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://itcrypto.github.io</a> for more information.</p>



<p>The conference will have two tracks: a conference track and a spotlight track. The conference track will operate like a traditional conference with the usual review process and published proceedings. The spotlight track consists of invited talks (not included in the proceedings) that highlight the most exciting recent advances in the area. We are soliciting nominations for spotlight talks from the community. (See the Call for Papers.)</p>



<p>ITC2022 will take place on July 5-7, 2022 in Boston, MA. We are planning for a hybrid online/in-person event.  The submission deadline is <strong>Jan 10, 2022</strong> and the call for papers (including a nomination procedure for the spotlight track) is available here: <a href="https://itcrypto.github.io/2022/2022cfp.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://itcrypto.github.io/2022/2022cfp.html</a>.</p>



<p>The Organizing Committee</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-03T21:40:19Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-03T21:40:19Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6202</id>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6202" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6202#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=6202" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">The demise of Scientific American: Guest post by Ashutosh Jogalekar</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Scott’s foreword One week ago, E. O. Wilson—the legendary naturalist and conservationist, and man who was universally acknowledged to know more about ants than anyone else in human history—passed away at age 92. A mere three days later, Scientific American—or more precisely, the zombie clickbait rag that now flaunts that name—published a shameful hit-piece, smearing […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><strong>Scott’s foreword</strong></p>



<p>One week ago, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._O._Wilson">E. O. Wilson</a>—the legendary naturalist and conservationist, and man who was universally acknowledged to know more about ants than anyone else in human history—passed away at age 92.  A mere three days later, <em>Scientific American</em>—or more precisely, the zombie clickbait rag that now flaunts that name—published a <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-complicated-legacy-of-e-o-wilson/">shameful hit-piece</a>, smearing Wilson for his “racist ideas” without, incredibly, so much as a single quote from Wilson, or any other attempt to substantiate its libel (see also <a href="https://whyevolutionistrue.com/2021/12/30/scientific-american-does-an-asinine-hit-job-on-e-o-wilson-calling-him-a-racist/">this response by Jerry Coyne</a>).  <em>SciAm</em>‘s <em>Pravda</em>-like attack included the following extraordinary sentence, which I thought worthy of <a href="https://physics.nyu.edu/faculty/sokal/transgress_v2/transgress_v2_singlefile.html">Alan Sokal’s <em>Social Text</em> hoax</a>:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>The so-called normal distribution of statistics assumes that there are default humans who serve as the standard that the rest of us can be accurately measured against.</p></blockquote>



<p>There are intellectually honest people who don’t know what the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normal_distribution">normal distribution</a> is.  There are no intellectually honest people who, not knowing what it is, figure that it must be something racist.</p>



<p>On Twitter, Laura Helmuth, the editor-in-chief now running <em>SciAm</em> into the ground, <a href="https://twitter.com/laurahelmuth/status/1476531766118682625">described</a> her magazine’s calumny against Wilson as “insightful” (the replies, including from Richard Dawkins, are fun to read).  I suppose it was as “insightful” as <em>SciAm</em>‘s <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/eric-lander-is-not-the-ideal-choice-for-presidential-science-adviser/">disgraceful attack</a> last year on Eric Lander, President Biden’s ultra-competent science advisor and a leader in the war on COVID, for … being a white male, which appears to have been E. O. Wilson’s crime as well.  (Think I must be misrepresenting the “critique” of Lander?  Read it!)</p>



<p>Anyway, in response to <em>Scientific American</em>‘s libel of Wilson, I wrote on my Facebook that I’ll no longer agree to write for or be interviewed by them (you can read my old stuff free of charge <a href="http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/The_Limits_of_Quantum_Computers.pdf">here</a> or <a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/cross-check/scott-aaronson-answers-every-ridiculously-big-question-i-throw-at-him/">here</a>), unless and until there’s a complete change of editorial direction.  I encourage all other scientists to commit likewise, thereby making it common knowledge that the entity that now calls itself “Scientific American” bears the same relation to the legendary home of Martin Gardner as does a corpse to a living being.  Fortunately, there are high-quality online venues (e.g., <em><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/">Quanta</a></em>) that partly fill the role that <em>Scientific American</em> abdicated.</p>



<p>After reading my Facebook post, my friend <a href="https://twitter.com/curiouswavefn?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor">Ashutosh Jogalekar</a> was inspired to post an essay of his own.  Ashutosh used to write regularly for <em>Scientific American</em>, until he was fired seven years ago over a <a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/the-curious-wavefunction/richard-feynman-sexism-and-changing-perceptions-of-a-scientific-icon/">column</a> in which he advocated acknowledging Richard Feynman’s flaws, including his arrogance and casual sexism, but also understanding those flaws within the context of Feynman’s whole life, including the tragic death of his first wife Arlene.  (Yes, that was really it!  Read the piece!)  Below, I’m sharing Ashutosh’s moving essay about E. O. Wilson with Ashutosh’s very generous permission. —<em>Scott Aaronson</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><strong>Guest Post by Ashutosh Jogalekar</strong></p>



<p>As some know, I was “fired” from Scientific American in 2014 for three “controversial” posts (among 200 that I had written for the magazine).  When I parted from the magazine I chalked up my departure to an unfortunate misunderstanding more than anything else.  I still respected some of the writers at the publication, and while I wore my separation as a badge of honor and in retrospect realized its liberating utility in enabling me to greatly expand my topical range, I occasionally still felt bad and wished things had gone differently.</p>



<p>No more.  Now the magazine has done me a great favor by allowing me to wipe the slate of my conscience clean. What happened seven years ago was not just a misunderstanding but clearly one of many first warning signs of a calamitous slide into a decidedly unscientific, irrational and ideology-ridden universe of woke extremism.  Its logical culmination two days ago was an absolutely shameless, confused, fact-free and purely ideological hit job on someone who wasn’t just a great childhood hero of mine but a leading light of science, literary achievement, humanism and biodiversity.  While Ed (E. O.) Wilson’s memory was barely getting cemented only days after his death, the magazine published an op-ed calling him a racist, a hit job endorsed and cited by the editor-in-chief as “insightful”.  One of the first things I did after reading the piece was buy a few Wilson books that weren’t part of my collection.</p>



<p>Ed Wilson was one of the gentlest, most eloquent, most brilliant and most determined advocates for both human and natural preservation you could find.  Under Southern charm lay hidden unyielding doggedness and immense stamina combined with a missionary zeal to communicate the wonders of science to both his fellow biologists and the general public.  His autobiography, “Naturalist”, is perhaps the finest, most literary statement of the scientific life I have read; it was one of a half dozen books that completely transported me when I read it in college.  In book after book of wide-ranging intellectual treats threading through a stunning diversity of disciplines, he sent out clarion calls for saving the planet, for enabling dialogue between the natural and the social sciences, for understanding each other better. In the face of unprecedented challenges to our fragile environment and continued barriers to interdisciplinary communication, this is work that likely will make him go down in history as one of the most important human beings who ever lived, easily of the same caliber and achievement as John Muir or Thoreau.  Even in terms of achievement strictly defined by accolades – the National Medal of Science, the Crafoord Prize which recognizes fields excluded by the Nobel Prize, and not just one but two Pulitzer Prizes – few scientists from any field in the 20th century can hold a candle to Ed Wilson.  My friend Richard Rhodes who knew Wilson for decades as a close and much-admired friend said that there wasn’t a racist bone in his body; Dick should know since he just came out with a first-rate biography of Wilson weeks before his passing.</p>



<p>The writer who wrote that train wreck is a professor of nursing at UCSF named Monica McLemore.  That itself is a frightening fact and should tell everyone how much ignorance has spread itself in our highest institutions.  She not only maligned and completely misrepresented Wilson but did not say a word about his decades-long, heroic effort to preserve the planet and our relationship with it; it was clear that she had little acquaintance with Wilson’s words since she did not cite any.  It’s also worth noting the gaping moral blindness in her article which completely misses the most moral thing Wilson did – spend decades advocating for saving our planet and averting a catastrophe of extinction, climate change and divisiveness – and instead focuses completely on his non-existent immorality.  This is a pattern that is consistently found among those urging “social justice” or “equity” or whatever else: somehow they seem to spend all their time talking about fictional, imagined immorality while missing the real, flesh-and-bones morality that is often the basis of someone’s entire life’s work.</p>



<p>In the end, the simple fact is that McLemore didn’t care about any of this.  She didn’t care because she had a political agenda and the facts did not matter to her, even facts as basic as the definition of the normal distribution in statistics.  For her, Wilson was some obscure white male scientist who was venerated, and that was reason enough for a supposed “takedown”.  And the editor of <em>Scientific American</em> supported and lauded this ignorant, ideology-driven tirade.</p>



<p>Ironically, Wilson would have found this ideological hit job all too familiar. After he wrote his famous book <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Sociobiology-Synthesis-Edward-Wilson-ebook/dp/B00L9XW7Q2">Sociobiology</a></em> in the 1970s, a volume in which, in a single chapter about human beings, he had the temerity to suggest that maybe, just maybe, human beings operate with the same mix of genes that other creatures do, the book was met by a disgraceful, below-the-belt, ideological response from Wilson’s far left colleagues Richard Lewontin and Stephen Jay Gould who hysterically compared his arguments to thinking that was well on its way down the slippery slope to that dark world where lay the Nazi gas chambers. The gas chamber analogy is about the only thing that’s missing from the recent hit job, but the depressing thing is that we are fighting the same battles in 2021 that Wilson fought forty years before, although turbocharged this time by armies of faithful zombies on social media. The sad thing is that Wilson is no longer around to defend himself, although I am not sure he would have bothered with a piece as shoddy as this one.</p>



<p>The complete intellectual destruction of a once-great science magazine is now clear as day.  No more should <em>Scientific American</em> be regarded as a vehicle for sober scientific views and liberal causes but as a political magazine with clearly stated ideological biases and an aversion to facts, an instrument of a blinkered woke political worldview that brooks no dissent. Scott Aaronson has taken a principled stand and said that after this proverbial last straw on the camel’s back, he will no longer write for the magazine or do interviews for them.  I applaud Scott’s decision, and with his expertise it’s a decision that actually matters.  As far as I am concerned, I now mix smoldering fury at the article with immense relief: the last seven years have clearly shown that leaving <em>Scientific American</em> in 2014 was akin to leaving the Soviet Union in the 1930s just before Stalin appointed Lysenko head biologist.  I could not have asked for a happier expulsion and now feel completely vindicated and free of any modicum of regret I might have felt.</p>



<p>To my few friends and colleagues who still write for the magazine and whose opinions I continue to respect, I really wish to ask: Why?  Is writing for a magazine which has sacrificed facts and the liberal voice of real science at the altar of political ideology and make believe still worth it?  What would it take for you to say no more?  As Oscar Wilde would say, one mistake like this is a mistake, two seems more like carelessness; in the roster of the last few years, this is “mistake” 100+, signaling that it’s now officially approved policy.  Do you think that being an insider will allow you to salvage the reputation of the magazine?  If you think that way, you are no different from the one or two moderate Republicans who think they can still salvage the once-great party of Lincoln and Eisenhower.  Both the GOP and <em>Scientific American</em> are beyond redemption from where I stand.  Get out, start your own magazine or join another, one which actually respects liberal, diverse voices and scientific facts; let us applaud you for it.  You deserve better, the world deserves better.  And Ed Wilson’s memory sure as hell deserves better.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update (from Scott):</span></strong> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=29778348">See here</a> for the Hacker News thread about this post.  I was amused by the conjunction of two themes: (1) people who were uncomfortable with my and Ashutosh’s expression of strong emotions, and (2) people who actually clicked through to the <em>SciAm</em> hit-piece, and then reported back to the others that the strong emotions were completely, 100% justified in this case.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-03T06:51:01Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-03T06:51:01Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Obviously I'm Not Defending Aaronson"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Rage Against Doofosity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <icon>https://scottaaronson.blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-Jacket-32x32.gif</icon>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2022-01-03T17:58:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-728035959634543419</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/728035959634543419/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/did-betty-white-die-in-2021why-do.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/728035959634543419" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/728035959634543419" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/did-betty-white-die-in-2021why-do.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Did Betty White  die in 2021?/Why do people have their `end-of-the-year' lists before the end of the year?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> I am looking at Parade Magazine's issue whose cover story is</p><p>                                          <i>We say goodbye to the stars we lost in 2021.</i></p><p>The date on the magazine is Dec 19-26. Betty White is not in it. Neither is Bishop Tutu. Why not? Maybe they did not die in 2021. No, that's not it.  They died after the magazine appeared. They also won't be in the issue a year from now which has cover story </p><p>                                          <i>We say goodbye to the stars we lost in 2022.</i></p><p>Why do magazines and TV shows have their <i>end-of-the-year </i>stuff before the end of the year? Because they want to beat the competition? Because they all do it, so its a race-to-the-bottom? Tradition? </p><p>This blog does the same--- we already posted our end-of-the-year post. Every year I worry that someone will prove P=NP or P NE NP between Dec 24 and Jan 1.  We don't have the Betty-White-Problem since the end-of-the-year post is based on when we blogged about it, not when it happened. So if  theorist X died on Dec 27 then we would do the blog obit in Jan, and would mention it in the end-of-the-year post for the next year. (This happened with Martin Kruskal who died on Dec 26, 2006.) </p><p>Why do we have our end-of-the-year post before the end of the year? Tradition! That might not be a good reason.  </p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-03T05:14:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-03T05:14:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T20:55:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/002</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/002" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-002 |  Extending Merge Resolution to a Family of Proof Systems | 

	Sravanthi Chede, 

	Anil Shukla</title>
    <summary>Merge Resolution (MRes [Beyersdorff et al. J. Autom. Reason.'2021]) is a recently introduced proof system for false QBFs. Unlike other known QBF proof systems, it builds winning strategies for the universal player within the proofs. Every line of this proof system consists of existential clauses along with countermodels. MRes stores the countermodels as merge maps. Merge maps are deterministic branching programs in which isomorphism checking is efficient as a result MRes is a polynomial time verifiable proof system.

In this paper, we introduce a family of proof systems MRes-$\mathcal{R}$ in which, the information of countermodels are stored in any pre-fixed complete representation $\mathcal{R}$, instead of merge maps. Hence corresponding to each possible complete representation $\mathcal{R}$, we have a sound and refutationally complete QBF-proof system in MRes-$\mathcal{R}$. To handle arbitrary representations for the strategies, we introduce consistency checking rules in MRes-$\mathcal{R}$ instead of isomorphism checking in MRes. As a result these proof systems are not polynomial time verifiable. Consequently, the paper shows that using merge maps is too restrictive and can be replaced with arbitrary representations leading to several interesting proof systems.

The paper also studies proof theoretic properties of the family of new proof systems MRes-$\mathcal{R}$. We show that eFrege+$\forall$red simulates all valid refutations from proof systems in MRes-$\mathcal{R}$. Since proof systems in MRes-$\mathcal{R}$ may use arbitrary representations, in order to simulate them, we first represent the steps used by the proof systems as a new simple complete structure. As a consequence, the corresponding proof system belonging to MRes-$\mathcal{R}$ is able to simulate all proof systems in MRes-$\mathcal{R}$. Finally, we simulate this proof system via eFrege+$\forall$red using the ideas from [Chew et al. ECCC.'2021].

On the lower bound side, we lift the lower bound result of regular MRes ([Beyersdorff et al. FSTTCS.'2020]) for all regular proof systems in MRes-$\mathcal{R}$. To be precise, we show that the completion principle formulas from [Jonata et al. Theor. Comput. Sci.'2015] which are shown to be hard for regular MRes in [Beyersdorff et al. FSTTCS.'2020], are also hard for any regular proof system in MRes-$\mathcal{R}$. Thereby, the paper lifts the lower bound of regular MRes to an entire class of proof systems, which use some complete representation, including those undiscovered, instead of merge maps.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-02T12:33:31Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-02T12:33:31Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/001</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/001" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-001 |  On (Simple) Decision Tree Rank | 

	Yogesh Dahiya, 

	Meena Mahajan</title>
    <summary>In the decision tree computation model for Boolean functions, the depth corresponds to query complexity, and size corresponds to storage space. The depth measure is the most well-studied one, and is known to be polynomially related to several non-computational complexity measures of functions such as certificate complexity. The size measure is also studied, but to a lesser extent. Another decision tree measure that has received very little attention is the minimal rank of the decision tree, first introduced by Ehrenfeucht and Haussler in 1989. This measure is not polynomially related to depth, and hence it can reveal additional information about the complexity of a function. It is characterised by the value of a Prover-Delayer game first proposed by Pudl{\'a}k and Impagliazzo in the context of tree-like resolution proofs. In this paper we study this measure further. We obtain upper and lower bounds on rank in terms of (variants of) certificate complexity. We also obtain upper and lower bounds on the rank for composed functions in terms of the depth of the outer function and the rank of the inner function. We compute the rank exactly for several natural functions and use them to show that all the bounds we have obtained are tight. We also observe that the size-rank relationship for decision trees, obtained by Ehrenfeucht and  Haussler, is tight upto constant factors.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-02T05:57:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-02T05:57:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6183</id>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6183" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6183#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=6183" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Book Review: “Viral” by Alina Chan and Matt Ridley</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Happy New Year, everyone! It was exactly two years ago that it first became publicly knowable—though most of us wouldn’t know for at least two more months—just how freakishly horrible is the branch of the wavefunction we’re on. I.e., that our branch wouldn’t just include Donald Trump as the US president, but simultaneously a global […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Happy New Year, everyone!</p>



<p>It was exactly two years ago that it first became publicly knowable—though most of us <em>wouldn’t</em> know for at least two more months—just how freakishly horrible is the branch of the wavefunction we’re on.  I.e., that our branch wouldn’t <em>just</em> include Donald Trump as the US president, but <em>simultaneously</em> a global pandemic far worse than any in living memory, and a world-historically bungled response to that pandemic.</p>



<p>So it’s appropriate that I just finished reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Viral-Search-COVID-19-Matt-Ridley/dp/006313912X/ref=cm_cr_arp_d_product_top?ie=UTF8">Viral: The Search for the Origin of COVID-19</a>, by Broad Institute genetics postdoc Alina Chan and science writer Matt Ridley.  Briefly, I think that this is one of the most important books so far of the twenty-first century.</p>



<p>Of course, speculation and argument about the origin of COVID goes back all the way to that fateful January of 2020, and most of this book’s information was already available in fragmentary form elsewhere.  And by their own judgment, Chan and Ridley don’t end their search with a smoking-gun: no Patient Zero, no Bat Zero, no security-cam footage of the beaker dropped on the Wuhan Institute of Virology floor.  Nevertheless, as far as I’ve seen, this is the first analysis of COVID’s origin to treat the question with the full depth, gravity, and perspective that it deserves.</p>



<p><em>Viral</em> is essentially a 300-page plea to follow every lead as if we actually wanted to get to the bottom of things, and in particular, yes, to take the possibility of a lab leak a hell of a lot more seriously than was publicly permitted in 2020.  (Fortuitously, much of this shift already happened as the authors were writing the book, but in June 2021 I was still <a href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=5542#comment-1893250">sneered at</a> for discussing the lab leak hypothesis on this blog.)  <em>Viral</em> is simultaneously a model of lucid, non-dumbed-down popular science writing and of cogent argumentation.  The authors never once come across like tinfoil-hat-wearing conspiracy theorists, railing against the sheeple with their conventional wisdom: they’re simply investigators carefully laying out what they’re confident should <em>become</em> conventional wisdom, with the many uncertainties and error bars explicitly noted.  If you read the book and your mind works anything like mine, be forewarned that you might come out agreeing with a lot of it.</p>



<p>I would say that <em>Viral</em> proves the following propositions beyond reasonable doubt:</p>



<ul><li>Virologists, including at Shi Zhengli’s group at WIV and at Peter Daszak’s EcoHealth Alliance, were engaged in <em>unbelievably</em> risky work, including collecting virus-laden fecal samples from thousands of bats in remote caves, transporting them to the dense population center of Wuhan, and modifying them to be more dangerous, e.g., through serial passage through human cells and the insertion of furin cleavage sites.  Years before the COVID-19 outbreak, there were experts remarking on how risky this research was and trying to stop it.  Had they known just <em>how</em> lax the biosecurity was in Wuhan—dangerous pathogens experimented on in BSL-2 labs, etc. etc.—they would have been louder.<br/></li><li>Even if it <em>didn’t</em> cause the pandemic, the massive effort to collect and enhance bat coronaviruses now appears to have been of dubious value.  It did not lead to an actionable early warning about how bad COVID-19 was going to be, nor did it lead to useful treatments, vaccines, or mitigation measures, all of which came from other sources.<br/></li><li>There are multiple routes by which SARS-CoV2, or its progenitor, could’ve made its way, otherwise undetected, from the remote bat caves of Yunnan province or some other southern location to the city of Wuhan a thousand miles away, as it has to do in any plausible origin theory.  Having said that, the regular Yunnan→Wuhan traffic in scientific samples of precisely these kinds of viruses, sustained over a decade, <em>does</em> stand out a bit!  On the infamous coincidence of the pandemic starting practically next door to the world’s center for studying SARS-like coronaviruses, rather than near where the horseshoe bats live in the wild, Chan and Ridley memorably quote Humphrey Bogart’s line from <em>Casablanca</em>: “Of all the gin joints in all the towns in all the world, she walks into mine.”<br/></li><li>The seafood market was probably “just” an early superspreader site, rather than the site of the original spillover event.  No bats or pangolins at all, and relatively few mammals of any kind, appear to have been sold at that market, and no sign of SARS-CoV2 was ever found in any of the animals despite searching.<br/></li><li>Most remarkably, <strong>Shi and Daszak have increasingly stonewalled</strong>, refusing to answer 100% reasonable questions from fellow virologists.  They’ve acted more and more like defendants exercising their right to remain silent than like participants in a joint search for the truth.  That might be understandable if they’d already answered ad nauseam and wearied of repeating themselves, but with many crucial questions, they haven’t answered even once.  They’ve refused to make available a key database of all the viruses WIV had collected, which WIV inexplicably took offline in September 2019.  When, in January 2020, Shi disclosed to the world that WIV had collected a virus called RaTG13, which was 96% identical to SARS-CoV2, she didn’t mention that it was collected from a mine in Mojiang, which the WIV had sampled from over and over because six workers had gotten a SARS-like pneumonia there in 2012 and three had died from it.  She didn’t let on that her group had been studying RaTG13 for years—giving, instead, the false impression that they’d just noticed it recently, when searching WIV’s records for cousins of SARS-CoV2.  And she didn’t see fit to mention that WIV had collected <em>eight other</em> coronaviruses resembling SARS-CoV2 from the same mine (!).  Shi’s original papers on SARS-CoV2 also passed in silence over the virus’s furin cleavage site—even though SARS-CoV2 was the first sarbecoronavirus with that feature, and Shi herself had recently demonstrated adding furin cleavage sites to other viruses to make them more transmissible, and the cleavage site would’ve leapt out immediately to any coronavirus researcher as the most interesting feature of SARS-CoV2 and as key to its transmissibility.  Some of these points had to be uncovered by Internet sleuths, poring over doctoral theses and the like, after which Shi would glancingly acknowledge the points in talks without ever explaining her earlier silences.  Shi and Daszak refused to cooperate with Chan and Ridley’s book, and have stopped answering questions more generally.  When people politely ask Daszak about these matters on Twitter, he blocks them.<br/></li><li>The Chinese regime has been every bit as obstructionist as you might expect: destroying samples, blocking credible investigations, censoring researchers, and preventing journalists from accessing the Mojiang mine.  So Shi at least has the excuse that, even if she’d <em>wanted</em> to come clean with everything relevant she knows about WIV’s bat coronavirus work, she might not be able to do so without endangering herself or loved ones.  Daszak has no such excuse.</li></ul>



<p>It’s important to understand that, even in the worst case—that (1) there was a lab leak, and (2) Shi and Daszak are knowingly withholding information relevant to it—they’re far from monsters.  Even in <em>Viral</em>‘s relentlessly unsparing account, they come across as genuine believers in their mission to protect the world from the next pandemic.</p>



<p>And it’s like: imagine devoting your life to that mission, having most of the world refuse to take you seriously, and then the calamity happens exactly like you said … <em>except</em> that, not only did your efforts fail to prevent it, but there’s a live possibility that they <em>caused</em> it.  It’s conceivable that your life’s work managed to save <em>minus</em> 15 million lives and create <em>minus</em> $50 trillion in economic value.</p>



<p>Very few scientists in history have faced that sort of psychic burden, perhaps not even the ones who built the atomic bomb.  I <em>hope</em> I’d maintain my scientific integrity under such an astronomical weight, but I’m doubtful that I would.  Would you?</p>



<p><em>Viral</em> very wisely never tries to psychoanalyze Shi and Daszak.  I fear that one might need a lot of conceptual space between “knowing” and “not knowing,” “suspecting” and “not suspecting,” to do justice to the planet-sized enormity of what’s at stake here.  Suppose, for example, that an initial investigation in January 2020 reassured you that SARS-CoV2 <em>probably</em> hadn’t come from your lab: would you continue trying to get to the bottom of things, or would you thereafter decide the matter was closed?</p>



<p>For all that, I agree with Chan and Ridley that COVID-19 might well have had a zoonotic origin after all.  And one point <em>Viral</em> makes abundantly clear is that, if our goal is to prevent the next pandemic, then resolving the mystery of COVID-19 actually matters less than one might think.  This is because, whichever possibility—zoonotic spillover <em>or</em> lab leak—turns out to be the truth of this case, <strong>the other possibility would remain absolutely terrifying and would demand urgent action as well</strong>.  Read the book and see for yourself.</p>



<p>Searching my inbox, I found an email from April 16, 2020 where I told someone who’d asked me that the lab-leak hypothesis seemed perfectly plausible to me (albeit no <em>more</em> than plausible), that I couldn’t understand why it wasn’t being investigated more, but that I was hesitant to blog about these matters.  As I <a href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=5542">wrote</a> seven months ago, I now see my lack of courage on this as having been a personal failing.  Obviously, I’m just a quantum computing theorist, not a biologist, so I don’t <em>have</em> to have any thoughts whatsoever about the origin of COVID-19 … but I <em>did</em> have some, and I didn’t share them here only because of the likelihood that I’d be called an idiot on social media.  Having now read Chan and Ridley, though, I think I’d take being called an idiot for this book review more as a positive signal about my courage than as a negative signal about my reasoning skills!</p>



<p>At one level, <em>Viral</em> stands alongside, I dunno, <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Eichmann-Jerusalem-Banality-Penguin-Classics/dp/0143039881">Eichmann in Jerusalem</a></em> among the saddest books I’ve ever read.  It’s 300 pages of one of the great human tragedies of our lifetime balancing on a hinge between happening and not happening, and we all know how it turns out.  On another level, though, <em>Viral</em> is optimistic.  Like with Richard Feynman’s famous <a href="https://science.ksc.nasa.gov/shuttle/missions/51-l/docs/rogers-commission/Appendix-F.txt">“personal appendix”</a> about the Space Shuttle <em>Challenger</em> explosion, the very act of writing such a book reflects a view that you’re still allowed to ask questions; that one or two people armed with nothing but arguments can run rings around governments, newspapers, and international organizations; that we don’t yet live in a post-truth world.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-01T23:54:04Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-01T23:54:04Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Nerd Interest"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <icon>https://scottaaronson.blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-Jacket-32x32.gif</icon>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2022-01-03T17:58:27Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19441</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/12/31/make-a-trillion-dollars/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Make A Trillion Dollars</title>
    <summary>For every problem, there is one solution which is simple, neat, and wrong— H. L. Mencken 2019 announcement Lance Fortnow was a colleague of mine for a long time at Georgia Tech and is now the Dean of the College of Computing at Illinois Institute of Technology. He started one of the top blogs in […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>For every problem, there is one solution which is simple, neat, and wrong— H. L. Mencken</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/12/31/make-a-trillion-dollars/lf2/" rel="attachment wp-att-19443"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-19443" height="108" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/lf2.png?resize=214%2C108&amp;ssl=1" width="214"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">2019 <a href="https://www.iit.edu/news/lance-fortnow-designated-new-college-science-dean">announcement</a></font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Lance Fortnow was a colleague of mine for a long time at Georgia Tech and is now the Dean of the College of Computing at Illinois Institute of Technology. He started one of the top blogs in theory of computing, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org">Computational Complexity</a>, which is partnered by Bill Gasarch of the University of Maryland at College Park.</p>
<p>
Today, New Year’s Eve, we discuss his angles on the status of P versus NP.</p>
<p>
Lance has written a <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2022/1/257448-fifty-years-of-p-vs-np-and-the-possibility-of-the-impossible/fulltext">new survey</a> on the current status of the P versus NP problem. It is titled, “Fifty Years of P vs. NP and the Possibility of the Impossible.” By this he means two things:</p>
<ul>
<li>
The believed impossibility of <em>solving</em> NP-hard problems is a valuable source of “computational friction.” The analogy is that without physical friction, movement would be too easy—we would be unable to control it. <p/>
</li><li>
The seeming impossibility of <em>resolving</em> the P=NP question has redistributed focus to coping with NP-hardness and finding ways around it. Indeed, this impossibility may be technically bound to the ability of heuristic approaches to achieve practical success.
</li></ul>
<p>
Well, as theorists, Ken and I would like to know about the status of resolving the question.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> 2022 and Beyond </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I am old enough that I am unlikely to see the resolution of P=NP. But that does not stop me from thinking about the what could be coming down the pike. Lance describes the importance of this great problem—it is roughly fifty years from its first statement by Steven Cook, and then Leonid Levin and Dick Karp—and reviews what can be called progress on it. But as this illustration from his article speaks, we are still at a crossroads about what kind of computational world we live in.</p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/12/31/make-a-trillion-dollars/cacm/" rel="attachment wp-att-19445"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19445" height="240" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/cacm.jpg?resize=240%2C240&amp;ssl=1" width="240"/></a></p>
<p>
We are just about to enter the new year—2022. This could be the year that resolves P=NP, or that could be another fifty years away. Another measure is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Millennium_Prize_Problems">Prize</a> of a million dollars for solving it is now entering its third decade. Yet there seems to be no hint whether we are close to its resolution or not. </p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/12/31/make-a-trillion-dollars/attachment/2022/" rel="attachment wp-att-19446"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19446" height="90" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/2022.png?resize=160%2C90&amp;ssl=1" width="160"/></a></p>
<p/><h2> Why P=NP Is So Hard </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
There is a fundamental issue with the P=NP problem. Yes it is hard. Yes we seem to have no clear path to resolving it. We do not even have a clear path to a partial result. But that does not really explain why the problem is so hard. Let’s try and look at why the problem is so impossible.</p>
<p>
The reason I believe that the problem is so difficult is due to the inherent nature of algorithms for NP problems. This nature makes the resolution especially difficult, and especially interesting. Consider the problem of finding some <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> so that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  f(X) = b " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++f%28X%29+%3D+b+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>Here <img alt="{f(X)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28X%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is an easy to compute function. The difficulty is that finding <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> given <img alt="{b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is hard. Think <img alt="{f(X)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bf%28X%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is some crypto type problem, or if you wish some search type problem. </p>
<p>
Why is this such a nasty problem? The obvious issue is how hard is it to map an <img alt="{b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> to an <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> so that 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  f(X) = b " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++f%28X%29+%3D+b+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>But {it what exactly does this mean?} The first issue is <i>when must we be able to do this?</i> The second is <i>how must we be able to do this?</i> Let’s look at these in turn.</p>
<p>
<i>When?</i> The obvious answer is <em>always</em>. We would love to be able to find <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> for each <img alt="{b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> that has a solution. This corresponds to being able to solve all problems. Clearly the best case. But in practice we might be quite happy with: </p>
<ul>
<li>
For most <img alt="{b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> find an <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>; <p/>
</li><li>
Or even, for many <img alt="{b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> find an <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>.
</li></ul>
<p>The latter could be: at least <img alt="{50\%}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B50%5C%25%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> of the time we can find the <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. In practice this could be more than enough. Think breaking a secret cryptosystem. If we could break even a positive fraction of the messages this could easily be enough. </p>
<p>
<i>How?</i> The obvious answer is with an efficient algorithm. We would love to be able to run a standard polynomial algorithm that finds <img alt="{X}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BX%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> from <img alt="{b}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bb%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>. But in practice there are at least two issues:</p>
<ul>
<li>
The standard algorithm could be replaced by algorithms that break the standard definition of algorithms. They could for example be quantum algorithms or could be DNA algorithms. <p/>
</li><li>
The algorithms could be standard conventional algorithms. But they might run in time bounds that are exponential but are tricky. For example suppose that there is an solution that runs in time 	<p/>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  2^{n/C} " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++2%5E%7Bn%2FC%7D+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/></p>
<p>If <img alt="{C}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is modest size then the solution is exponential in practice. But if <img alt="{C}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is large, then the algorithm for real problems would be efficient.
</p></li></ul>
<p>
The latter is interesting. If <img alt="{C}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is any constant <i>no matter the size</i> you would collect the million dollar prize for solving P=NP. But if <img alt="{C}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BC%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> is large enough, this would also make a trillion dollars. This is because you could use the method to solve realistic sized problems. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Enter A Trillion Dollars </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The following image hopefully helps set the stage for what a trillion dollars looks like, compared to a million.</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/12/31/make-a-trillion-dollars/tri/" rel="attachment wp-att-19448"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19448" height="244" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/tri.png?resize=425%2C244&amp;ssl=1" width="425"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">2011 <a href="http://www.strata-sphere.com/blog/index.php/archives/15154">source</a>, origin untraceable?</font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p>
The reason for showing this that if P=NP has better when and how solutions some yield attacks that could make immense amounts of money. For example, an algorithm that breaks <img alt="{50\%}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B50%5C%25%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> of the problems in a practical time would be worth an immense amount of money. </p>
<p>
So if you could show P=NP, even in some practical way that’s better than what we can do now, you could be richer than <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auric_Goldfinger">Auric Goldfinger</a> or some other James Bond masterminds. We might all, however, end up with the poorer world that these villains would have created. </p>
<p>
What has grown over the past fifty years—and the past decade in particular—is ways to make a trillion dollars by <em>not</em> resolving P versus NP. Discussion of these occupies latter sections of Lance’s survey where a “payoff” would ordinarily come in a review article.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
What do you think about P=NP? Could the solvers win much more than the one million dollar prize? What would you do if you made progress? Is the real win the way the question acts as a ridge framing a valley that guides the flow of progress?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-31T22:23:42Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-31T22:23:42Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="P=NP"/>
    <category term="heuristics"/>
    <category term="Lance Fortnow"/>
    <category term="New Year's"/>
    <category term="status"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:31Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/12/31/new-years-eve</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/12/31/new-years-eve.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>New Year’s Eve linkage</title>
    <summary>Interview with Annie Rauwerda (\(\mathbb{M}\), via), known for publishing odd stuff from Wikipedia on her social media accounts.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://diff.wikimedia.org/2021/12/07/from-the-depths-of-wikipedia-an-interview-with-wikimedian-and-influencer-annie-rauwerda/">Interview with Annie Rauwerda</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107461087724307059">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://boingboing.net/2021/12/15/interview-with-boing-boing-contributor-annie-rauwerda-of-depths-of-wikipedia-fame.html">via</a>), known for publishing odd stuff from Wikipedia on her social media accounts.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://illusionoftheyear.com/cat/top-10-finalists/2021/">2021 illusion of the year finalists</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107463658141187162">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2021-12-17/fake-student-bots-enrolled-in-community-colleges-one-professor-has-become-a-bot-sleuthing-continues-to-fight-them">Pierce College professor Kim Rich tracks down fake student bots that enroll in community college courses in order to commit financial aid fraud</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107475116980269890">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://community.wolfram.com/groups/-/m/t/2409294">Fewer 45-60-75 triangles tile the square</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107483368100385397">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://twitter.com/mathpuzzle/status/1461421712956956673">via</a>). It’s <a href="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/junkyard/acute-square/">possible to tile squares edge-to-edge with fewer acute triangles</a> but if you allow non-edge-to-edge tilings you can use only a single shape (but different sizes) of acute triangle, this one. The minimum number of triangles has been gradually reduced since 1990 when this was discovered; now it’s down to 32.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I posted a link to <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.01543">Ben Green’s super-polynomial lower bounds</a> for off-diagonal van der Waerden numbers <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/02/15/linkage.html">last February</a>, based on <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/02/08/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-20-ben-green-presents-super-polynomial-lower-bounds-for-off-diagonal-van-der-waerden-numbers-w3k/">a blog post by Gil Kalai</a>; now <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/oxford-math"><em>Quanta Magazine</em> has a writeup</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107489055840096416">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regular_number">Regular number</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107491473069445206">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> the numbers that divide powers of 60, now a Good Article on Wikipedia. These actually have different names in the different contexts they come from:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Regular numbers in the study of Babylonian mathematics</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>5-smooth numbers in modern mathematics</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Harmonic whole numbers in music theory and architecture</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Hamming numbers in computer science</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://github.com/woodrush/lisp-in-life">Lisp in Conway’s Game of Life</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107497380214288478">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://lobste.rs/s/lqt472/lisp_interpreter_implemented_conway_s">via</a>). The implementation involves compiling a C implementation of lisp onto a custom CPU in Life, modified from one <a href="https://codegolf.stackexchange.com/questions/11880/build-a-working-game-of-tetris-in-conways-game-of-life/142673">used four years ago to implement Tetris in Life</a>. It would be capable of running other C programs in the same way.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ocean rain, Mendocino, Christmas afternoon <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107511339824111098">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span></p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Ocean rain, Mendocino, Christmas afternoon" src="https://www.ics.uci.edu/~eppstein/pix/xmen/OceanRainMendocinoXmas-m.jpg" style="border-style: solid; border-color: black;"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Square_pyramidal_number">Square pyramidal number</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107516162974520461">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> another new Wikipedia Good Article. Some things I learned in working on this article:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>They were part of a family of figurate numbers studied by Japanese mathematicians of the wasan period.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>As well as counting points or balls in a square pyramid shape, they count the number of acute triangles in an odd regular polygon.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>They give the denominators of an infinite alternating summation for \(\pi-3\).</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Transfinite algorithm analysis: with real edge weights on a finite graph with \(m\) edges, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1504.04363">the Ford–Fulkerson algorithm can take time \(\omega^{\Theta(m)}\)</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@gnivasch/107462555115098475">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> 2015 preprint by Backman and Huynh, <a href="https://doi.org/10.3233/COM-180082">later published in <em>Computability</em></a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@henryseg/107500629939378459">Approximation to a fundamental domain for the Cannon-Thurston map for the figure eight knot complement</a>. Henry Segerman posts an image from joint work by Saul Schleimer, of an intricately filled fractal-looking shape. One commenter suggests it looks like Escher’s work; my own comparison is to <a href="https://botsin.space/@APoD/107500725269227434">an image of the Crab nebula</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.ams.org/journals/notices/202201/rnoti-p22.pdf">On an angle with magical properties</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107533528388789130">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> Horgan and Murphy in the <em>Notices</em>.  The angle is the larger of the two acute angles in the right triangle formed by a side, short diagonal, and long diagonal of a cube, roughly 54.74°. It appears frequently in cylindrical structures reinforced by helical fibers, as the pitch angle maximizing volume per fiber length. Examples occur in worms, octopi arms, elephant trunks, water hoses, and blood vessels.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Wikipedia_Signpost/2021-12-28/Serendipity">Born three months before her brother?</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107540664762715818">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>)</span> I was amused by this example of how errors or discrepancies (in this case, in the birthdate of a pianist) can propagate through historical sources (including Wikipedia) and how the circularity of that propagation can hamper efforts to determine which of two inconsistent claims is the incorrect one.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://webb.nasa.gov/content/features/origami.html">Webb and origami</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107544466738561736">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> This site features an origami papercraft model of the 18-hex honeycomb mirror of the James Webb Space Telescope, currently on a path to its L2 orbit. But I’m more interested in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RzGLKQ7_KZQ">how the spaceship unfolds itself as it travels, from a more compact configuration that would fit into a rocket into its final form</a>.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-31T17:26:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-31T17:26:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2022-01-01T01:27:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/182</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/182" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-182 |  On the strength of Sherali-Adams and Nullstellensatz as propositional proof systems | 

	Ilario Bonacina, 

	Maria Luisa Bonet</title>
    <summary>The propositional proof system Sherali-Adams (SA) has polynomial-size proofs of the pigeonhole principle (PHP). Similarly, the Nullstellensatz (NS) proof system has polynomial size proofs of the bijective (i.e. both functional and onto) pigeonhole principle (ofPHP). We characterize the strength of these algebraic proof systems in terms of Boolean proof systems the following way. We show that SA (resp. NS over ${\bf Z}$) with unary coefficients lies strictly between tree-like resolution and tree-like depth-$1$ Frege + PHP (resp. ofPHP).  We introduce weighted versions of PHP and ofPHP, resp. wtPHP and of-wtPHP and we show that SA (resp. NS over ${\bf Z}$)  lies strictly between resolution and tree-like depth-$1$ Frege + wtPHP (resp. of-wtPHP). We also show analogue results for depth-$d$ versions of SA and NS.</summary>
    <updated>2021-12-30T20:42:36Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-30T20:42:36Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/181</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/181" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-181 |  The KW Games as a Teaser | 

	Oded Goldreich</title>
    <summary>This is a purely pedagogical text.
We advocate using KW-games as a teaser (or ``riddle'') for a complexity theoretic course. 
In particular, stating the KW-game for a familiar NP-complete problem such as 3-Colorability and asking to prove that it requires more than polylogarithmic communication poses a seemingly tractable question that requires no background. 
The fact that this is actually a formidable question puts much of complexity theory in the right perspective.  
Indeed, complexity theory contains numerous extremely appealing problems that require little background (beyond basic comfort with the notion of computation) and yet are formidable.</summary>
    <updated>2021-12-30T15:37:31Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-30T15:37:31Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/27/postdoc-opportunity-in-algebraic-complexity-at-at-boston-college-apply-by-february-1-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/27/postdoc-opportunity-in-algebraic-complexity-at-at-boston-college-apply-by-february-1-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>POSTDOC OPPORTUNITY IN ALGEBRAIC COMPLEXITY AT at BOSTON COLLEGE (apply by February 1, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Computer Science department at Boston College invites applications for a postdoctoral position in the area of algebraic complexity (or an adjacent field) under the supervision of Ilya Volkovich. Please direct any inquiries to Ilya Volkovich (Email: ilya.volkovich@bc.edu) Website: https://bc.csod.com/ux/ats/careersite/2/home/requisition/5363?c=bc Email: ilya.volkoivich@bc.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Computer Science department at Boston College invites applications for a postdoctoral position in the area of algebraic complexity (or an adjacent field) under the supervision of Ilya Volkovich.</p>
<p>Please direct any inquiries to Ilya Volkovich (Email: ilya.volkovich@bc.edu)</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://bc.csod.com/ux/ats/careersite/2/home/requisition/5363?c=bc">https://bc.csod.com/ux/ats/careersite/2/home/requisition/5363?c=bc</a><br/>
Email: ilya.volkoivich@bc.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-27T23:00:03Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-27T23:00:03Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/180</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/180" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR21-180 |  Proving as Fast as Computing: Succinct Arguments with Constant Prover Overhead | 

	Noga Ron-Zewi, 

	Ron Rothblum</title>
    <summary>Succinct arguments are proof systems that allow a powerful, but untrusted, prover to convince a weak verifier that an input $x$ belongs to a language $L \in NP$, with communication that is much shorter than the $NP$ witness. Such arguments, which grew out of the theory literature, are now drawing immense interest also in practice, where a key bottleneck that has arisen is the high computational cost of \emph{proving} correctness.

In this work we address this problem by constructing succinct arguments for general computations, expressed as Boolean circuits (of bounded fan-in), with a \emph{strictly linear} size prover. The soundness error of the protocol is an arbitrarily small constant. Prior to this work, succinct arguments were known with a \emph{quasi-}linear size prover for general Boolean circuits or with linear-size only for arithmetic circuits, defined over large finite fields.

In more detail, for every Boolean circuit $C=C(x,w)$, we construct an $O(\log |C|)$-round argument-system in which the prover can be implemented by a size $O(|C|)$ Boolean circuit (given as input both the instance $x$ and the witness $w$), with arbitrarily small constant soundness error and using $poly(\lambda,\log |C|)$ communication, where $\lambda$ denotes the security parameter. The verifier can be implemented by a size $O(|x|) + poly(\lambda, \log |C|)$ circuit following a size $O(|C|)$ private pre-processing step, or, alternatively, by using a purely public-coin protocol (with no pre-processing) with a size $O(|C|)$ verifier. The protocol can be made zero-knowledge using standard techniques (and with similar parameters). The soundness of our protocol is computational and relies on the existence of collision resistant hash functions that can be computed by linear-size circuits, such as those proposed by Applebaum et al. (ITCS, 2017).

 At the heart of our construction is a new information-theoretic  \emph{interactive oracle proof} (IOP), an interactive analog of a PCP, for circuit satisfiability, with constant prover overhead. The improved efficiency of our IOP is obtained by bypassing a barrier faced by prior IOP constructions, which needed to (either explicitly or implicitly) encode the entire computation using a multiplication code.</summary>
    <updated>2021-12-27T03:47:01Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-27T03:47:01Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:21Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=17929</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/12/24/test-your-intuition-47-agc-gtc-tgc-gtc-tgc-gac-gatc-what-comes-next-in-the-sequence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Test your intuition 47:  AGC-GTC-TGC-GTC-TGC-GAC-GATC-?  what comes next in the sequence?</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before getting to the main topic of this post, first, Happy New Year 2022 and Merry Christmas to all readers, and second, a quick update: A community blog to discuss open problems in algebraic combinatorics was created. Everybody is invited … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2021/12/24/test-your-intuition-47-agc-gtc-tgc-gtc-tgc-gac-gatc-what-comes-next-in-the-sequence/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Before getting to the main topic of this post, first, Happy New Year 2022 and Merry Christmas to all readers, and second, a quick update: A <a href="https://realopacblog.wordpress.com/">community blog</a> to discuss open problems in algebraic combinatorics was created. Everybody is invited to check out the problems posted there, to subscribe, and to contribute their own problems.</p>
<h3>Virtual Poll:</h3>
<p>What will be the next term in the sequence <strong>AGC-GTC-TGC-GTC-TGC-GAC-GATC- ???</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><strong>GTC</strong></li>
<li><strong>GATC</strong></li>
<li><strong>TAGC</strong></li>
<li><strong>GCTC</strong></li>
<li><strong>C:GAT</strong></li>
<li>Another answer</li>
</ol>
<p><span id="more-17929"/></p>
<h3><img alt="owi19" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-22323" height="527" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2021/12/owi19.jpg" width="527"/></h3>
<p><span class="d2edcug0 hpfvmrgz qv66sw1b c1et5uql lr9zc1uh a8c37x1j keod5gw0 nxhoafnm aigsh9s9 fe6kdd0r mau55g9w c8b282yb d3f4x2em iv3no6db jq4qci2q a3bd9o3v b1v8xokw oo9gr5id" dir="auto" style="color: #ff0000;">Oberwolfach, Geometric, algebraic and topological combinatorics, 2019. Giulia Codenotti, Aldo Conca, Sandra Di Rocco, Bruno Benedetti, and Lorenzo Venturello </span></p>
<h3>Our August 2019 Oberwolfach meeting.</h3>
<p>At the end of August 2019 we had in Oberwolfach a very fruitful meeting on Geometric, algebraic, and topological combinatorics. (In <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/09/01/richard-ehrenborgs-problem-on-spanning-trees-in-bipartite-graphs/">this post</a>, I mentioned an open problem from the problem session.) I came to Oberwolfach just after a visit, with my son-in-law, Eran, to CERN near Genève. (See <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/09/04/computer-science-and-its-impact-on-our-future/">this post</a> for pictures from ATLAS, CERN, and this post regarding my <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2019/08/21/the-argument-against-quantum-computers-a-cern-colloquium-and-a-new-paper/">CERN colloquium</a>.)</p>
<p>The August 2019 Oberwolfach meeting was the seventh meeting in a series of meetings that started in 1995.  Here is, by the way, is <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematics-as-a-team-sport-20200331/"> very nice article i</a>n Quanta Magazine about an Oberwolfach Meeting. (And feel free to share Oberwolfach memories in the comment section.)</p>
<p>The sequence in the title of the post is not a DNA sequence or something similar but rather it refers to these meetings in Oberwolfach and this post is devoted to these series of meetings and other meetings in Oberwolfach.</p>
<h2>Oberwolfach: AGC, 1995; GTC, 1999; TGC, 2003; GTC, 2007; TGC, 2011; GAC, 2015; GATC, 2019.</h2>
<p>Here A stands for ‘Algebraic’, G stands for ‘Geometric’, T stands for ‘Topological’ and C stands for ‘Combinatorics’.</p>
<p>These series of conferences are devoted to algebraic, geometric, and topological combinatorics. Both algebraic and geometric combinatorics are very large areas (and topological combinatorics is pretty large) and usually participants of the conference are divided into several overlapping, much appreciated minorities. Actually, living in a country where every citizen is a member of a much appreciated minority seems like a nice political setting to me.</p>
<p>Here is <a href="https://oda.mfo.de/handle/mfo/397">the review</a> of the first conference in the series AGC95.</p>
<h3>AGC 1995</h3>
<p>I was slightly younger than 40 years old. The meeting, organized by Anders Björner, Günter Ziegler and me, took place before a sabbatical semester at IAS, Princeton in the fall 1995. Here are a few topics that were discussed:</p>
<p><strong>Cluster algebras to be.</strong> Sergey Fomin’s lecture was on Piecewise-linear maps, total positivity, and pseudoline arrangements, it represented a joint work with Arkady Bernstein and Andrei Zelevinsky. This paper was the starting point of vastly influential cluster algebras that Sergey, Arkady, and Andrei started developing around that time.</p>
<p><strong>Polytopes spheres and face numbers.</strong> Tom Braden talked about Intersection homology and polytopes – recent progress, this was about his paper with Bob MacPherson where (among other things) a conjecture that I made some years earlier was settled.</p>
<p><strong>Convexity in the Grassmannian.</strong> Eli Goodman talked about a joint work with Ricky Pollack on  some combinatorial questions for convex sets on affine Grassmanian. Finding the right notion of convexity for a subset of the Grassmannian is a fascinating and unexplored question.</p>
<p><strong>Optimization.</strong> Monique Laurent talked about  the geometry of the set of positive semidefinite matrices with diagonal entries. Rekha Thomas talked about using Gröbner bases to solve integer programs (and a comparison between linear and integer programming).</p>
<p><strong>The two 2-lecture series.  </strong>Nati Linial gave a series of two lectures on <strong>the geometry of graphs</strong>. He talked about his program to think about graphs as metric objects and apply insights regarding metric spaces to theoretical computer science. This was shortly after the Linial-London Rabinovich paper that had large impact in theoretical computer science and combinatorics had appeared.  Rade Zivaleivich  gave two lectures on methods of obstruction theory, related to topological and colorful Tverberg theorems and measure partitions and other questions. We came back to this topic in subsequent  conferences in the series.</p>
<p><strong>Real algebraic geometry.</strong> Ricky Pollack talked about Complexity and algorithms in real algebraic geometry.</p>
<p><strong>Triangulations of cyclic polytopes and the generalized Baues Conjecture</strong>.<br/>
Jorg Rambau talked about a counterexample to the “Generalized Baues Conjecture” and Vic Reiner talked about Triangulations of cyclic polytopes: the higher Stasheff-Tamari posets.</p>
<p><strong>Universality. </strong>Jürgen Richter Gebert explained why Realization spaces of 4-polytopes are universal!</p>
<p>See the review for some more talks on the topics listed above and on other topics such as <strong>Lattices of parabolic subgroups, </strong><strong>Discrepancy theory, </strong><strong>Combinatorics of knots </strong>and more<strong>.</strong></p>
<p>Here are links to the workshop pages (WP) and full reviews (FR) of AGC, 1995 (<a href="https://www.mfo.de/occasion/9506/www_view">WP</a>, <a href="https://oda.mfo.de/handle/mfo/397">FR</a>) ; GTC, 1999 (<a href="https://www.mfo.de/occasion/9915/www_view">WP</a>, <a href="https://publications.mfo.de/handle/mfo/2557">FR</a>); TGC, 2003  (<a href="https://www.mfo.de/occasion/0315/www_view">WP</a>, <a href="https://www.mfo.de/document/0315/Report16_2003.pdf">FR</a>); GTC, 2007 (<a href="https://www.mfo.de/occasion/0705/www_view">WP</a>, <a href="https://www.mfo.de/document/0705/OWR_2007_04.pdf">FR</a>); TGC, 2011 (<a href="https://www.mfo.de/occasion/1106/www_view">WP</a>, <a href="https://www.mfo.de/document/1106/OWR_2011_08.pdf">FR</a>); GAC, 2015 (<a href="https://www.mfo.de/occasion/1506/www_view">WP</a>, <a href="https://www.mfo.de/document/1506/OWR_2015_05.pdf">FR</a>); and GATC, 2019 (<a href="https://www.mfo.de/occasion/1935/www_view">WP</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.14760/OWR-2019-39">FR</a>).</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #ff0000;">Flashback: my first meeting at Oberwolfach</span></strong></p>
<h3><a href="https://www.mfo.de/occasion/8229/www_view">Konvexe Körper 1982</a></h3>
<p>I was a 27 year old graduate student. It was just after the 1982 Lebanon war. I had a one year old daughter and following the meeting my wife and I toured Italy for a week. It was great!  My thesis supervisor Micha A. Perles and my academic brother Michael Kallay also participated. At that conference I met for the first time many mathematicians and some of them have remained my good friends ever since. The meetings on Konvexe Körper took place every two years and I participated in several subsequent meetings.</p>
<h3>Oberwolfach’s Combinatorics meetings from January 2000 to January 2020</h3>
<p>The other series of conferences in Oberwolfach that I attended regularly, is the combinatorics meeting that takes place in the first week of January every 2-3 years. The <a href="https://www.mfo.de/occasion/0001/www_view">first one</a> in the series was also the first Oberwolfach meeting after 2000.  The <a href="https://www.mfo.de/occasion/2002/www_view">last meeting</a> in this series was in January 2020 and just before the meeting my wife and I spent four great days in Rome. This was in fact our last trip outside Israel until September 2021 (not counting a 1-day <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/02/11/petra-jordan/">visit to Petra</a>).</p>
<h2><strong><span style="color: #ff0000;">And the answer is: GATC (2023) </span></strong></h2>
<p>Half a year ago Isabella Novik, Paco Santos, Volkmar Welker and I submitted a proposal for a 2023 meeting which is going to be the 8th meeting in this series. Recently the meeting was approved! It will take place on December 10-16, 2023.</p>
<p>Useful links:<a href="https://www.mfo.de/"> Oberwolfach</a>; <a href="https://opc.mfo.de/">Oberwolfach photo collection</a><a href="https://opc.mfo.de/">;</a><a href="https://www.mfo.de/www/schedule/all/all"> List of workshops since 1949</a>;</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-24T12:53:28Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-24T12:53:28Z</published>
    <category term="Algebra"/>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <category term="Test your intuition"/>
    <category term="Oberwolfach"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:25Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/12/23/raytracing-diamonds</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2021/12/23/raytracing-diamonds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Raytracing diamonds</title>
    <summary>This comes from a question posed to me and others in 2019 by Stefan Langerman, a computational geometer who also happens to be a diamond dealer. The classic brilliant cut shape of diamonds has a flat “table” face on the top (visible) side of the gem, and many other smaller facets on the sides (“crown”) and back (“pavilion”), with angles chosen so that most of the light that enters through the table is reflected back out through the table, making the diamond look bright. Can we simulate this reflection process efficiently, without having to trace all the reflections of all (or a sufficiently dense sample of all) possible light rays?</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This comes from a question posed to me and others in 2019 by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Langerman">Stefan Langerman</a>, a computational geometer who also happens to be a diamond dealer. The classic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brilliant_(diamond_cut)">brilliant cut</a> shape of diamonds has a flat “table” face on the top (visible) side of the gem, and many other smaller facets on the sides (“crown”) and back (“pavilion”), with angles chosen so that most of the light that enters through the table is reflected back out through the table, making the diamond look bright. Can we simulate this reflection process efficiently, without having to trace all the reflections of all (or a sufficiently dense sample of all) possible light rays?</p>

<p>This appears to be an interesting problem even for a very simple abstraction of the diamond’s shape: a two-dimensional isosceles triangle, with the base of the triangle as its table and the two equal sides as its pavilion. What you need to know about light reflections in gems is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critical_angle_(optics)">critical angle</a>, determined from the high <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Refractive_index">refractive index</a> of diamonds and other gems. Inside the gem, rays that hit a face at an angle shallower than the critical angle; rays that hit more steeply than the critical angle will escape. Any light ray hitting the table will always enter the gem, and will be refracted so that it enters along a ray steeper than the critical angle. It will then bounce around within the gem until it happens to hit a face steeply enough to escape. The question is to predict where this escape ray escapes, more quickly than the obvious algorithm of calculating explicitly the entire sequence of reflections that it performs. Or if we can’t, can we at least provide good bounds on the lengths of these reflection sequences?</p>

<p>Three of the simplest cases involve the isosceles triangles for which the triangle <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edge_tessellation">tiles the plane by copies reflected across its edges</a>, the equilateral triangle, isosceles right triangle, and 30-30-120 isosceles triangle. The paths of a reflected light ray within such a triangle are combinatorially equivalent to the paths of a straight line through this triangulation: they pass through the same types of edges, at the same angles.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Reflection through many faces in a 30-30-120 gem" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2021/30-30-120.svg" width="80%"/></p>

<p>For all three of these triangle shapes, a line that enters the gem through any edge can only pass through a constant number of tiles in the tiling, before passing through another edge with the same angle, at which it must necessarily leave the gem (if it has not done so already). For instance, the red line shown, if it enters at its bottom left endpoint on the table of a green triangle, will exit after at most three reflections, through the parallel table of a blue triangle. The constant in the number of reflections here is absolute, not depending on the critical angle.</p>

<p>The next simplest case is the isosceles triangle with apex angle \(2\pi/5\). This triangle does not tile the plane, but we can still form a partial tiling by “unrolling” the path of reflections through the triangle into a line through a sequence of reflected triangles. In order to avoid exiting through one of the sides (by passing through it more perpendicularly than the entrance angle) and in order to miss the closest two copies of the table that are parallel to the entrance, there is only one passage that can be followed in the unrolled triangulation, the one shown by the red ray in the figure. Because this passage is perpendicular to one of the reflected sides of the triangle, a ray that is more perpendicular to the table than to this side can only continue for \(O(1)\) steps through this passage before hitting an exit. Here, though, the critical angle comes into play: critical angles that are closer to a right angle will allow larger (but constant) numbers of reflections.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Reflection in a 2pi/5 isosceles triangle" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2021/pentagonal-isosceles-reflections.svg" width="40%"/></p>

<p>Isosceles triangles with apex \(\pi/4\) are even messier. When a ray entering the table exits by a side, or exits by the table without first bouncing off the table, it always does so within $O(1)$ steps. The trickier cases are when a ray entering through the table misses the opposite table in the octagon formed by reflected copies of the triangle, and passes through a sequence of diagonal or horizontal reflections into other octagons before escaping. In the case that there are no horizontal reflections, only diagonal ones, we just need to divide the vertical distance that the ray needs to travel to hit the next row of vertical edges by the slope of the ray, and round. The case that there is at least one horizontal reflection (shown) is a little more compicated, but again appears to involve a finite calculation. So it seems that with a little more calculation it is still possible to determine algorithmically what happens in this case, in constant time rather than having to simulate the unbounded number of bounces triangle-by-triangle.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Reflection in a pi/4 isosceles triangle" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2021/octagonal-reflex.svg"/></p>

<p>All of these triangles have angles that are rational multiples of \(2\pi\). For reflections within polygons of this type, the reflected line will only pass through a constant number of slopes. The rays of a single slope that hit a given line of the polygon can be describes as an interval, and the mapping on rays that takes each ray starting on one of the sides with one of these slopes to the start of its next reflection is a special kind of mapping studied in the theory of dynamical systems, an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interval_exchange_transformation">interval exchange transformation</a>. So from a geometric question on ray-tracing, we are led to a more abstract question: given an interval exchange transformation, and a starting point in that transformation, how easy is it to determine the number of times one would need to repeat the transformation to return back to the same interval?</p>

<p>I have no real progress to report on any of these questions, in part because the continuous nature of these problems lead to difficult numerical issues. Instead, I have a new arXiv preprint <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.11607">“The Complexity of Iterated Reversible Computation” (arXiv:2112.11607
)</a> on related but more combinatorial problems. Suppose one has an invertible mapping \(f\) on a finite (but exponentially large) set of states, that is easy to compute, such as an interval exchange transformation on integers rather than real numbers. Suppose also that you want to repeat this mapping for a given initial state \(x\) and a large number \(n\) of steps. Is there anything you can do to compute the result \(f^{(n)}(x)\) of this iterated mapping, more efficiently than the obvious method of just computing \(x\), \(f(x)\), \(f(f(x))\), one step at a time? One property that appears highly relevant here is that these mappings are reversible: they are one-to-one, and more strongly the inverse mapping is also an interval exchange transformation. In contrast, it is easy to find mappings that are not reversible and for which computing iterated values is \(\mathsf{PSPACE}\)-complete: consider, for instance, the state transition map of a space-bounded Turing machine.</p>

<p>For some similar systems, we do know of effective methods in practice if not in theory. For Conway’s Game of Life, for instance, it appears to be \(\mathsf{PSPACE}\)-complete to compute what happens to an initial state after \(n\) steps (although I’m not sure this exact claim has been published in the literature), but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hashlife">hashlife</a> (as implemented in <a href="http://golly.sourceforge.net/">Golly</a>) can run many complicated and large patterns in an amount of runtime substantially less than the number of generated steps. The Game of Life is not reversible, but some other interesting cellular automata with similar behavior such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critters_(cellular_automaton)">Critters</a> are. Can we say anything about the computational complexity of simulating Critters or other reversible rules? My new paper addresses these questions by formulating a complexity class that includes computing \(f^{(n)}(x)\) for reversible cellular automaton simulation, integer interval exchange transformations, and others. It sandwiches this class between \(\mathsf{P}^{\mathsf{PH}}\) and \(\mathsf{PSPACE}\), and finds complete problems for it including the simulation of reversible cellular automata and of piecewise linear tranformations. The complete cellular automata include the two-dimensional billiard ball model, already known for its ability to simulate reversible circuits, and a new one-dimensional automata that can simulate some two-dimensional automata including the billiard ball model. Because Critters can in turn simulate the billiard ball model, it is also complete in the same sense. But I wasn’t able to prove completeness for integer interval exchange transformations, let alone say anything useful about the non-integer transformations needed to understand diamond reflections.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107498938838238948">Discuss on Mastodon</a> or <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=29695281">YC</a>)</p>

<p>PS, added 2021-12-27 to appease the request on the YC discussion for an actual ray-traced diamond image: Here’s one from my paper “<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0807.2218">Isometric diamond subgraphs</a>”, otherwise unrelated to this latest post:</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Ray-traced diamond" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2021/diapov.png"/></p>

<p>Generated by POVray from a scene generated by <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2021/diapov.py">this Python script</a>, which all ran ok in 2008 when I wrote the paper (haven’t re-tested it recently).</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-23T15:42:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-23T15:42:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2022-01-01T01:27:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7781625779470350536</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7781625779470350536/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/12/complexity-year-in-review-2021.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7781625779470350536" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7781625779470350536" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/12/complexity-year-in-review-2021.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Complexity Year in Review 2021</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The pandemic hampered many activities but research flourished with a number of great results in complexity. Result of the year goes to</p><p><a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/151/">Locally Testable Codes with constant rate, distance, and locality</a> by Irit Dinur, Shai Evra, Ron Livne, Alexander Lubotzky and Shahar Mozes<br/>and independently in<br/><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03654">Asymptotically Good Quantum and Locally Testable Classical LDPC Codes</a> by Pavel Panteleev and Gleb Kalachev</p><p>They achieved the seemingly impossible, a code that can be checked with constant queries, constant rate, constant distance and constant error. Here's <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pjc6GCRFnpg">Irit's presentation</a>, a <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/researchers-defeat-randomness-to-create-ideal-code-20211124/">Quanta article</a> and an <a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/175/">overview</a> by Oded Goldreich. Ryan O'Donnell <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k7LuOiOBYyQ">presents</a> the Panteleev-Kalachev paper, which also resolved a major open question in quantum coding theory.</p><p>Other great results include <a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/081/">Superpolynomial Lower Bounds Against Low-Depth Algebraic Circuits</a> by Nutan Limaye, Srikanth Srinivasan and Sébastien Tavenas, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/07/intersecting-classes.html">The Complexity of Gradient Descent</a> by John Fearnley, Paul W. Goldberg, Alexandros Hollender and Rahul Savani, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/03/slicing-hypercube.html">Slicing the Hypercube is not easy</a> by Gal Yehuda and Amir Yehudayoff, and <a href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2021/164/">The Acrobatics of BQP</a> by Scott Aaronson, DeVon Ingram, and William Kretschmer. The latter paper answers a <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2005/12/pulling-out-quantumness.html">16-year old open question of mine</a> that suggests you cannot pull out quantumness like you can pull out randomness from a computation.</p><p>In computing overall, the story continues to be the growth in machine learning and the power of data. We're entering a phase where data-driven programming often replaces logic-based approaches to solving complex problems. This is also the year that the <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2021/11/everyone-pitching-the-metaverse-has-a-different-idea-of-what-it-is/">metaverse</a> started to gain attention. Too early to know where that will take use, but the virtual space may become as disruptive as the Internet over the next decade, and its potential effect in research and education should not be ignored. In the next pandemic, we may wonder how we survived earlier pandemics without it.</p><p>The NSF might be going through some major changes and significant increases, or not, especially with the Build Back Better bill on hold. The <a href="https://cra.org/govaffairs/blog/">Computing Research Policy Blog</a> can help you through the morass. </p><p>We remember <a href="https://cms.math.ca/news-item/the-canadian-mathematical-society-mourns-the-loss-of-matthew-brennan/">Matthew Brennan</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/06/benny-chor-1956-2021.html">Benny Chor</a>, <a href="https://www.informs.org/content/view/full/268792">Alan Hoffman</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/09/science/arianna-wright-dead.html?unlocked_article_code=AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACEIPuonUktbfqohkSlUbCibOVtkqqBaLwvHVwbU6gHa7MzKURjZeiugYCoTG-1vIYeArQeoP6AmhZY0LNq4zFrs1x_VDPkdpRk7w85fVxp4Lf2Btp9m4Gz5rh8mIDL1lqnq6MDLmdrkuz7Dk40rMeCK9DvykpH4qIApup5Znd0j7miBbg_eYTZMmn4V2zvwjBZhlRTwfZCDsvPDgCxh2OtjufQiLo0BtGLkfAWeP6Ibav7EQcwxSCUbFT2d_5As86dBfPdAWOcXvPrNpT77c47lyKR5DIrGzoGI&amp;smid=url-share">Arianna Rosenbluth</a>, <a href="https://adminrecords.ucsd.edu/Notices/2021/2021-2-23-3.html">Walter Savitch</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/01/alan-selman-1941-2021.html">Alan Selman</a>, <a href="https://math.cornell.edu/professor-robert-strichartz-dies-78">Bob Strichartz</a> and <a href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=5730">Stephen Wiesner</a>. </p><p>We thank our guest posters <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/08/the-long-road.html">Varsha Dani</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/11/reflections-on-trusting-trustlessness.html">Evangelos Georgiadis</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/09/guest-post-on-solving-or-trying-to-poly.html">Bogdan Grechuk</a>, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/08/do-four-colors-suffice.html">David Marcus</a> and <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/12/yes-virginia-there-is-santa-clause-for.html">Hunter Monroe</a>.</p><p>In May I <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/05/emerging-from-pandemic.html">posted</a> on emerging from the pandemic. Then came Delta. Now comes Omicron pushing us back online next month. I hope Pi-day doesn't bring us the Pi-variant.</p><p>Wishing for a more normal 2022.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-23T14:20:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-23T14:20:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-01-04T20:55:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/23/postdoc-in-complexity-theory-at-university-of-warwick-apply-by-january-20-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/23/postdoc-in-complexity-theory-at-university-of-warwick-apply-by-january-20-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc in Complexity Theory at University of Warwick (apply by January 20, 2022)</title>
    <summary>A postdoc position in complexity theory is available in the research group of Igor Carboni Oliveira at the University of Warwick. It offers flexible conditions and comes with generous travel support. More information about the position is available on my homepage. To be considered, please send me an email with your CV and list of […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A postdoc position in complexity theory is available in the research group of Igor Carboni Oliveira at the University of Warwick. It offers flexible conditions and comes with generous travel support. More information about the position is available on my homepage.</p>
<p>To be considered, please send me an email with your CV and list of publications. Informal enquiries are also welcome.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.dcs.warwick.ac.uk/~igorcarb/postdoc-position.html">https://www.dcs.warwick.ac.uk/~igorcarb/postdoc-position.html</a><br/>
Email: igorcarb@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-23T11:22:37Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-23T11:22:37Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/23/three-faculty-positions-in-tcs-at-university-of-amsterdam-apply-by-february-7-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/23/three-faculty-positions-in-tcs-at-university-of-amsterdam-apply-by-february-7-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Three Faculty Positions in TCS at University of Amsterdam (apply by February 7, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The ILLC and Informatics Institute at the University of Amsterdam wish to significantly strengthen their profiles in the area of Theoretical Computer Science, and we currently are inviting applications for three faculty positions (in any area of specialisation). There are opportunities at the Assistant, Associate, and Full Professor level. We specifically encourage women to apply. […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The ILLC and Informatics Institute at the University of Amsterdam wish to significantly strengthen their profiles in the area of Theoretical Computer Science, and we currently are inviting applications for three faculty positions (in any area of specialisation). There are opportunities at the Assistant, Associate, and Full Professor level. We specifically encourage women to apply.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://theory.amsterdam">https://theory.amsterdam</a><br/>
Email: ulle.endriss@uva.nl</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-23T09:42:00Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-23T09:42:00Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/22/postdoc-at-university-of-salzburg-apply-by-february-20-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2021/12/22/postdoc-at-university-of-salzburg-apply-by-february-20-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at University of Salzburg (apply by February 20, 2022)</title>
    <summary>A full-time postdoc position for two years is available in the “Big Data Algorithms” research group led by Assistant Professor Sebastian Forster at University of Salzburg. The position is within an ERC-funded project with the main goal of designing new dynamic algorithms with theoretical guarantees for fundamental graph problems. The start date is fall 2022 […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>A full-time postdoc position for two years is available in the “Big Data Algorithms” research group led by Assistant Professor Sebastian Forster at University of Salzburg. The position is within an ERC-funded project with the main goal of designing new dynamic algorithms with theoretical guarantees for fundamental graph problems. The start date is fall 2022 (negotiable).</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.cs.sbg.ac.at/~forster/jobs.html">https://www.cs.sbg.ac.at/~forster/jobs.html</a><br/>
Email: forster@cs.sbg.ac.at</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2021-12-22T22:29:41Z</updated>
    <published>2021-12-22T22:29:41Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-05T02:37:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
