<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2022-01-29T10:38:52Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11731</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11731" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An Algorithmic Framework for Locally Constrained Homomorphisms</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643414400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bulteau:Laurent.html">Laurent Bulteau</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dabrowski:Konrad_K=.html">Konrad K. Dabrowski</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/K=ouml=hler:Noleen.html">Noleen Köhler</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/o/Ordyniak:Sebastian.html">Sebastian Ordyniak</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Paulusma:Dani=euml=l.html">Daniël Paulusma</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11731">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A homomorphism $f$ from a guest graph $G$ to a host graph $H$ is locally
bijective, injective or surjective if for every $u\in V(G)$, the restriction of
$f$ to the neighbourhood of $u$ is bijective, injective or surjective,
respectively. The corresponding decision problems, LBHOM, LIHOM and LSHOM, are
well studied both on general graphs and on special graph classes. Apart from
complexity results when the problems are parameterized by the treewidth and
maximum degree of the guest graph, the three problems still lack a thorough
study of their parameterized complexity. This paper fills this gap: we prove a
number of new FPT, W[1]-hard and para-NP-complete results by considering a
hierarchy of parameters of the guest graph $G$. For our FPT results, we do this
through the development of a new algorithmic framework that involves a general
ILP model. To illustrate the applicability of the new framework, we also use it
to prove FPT results for the Role Assignment problem, which originates from
social network theory and is closely related to locally surjective
homomorphisms.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11602</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11602" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Budgeted Steiner Networks: Three Terminals with Equal Path Weights</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643414400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Szegedy:Mario.html">Mario Szegedy</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/y/Yu:Jingjin.html">Jingjin Yu</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11602">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Given a set of terminals in 2D/3D, the network with the shortest total length
that connects all terminals is a Steiner tree. On the other hand, with enough
budget, every terminal can be connected to every other terminals via a straight
edge, yielding a complete graph over all terminals. In this work, we study a
generalization of Steiner trees asking what happens in between these two
extremes. Focusing on three terminals with equal pairwise path weights, we
characterize the full evolutionary pathway between the Steiner tree and the
complete graph, which contains intriguing intermediate structures.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11542</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11542" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>An improved judgement algorithm of point in-out convex polygons</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643414400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Sun Yixuan, Zhu Zhehao <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11542">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This paper proposed a method to judge whether the point is inside or outside
of the simple convex polygon by the intersection of the vertical line. It
determined the point to an area enclosed by two straight lines, then convert
the problem of determining whether a point is inside or outside of a convex
polygon into the problem of determining whether a point is inside or outside of
a quadrilateral. After that, use the ray method to judge it. The complexity of
this algorithm is O(1) to O(n). As the experimental results show, the algorithm
has fewer intersections and greatly improves the efficiency of the judgment.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11412</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11412" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Reduction of Two-Dimensional Data for Speeding Up Convex Hull Computation</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643414400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mukherjee:Debashis.html">Debashis Mukherjee</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11412">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>An incremental approach for computation of convex hull for data points in
two-dimensions is presented. The algorithm is not output-sensitive and costs a
time that is linear in the size of data points at input. Graham's scan is
applied only on a subset of the data points, represented at the extremal of the
dataset. Points are classified for extremal, in proportion with the modular
distance, about an imaginary point interior to the region bounded by convex
hull of the dataset assumed for origin or center in polar coordinate. A subset
of the data is arrived by terminating at until an event of no change in maximal
points is observed per bin, for iteratively and exponentially decreasing
intervals.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11358</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11358" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fairness implications of encoding protected categorical attributes</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643414400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/Mougan:Carlos.html">Carlos Mougan</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Alvarez:Jose_M=.html">Jose M. Alvarez</a>, Gourab K Patro, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Ruggieri:Salvatore.html">Salvatore Ruggieri</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Staab:Steffen.html">Steffen Staab</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11358">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Protected attributes are often presented as categorical features that need to
be encoded before feeding them into a machine learning algorithm. Encoding
these attributes is paramount as they determine the way the algorithm will
learn from the data. Categorical feature encoding has a direct impact on the
model performance and fairness. In this work, we compare the accuracy and
fairness implications of the two most well-known encoders: one-hot encoding and
target encoding. We distinguish between two types of induced bias that can
arise while using these encodings and can lead to unfair models. The first
type, irreducible bias, is due to direct group category discrimination and a
second type, reducible bias, is due to large variance in less statistically
represented groups. We take a deeper look into how regularization methods for
target encoding can improve the induced bias while encoding categorical
features. Furthermore, we tackle the problem of intersectional fairness that
arises when mixing two protected categorical features leading to higher
cardinality. This practice is a powerful feature engineering technique used for
boosting model performance. We study its implications on fairness as it can
increase both types of induced bias
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11297</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11297" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Generation Matrix: An Embeddable Matrix Representation for Hierarchical Trees</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643414400</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/c/Cai:Jianping.html">Jianping Cai</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Ximeng.html">Ximeng Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Li:Jiayin.html">Jiayin Li</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Shuangyue.html">Shuangyue Zhang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11297">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Starting from the local structures to study hierarchical trees is a common
research method. However, the cumbersome analysis and description make the
naive method challenging to adapt to the increasingly complex hierarchical tree
problems. To improve the efficiency of hierarchical tree research, we propose
an embeddable matrix representation for hierarchical trees, called Generation
Matrix. It can transform the abstract hierarchical tree into a concrete matrix
representation and then take the hierarchical tree as a whole to study, which
dramatically reduces the complexity of research. Mathematical analysis shows
that Generation Matrix can simulate various recursive algorithms without
accessing local structures and provides a variety of interpretable matrix
operations to support the research of hierarchical trees. Applying Generation
Matrix to differential privacy hierarchical tree release, we propose a
Generation Matrix-based optimally consistent release algorithm (GMC). It
provides an exceptionally concise process description so that we can describe
its core steps as a simple matrix expression rather than multiple complicated
recursive processes like existing algorithms. Our experiments show that GMC
takes only a few seconds to complete a release for large-scale datasets with
more than 10 million nodes. The calculation efficiency is increased by up to
100 times compared with the state-of-the-art schemes.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11655</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11655" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>BFS based distributed algorithm for parallel local directed sub-graph enumeration</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643328000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Levinas:Itay.html">Itay Levinas</a>, Roy Scherz, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Louzoun:Yoram.html">Yoram Louzoun</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11655">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Estimating the frequency of sub-graphs is of importance for many tasks,
including sub-graph isomorphism, kernel-based anomaly detection, and network
structure analysis. While multiple algorithms were proposed for full
enumeration or sampling-based estimates, these methods fail in very large
graphs. Recent advances in parallelization allow for estimates of total
sub-graphs counts in very large graphs. The task of counting the frequency of
each sub-graph associated with each vertex also received excellent solutions
for undirected graphs. However, there is currently no good solution for very
large directed graphs.
</p>
<p>We here propose VDMC (Vertex specific Distributed Motif Counting) -- a fully
distributed algorithm to optimally count all the 3 and 4 vertices connected
directed graphs (sub-graph motifs) associated with each vertex of a graph. VDMC
counts each motif only once and its efficacy is linear in the number of counted
motifs. It is fully parallelized to be efficient in GPU-based computation. VDMC
is based on three main elements: 1) Ordering the vertices and only counting
motifs containing increasing order vertices, 2) sub-ordering motifs based on
the average length of the BFS composing the motif, and 3) removing isomorphisms
only once for the entire graph. We here compare VDMC to analytical estimates of
the expected number of motifs and show its accuracy. VDMC is available as a
highly efficient CPU and GPU code with a novel data structure for efficient
graph manipulation. We show the efficacy of VDMC and real-world graphs. VDMC
allows for the precise analysis of sub-graph frequency around each vertex in
large graphs and opens the way for the extension of methods until now limited
to graphs of thousands of edges to graphs with millions of edges and above.
</p>
<p>GIT: https://github.com/louzounlab/graph-measures
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11587</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11587" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Two-Commodity Flow is Equivalent to Linear Programming under Nearly-Linear Time Reductions</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643328000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Ding:Ming.html">Ming Ding</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kyng:Rasmus.html">Rasmus Kyng</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zhang:Peng.html">Peng Zhang</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11587">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We give a nearly-linear time reduction that encodes any linear program as a
2-commodity flow problem with only a small blow-up in size. Under mild
assumptions similar to those employed by modern fast solvers for linear
programs, our reduction causes only a polylogarithmic multiplicative increase
in the size of the program and runs in nearly-linear time. Our reduction
applies to high-accuracy approximation algorithms and exact algorithms. Given
an approximate solution to the 2-commodity flow problem, we can extract a
solution to the linear program in linear time with only a polynomial factor
increase in the error. This implies that any algorithm that solves the
2-commodity flow problem can solve linear programs in essentially the same
time. Given a directed graph with edge capacities and two source-sink pairs,
the goal of the 2-commodity flow problem is to maximize the sum of the flows
routed between the two source-sink pairs subject to edge capacities and flow
conservation. A 2-commodity flow can be directly written as a linear program,
and thus we establish a nearly-tight equivalence between these two classes of
problems.
</p>
<p>Our proof follows the outline of Itai's polynomial-time reduction of a linear
program to a 2-commodity flow problem (JACM'78). Itai's reduction shows that
exactly solving 2-commodity flow and exactly solving linear programming are
polynomial-time equivalent. We improve Itai's reduction to nearly preserve the
problem representation size in each step. In addition, we establish an error
bound for approximately solving each intermediate problem in the reduction, and
show that the accumulated error is polynomially bounded. We remark that our
reduction does not run in strongly polynomial time and that it is open whether
2-commodity flow and linear programming are equivalent in strongly polynomial
time.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11550</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11550" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Predecessor on the Ultra-Wide Word RAM</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643328000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Bille:Philip.html">Philip Bille</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/G=oslash=rtz:Inge_Li.html">Inge Li Gørtz</a>, Tord Stordalen <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11550">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We consider the predecessor problem on the ultra-wide word RAM model of
computation, which extends the word RAM model with 'ultrawords' consisting of
$w^2$ bits [TAMC, 2015]. The model supports arithmetic and boolean operations
on ultrawords, in addition to 'scattered' memory operations that access or
modify $w$ (potentially non-contiguous) memory addresses simultaneously. The
ultra-wide word RAM model captures (and idealizes) modern vector processor
architectures.
</p>
<p>Our main result is a simple, linear space data structure that supports
predecessor in constant time and updates in amortized, expected constant time.
This improves the space of the previous constant time solution that uses space
in the order of the size of the universe.
</p>
<p>Our result is based on a new implementation of the classic $x$-fast trie data
structure of Willard [Inform.~Process.~Lett. 17(2), 1983] combined with a new
dictionary data structure that supports fast parallel lookups.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11369</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11369" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>$c^3$-Local Testable Codes from Lossless Expanders</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643328000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lin:Ting=Chun.html">Ting-Chun Lin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hsieh:Min=Hsiu.html">Min-Hsiu Hsieh</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11369">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>A locally testable code (LTC) is an error correcting code with a property
tester. The tester tests if a word is codeword by reading constant random bits
and rejects the word with probability proportional to the distance from the
word to the closest codeword. An important open question until recently is
whether there exist $c^3$-LTCs which are LTCs with constant rate, constant
relative distance and constant locality. In this work, we construct a new LTC
family using 1-sided lossless expanders and balanced products.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T22:42:44Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11326</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11326" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>High-order Line Graphs of Non-uniform Hypergraphs: Algorithms, Applications, and Experimental Analysis</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1643328000</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Liu:Xu_T=.html">Xu T. Liu</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/f/Firoz:Jesun.html">Jesun Firoz</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Aksoy:Sinan.html">Sinan Aksoy</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Amburg:Ilya.html">Ilya Amburg</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lumsdaine:Andrew.html">Andrew Lumsdaine</a>, Cliff Joslyn, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Gebremedhin:Assefaw_H=.html">Assefaw H. Gebremedhin</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/p/Praggastis:Brenda.html">Brenda Praggastis</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2201.11326">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Hypergraphs offer flexible and robust data representations for many
applications, but methods that work directly on hypergraphs are not readily
available and tend to be prohibitively expensive. Much of the current analysis
of hypergraphs relies on first performing a graph expansion -- either based on
the nodes (clique expansion), or on the edges (line graph) -- and then running
standard graph analytics on the resulting representative graph. However, this
approach suffers from massive space complexity and high computational cost with
increasing hypergraph size. Here, we present efficient, parallel algorithms to
accelerate and reduce the memory footprint of higher-order graph expansions of
hypergraphs. Our results focus on the edge-based $s$-line graph expansion, but
the methods we develop work for higher-order clique expansions as well. To the
best of our knowledge, ours is the first framework to enable hypergraph
spectral analysis of a large dataset on a single shared-memory machine. Our
methods enable the analysis of datasets from many domains that previous
graph-expansion-based models are unable to provide. The proposed $s$-line graph
computation algorithms are orders of magnitude faster than state-of-the-art
sparse general matrix-matrix multiplication methods, and obtain approximately
$5-31{\times}$ speedup over a prior state-of-the-art heuristic-based algorithm
for $s$-line graph computation.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/01/27/open-algorithmic-problems</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/01/27/open-algorithmic-problems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Open algorithmic problems from a talk by Alon</title>
    <summary>The UCI mathematics department had a departmental colloquium today given by Noga Alon, titled “The Polynomial Method and its Algorithmic Aspects”. One part of his talk that I found very interesting was a collection of easy-to-state combinatorial problems where the existence of a solution can be proved, but there is no known efficient (polynomial time) algorithm for finding the solution:</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The UCI mathematics department had a departmental colloquium today given by Noga Alon, titled “The Polynomial Method and its Algorithmic Aspects”. One part of his talk that I found very interesting was a collection of easy-to-state combinatorial problems where the existence of a solution can be proved, but there is no known efficient (polynomial time) algorithm for finding the solution:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Let \(p\) be a prime number, and suppose that we are given two inputs: a sequence \(A=a_1,a_2,\dots a_k\) of elements of \(\mathbb{Z}_p\), of length \(k\lt p\), not necessarily distinct from each other, and a set \(B\), also consisting of \(k\) elements of \(\mathbb{Z}_p\), distinct but not ordered. Can we pair them up by assigning an ordering \(b_1,b_2,\dots\) to the elements of \(B\) so that all of the sums \(a_i+b_i\) are distinct? For instance, if all of the \(A\)’s are equal, then any ordering of the \(B\)’s will work.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Let \(G\) be a bipartite graph that has a perfect matching. Assign “non-degrees” to the vertices on one side of the bipartition, numbers that should not be the degree of the vertex. Can we delete some subset of the vertices on the other side, so that in the remaining graph each vertex’s degree is different from its non-degree? For instance, if the non-degrees are all zero, then \(G\) itself will work (it has nonzero degree because it has a perfect matching). If the non-degrees are all non-zero, then we can delete all of the vertices on the other side of the bipartition.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Let \(G\) be a planar graph with degree three at every vertex, and suppose also that each edge of \(G\) has a list of three colors available to it. Can we assign colors from these lists to the edges so that each vertex touches edges of three different colors?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Let \(C_1\) and \(C_2\) be proper colorings of a large \(d\)-dimensional grid, using \(q\ge d+2\) colors, and let \(S_1\) and \(S_2\) be subsets of the vertices of the grid that are far apart from each other (I am not sure how far this needs to be but it seems to be \(d\pm O(1)\) or maybe \(q\pm O(1)\)). Can we find a proper coloring of the whole grid that blends between the two colorings, agreeing with each \(C_i\) on \(S_i\)? This one comes from a new paper by Alon, Raimundo Briceño, Nishant Chandgotia, Alexander Magazinov, and Yinon Spinka, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0963548320000395">“Mixing properties of colourings of the \(\mathbb{Z}^d\) lattice”, <em>Combinatorics, Probability and Computing</em> 2021</a>. Fewer colors will not always work.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>In all of these cases, the answer to the existence problem is yes, but we don’t know of an efficient algorithm for finding the structure that is supposed to exist. Instead, Alon proves the existence non-constructively, through a combinatorial <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilbert%27s_Nullstellensatz">Nullstellensatz</a> encoding the principle that low-degree polynomials don’t have many roots. For one-variable polynomials of degree \(d\), for instance, there cannot be more than \(d\) values at which the polynomial is zero. But the degree really has to be \(d\), and not merely at most \(d\), because the degree-zero constant-zero polynomial is zero everywhere.</p>

<p>The analogous principle Alon uses for higher numbers of variables is the following: Let \(p\) be a polynomial of degree \(d\) in the variables \(x_1,x_2,\dots x_n\), over some field, and let \(t_i\) be the exponents of a nonzero monomial \(\prod_i x_i^{t_i}\) of degree \(d\) in \(p\). Additionally, let \(S_i\) be (not necessarily distinct) sets of \(t_i+1\) elements. Then we can choose an element \(s_i\) in each \(S_i\) such that \(p(s_1,s_2,\dots)\) is non-zero. Alon surveys this principle and its applications in his paper <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0963548398003411">“Combinatorial Nullstellensatz”, <em>Combinatorics, Probability and Computing</em> 1999</a>.</p>

<p>The hard parts about using this method to prove existence in combinatorial problems such as the ones above are finding the right polynomial and proving that it has a nonzero coefficient at the right monomial. The problem on reordering with distinct pairwise sums, for instance, comes from Alon’s paper <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02773567">“Additive Latin transversals”, <em>Israel J. Math.</em> 2000</a> and uses the polynomial</p>

\[\prod_{i\lt j}(x_i-x_j)(a_i+x_i-a_j-x_j)\]

<p>where each \(S_i=B\), the first terms in the product can only be nonzero if each \(x_i\) is chosen to be a distinct member of \(B\), and the second terms in the product can only be nonzero if the pairwise sums are different from each other. The coefficient of the monomial \(\prod x_i^{k-1}\) turns out to be (up to sign) exactly \(k!\), which is nonzero modulo \(p\) by the assumptions that \(p\) is prime and \(k\lt p\). The nonzero coefficients for the other two problems are not so easy to compute: they are the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permanent_(mathematics)">permanent</a> (number of perfect matchings) and the number of 3-edge-colorings of the given graphs. For the case of 3-edge-colorings, the fact that this number is nonzero is one of the equivalent forms of the 4-color theorem.</p>

<p>The general problem of constructing a nonzero solution to an instance of the combinatorial Nullstellensatz whose polynomial is described by an arithmetic circuit is (according to Alon) as hard as inverting arbitrary one-way permutations, a standard cryptographic primitive. This suggests that a polynomial-time construction algorithm does not exist; if it did exist, it would break a lot of modern cryptography. On the other hand, proving that it does not exist would also prove \(\mathsf{P}\ne\mathsf{NP}\). Despite this relation to standard hard problems, there’s no strong reason for believing that any of the combinatorial problems outlined above is as hard as the general case, so maybe they might still have an efficient algorithm. If so, it would probably translate into an existence proof that is substantially different than the ones we already have for these problems.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107698894668333119">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-27T23:08:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-27T23:08:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T07:26:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://differentialprivacy.org/synth-data-1/</id>
    <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/synth-data-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A simple recipe for private synthetic data generation</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In the <a href="https://differentialprivacy.org/synth-data-0/">last blog post</a>, we covered the potential pitfalls of synthetic data without formal privacy guarantees, and motivated the need for differentially private synthetic data mechanisms.  In this blog post, we will describe the <strong>select-measure-generate</strong> paradigm, which is a simple and effective template for designing synthetic data mechanisms.  The three steps underlying the select-measure-generate paradigm are illustrated and explained below.</p>

<p><img alt="" src="https://differentialprivacy.org/images/select-measure-reconstruct.png"/></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Select</strong> a collection of queries to measure — typically low-dimensional marginals.</li>
  <li><strong>Measure</strong> the selected queries privately using a noise-addition mechanism.</li>
  <li><strong>Generate</strong> synthetic data that best explains the noisy measurements.<sup id="fnref:0"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:0" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
</ol>

<p>Mechanisms in this class differ primarily in their methodology for selecting queries and their algorithm for generating synthetic data from noisy measurements.  The focus of this blog post is the final <strong>Generate</strong> step.  Specifically, we will explore different ways in which one can model data distributions for the purpose of generating synthetic data, outlining the qualitative pros and cons of each method. We will then introduce the <strong><a href="https://github.com/ryan112358/private-pgm" target="_blank">Marginal-Based Inference (MBI)</a></strong> repository that provides methods that, given some set of noisy measurements, enables users to generate synthetic data in a generic and scalable way.</p>

<p>Separating the Generate subroutine from the existing synthetic data generation mechanisms greatly simplifies the design space of new differentially private mechanisms.  It allows the mechanism designer to focus on <em>selecting the queries</em> to maximize utility of the synthetic data, rather than <em>how to generate synthetic data</em> that explain the noisy measurements well.  Both are challenging technical problems that require different techniques to solve, and MBI provides principled solutions to the latter problem, while exposing an interface that can be readily adopted by mechanism designers.</p>

<h1 id="the-generate-subproblem-a-unifying-view">The Generate Subproblem: A Unifying View</h1>

<p>In this section we will introduce the main optimization problem that underlies several methods for the Generate subproblem, and provide a high-level overview of how each method attempts to solve this optimization problem. Let \( y = \mathcal{M}(D) \) be the noisy measurements obtained from running a privacy mechanism on a discrete dataset \( D \).  Our goal is to post-process these noise measurements to obtain synthetic data that explains them well.  In particular, we wish to minimize over the space of all <em>datasets</em> for one that maximizes the likelihood of the observations \( y \).<sup id="fnref:1"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:1" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>\[ \hat{D} \in \text{arg} \max_{D \in \mathcal{D}} \log \mathbb{P}[\mathcal{M}(D) = y] \]</p>

<p>This is a high-dimensional discrete optimization problem, and is generally intractable to solve in practice, even in low-dimensional settings.  It is common to consider the relaxed problem that instead optimizes over the set of <em>probability distributions</em> \( \mathcal{S} \):</p>

<p>\[ \hat{P} \in \text{arg} \max_{P \in \mathcal{S}} \log \mathbb{P}[\mathcal{M}(P) = y] \label{eq1} \tag{1} \]</p>

<p>More generally, we can consider any objective function that measures how well \( P \) explains \( y \).  The log-likelihood is a natural choice, although other choices are also possible and used in practice.  In the special-but-common case where the mechanism is an instance of the Gaussian mechanism, we have \( \mathcal{M}(D) = f(D) + \mathcal{N}(0, \sigma^2)^k \) and \( \log \mathbb{P}[\mathcal{M}(P) = y] \propto - || f(P) - y ||_2^2 \).  If \( f \) is a linear function of \( P \), then Problem \ref{eq1} is simply a quadratic program.  In the subsequent subsections, we will describe different approaches to solve or approximately solve Problem \ref{eq1}.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Remark 1</strong>: The distribution learned from solving Problem \ref{eq1} will resemble the true data with respect to the statistics measured by \( \mathcal{M} \).  It may or may not accurately preserve other statistics — that is data dependent.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Remark 2</strong>: The most common statistics to measure are <strong>low-dimensional marginals</strong>.  A marginal for a subset of attributes counts the number of records in the dataset that match each setting of possible values. They are appealing statistics to measure because:</p>
  <ul>
    <li>They capture low-dimensional structure common in real world data distributions.</li>
    <li>Each cell in a marginal is a count, a statistic that is fairly robust to noise.</li>
    <li>One individual can only contribute to a single cell of a marginal, so all cells have low sensitivity and can be measured simultaneously with low privacy cost.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="direct">Direct</h3>

<p>We can attempt to solve Problem \ref{eq1} directly by utilizing any algorithm for convex optimization over the probability simplex, such as multiplicative weights.  This method works well in low-dimensional regimes, although quickly becomes intractable for higher-dimensional domains, where it is generally intractable to even enumerate all the entries of a single distribution \( P \), let alone optimize over the space of all distributions.</p>

<p>Until recently, variants of the direct method were the only general-purpose solutions available for this problem, and as a result, many mechanisms struggled to scale to high-dimensional domains.  Recently, several methods have been proposed that attempt to overcome the curse of dimensionality inherent in the direct approach, which scale by imposing additional assumptions on the mechanism \( \mathcal{M} \) and/or by relaxing the optimization problem.  A common theme is to restrict attention to a subset of joint distributions which have tractable representations.     The sections below describe these more scalable methods, including the different (implicit) assumptions each method makes, as well as the consequences of those assumptions.</p>

<h3 id="probabilistic-graphical-models-pgm">Probabilistic Graphical Models (PGM)</h3>

<p>The first method we describe is <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.09136" target="\_blank">PGM</a>, which was a key component of the first-place solution in the 2018 NIST Differential Privacy <a href="https://www.nist.gov/ctl/pscr/open-innovation-prize-challenges/past-prize-challenges/2018-differential-privacy-synthetic" target="\_blank">Synthetic Data Competition</a> and in both the first and second-place solutions in the follow-up <a href="https://www.nist.gov/ctl/pscr/open-innovation-prize-challenges/current-and-upcoming-prize-challenges/2020-differential" target="\_blank">Temporal Map Competition</a>.</p>

<p>PGM scales by restricting attention to distributions that can be represented as a graphical model \( P_{\theta} \).  The key observation of PGM is that when \( \mathcal{M} \) only depends on \( P \) through its low-dimensional marginals, then one of the optimizers of Problem \ref{eq1} is a graphical model with parameters \( \theta \).  In this case, Problem \ref{eq1} is under-determined and typically has infinitely many solutions.  It turns out that the solution found by PGM has maximum entropy among all solutions to the problem — a very natural way to break ties among equally good solutions. Remarkably, these facts are true for any dataset — they do not require the underlying data to be generated from a graphical model with the same structure <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.04978" target="\_blank">[MMS21]</a>.</p>

<p>The parameter vector \( \theta \) is often much smaller than \( P \), and we can efficiently optimize it, bypassing the curse of dimensionality in this special case.  The size of \( \theta \) and in turn the complexity of PGM depends on the mechanism \( \mathcal{M} \), and in the worst case is the same as the Direct method.<sup id="fnref:6"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:6" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>  However, in many common cases of practical interest, the complexity of PGM is exponentially better than that of Direct, in which case we can efficiently solve the optimization problem above, finding \( \theta \) and thus a tractable representation of \( \hat{P} \).  The complexity ultimately depends on the size of the junction tree derived from the mechanism \( \mathcal{M} \), and understanding this relationship requires some expertise in graphical models.  However, if we utilize this understanding to design \( \mathcal{M} \), we can avoid this worst-case behavior, as <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.04978" target="\_blank">MST</a> and <a href="http://vldb.org/pvldb/vol14/p2190-cai.pdf" target="\_blank">PrivMRF</a> do.</p>

<h3 id="relaxed-tabular">Relaxed Tabular</h3>

<p>An alternative approach was proposed in the recent <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.06641" target="\_blank">RAP</a> paper.  The key idea is to restrict attention to “pseudo-distributions” that can be represented in a relaxed tabular format.  The format is similar to the one-hot encoding of a discrete dataset, although the entries need not be \( 0 \) or \( 1 \), which enables gradient-based optimization to be performed on the cells in this table.  The number of rows is a tunable knob that can be set to trade off expressive capacity with computational efficiency.  With a sufficiently large knob size, the true minimizer of the original problem can be expressed in this way, but there is no guarantee that gradient-based optimization will converge to it because this representation introduces non-convexity.  Moreover, the search space of this method includes “spurious” distributions, so even the global optimum of relaxed problem would not necessarily solve the original problem.<sup id="fnref:9"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:9" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>  Despite these drawbacks, this method appears to work well in practice.</p>

<h3 id="generative-networks">Generative Networks</h3>

<p>Among the iterative methods introduced by <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.07153" target="\_blank">[LVW21]</a> is GEM (Generative networks with the exponential mechanism), an approach inspired by generative adversarial networks. They propose representing any dataset as mixture of product distributions over attributes in the data domain. They implicitly encode such distributions using a generative neural network with a softmax layer. In concrete terms, given some Gaussian noise \( \mathbf{z} \sim \mathcal{N}(0, I) \), their <strong>Generate</strong> step outputs \( f_\theta(\mathbf{z}) \) where \( f \) is some feedforward neural network parametrized by \( \theta \). \( f_\theta(\mathbf{z}) \) represents a collection of marginal distributions for each individual attribute in the domain, which can be used to directly answer any k-way marginal query. Alternatively, one can sample directly from \( f_\theta(\mathbf{z}) \) if the goal is generate synthetic tabular data.</p>

<p>Note that the size of \( \mathbf{z} \) can be arbitrarily large, meaning that this generative network approach can theoretically be scaled up to capture any distribution \( P \). Moreover, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.07153">[LVW21]</a> show that one can achieve strong performance in practical settings even when \( \mathbf{z} \) is small, making such generative network approaches to scale in terms of both computation and memory. Howevever, as is commonly found in deep learning methods, this optimization problem is nonconvex.</p>

<h3 id="local-consistency">Local Consistency</h3>

<p>Finally, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.07153" target="\_blank">GUM</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.06153" target="\_blank">APPGM</a> do not search over any space of distributions, but instead impose <em>local consistency</em> constraints on the noisy measurements.  These methods relax Problem \ref{eq1} to optimize over the space of pseudo-marginals, rather than distributions.  The pseudo-marginals are required to be internally consistent, but there is no guarantee that there is a distribution which realizes those pseudo-marginals.  As a result, the solution found by these methods need not be feasible in Problem \ref{eq1}.  Nevertheless, we can attempt to generate synthetic data using heuristics to translate these locally consistent pseudo-marginals into synthetic tabular data.  This approach was used by team DPSyn in both NIST competitions.</p>

<h3 id="summary">Summary</h3>

<p>A qualitative comparison between the discussed methods is given in the table below.<sup id="fnref:7"><a class="footnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fn:7" rel="footnote">5</a></sup></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Remark 3</strong>: Among the alternatives discussed here, only Direct and PGM can be expected to solve Problem \ref{eq1}.    The alternatives fail to solve Problem \ref{eq1} in general, either from non-convexity, or from introducing spurious distributions to the search space.  This distinguishing feature of PGM comes at a cost: the complexity can be much higher than the alternatives, and in the worst-case, will not be feasible to run.  In such cases, one of the approximations must be used instead.</p>
</blockquote>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td><strong>Direct</strong></td>
      <td><strong>PGM</strong></td>
      <td><strong>Relaxed Tabular</strong></td>
      <td><strong>Generative Networks</strong></td>
      <td><strong>Local Consistency</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Search space includes optimum</td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Search space excludes spurious distributions</td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: red;">No</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: red;">No</span></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Convexity preserving</td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: red;">No</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: red;">No</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Solves Problem \ref{eq1}</td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Yes</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: red;">No</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: red;">No</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: red;">No</span></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Factors influencing scalability</td>
      <td><span style="color: red;">Size of Entire Domain</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: orange;">Size of Junction Tree</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Size of Largest Marginal</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Size of Largest Marginal</span></td>
      <td><span style="color: green;">Size of Largest Marginal</span></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h1 id="generating-synthetic-data-with-mbi">Generating Synthetic Data with MBI</h1>

<p>Now that we have introduced the techniques underlying the Generate step, we will show how to utilize the implementations in the MBI repository to develop end-to-end mechanisms for differentially private synthetic data.</p>

<h2 id="preparing-noisy-measurements">Preparing Noisy Measurements</h2>

<p>The input to any method for Generate is a collection of noisy measurements.  We show below how to prepare these measurements in a format compatible with the methods for Generate implemented in the MBI repository.  The measurements are represented as a list, where each element of the list is a noisy marginal (represented as a numpy array), along with relevant metadata including the attributes in the marginal and the amount of noise used to answer it.  In the code snippet below, the selected marginals are hard-coded, but in general this list can be modified to tailor the synthetic data towards a different set of marginals.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python"><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="nn">numpy</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">np</span>
<span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">scipy</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">sparse</span>
<span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">mbi</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">Dataset</span>

<span class="n">data</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Dataset</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">load</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'adult.csv'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'adult-domain.json'</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># SELECT the marginals we'd like to measure
</span><span class="n">marginals</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[(</span><span class="s">'marital-status'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'sex'</span><span class="p">),</span>
             <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'education-num'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'race'</span><span class="p">),</span>
             <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'sex'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'hours-per-week'</span><span class="p">),</span>
             <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'workclass'</span><span class="p">,),</span>
             <span class="p">(</span><span class="s">'marital-status'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'occupation'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s">'income&gt;50K'</span><span class="p">)]</span>

<span class="c1"># MEASURE the marginals and log the noisy answers
</span><span class="n">sigma</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">50</span> 
<span class="n">measurements</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[]</span>
<span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">M</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">marginals</span><span class="p">:</span>
    <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">data</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">project</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">M</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="n">datavector</span><span class="p">()</span>
    <span class="n">y</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">random</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">normal</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">loc</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">scale</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">sigma</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">size</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">shape</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">I</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">sparse</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">eye</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">size</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">measurements</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">append</span><span class="p">(</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">I</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">y</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">sigma</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">M</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">)</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>The above code snippet is a 5-fold composition of Gaussian mechanisms with \( \sigma = 50 \), and hence the entire mechanism is \( \frac{5}{2 \sigma^2} = \frac{1}{1000} \)-zCDP.</p>

<h2 id="generating-synthetic-data-from-measurements">Generating Synthetic Data from Measurements</h2>

<p>Given measurements represented in the format above, we can readily generate synthetic data using one of several methods.  For example, the code snippet below generates synthetic data that approximately matches the noisy measurements:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python"><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">mbi</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">FactoredInference</span> <span class="c1"># PGM
</span><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">mbi</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">MixtureInference</span>  <span class="c1"># Relaxed Tabular + Softmax
</span><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">mbi</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">LocalInference</span>    <span class="c1"># Local Consistency
</span><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="nn">mbi</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">PublicInference</span>   <span class="c1"># Not Discussed
</span>
<span class="c1"># GENERATE synthetic data using PGM 
</span><span class="n">engine</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">FactoredInference</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">data</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">domain</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">iters</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">2500</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">model</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">engine</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">estimate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">measurements</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">synth</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">model</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">synthetic_data</span><span class="p">()</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>To generate synthetic data, we have to simply instantiate one of the inference engines imported.  In the code snippet above, we use the FactoredInference engine, which corresponds to the PGM method.  The other inference engines share the same interface, and can be used instead if desired.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Remark 4</strong>: By utilizing the inference engines implemented in MBI, end-to-end synthetic data mechanisms can be written with remarkably little code.  This simple example required less than 25 lines of code, and <a href="https://github.com/ryan112358/private-pgm/tree/master/mechanisms" target="\_blank">more complex mechanisms</a> can usually be written in a single file with less than 200 lines of code.  As a result, future research can focus on the measurement selection subproblem, and new ideas can more rapidly be evaluated and iterated on.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We evaluated the quality of the synthetic data generated by measuring the error of the measured marginals.  Interestingly, the synthetic data has lower error than the noisy marginals, with reductions in error up to 30% for the larger marginals, and around 3% for the smaller ones.</p>

<p><img alt="" src="https://differentialprivacy.org/images/smr1.png"/></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Remark 5:</strong> It is not surprising that the synthetic data enjoys lower error than the noisy marginals.  Problem \ref{eq1} can be seen as a <em>projection problem</em>, and there is substantial theoretical <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1212.0297" target="\_blank">[NTZ12]</a> and empirical [<a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/2783258.2783366" target="\_blank">LWK15</a>, <a href="https://systems.cs.columbia.edu/private-systems-class/papers/Abowd2019Census.pdf" target="\_blank">AAGK+19</a>] evidence that solving this problem reduces error.  Intuitively, the benefit arises due to the inconsistencies in the noisy observations that are resolved through the optimization procedure.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We can also use the synthetic data to estimate marginals we didn’t measure with the Gaussian mechanism.  These estimates may or may not be accurate, it depends on the data and the marginal being estimated.  For example, the error on the (sex, income&gt;50K) marginal is around 0.02, while the error on the (education-num, occupation) marginal is about 0.5.</p>

<p><img alt="" src="https://differentialprivacy.org/images/smr2.png"/></p>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Remark 6:</strong> The fact that the synthetic data is not accurate for some marginals is not a limitation of the method used for Generate, but rather an artifact of what marginals were selected.  Thus, it is clear that selecting the right marginals to measure plays a crucial role in the quality of the synthetic data. This is an important open problem that will be the topic of a future blog post.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="coming-up-next">Coming up Next</h1>

<p>In this blog post, we focused on the <strong>Generate</strong> step of the select-measure-generate paradigm.  For the next blog post in this series, we will focus on state-of-the-art approaches to the <strong>Select</strong> sub-problem.  If you have any comments, questions, or remarks, please feel free to share them in the comments section below.  If you would like to try generating synthetic data with MBI, check out this <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1c8gT5m_GWfQoa_mx8eXh4sPD48Y0z3ML?usp=sharing">jupyter notebook</a> on Google Colab!</p>

<hr/>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:0">
      <p>The Generate step is a post-processing of already privatized noisy marginals, and therefore the privacy analysis only needs to reason about the first two steps. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:0">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Here we assume that \( \mathcal{M} \) is a mechanism with a discrete output space.  In practice, this is always the case because any mechanism implemented on a finite computer must have a discrete output space.  For continuous output spaces, interpret the objective function as a log density rather than a log probability. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:1">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>For example, this worst-case behavior is realized if <strong>all</strong> 2-way marginals are measured.  While this can be seen as a limitation of PGM, <a href="http://people.seas.harvard.edu/~salil/research/synthetic-Feb2010.pdf">it is known</a> that generating synthetic data that preserves all 2-way marginals is computationally hard in the worst-case. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:6">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:9">
      <p>This idea was refined into <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.07153" target="\_blank">RAP<sup>softmax</sup></a> in follow-up-work, which overcomes the latter issue, but does not resolve the non-convexity issue. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:9">↩</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:7">
      <p>These approximations were all developed concurrently, and systematic empirical comparisons between them (and PGM) have not been done to date.  Some experimental comparisons can be found in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.07153" target="\_blank">[LVW21]</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.06153">[MPSM21]</a>. <a class="reversefootnote" href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml#fnref:7">↩</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2022-01-27T17:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-27T17:00:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Terrance Liu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://differentialprivacy.org</id>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://differentialprivacy.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Website for the differential privacy research community</subtitle>
      <title>Differential Privacy</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T00:19:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/27/research-fellow-postdoc-at-national-university-of-singapore-apply-by-july-31-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/27/research-fellow-postdoc-at-national-university-of-singapore-apply-by-july-31-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Research Fellow (Postdoc) at National University of Singapore (apply by July 31, 2022)</title>
    <summary>I (Prashant Nalini Vasudevan) have a postdoctoral position available at the Department of Computer Science at NUS. I am looking for someone who works on the foundations of cryptography, information-theoretic cryptography, and/or related areas of theoretical computer science. See the website below for details, and feel free to email me if you have questions. Website: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I (Prashant Nalini Vasudevan) have a postdoctoral position available at the Department of Computer Science at NUS. I am looking for someone who works on the foundations of cryptography, information-theoretic cryptography, and/or related areas of theoretical computer science. See the website below for details, and feel free to email me if you have questions.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://careers.nus.edu.sg/NUS/job/Kent-Ridge-Research-Fellow%2C-Theory-of-Cryptography-Kent/7003544/">https://careers.nus.edu.sg/NUS/job/Kent-Ridge-Research-Fellow%2C-Theory-of-Cryptography-Kent/7003544/</a><br/>
Email: prashant@comp.nus.edu.sg</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-27T09:35:49Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-27T09:35:49Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://thmatters.wordpress.com/?p=1348</id>
    <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/2022/01/26/theory-fest22-call-for-workshop-proposals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>STOC’22: Call for Workshop Proposals</title>
    <summary>The Theory Fest workshops committee is soliciting proposals for workshops. Workshops will be held during the STOC conference week, June 20-24, 2022. The (updated) deadline for submitting proposals is Feb 15, 2022. Details on how to submit a proposal can be found at http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2022/callforworkshops.html.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Theory Fest workshops committee is soliciting proposals for workshops. Workshops will be held during the STOC conference week, June 20-24, 2022. The (updated) deadline for submitting proposals is <strong>Feb 15, 2022</strong>. Details on how to submit a proposal can be found at <a href="http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2022/callforworkshops.html" rel="nofollow">http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2022/callforworkshops.html</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-26T23:43:17Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-26T23:43:17Z</published>
    <category term="Deadlines"/>
    <author>
      <name>shuchic</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://thmatters.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theory Matters</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:47Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-8274979502456032700</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/8274979502456032700/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/a-failure-to-communicate.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8274979502456032700" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/8274979502456032700" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/a-failure-to-communicate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A Failure to Communicate</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The screenwriter Aaron Sorkin wrote an <a href="https://ew.com/movies/aaron-sorkin-column-biopics-being-the-ricardos/">article</a> on prioritizing "Truth over Accuracy". He tells stories from his movies The Social Network and Being the Ricardos, of where he moves away from accuracy to get to the truth of a situation.</p><blockquote><p>My friend and teacher, the late William Goldman, said of his Academy Award-winning screenplay for All the President's Men, "If I'm telling the true story of the fall of the President of the United States, the last thing I'm going to do is make anything up." I understand what he meant in context, but the fact is, as soon as he wrote "FADE IN," he'd committed to making things up. People don't speak in dialogue, and their lives don't play out in a series of scenes that form a narrative. Dramatists do that. They prioritize truth over accuracy. Paintings over photographs.</p></blockquote><p>As scientists we focus on accuracy, as we should in our scientific publications. However being fully accurate can distract from the "truth", the underlying message you want to say, particularly in the title, abstract and introduction of our papers </p><p>Even more so when we promote our research to the public. A science writer once <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2004/04/view-of-science-writer.html">lamented to me</a> that scientists would focus too much on the full accuracy of the science and the names behind it, even though neither serves the reader well.</p><p>Reminds me of the recent Netflix movie <a href="https://www.netflix.com/title/81252357">Don't Look Up</a> satirizes scientists trying to communicate an end-of-the-world event to an untrusting society. I wish it was a better movie but still worth watching just to see Leo DiCaprio and Jennifer Lawrence play scientists frustrated with their ability to communicate a true existential crisis to the government and the general public. </p><p>So how should we as scientists try to frame our messaging to get people onboard, particularly when we say things they don't want to hear? Most importantly, how do scientists regain trust in a world where trust is in short supply. Perhaps we should paint more and photograph less.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-26T17:49:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-26T17:49:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T09:42:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19580</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/26/a-list-of-most-theory-blogs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>A List of Most Theory Blogs</title>
    <summary>The list doesn’t destroy culture; it creates it. Wherever you look in cultural history, you will find lists—Umberto Eco Luca Trevisan, Stefan Schmid, James Lee, Scott Aaronson, Michael Mitzenmacher, Omer Reingold, Lance Fortnow, David Eppstein are some of the top bloggers in theory. That is not “in theory” but “in the area of theory”. This […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<i>The list doesn’t destroy culture; it creates it. Wherever you look in cultural history, you will find lists—Umberto Eco</i></p>
<p>
Luca Trevisan, Stefan Schmid, James Lee, Scott Aaronson, Michael Mitzenmacher, Omer Reingold, Lance Fortnow, David Eppstein are some of the top bloggers in theory. That is not “in theory” but “in the area of theory”. </p>
<p>
<a href="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/all.png?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19583" height="424" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/all.png?resize=600%2C424&amp;ssl=1" width="600"/></a></p>
<p>
This led us to spend some time while watching NFL football to put together a list of theory blogs for computer science. We insist that they are reasonably current. Our rule is: They must have some posts in 2021.</p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Our List </b></p>
<p/><p>
The next is the list:</p>
<ol>
<li> <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/">11011110</a>
</li><li> <a href="http://aaronsadventures.blogspot.com">Adventures in Computation</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://liorpachter.wordpress.com">Bits of DNA</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://blog.simons.berkeley.edu">Calvin Cafe: The Simons Institute</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com">Combinatorics and more</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org">Computational Complexity</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/stavins/blog-posts-economic-view-environment">Constructive Economics</a> <a href="https://math.williams.edu/morgan/">Frank Morgan</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com">Godel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://ai.googleblog.com">Google Research</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://gowers.wordpress.com">Gowers</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://igorpak.wordpress.com">Igor Pak’s</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com">in theory</a>
</li><li> <a href="http://jdh.hamkins.org">Joel David Hamkins</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://www.benkdpearce.com/blog/tag/PhD">kd-PhD</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://jeremykun.com">Math <img alt="{\cap}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Ccap%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> Programming</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://mathprofessorquotes.com">Math Professor Quotes</a>
</li><li> <a href="http://math.andrej.com">Mathematics and Computation</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://micromath.wordpress.com">Mathematics under the Microscope</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=7479">Mathematics without Apologies, by Michael Harris</a>
</li><li> <a href="http://mybiasedcoin.blogspot.com">My Biased Coin</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://www.wisdom.weizmann.ac.il/~oded/my-choice.html">My Choices (Oded Goldreich)</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://www.offconvex.org">Off the convex path</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://cameroncounts.wordpress.com">Peter Cameron</a>
</li><li> <a href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com">Process Algebra Diary</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://daveagp.wordpress.com/category/math/">QED and NOM</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/">Shtetl-Optimized</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://adamsheffer.wordpress.com">Some Plane Truths</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://blog.tanyakhovanova.com">Tanya Khovanova’s Math</a>
</li><li> <a href="http://grigory.us/blog/">The Big Data Theory</a>
</li><li> <a href="http://blog.geomblog.org">The Geomblog</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://polymathprojects.org">The polymath blog</a>
</li><li> <a href="http://dmatheorynet.blogspot.com">Theory Announcements</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://thmatters.wordpress.com/tcs-blogs/">Theory Matters</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://tjoresearchnotes.wordpress.com">Tobias Osborne’s research notes</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://agtb.wordpress.com">Turing’s Invisible Hand</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com">What’s new</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://windowsontheory.org">Windows On Theory</a>
</li><li> <a href="https://xorshammer.com">XOR’s Hammer</a>
</li></ol>
<p>
</p><p><b> Open Problems </b></p>
<p>We would like to get some feedback. First any typos in the above? Second any we should have included? Third, any we should have left out—they do not satisfy our 2021 rule?</p>
<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-26T13:17:40Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-26T13:17:40Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6244</id>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6244" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6244#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=6244" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Why Quantum Mechanics?</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">In the past few months, I’ve twice injured the same ankle while playing with my kids. This, perhaps combined with covid, led me to several indisputable realizations: I am mortal. Despite my self-conception as a nerdy little kid awaiting the serious people’s approval, I am now firmly middle-aged. By my age, Einstein had completed general […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In the past few months, I’ve twice injured the same ankle while playing with my kids.  This, perhaps combined with covid, led me to several indisputable realizations:</p>



<ol><li>I am mortal.</li><li>Despite my self-conception as a nerdy little kid awaiting the serious people’s approval, I am now firmly middle-aged.  By my age, Einstein had completed general relativity, Turing had founded CS, won WWII, <em>and</em> proposed the Turing Test, and Galois, Ramanujan, and Ramsey had been dead for years.</li><li>Thus, whatever I wanted to accomplish in my intellectual life, I should probably get started on it <em>now</em>.</li></ol>



<p>Hence today’s post.  I’m feeling a strong compulsion to write an essay, or possibly even a book, surveying and critically evaluating a century of ideas about the following question:</p>



<p><strong>Q: Why should the universe have been quantum-mechanical?</strong></p>



<p>If you want, you can divide Q into two subquestions:</p>



<p><strong>Q1: Why didn’t God just make the universe classical and be done with it?  What would’ve been wrong with <em>that</em> choice?</strong></p>



<p><strong>Q2: Assuming classical physics wasn’t good enough for whatever reason, why this specific alternative?  Why the complex-valued amplitudes?  Why unitary transformations?  Why the Born rule?  Why the tensor product?</strong></p>



<p>Despite its greater specificity, Q2 is ironically the question that I feel we have a better handle on.  I could spend half a semester teaching theorems that admittedly don’t <em>answer</em> Q2, as satisfyingly as Einstein answered the question “why the Lorentz transformations?,” but that at least render this particular set of mathematical choices (the 2-norm, the Born Rule, complex numbers, etc.) orders-of-magnitude less surprising than one might’ve thought they were <em>a priori</em>.  Q1 therefore stands, to me at least, as the more mysterious of the two questions.</p>



<p>So, I want to write something about the space of credible answers to Q, and especially Q1, that humans can currently conceive.  I want to do this for my own sake as much as for others’.  I want to do it because I regard Q as one of the biggest questions ever asked, for which it seems plausible to me that there’s simply an <em>answer</em> that most experts would accept as valid once they saw it, but for which no such answer is known.  And also because, besides having spent 25 years working in quantum information, I have the following qualifications for the job:</p>



<ul><li><span style="color: initial;">I don’t dismiss either Q1 </span><em style="color: initial;">or</em><span style="color: initial;"> Q2 as silly; and</span></li><li>crucially, I don’t think I already know the answers, and merely need better arguments to justify them.  I’m genuinely uncertain and confused.</li></ul>



<p><strong>The purpose of this post is to invite you to share your own answers to Q in the comments section.</strong>  Before I embark on my survey project, I’d better know if there are promising ideas that I’ve missed, and this blog seems like as good a place as any to crowdsource the job.</p>



<p>Any answer is welcome, no matter how wild or speculative, <em>so long as it honestly grapples with the actual nature of QM</em>.  To illustrate, nothing along the lines of “the universe is quantum because it needs to be holistic, interconnected, full of surprises, etc. etc.” will cut it, since such answers leave utterly unexplained why the world wasn’t simply endowed with those properties directly, rather than specifically via <em>generalizing the rules of probability to allow interference and noncommuting observables</em>.</p>



<p>Relatedly, whatever “design goal” you propose for the laws of physics, if the goal is satisfied by QM, but satisfied <em>even better</em> by theories that provide <em>even more</em> power than QM does—for instance, superluminal signalling, or violations of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsirelson%27s_bound">Tsirelson’s bound</a>, or the efficient solution of NP-complete problems—then your explanation is out.  This is a remarkably strong constraint.</p>



<p>Oh, needless to say, don’t try my patience with anything about the uncertainty principle being due to floating-point errors or rendering bugs, or anything else that relies on a travesty of QM lifted from a popular article or meme! <img alt="&#x1F642;" class="wp-smiley" src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/1f642.png" style="height: 1em;"/></p>



<p>OK, maybe four more comments to enable a more productive discussion, before I shut up and turn things over to you:</p>



<ol><li>I’m aware, of course, of the radical uncertainty about what form an answer to Q should even take.  Am I asking you to psychoanalyze the will of God in creating the universe?  Or, what perhaps amounts to the same thing, am I asking for the design objectives of the giant computer simulation that we’re living in?  (As in, “I’m 100% fine with living inside a Matrix … I just want to understand why it’s a <em>unitary</em> matrix!”)  Am I instead asking for an anthropic explanation, showing why <em>of course</em> QM would be needed if you wanted life or consciousness like ours?  Am I “merely” asking for simpler or more intuitive physical principles from which QM is to be derived as a consequence?  Am I asking why QM is the “most elegant choice” in some space of mathematical options … even to the point where, with hindsight, a 19th-century mathematician or physicist could’ve been convinced that <em>of course</em> this must be part of Nature’s plan?  Am I asking for something else entirely?  <strong>You get to decide</strong>!<strong>  Should you take up my challenge, this is both your privilege and your terrifying burden.</strong><br/></li><li>I’m aware, of course, of the dizzying array of central physical phenomena that rely on QM for their ultimate explanation.  These phenomena range from the stability of matter itself, which depends on the Pauli exclusion principle; to the nuclear fusion that powers the sun, which depends on a quantum tunneling effect; to the discrete energy levels of electrons (and hence, the combinatorial nature of chemistry), which relies on electrons being waves of probability amplitude that can only circle nuclei an integer number of times if their crests are to meet their troughs.  Important as they are, though, I don’t regard any of these phenomena as satisfying answers to Q in themselves.  The reason is simply that, in each case, it would seem like child’s-play to contrive some classical mechanism to produce the same effect, were that the goal.  QM just seems far too grand to have been the answer to <em>these</em> questions!  An exponentially larger state space for all of reality, <em>plus</em> the end of Newtonian determinism, just to overcome the technical problem that accelerating charges radiate energy in classical electrodynamics, thereby rendering atoms unstable?  It reminds me of the <em>Simpsons</em> episode where Homer <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GZ6cCaEy5eo">uses a teleportation machine</a> to get a beer from the fridge without needing to get up off the couch.<br/></li><li>I’m aware of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gleason%27s_theorem">Gleason’s theorem</a>, and of the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0401062">specialness</a> of the 1-norm and 2-norm in linear algebra, and of the <a href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=4021">arguments for complex amplitudes</a> as opposed to reals or quaternions, and of the beautiful work of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0101012">Lucien Hardy</a> and of <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1506.00398">Chiribella et al.</a> and others on axiomatic derivations of quantum theory.  As some of you might remember, I even discussed much of this material in <em><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Quantum-Computing-since-Democritus-Aaronson/dp/0521199565">Quantum Computing Since Democritus</a></em>!  There’s a <em>huge</em> amount to say about these fascinating justifications for the rules of QM, and I hope to say some of it in my planned survey!  For now, I’ll simply remark that every axiomatic reconstruction of QM that I’ve seen, impressive though it was, has relied on one or more axioms that struck me as <em>weird</em>, in the sense that I’d have little trouble dismissing the axioms as totally implausible and unmotivated if I hadn’t already known (from QM, of course) that they were true.  The axiomatic reconstructions <em>do</em> help me somewhat with Q2, but little if at all with Q1.<br/></li><li>To keep the discussion focused, in this post I’d like to exclude answers along the lines of “but what if QM is merely an approximation to something else?,” to say nothing of “a century of evidence for QM was all just a massive illusion!  LOCAL HIDDEN VARIABLES FOR THE WIN!!!”  We can have those debates another day—God knows that, here on <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em>, we <a href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6215">have</a> and we will.  Here I’m asking instead: imagine that, as fantastical as it sounds, QM were not only exactly true, but (along with relativity, thermodynamics, evolution, and the tastiness of chocolate) one of the profoundest truths our sorry species had ever discovered.  Why should I have <em>expected</em> that truth all along?  What possible reasons to expect it have I missed?</li></ol>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-25T07:00:45Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-25T07:00:45Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Embarrassing Myself"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Metaphysical Spouting"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <icon>https://scottaaronson.blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-Jacket-32x32.gif</icon>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2022-01-25T23:53:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/25/chair-of-the-department-of-computer-science-at-university-of-victoria-apply-by-march-8-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/25/chair-of-the-department-of-computer-science-at-university-of-victoria-apply-by-march-8-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Chair of the Department of Computer Science at University of Victoria (apply by March 8, 2022)</title>
    <summary>We invite applications for the position of Chair of the Department of Computer Science as a tenured Associate Professor or tenured Professor effective on or before September 1, 2022. Candidates should have a Ph.D. in the field of Computer Science. Website: https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/21010 Email: csc-chair-search@uvic.ca</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We invite applications for the position of Chair of the Department of Computer Science as a tenured Associate Professor or tenured Professor effective on or before September 1, 2022. Candidates should have a Ph.D. in the field of Computer Science.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/21010">https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/21010</a><br/>
Email: csc-chair-search@uvic.ca</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-25T06:16:35Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-25T06:16:35Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-events.org/2022/01/25/stoc-2022-workshops-call-for-proposals/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/2022/01/25/stoc-2022-workshops-call-for-proposals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>STOC 2022 Workshops: Call for Proposals</title>
    <summary>June 20-24, 2022 Rome, Italy http://acm-stoc.org/stoc2022/callforworkshops.html Submission deadline: January 15, 2022 STOC/TheoryFest 2022 will hold workshops during the conference week, June 20–24, 2022. We invite groups of interested researchers to submit workshop proposals. The due date for proposals is February 15, 2022. Submission instructions can be found on the STOC’22 website.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-25T00:03:12Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-25T00:03:12Z</published>
    <category term="conference"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-events.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-events.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Aggregator for CS theory workshops, schools, and so on</subtitle>
      <title>CS Theory Events</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:38:20Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19570</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/24/cheating-in-chess/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Cheating In Chess</title>
    <summary>Colonel Stok: Do you play chess? Harry Palmer: Yes, but I prefer a game with a better chance of cheating.—Funeral in Berlin Ken Regan is well known to us all, and is the co-author of this blog. He is in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering, University at Buffalo (SUNY)–as part of the theory […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<i>Colonel Stok: Do you play chess? <br/>
 Harry Palmer: Yes, but I prefer a game with a better chance of cheating.—<a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=Funeral+in+Berlin1966&amp;source=hp&amp;ei=9IHtYdaRB6ChptQPha-1wAE&amp;iflsig=ALs-wAMAAAAAYe2QBI_BvUjvZLRDMJfKiHAGuQzsBNNU&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjW27yhpcj1AhWgkIkEHYVXDRgQ4dUDCAw&amp;uact=5&amp;oq=Funeral+in+Berlin1966&amp;gs_lcp=Cgdnd3Mtd2l6EAMyBAguEA0yBggAEA0QHjIGCAAQDRAeMgYIABANEB4yBggAEA0QHjIGCAAQDRAeMgYIABANEB4yBggAEA0QHjIGCAAQDRAeMgYIABANEB5QAFgAYOIDaABwAHgAgAFUiAFUkgEBMZgBAKABAqABAQ&amp;sclient=gws-wiz">Funeral in Berlin</a></i></p>
<p>
Ken Regan is well known to us all, and is the co-author of this blog. He is in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering, University at Buffalo (SUNY)–as part of the theory group. He is also an International Master from the World Chess Federation (FIDE).<br/>
<a href="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/kr.png?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19573" height="643" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/kr.png?resize=600%2C643&amp;ssl=1" width="600"/></a></p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Ken’s Trip </b></p>
<p/><p>
Ken has used his ability in theory with his expertise in chess to study how to detect cheating in chess. Unfortunately people do currently cheat in chess, and so detecting them is an important problem for FIDE. Ken has just spent some time in Bologna, Italy at the International Chess Federation Fair Play Commission’s meeting. The group’s goal is:  There is an increasing demand for fair play experts during chess events, and we want to provide the organizers with professionals who know how to collect evidence, apply law, use the state-of-the-art detection tools. And do it in the way that players are protected and public perception of how important the fair play is improved. </p>
<p>
Ken is on the way back from Italy and soon will explain in detail what is the latest about cheating in chess.</p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Cheating In The Past </b></p>
<p/><p>
In the past cheating at chess started with machines like the famous <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mechanical_Turk">Turk</a> of 1770. This was a machine that claimed to play chess without human help. Even just playing legal moves would have been impressive, but the Turk played strong chess.</p>
<p>
<a href="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/turk.jpg?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19574" height="462" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/turk.jpg?resize=600%2C462&amp;ssl=1" width="600"/></a></p>
<p>
The secret to the Turk is it used a hidden human chess player to make its moves. The player was hidden inside the machine. The audience was allowed to examine the machine by opening and looking at parts of the machine. The audience member could only examine one part of the Turk at a time. The trick was that the player could move from one part of the Turk to another. At each time some parts of the Turk would be visible, but some part stayed invisible. This meant the player could move from one part to another of the Turk. This fooled the audience and made it seem “magical” that the mechanical system could play chess.</p>
<p>
<a href="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/show.png?ssl=1"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19577" height="168" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/show.png?resize=300%2C168&amp;ssl=1" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Cheating Now and in the Future </b></p>
<p/><p>
Cheating at chess became interesting again when computer programs started to play strong chess—<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheating_in_chess">cheating</a>. The fundamental insight was that once programs could play master level chess, players could cheat and play at this level. The idea was simple: A player would not look at the board and select the next move. They would instead ask the program what move should they do. They would then use that move.</p>
<p>
Of course a serious issue was how could the player ask a program to make the next move? If the game they were playing was offline, then the player should be able to use their laptop to remotely run the program. If the game was played in some public place, then the player might have to work harder to run the program. But a player could perhaps still do this without being detected. </p>
<p>
 Technology has been used by chess cheaters in several ways. The most common way is to use a chess program while playing chess remotely, such as on the Internet or in correspondence chess. Rather than play the game directly, the cheater simply inputs the moves so far into the program and follows its suggestions, essentially letting the program play for them. Electronic communication with an accomplice during face-to-face competitive chess is a similar type of cheating; the accomplice can either be using a computer program or else simply be a much better player than their associate.  </p>
<p>
</p><p><b> Open Problems </b></p>
<p/><p>
The main open problem is still: How well can cheating be detected? The basic idea is simple: Suppose that the player named Carol plays a game in some tournament. We wish to determine whether Carol played her own moves or whether she used moves of some program. How can we do this? There are several issues that make this hard. </p>
<ol>
<li> Carol may stay on “book” at the beginning. How do we factor this in?
</li><li> Carol may have used a program that is secret. Does this effect the detection?
</li><li> Carol may follow a program for all moves or for some of the moves. Does this make the detection more difficult?
</li><li> Carol may already be a strong player. Suppose she uses the program to play at a stronger level. Is this even more difficult to detect?
</li></ol>
<p>
Ken will update us on the latest views of these and other issues. </p>
<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-24T17:44:23Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-24T17:44:23Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-9122075582706163619</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/9122075582706163619/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/personal-reflections-on-dick-lipton-in.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/9122075582706163619" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/9122075582706163619" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/personal-reflections-on-dick-lipton-in.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Personal Reflections on Dick Lipton in honor of his 1000th blog/75th bday.</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> Is it an irony that Lipton's 1000th post and 75th bday are close together? No. Its a coincidence. People use irony/paradox/coincidence interchangeably. Hearing people make that mistake makes me literally want to strangle them. </p><p>The community celebrated this milestone by having  talks on zoom in Lipton's honor. The  blog post by Ken Regan that announced the event and has a list of speakers is <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/14/happy-1000th-post-and-75th-birthday-dick/">here</a>. The talks were recorded so they should be available soon. YEAH KEN for organizing the event! We may one day be celebrating his 2000th blog post/Xth bday. </p><p>I will celebrate this milestone by writing on how Lipton and his work have inspired and enlightened me. </p><p><br/></p><p>1) My talk at the Lipton zoom-day-of-talks was on the Chandra-Furst-Lipton (1983)  paper (see <a href="http://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/CFG-multiparty.pdf">here</a>) that sparked my interest in Ramsey Theory, lead to a paper I wrote that improved their upper and lower bounds, and lead to an educational open problem that I posted on this blog, that was answered. There is still more to do.  An expanded version of the slide talk I gave on the zoom-day is <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/liptonbdaytalk.pdf">here</a>. (Their paper also got me interested in Communication complexity.) </p><p>2) I read the De Millo-Lipton-Perlis (1979) paper (see <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/BLOGPAPERS/social.pdf">here</a>) my first year in graduate school and found it very enlightening. NOT about program verification, which I did not know much about, but about how mathematics really works.  As an ugrad I was very much into THEOREM-PROOF-THEOREM-PROOF as the basis for truth. This is wrongheaded for two reasons (1) I did not see the value of intuition, and (2) I did not realize that the PROOF is not the END of the story, but the BEGINNING of a process of checking it- many people over time have to check a result. DLP woke me up to point (2) and (to a lesser extend) point (1). A scary thought: most results in math, once published, are never looked at again. So their could be errors in the math literature. However, the important results DO get looked at quite carefully. Even so, I worry that an important result will depend on one that has not been looked at much...Anyway, a link to a  blog post about a symposium about DLP is <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/06/i-went-to-debate-about-program-verif.html">here</a>.</p><p>3) The Karp-Lipton theorem is: <i> if SAT has poly sized circuits than PH collapses</i> (see <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/800141.804678">here</a>), It connects uniform and non-uniform complexity.  This impressed me but also made me thing about IF-THEN statements. In this case something we don't think is true implies something else we don't think is true. So--- do we know something? Yes! The result has been used to get results like </p><p>                                                   If GI is NPC then PH collapses.</p><p>This is evidence that GI is not NPC. </p><p>4) Lipton originally blogged by himself and a blog book came out of that. I reviewed it in <a href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~gasarch/bookrev/41-4.pdf">this</a> column. Later it became the  Lipton-Regan blog, which also gave rise to a book, which I reviewed   <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2014/05/review-of-people-problems-and-proofs-by.html#comment-form">here</a>.  Both of these books inspired my blog book. This is a shout-out to BOTH Lipton AND Regan.</p><p>5) Lipton either thinks P=NP or pretends to since he wants people to NOT all think the same thing. Perhaps someone will prove P NE NP while trying to prove P=NP. Like in <i>The Hitchhiker's Guide to the</i> <i>Galaxy </i>where they say that to fly, you throw yourself on the ground and miss. I took Lipton's advice in another context: While trying to prove that there IS a protocol for 11 muffins, 5 students where everyone gets 11/5 and the smallest piece is 11/25, I wrote down what such a protocol  would have to satisfy (I was sincerely trying to find such a protocol) and ended up proving that you could not do better than 13/30 (for which I already had a protocol). Reminds me of a quote attributed to Erdos: when trying to prove X, spend half your time trying to prove X and half trying to prove NOT(X).</p><p>6) Lipton had a blog post (probably also a paper someplace) about using Ramsey Theory as the basis for a proof system (see <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/06/13/a-proof-system-based-on-ramsey-theory/">here</a>).  That inspired me to propose a potential randomized n^{log n) algorithm for the CLIQUE-GAP problem (see <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2011/07/slightly-diff-take-on-liptons-use-or.html">here</a>). The comments showed why the idea could not work-- no surprise as my idea would have lead to NP contained in RTIME(n^{log n}). Still, it was fun to think about and I learned things in the effort. </p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-23T20:28:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-23T20:28:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T09:42:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/010</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/010" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-010 |  (Nondeterministic) Hardness vs. Non-Malleability | 

	Marshall Ball, 

	Dana Dachman-Soled, 

	Julian Loss</title>
    <summary>We present the first truly explicit constructions of \emph{non-malleable codes} against tampering by bounded polynomial size circuits. These objects imply unproven circuit lower bounds and our construction is secure provided E requires exponential size nondeterministic circuits, an assumption from the derandomization literature.
	
	Prior works on NMC for polysize circuits, either required an untamperable CRS [Cheraghchi, Guruswami ITCS'14; Faust, Mukherjee, Venturi, Wichs EUROCRYPT'14] or very strong cryptographic assumptions [Ball, Dachman-Soled, Kulkarni, Lin, Malkin EUROCRYPT'18; Dachman-Soled, Komargodski, Pass CRYPTO'21]. Both of works in the latter category only achieve non-malleability with respect to efficient distinguishers and, more importantly, utilize cryptographic objects for which no provably secure instantiations are known outside the random oracle model. In this sense, none of the prior yields fully explicit codes from non-heuristic assumptions. Our assumption is not known to imply the existence of one-way functions, which suggests that cryptography is unnecessary for non-malleability against this class.
	
	Technically, security is shown by \emph{non-deterministically} reducing polynomial size tampering to split-state tampering. The technique is general enough that it allows us to to construct the first \emph{seedless non-malleable extractors} [Cheraghchi, Guruswami TCC'14] for sources sampled by polynomial size circuits [Trevisan, Vadhan FOCS'00] (resp. recognized by polynomial size circuits [Shaltiel CC'11]) and tampered by polynomial size circuits. Our construction is secure assuming E requires exponential size $\Sigma_4$-circuits (resp. $\Sigma_3$-circuits), this assumption is the state-of-the-art for extracting randomness from such sources (without non-malleability).
	
	We additionally observe that non-malleable codes and non-malleable secret sharing [Goyal, Kumar STOC'18]  are essentially equivalent with respect to polynomial size tampering. In more detail, assuming E is hard for exponential size nondeterministic circuits, any efficient secret sharing scheme can be made non-malleable against polynomial size circuit tampering.
	
	Unfortunately, all of our constructions only achieve inverse polynomial (statistical) security. Extending a result from [Applebaum, Artemenko, Shaltiel, Yang CC'16] we show it is impossible to do better using black-box reductions. However, we extend the notion of relative error from [Applebaum, Artemenko, Shaltiel, Yang CC'16] to non-malleable extractors and show that they can be constructed from similar assumptions. We additionally observe that relative-error non-malleable extractors can be utilized to render a broad class of cryptographic primitives tamper and leakage resilient, while preserving negligible security guarantees.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-22T21:06:49Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-22T21:06:49Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/21/postdoc-at-faculty-of-computer-science-of-hse-university-apply-by-january-31-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/21/postdoc-at-faculty-of-computer-science-of-hse-university-apply-by-january-31-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>postdoc at Faculty of Computer Science of HSE University (apply by January 31, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Faculty of Computer Science of HSE University (Moscow, Russia) accepts applications for postdoctoral positions in the following research areas: theoretical computer science, theoretical foundation of ML, interpretable knowledge discovery and explainable AI, complex systems and applied mathematics, formal concept analysis, process mining. The application deadline is January 31, 2022. Website: https://cs.hse.ru/en/news/554897133.html Email: fellowship@hse.ru</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Faculty of Computer Science of HSE University (Moscow, Russia) accepts applications for postdoctoral positions in the following research areas: theoretical computer science, theoretical foundation of ML, interpretable knowledge discovery and explainable AI, complex systems and applied mathematics, formal concept analysis, process mining. The application deadline is January 31, 2022.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://cs.hse.ru/en/news/554897133.html">https://cs.hse.ru/en/news/554897133.html</a><br/>
Email: fellowship@hse.ru</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-21T10:06:35Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-21T10:06:35Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19548</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/20/dinner-drinks-denominators/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Dinner! Drinks! Denominators!</title>
    <summary>Mathematics is only a systematic effort of solving puzzles posed by nature—Shakuntala Devi. source—note MoMath cap Peter Winkler is featured in the current issue of the New Yorker magazine. Peter is a famous Dartmouth mathematics professor. He is an expert on math puzzles, both for making them and solving them—see his book, simply titled Mathematical […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Mathematics is only a systematic effort of solving puzzles posed by nature—Shakuntala Devi.</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/20/dinner-drinks-denominators/peter/" rel="attachment wp-att-19550"><img alt="" class="alignright size-full wp-image-19550" height="208" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/peter.png?resize=147%2C208&amp;ssl=1" width="147"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2"><a href="https://art19.com/shows/the-sydcast/episodes/18162392-6c05-4727-a8e9-57df23b28e30">source</a>—note MoMath cap</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Peter Winkler is featured in the current issue of the <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2022/01/17/dinner-drinks-denominators">New Yorker</a> magazine. Peter is a famous Dartmouth mathematics professor. He is an expert on math puzzles, both for making them and solving them—see his <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Mathematical_Puzzles/XWwNEAAAQBAJ?hl=en">book</a>, simply titled <em>Mathematical Puzzles</em>.</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/20/dinner-drinks-denominators/mathpuzzlescover/" rel="attachment wp-att-19552"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19552" height="162" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/MathPuzzlesCover.jpg?resize=105%2C162&amp;ssl=1" width="105"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p/><p><br/>
A recent evening of mathematical dinner theater hosted by Peter is the subject of the article, which is by <a href="https://faculty-directory.dartmouth.edu/daniel-rockmore">Dan Rockmore</a>, also of the Dartmouth math department. This event was co-coordinated by <a href="https://momath.org/cindy-lawrence/">Cindy Lawrence</a>, who is executive director of the National Museum of Mathematics:</p>
<p/><p/>
<table style="margin: auto;">
<tbody><tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/20/dinner-drinks-denominators/cl/" rel="attachment wp-att-19554"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19554" height="241" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/cl.jpg?resize=315%2C241&amp;ssl=1" width="315"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2"><a href="https://www.6sqft.com/spotlight-momaths-executive-director-cindy-lawrence-makes-math-fun-and-interactive/">source</a> (malfunctioned for us)</font>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>
<p/><p><br/>
The event was attended by a group of investors, economists. and teachers in a suitable alcove of a restaurant in Manhattan.  Quoting Rockmore’s article:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Winkler began the evening’s program. The first course of math, delivered during the first course of dinner (a scattering of salads), was a statistics starter called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simpson's_paradox">Simpson’s paradox</a>. The paradox explains how apparent biases in large samples can disappear in smaller ones. A famous example: For the University of California at Berkeley’s graduate programs in 1975, over all, men were admitted at a higher rate than women, but, program by program, women were admitted at a higher rate. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
About Berkeley, see <a href="https://www.refsmmat.com/posts/2016-05-08-simpsons-paradox-berkeley.html">this</a> first. We covered Simpson’s paradox <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2014/01/30/global-warming/">here</a>. The article goes on the mention the famous trick of how a biased coin can be made to simulate a fair coin by tossing it twice, and continues:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Winkler let loose with the last official mind bender, a gambling thought experiment involving a fictitious couple named Alice and Bob, who are famous in math circles. Each of them has a biased coin—fifty-one-per-cent chance of heads, forty-nine-per-cent chance of tails. They each start with a hundred dollars, flipping the coin and betting against the bank on the outcome. Alice calls heads every time; Bob calls tails. The puzzle: Given that they both go broke, which one is more likely to have gone broke first? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
The article relates that most diners guessed Bob, but the correct answer is Alice. Former Times math and science columnist John Tierney, a serious enough math fan to have remarked once that the term “recreational mathematics” is a self-contradiction, reasoned it out: “The longer Alice plays, the less likely she is to go broke.” We finish Tierney’s intent by contraposing: hence given that she too went broke, the more likely it was she that played less time.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Old Friend </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Peter is a long time friend of mine. See him in action <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jg6XZcNAgrw">here</a>. He is a delight to talk to about many things—just about any part of math. </p>
<p>
Peter has a <a href="https://math.dartmouth.edu/~pw/solutions.pdf">paper</a> with the title, “Seven Puzzles You Think You Must Not Have Heard Correctly.” I had already started writing this post when I looked up this paper to get a few more puzzle examples. I found this one:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> #4 <b>Unwanted Expansion:</b> <br/>
Suppose you have an algebraic expression involving variables, addition, multiplication, and parentheses. You repeatedly attempt to expand it using the distributive law. How do you know that the expression doesn’t continue to expand forever? Comment: Note that applying the distributive law to, say, the outer product in <img alt="{(x + y)(s(u + v) + t)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%28x+%2B+y%29%28s%28u+%2B+v%29+%2B+t%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>, yields <img alt="{x(s(u + v) + t) + y(s(u + v) + t)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx%28s%28u+%2B+v%29+%2B+t%29+%2B+y%28s%28u+%2B+v%29+%2B+t%29%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/> which has more parentheses than before. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>I thought about this for a little. Then I looked up the answer. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> One can analyze the expression in terms of depth of trees, but there’s an easier way: set all the variables equal to 2. The point of the distributive law is that its application doesn’t change the value of the expression. The value of the initial expression limits the size of anything you can get from it by expansion. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Peter then says: <i>This proof of stopping is due to Dick Lipton.</i> I must say that surprised me. I am getting old. Oops.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Let’s end with a fun puzzle about the dictionary that is also mentioned in the <em>New Yorker</em> article.</p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/20/dinner-drinks-denominators/dictionary/" rel="attachment wp-att-19556"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-19556" height="156" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/dictionary.jpg?resize=240%2C156&amp;ssl=1" width="240"/></a></p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> If each number between one and ten billion was written down in English, which odd number would appear first alphabetically? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Given that spaces do not count, here is the <a href="https://puzzleaday.wordpress.com/2018/10/05/what-is-the-first-odd-number-in-the-dictionary/">answer</a>. The last part changes because the number must be odd. If spaces do count—as in many dictionaries of phrases—then what is the answer?</p>
<p/></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-20T17:30:07Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-20T17:30:07Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Teaching"/>
    <category term="trick"/>
    <category term="Cindy Lawrence"/>
    <category term="coin puzzles"/>
    <category term="Dan Rockmore"/>
    <category term="Museum of Mathematics"/>
    <category term="New Yorker"/>
    <category term="Peter Winkler"/>
    <category term="puzzles"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/20/research-associate-postdoc-at-the-university-of-edinburgh-apply-by-february-18-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/20/research-associate-postdoc-at-the-university-of-edinburgh-apply-by-february-18-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Research Associate (postdoc) at the University of Edinburgh (apply by February 18, 2022)</title>
    <summary>Applications are invited for research associate positions in Algorithms and Complexity, funded by the European Research Council (ERC) starting grant “New Approaches to Counting and Sampling” (NACS), led by Dr. Heng Guo in the School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh. Website: https://elxw.fa.em3.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_1001/job/3010/ Email: hguo at inf.ed.ac.uk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Applications are invited for research associate positions in Algorithms and Complexity, funded by the European Research Council (ERC) starting grant “New Approaches to Counting and Sampling” (NACS), led by Dr. Heng Guo in the School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://elxw.fa.em3.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_1001/job/3010/">https://elxw.fa.em3.oraclecloud.com/hcmUI/CandidateExperience/en/sites/CX_1001/job/3010/</a><br/>
Email: hguo at inf.ed.ac.uk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-20T15:21:25Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-20T15:21:25Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6232</id>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6232" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=6232#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=6232" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Win a Scott Aaronson Speculation Grant!</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Exciting news, everyone! Jaan Tallinn, who many of you might recognize as a co-creator of Skype, tech enthusiast, and philanthropist, graciously invited me, along with a bunch of other nerds, to join the new Speculation Grants program of the Survival and Flourishing Fund (SFF). In plain language, that means that Jaan is giving me $200,000 […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Exciting news, everyone!  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaan_Tallinn">Jaan Tallinn</a>, who many of you might recognize as a co-creator of Skype, tech enthusiast, and philanthropist, graciously invited me, along with a bunch of other nerds, to join the new <a href="https://survivalandflourishing.fund/speculation-grants">Speculation Grants</a> program of the <a href="https://survivalandflourishing.fund/">Survival and Flourishing Fund (SFF)</a>.  In plain language, that means that Jaan is <strong>giving me $200,000 to distribute to charitable organizations in any way I see fit</strong>—though ideally, my choices will have <em>something</em> to do with the survival and flourishing of our planet and civilization.</p>



<p>(If all goes well, this blog post will actually lead to a lot <em>more</em> than just $200,000 in donations, because it will inspire applications to SFF that can then be funded by other “Speculators” or by SFF’s usual process.)</p>



<p>Thinking about how to handle the responsibility of this amazing and unexpected gift, I decided that I couldn’t possibly improve on what Scott Alexander did with his <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/acx-grants-results">personal grants program</a> on <em>Astral Codex Ten</em>.  Thus: I hereby invite the readers of <em>Shtetl-Optimized</em> to pitch registered charities (which might or might not be their own)—especially, charities that are relatively small, unknown, and unappreciated, yet that would resonate strongly with someone who thinks the way I do.  Feel free to renominate (i.e., bring back to my attention) charities that were mentioned when I <a href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?p=5448">asked a similar question</a> after winning $250,000 from the ACM Prize in Computing.</p>



<p>If you’re interested, there’s a two-step process this time:</p>



<p><strong>Step 1</strong> is to make your pitch to me, either by a comment on this post or by email to me, depending on whether you’d prefer the pitch to be public or private.  Let’s set a deadline for this step of <strong>Thursday, January 27, 2022</strong> (i.e., one week from now).  Your pitch can be extremely short, like 1 paragraph, although I might ask you followup questions.  After January 27, I’ll then take one of two actions in response: I’ll either</p>



<p>(a) commit a specified portion of my $200,000 to your charity, <em>if</em> the charity formally applies to SFF, and <em>if</em> the charity isn’t excluded for some unexpected reason (5 sexual harassment lawsuits against its founders or whatever), and <em>if</em> one of my fellow “Speculators” doesn’t fund your charity before I do … or else I’ll</p>



<p>(b) not commit, in which case your charity <strong>can still apply</strong> for funding from SFF!  One of the other Speculators might fund it, or it might be funded by the “ordinary” SFF process.</p>



<p><strong>Step 2</strong>, which <strong>cannot</strong> be skipped, is then to have your charity <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSc4PRBIP8CNCviFiNkSSMKy6Ms3sUJBOi_ykE8IDvTeB5Nr_A/viewform">submit a formal application</a> to SFF.  The application form isn’t too bad.  But if the charity isn’t your own, it would help enormously if you at least <em>knew</em> someone at the charity, so you could tell them to apply to SFF.  Again, Step 2 can be taken regardless of the outcome of Step 1.</p>



<p>The one big rule is that anything you suggest has to be a registered, tax-exempt charity in either the US or the UK.  I won’t be distributing funds myself, but only advising SFF how to do so, and this is SFF’s rule, not mine.  So alas, no political advocacy groups and no individuals.  Donating to groups outside the US and UK is apparently possible but difficult.</p>



<p>While I’m not putting any restrictions on the scope, let me list a few examples of areas of interest to me.</p>



<ul><li>Advanced math and science education at the precollege level: gifted programs, summer camps, online resources, or anything, really, that aims to ensure that the next Ramanujan or von Neumann isn’t lost to the world.</li><li>Conservation of endangered species.</li><li>Undervalued approaches to dealing with the climate catastrophe (including new approaches to nuclear energy, geoengineering, and carbon capture and storage … or even, e.g., studies of the effects of rising CO<sub>2</sub> on cognition and how to mitigate them).</li><li>Undervalued approaches to preventing or mitigating future pandemics—basically, anything dirt-cheap that we <em>wish</em> had been done before covid.</li><li>Almost anything that <a href="https://astralcodexten.substack.com/p/acx-grants-results">Scott Alexander might have funded</a> if he’d had more money.</li><li>Anything that would enrage the SneerClubbers or those who attack me on Twitter, by doing stuff that even <em>they</em> would have to acknowledge makes the world better, but that does so via people, organizations, and means that they despise.</li></ul>



<p>Two examples of areas that I <em>don’t</em> plan to focus on are:</p>



<ul><li>AI-risk and other “strongly rationalist-flavored” organizations (these are already well-covered by others at SFF, so that I don’t expect to have an advantage), and</li><li>quantum computing research (this is already funded by a zillion government agencies, companies, and venture capitalists).</li></ul>



<p>Anyway, thanks so much to Jaan and to SFF for giving me this incredible opportunity, and I look forward to seeing what y’all come up with!</p>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Note:</span></strong> Any other philanthropists who read this blog, and who’d like to add to the amount, are more than welcome to do so!</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-20T14:42:16Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-20T14:42:16Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="Contests"/>
    <category scheme="https://scottaaronson.blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom</id>
      <icon>https://scottaaronson.blog/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/cropped-Jacket-32x32.gif</icon>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://scottaaronson.blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2022-01-25T23:53:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/19/tenure-track-assistant-professor-in-algorithms-at-university-of-vienna-apply-by-january-24-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/19/tenure-track-assistant-professor-in-algorithms-at-university-of-vienna-apply-by-january-24-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure-track assistant professor in algorithms at University of Vienna (apply by January 24, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The department of Computer Science at the University of Vienna invites applications for a tenure-track assistant professor position in algorithms. The starting date is negotiable. Website: https://univis.univie.ac.at/ausschreibungstellensuche/flow/bew_ausschreibung-flow?_flowExecutionKey=_c0BC6DB4A-6047-8758-BA4B-005110088D19_k7DD77CC1-13FE-009B-5AB9-3185BE466C0D&amp;tid=88323.28 Email: monika.henzinger@univie.ac.at</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The department of Computer Science at the University of Vienna invites applications for a tenure-track assistant professor position in algorithms. The starting date is negotiable.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://univis.univie.ac.at/ausschreibungstellensuche/flow/bew_ausschreibung-flow?_flowExecutionKey=_c0BC6DB4A-6047-8758-BA4B-005110088D19_k7DD77CC1-13FE-009B-5AB9-3185BE466C0D&amp;tid=88323.28">https://univis.univie.ac.at/ausschreibungstellensuche/flow/bew_ausschreibung-flow?_flowExecutionKey=_c0BC6DB4A-6047-8758-BA4B-005110088D19_k7DD77CC1-13FE-009B-5AB9-3185BE466C0D&amp;tid=88323.28</a><br/>
Email: monika.henzinger@univie.ac.at</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-19T12:45:26Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-19T12:45:26Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/19/postdoctoral-researcher-at-george-mason-university-apply-by-january-31-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/19/postdoctoral-researcher-at-george-mason-university-apply-by-january-31-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoctoral Researcher at George Mason University (apply by January 31, 2022)</title>
    <summary>Postdoctoral position available starting Fall’22. Want to do bold cutting-edge research on the foundations of Algorithms/AI/ML? Interested in living in the Washington, DC area? Shoot me your CV. Soft deadline: Jan 31. Website: https://www.linkedin.com/jobs/view/2879807616/ Email: grigory@grigory.us</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Postdoctoral position available starting Fall’22. Want to do bold cutting-edge research on the foundations of Algorithms/AI/ML? Interested in living in the Washington, DC area? Shoot me your CV. Soft deadline: Jan 31.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/jobs/view/2879807616/">https://www.linkedin.com/jobs/view/2879807616/</a><br/>
Email: grigory@grigory.us</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-19T00:20:35Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-19T00:20:35Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/009</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/009" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-009 |  On Finer Separations between Subclasses of Read-once Oblivious ABPs | 

	C. Ramya, 

	Anamay Tengse</title>
    <summary>Read-once Oblivious Algebraic Branching Programs (ROABPs) compute polynomials as products of univariate polynomials that have matrices as coefficients. In an attempt to understand the landscape of algebraic complexity classes surrounding ROABPs, we study classes of ROABPs based on the algebraic structure of these coefficient matrices. We study connections between polynomials computed by these structured variants of ROABPs and other well-known classes of polynomials (such as depth-three powering circuits, tensor-rank and Waring rank of polynomials).

Our main result concerns commutative ROABPs, where all coefficient matrices commute with each other, and diagonal ROABPs, where all the coefficient matrices are just diagonal matrices. In particular, we show a somewhat surprising connection between these models and the model of depth-three powering circuits that is related to the Waring rank of polynomials. We show that if the dimension of partial derivatives captures Waring rank up to polynomial factors, then the model of diagonal ROABPs efficiently simulates the seemingly more expressive model of commutative ROABPs. Further, a commutative ROABP that cannot be efficiently simulated by a diagonal ROABP will give an explicit polynomial that gives a super-polynomial separation between dimension of partial derivatives and Waring rank.

Our proof of the above result builds on the results of Marinari, Möller and Mora (1993), and Möller and Stetter (1995), that characterise rings of commuting matrices in terms of polynomials that have small dimension of partial derivatives. The algebraic structure of the coefficient matrices of these ROABPs plays a crucial role in our proofs.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-18T09:42:14Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-18T09:42:14Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19527</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/17/zoom-workshop-e-minder-4pm-et-today/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Zoom Workshop E-Minder: 4pm ET Today</title>
    <summary>And a place to look for fallback info in case things go wrong This is a deviation from the “blog invariants” that were maintained for 1,000 posts. We’ll be happy to have suggestions for style changes and general ideas going forward. Here were the open links for the workshop. Rewritten afterward: Things went smoothly, despite […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>And a place to look for fallback info in case things go wrong</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p>
This is a deviation from the “blog invariants” that were maintained for 1,000 posts.  We’ll be happy to have suggestions for style changes and general ideas going forward. </p>
<p>
Here <i>were</i> the open links for the workshop.  <b>Rewritten afterward:</b> Things went smoothly, despite even my “Heisenberg” feeling of uncertainty about whether I had altered the setup by testing the links beforehand.  Dick’s talk for Princeton’s 2012 Turing <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2012/05/17/turings-tiger-birthday-party/">centennial</a> included among “Grand Challenges” getting AV equipment for lectures to work—well Zoom etc. are a decade-later evolution of that.</p>
<p>
Again we thank all who spoke—note the enlarged list of speakers in the original <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/14/happy-1000th-post-and-75th-birthday-dick/">post</a>.  We will do some combination of a curated video and followup blog post(s).</p>
<p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p>
This is post <b>7*11*13</b> = <b>1001</b>.  The passcode—which should not be needed—remains 111317.  Looking forward to a fun session, and thanks again to all speakers and other visitors.</p>
<p>
[added update]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-17T17:44:29Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-17T17:44:29Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="1001st post"/>
    <category term="4pmET today"/>
    <category term="anniversary"/>
    <category term="GLL"/>
    <category term="Richard Lipton"/>
    <category term="workshop"/>
    <author>
      <name>KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/01/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2022/01/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>You can find plenty of online stories celebrating the release into the public domain of Winnie the Pooh (text, not film), Hemingway’s The Sun Also Rises, etc. But the situation for Ludwig Wittgenstein is more complicated. All his own writing is now public domain in life+70 countries, but the work of later editors might not be. Michele Lavazza explains (\(\mathbb{M}\), via).</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p>You can find <a href="https://boingboing.net/2022/01/01/winnie-the-pooh-is-now-officially-public-domain.html">plenty of online stories</a> celebrating the release into the public domain of Winnie the Pooh (text, not film), Hemingway’s The Sun Also Rises, etc. But the situation for Ludwig Wittgenstein is more complicated. All his own writing is now public domain in life+70 countries, but the work of later editors might not be. <a href="https://www.wittgensteinproject.org/w/index.php?title=Project:Why_are_some_of_Wittgenstein%E2%80%99s_texts_missing_from_this_website%3F">Michele Lavazza explains</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107549495811533662">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=29760747">via</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CW0z3zZAlZU/">Math rock</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107554494911062896">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://boingboing.net/2022/01/02/the-breathtakingly-gorgeous-work-of-french-comic-artist-jordi-lafebre.html">via</a>), Jordi Lefebre.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_abelian_group">Free abelian group</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107557410158230373">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> now a Good Article at Wikipedia. This concept may seem trivial at first, wrapped in unnecessary formalism. But these things come up in a lot of seemingly-unrelated contexts: multiplication of rational numbers, addition of integer polynomials, lattices in the geometry of numbers, chains in homology theory, and divisors in algebraic geometry. I worried that its technicality might make it hard to pass GA but fortunately I got a sympathetic reviewer.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/05/quantum-graph-theory/">Quantum graph theory</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107571090684894770">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span> what happens when qubits have pairwise entanglements described by some graph? And which graphs can be transformed into each other by local quantum operations? Ken Regan explains.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.atlasobscura.com/places/gomboc">Giant weeble in a Budapest plaza</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107574673412832258">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2022/01/gomboc.html">via</a>): it wobbles but it won’t fall down. But unlike the childhood toy, it does it despite being of uniform density, because of its special shape, rather than by having a much denser weight near one end. It’s theorized that tortoises have evolved a similar shape so that they can automatically right themselves. For more mathematical details, see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6mb%C3%B6c">Gömböc on Wikipedia</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.flyingcoloursmaths.co.uk/the-dictionary-of-mathematical-eponymy-the-laves-graph/">Dictionary of mathematical eponymy: The Laves Graph</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107580283699756452">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> I did a lot of work in 2014 on this topic in Wikipedia, but it evidently needs more editing for accessibility. I did not know the part about Laves being sent to the army because the Nazis viewed him as sympathetic to Jews, and then pulled into a secret project to develop unobtanium for Göring, guarded by an alchemist who helpfully insisted on adding lizard bones to the alloys and dangling crystal spheres over them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Our quarter started this week, online through Zoom, accessed in Canvas <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107585920689338985">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> To set it up I have to:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Find and navigate to another site in which I can request a Canvas site, but get redirected to the campus login page, where I have to hand-type my name and password, then get to a page to choose my two-factor authentication, select the phone option on that page, find and unlock my phone, and find and approve the two-factor authentication request on my phone</li>
      <li>Back at the site to request a Canvas site, use it to actually request a Canvas site; this does not actually create the site, but rather puts it into a queue to be processed one or two hours later</li>
      <li>Once the site is created, navigate to Canvas, going through all the same campus login steps first.</li>
      <li>Search the web for the <a href="https://sites.uci.edu/teachanywhere/home/tools/zoom/">campus page on how to enable Zoom</a>, because the steps to do so are not simple or obvious enough to remember, and neither is the location of the campus page.</li>
      <li>Follow the five non-obvious steps on that page for adding Zoom to a Canvas site.</li>
      <li>Go to the new Zoom tab of my new Canvas site where I still have to go through all of the usual Zoom things to schedule a meeting that repeats weekly but only for some of the weekdays (many more steps).</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Someone else in the discussion said that to manage their online classes they have to go through seven different web sites; my count is not nearly that high. Whatever happened to the science of user-friendly interfaces?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2021/04/14/guest-post-an-early-look-at-the-impact-of-the-chinese-academy-of-sciences-journals-warning-list/">An early look at the impact of the Chinese Academy of Sciences journals warning list</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107591437363977756">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> The CAS list does not seem helpful as a tool for identifying specific journals as predatory, because it lists so few, and one has to filter for  political motivation, but maybe it can still find patterns of bad publishing practices. I wasn’t particularly surprised to see MDPI and Hindawi high on their hit list, but the presence of a major IEEE journal (IEEE Access) was more interesting.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.combinatoire.ca/ArsCombinatoria/index.html">The new web site of the journal <em>Ars Combinatoria</em></a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107593800163410461">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> after the old site got taken over by gambling spammers. Thanks to Jannis Harder for finding it for me by tracing through DNS history and trying its old IP address; it wasn’t coming up on searches and I wouldn’t have thought of doing that. Despite being found again, the journal may be in trouble: MathSciNet doesn’t list anything from them in 2021 and the new site says that as of December 2021 the entire editorial board has resigned (with no explanation other than “ask the publisher”).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CslIgQvbx0U">Short video of curve-folded squishable paper helix by Richard Sweeney</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107602947906293833">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>,</span> <a href="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/2022/01/richard-sweeney-paper-sculpture/">via</a>). <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2015/01/31/linkage.html">Sweeney, previously</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://igorpak.wordpress.com/2022/01/09/the-insidious-corruption-of-open-access-publishers/">The insidious corruption of open access publishers</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107608628939783540">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span> Igor Pak looks at predatory publishing and MDPI through a deep examination of MDPI’s journal <em>Mathematics</em>. Ultimately he concludes that it is not actually a predatory journal, but that doesn’t mean that he thinks it is doing good work. Instead, he favors diamond open-access and in particular arXiv-overlay journals.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.thisiscolossal.com/2022/01/david-rivillo-pasta/">Colorful geometric designs for pasta interact interestingly with the pasta’s intricate shapes</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107613972021621156">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> by David Rivillo.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/mathematicians-clear-hurdle-in-quest-to-decode-prime-numbers-20220113/">Typical incoherence from <em>Quanta</em>’s attempts at making mathematics accessible</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107616481712855051">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>):</span> “the Riemann hypothesis says that the Riemann zeta function equals zero whenever the real part of \(s\) equals \(\tfrac12\)”. No. No, it doesn’t.  Fortunately they fixed it quickly. The actual result in question concerns proving better-than-trivial growth rate on the critical line of \(L\)-functions; see “Bounds for standard \(L\)-functions”, Paul D. Nelson, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.15230">arXiv:2109.15230</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://cp4space.hatsya.com/2022/01/14/conway-conjecture-settled/">An unconstructable still life in Conway’s Game of Life</a> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107621849707591699">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>).</span> The configuration shown in the link is stable (if its boundary is stabilized appropriately) but, if it appears in any pattern, it must always have been that way, in all predecessors of the pattern. As such, it answers the question “can every still life be constructed by gliders?” negatively.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><em><a href="http://www.science.smith.edu/~jorourke/PopUps/">Pop-Up Geometry: The Mathematics behind Pop-Up Cards</a></em> <span style="white-space: nowrap;">(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/107629200040843502">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>),</span> new book by Joe O’Rourke, to appear this year. The link goes to Joe’s web site for the book. I haven’t yet seen the actual book, but it looks likely to be very interesting.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-15T23:02:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-15T23:02:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2022-01-28T07:26:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/?p=19500</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/14/happy-1000th-post-and-75th-birthday-dick/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Happy 1,000th Post and 75th Birthday, Dick</title>
    <summary>Plus an open Zoom mini-workshop Monday 1/17, 4–5:30pm ET From Rich DeMillo Richard Lipton founded this blog 1,000 posts ago. He was not quite as young as in the photo. This blog is almost 13 years old but measures time by the count of posts. Time itself occurs only between posts. Unlike what we said […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Plus an open Zoom mini-workshop Monday 1/17, 4–5:30pm ET</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<table class="image alignright">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/14/happy-1000th-post-and-75th-birthday-dick/rjl1980scropped/" rel="attachment wp-att-19502"><img alt="" class="alignright wp-image-19502" height="160" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/RJL1980scropped.png?resize=200%2C160&amp;ssl=1" width="200"/></a>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="caption alignright"><font size="-2">From Rich DeMillo</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>
Richard Lipton founded this blog 1,000 posts ago. He was not quite as young as in the photo. This blog is almost 13 years old but measures time by the count of posts. Time itself occurs only between posts. Unlike what we said <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2018/03/14/happy-0x50th-birthday-donald-knuth/">here</a> about counting birthdays, we are counting “1,000 posts ago” correctly—because the blog was created before the first post with the <em>pages</em> one can click on above.</p>
<p>
Today we—including many from the community—also salute Dick’s 75th birthday.</p>
<p>
The birthday was last September 6. A year ago, I thought the anniversaries could be made to coincide, but the time between posts flowed heavily. Much as a ship captain’s personal attributes become vested in the ship, I felt the birthday could best be hailed at the blog milestone. In this we take after the Queen of England. Elizabeth Windsor was born on April 21 (1926), but follows the centuries-old royal custom of celebrating the birthday in late spring. </p>
<p>
It has been my great pleasure to know Dick for 35 years in-person and several years before that through his papers. His STOC 1980 <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/221590666_The_Consistency_of_P_NP_and_Related_Problems_with_Fragments_of_Number_Theory">paper</a> with Rich DeMillo on the possible independence of P versus NP influenced me to focus on systems of logic as a graduate student. We talked most at STACS 1994 in Caen, France, and this led to a <a href="https://miami.pure.elsevier.com/en/publications/communication-complexity-of-key-agreement-on-small-ranges">paper</a> with four others in the next STACS. I gave an invited talk at Dick’s 2008 birthday celebration workshop—of which more below—and this began our closer association the next year. Dick and the blog are a fount of ideas, and if I say I wish I had time to develop them all, the answer is that our readers are always freely welcome to do so.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Elevator Workshop </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
It is also my delight to have a slate of volunteer speakers for a <b>mini-workshop</b> this coming <b>Monday</b> (Martin Luther King Day, <b>January 17</b>) starting at <b>4pm Eastern Time</b> (US). It will have the theme “Open Problems”—what else?—actually there is “else” as some of the brief talks will be personal notes or nuggets of work that influenced careers. It is open to the public—all readers are invited to attend on Monday via the following Zoom link.  <b>Update:</b> things worked fine, and I have removed the link…</p>
<p>
…except to note that the passcode I made was 111317.  I intended the passcode to be the three primes that multiply to <b>1,001</b>, thinking of what comes next, but those three multiply to 2,431—way far ahead, but see Lance Fortnow’s comment below.  There is no “Waiting Room” and no restriction on when to come or go.</p>
<p>
Here are speakers who have volunteered so far—alphabetical except those in overseas time zones beginning with India will go first:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Subruk Kalyanasundaram <p/>
</li><li>
Ravi Kannan <p/>
</li><li>
Gil Kalai <p/>
</li><li>
Joel Ouaknine<p/>
</li><li>
Harry Buhrman <p/>
</li><li>
Jin-Yi Cai<p/>
</li><li>
Zvi Galil <p/>
</li><li>
Bill Gasarch <p/>
</li><li>
Mitsunori Ogihara <p/>
</li><li>
Rafail Ostrovsky<p/>
</li><li>
Atri Rudra <p/>
</li><li>
Santosh Vempala <p/>
</li><li>
Michael Wehar <p/>
</li><li>
Ryan Williams
</li></ul>
<p>
And possibly a few more. Among the open problems, some may be “Favorite Problems” and some “Formative Problems.” The latter means ones that can shape the field during the coming decade. They should be both important and <em>pliable</em>. The latter word is a pun: it means flexible, but we also mean something a beginning researcher can <em>ply</em> into a dissertation and early career. Computational complexity has many problems that seem to have become rigid, but its sideways growth shows pliable ones are out there. </p>
<p>
One of this blog’s first posts in February, 2009, was on conveying the key idea to solve a problem in the time of an <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/02/16/proofs-and-elevator-rides/">elevator pitch</a>. The same goes for the time to state a good problem. The talks, including pauses and time for questions, will aim to fit within an hour, or 90 minutes at most. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Some Well-Wishes </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
I am also thankful to have the following well-wishes thus far from around the community, including several more fellow bloggers. </p>
<ul>
<li>
<b>Scott Aaronson</b>: Happy birthday Dick! Your results have been an inspiration to me, from DeMillo-Lipton in 1979 on the independence of P vs NP to self-testing of the permanent (which played a central role in my work on BosonSampling). I hear some of your students, like Avi Wigderson, have done OK stuff as well. I look forward to checking your blog for many years to come! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Andrew Appel</b>: I have <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/1676454">Massive Memories</a> of the decade and a half that we overlapped at Princeton, in which you were one of my mentors, explaining to me the ways of the world. When I arrived there from from my PhD it seemed like all the really senior professors (you among them) were celebrating their 40th birthdays. Very best wishes for your 75th. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Boaz Barak</b>: Congratulations to GLL for its 1,000th post and to Dick for his 75th birthday! Dick has done so much for computer science, including many works that have become part of our canon and shaped our “conventional wisdom.” And then with GLL both Ken and Dick have managed to inject fun and humanity into our technical field and also question some of that conventional wisdom itself. Looking forward to the next 1,000 posts! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Paul Beame</b>: Double congratulations, Dick! and congratulations to Ken, too. Through GLL you have helped foster a closer sense of community in our field. Your thought-provoking and informative posts and depth of engagement are inspirational.<p/>
</li><li>
<b>Avrim Blum</b>: Very happy 75th birthday, Dick! We are fortunate to have you in our field! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Harry Buhrman</b>: Congratulations to Dick on his birthday and edition 1,000 of this blog. For me it is also the 42nd birthday of the beautiful Karp-Lipton theorem which is one of my favourite theorems. Its quantum variants are still very relevant and are currently of importance in the quantum computing community. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Jin-Yi Cai</b>: My most sincere well wishes to Dick’s 75th birthday! You have been an inspiration to so many of us over many decades! And warm congratulations to your successful 1,000th post! Your blog GLL, now with Ken, has become a most important landmark in our community. (And will speak, as above.)<p/>
</li><li>
<b>Rich DeMillo</b>—see below. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>David Dobkin</b>—see below. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>David Eppstein</b>: Happy birthday, and congratulations on the 1,000th post! I always look forward to your posts, both for their clear explanations of difficult topics and for the way you lighten them up with the biographical parts. May you have many more excellent birthdays and posts.<p/>
</li><li>
<b>Ron Fagin</b>: I have always enjoyed the Gödel’s Lost Letter blog. In fact, I view it as an important part of my computer science experience! Congratulations, Dick and Ken, on the 1,000th post! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Lance Fortnow</b>: Congrats to Dick and Ken for their millenary post. Learned much about chess, leprechauns, and even some theory. Best wishes for the next 1,000. BTW, Bill Gasarch and I are at 2895 posts so you have some catching up to do. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Merrick Furst</b>: Dick, it’s been an incredible pleasure to work with you and play with you and be allies with you since we first met and became fast friends in the late 70’s.  What a long, strange, wonderfully complex trip it’s been.  Wishing you all the best and hope to find a way to see you sometime soon.<p/>
</li><li>
<b>Bill Gasarch</b>—will speak, as above. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Gil Kalai</b>—will speak, as above. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Subruk Kalyanasundaram</b>: I am delighted to see GLL complete 1,000 posts! Since its inception in February 2009, GLL has created and continues to exist in its own unique space. After putting up a handful of posts, Dick sent a few of us students an understated email that went something like “started a new blog. see if you like it.” At that time, I had no idea that Dick could keep it going for 1,000 posts. I was actively involved in proofreading posts in the first couple of years, but am still a regular reader. It was a privilege to see the posts a day or two before the rest of the world. GLL has been such a successful and popular blog, and wishing many many more exciting posts! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Richard Karp</b>: Dear Dick, It has been my good fortune to be your friend and collaborate with you over many years, especially during your Berkeley period. Gödel’s Last Letter has been a major source of information and insight for me, consistently demonstrating your virtuosity and the depth of your knowledge. Congratulations also to Kathryn for her support of your efforts, and to Ken for his fruitful partnership with you. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Andrea LaPaugh</b>: Dick, congratulations and the best of wishes as you celebrate your 1,000th GLL post and your 75th birthday! The great energy, insight and joy you bring to computational theory has been an inspiration to me and many others. May you enjoy your passion for theory, and life, for many years to come. (And more below.) <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Jonathan Lenchner</b>: Congratulations on the 1,000th posting to the GLL blog—an incredible go-to reference for the computational complexity community! It has been great to reconnect with Ken, who I first met through chess, over logic. Sending belated well wishes also to Dick on the occasion of his 75th birthday! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Harry Lewis</b>: Dick—Thank you for being the guy who always made TCS fun! There is no one who better exemplifies the principle that irreverence is key to the creative process. You have always had the gift of showing how seriously you took the questions of the field by taking their canonical answers so lightly. Your milestone sounds better in French, so I’ll paraphrase: Happy sixty-somethingth! And may you be forever young. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Daniel Lopresti</b>: Dick, I want to wish you a happy (belated) 75th birthday. Your deep and broad insights have had a tremendous impact on me and many of our colleagues in the field of computer science over the years. With warm regards, Dan Lopresti.<p/>
</li><li>
<b>Danupon Nanongkai</b>: About a decade ago, I had the privilege to learn about many exciting problems and insights from many meetings with Dick while I was his PhD student. That was when the Gödel’s Lost Letter blog started, and I am grateful that I can continue to learn by reading this blog. Congratulations on the 1,000th post and Dick’s 75th birthday! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Mitsunori Ogihara</b>—will speak, as above. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Rafail Ostrovsky</b>: My warmest congratulations to Dick and Kathryn on Dick’s birthday wishing Dick many more equally productive and healthy years to come and enjoy. GLL is a truly an inspiration to us all—big thank you to Dick and Ken for an amazing and always inspiring content. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Joel Ouaknine</b>: Thanks for the many many inspirational and insightful posts! I’ve learned more computer science and mathematics on GLL than in any other single source I can think of! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Vijaya Ramachandran</b>: As one of the Dick’s earlier Ph.D. students (graduating in 1983), I would like to offer Dick my best wishes for a very happy 75th birthday, and for many more years to come. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Atri Rudra</b>: I have always been and continue to be amazed by the frequency of posts on GLL especially given the mathematical depth of the exposition, which somehow still manages to be accessible to a wide audience. Here’s wishing to many more years of GLL posts being prolific!  <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Terence Tao</b>: Happy 1,000th post Dick! I very much appreciate the personal and inclusive style of mathematical storytelling that you bring to the mathematical blogging community. Look forward to the next 1,000. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Santosh Vempala</b>: My best wishes to Dick and many thanks to Dick and Ken for a 1,000 interesting posts! Here’s to the next 1,000. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Suresh Venkatasubramanian</b>: On the internet, last week is like 2 years ago. Or so it feels that way. While some of us are frantically trying to tweet our papers and TikTok our talks, it’s a testimonial to persistence and steadiness that GLL has reached its 1,000th <em>blog</em> post (although I would subscribe to a TikTok live feed of Ken and Dick composing their latest post). GLL is an oasis of depth and substance in the desert of social media, and I for one am glad it’s going strong. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Avi Wigderson</b>: I had the good fortune to be Dick Lipton’s PhD student in the years 1980-83. Being with a researcher so knowledgeable, curious, original and passionate in these formative years has shaped my own research path. Happy 75th, Dick, and many happy returns! <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Ryan Williams</b>—will speak, as above. <p/>
</li><li>
<b>Virginia Vassilevska Williams</b>: Happy 1,000th post, Dick! Your blog posts are always so fun to read, highly informative and polished, a treasured gift to our community. Thank you for working on them all this time. I’m looking forward to many more!
</li></ul>
<p>
More may be added, and our readers are welcome to add more in the comments.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Some Words From Princeton—and Yale </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Andrea LaPaugh <a href="https://dof.princeton.edu/about/clerk-faculty/emeritus/andrea-s-lapaugh">became</a> Dean of the Faculty at Princeton and served until her recent retirement. She has some further words from that perspective going back to the beginning of her 38 years at Princeton.</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Dick was a major force in the development of the CS department at Princeton. His work was instrumental in the creation of the department as separate from Electrical Engineering, in recruiting faculty to grow the department, and in acquiring resources. He arrived in 1980 and immediately recruited David Dobkin as a full professor and me as an assistant professor. He continued to have major involvement in recruiting, not only in theoretical computer science, but across the CS disciplines. He was never chair, but worked first with Bruce Arden, chair of the Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, and then with Bob Sedgewick, the first chair of the Department of Computer Science (after Dick recruited him) to implement a vision of a strong and well-rounded CS department. Of course Dick was not alone in this mission. David Dobkin in particular was an important partner. But from my perspective, Dick was the spark. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
David Dobkin, also writing from Princeton, goes back a few years further still to Yale:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> In 1973 when I arrived at Yale as a new faculty member with a fresh PhD, Dick Lipton was the person in the next office who had arrived perhaps a week earlier. He came by to introduce himself. After a bit of formalities, we began to discuss research problems and he asked me about NP-complete problems which were all the rage at the time. The only problem I knew about was the knapsack problem and so I described it.</em></p><em>
<p>
This led to a discussion about integer programming (which neither of us had a good handle on) and then to a discussion about determining in which region of a subdivision of <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002"/>-space (by a set of hyperplanes) a new point was in. Here again, neither Dick nor I had much background and so we invented things as we went. I had this idea that we could understand things with visual help and so we took one of my moving boxes as our universe and the back of some tablets as planes and began to simulate how regions would be determined in 3d.</p>
<p>
From this work emerged our first paper together which was presented at STOC ’74. This on planar subdivision searching opened up a field and led to a long and enjoyable collaboration that followed.</p>
</em><p><em>
So, congratulations Dick on having escaped the world of cardboard planes in a moving box and headed on to a remarkable career in the field. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> More Words From Georgia Tech </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Rich DeMillo sent the following from summer sunshine and open water:</p>
<p>
The last time I missed Dick’s birthday was 2008. In 2007, Dan Boneh, Merrick Furst, Santosh Vempala, and I sent the following 60th birthday symposium invitation to twenty of Lipton’s closest friends and collaborators:</p>
<p>
<a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2022/01/14/happy-1000th-post-and-75th-birthday-dick/rjl2008invite/" rel="attachment wp-att-19503"><img alt="" class="aligncenter wp-image-19503" height="215" src="https://i0.wp.com/rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/RJL2008invite.jpg?resize=327%2C215&amp;ssl=1" width="327"/></a></p>
<p>
The <a href="http://denseoutliers.blogspot.com/2008/03/lipton-theory-symposium.html">Lipton-60</a> <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2008/05/report-on-sym-for-liptons-60th-bday.html">Symposium</a> was finally held in April 2008. It was less the retrospective I had imagined than a mile marker in a career that continued to accelerate in unexpected ways. A few years later, he was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. A few months after that, he was announced as winner of the 2014 Knuth Prize. Even more memorable was the other thing that draws us together here today: the launch in 2009 of the GLL blog that he now writes with Ken. </p>
<p>
I have long since strayed from the mainstream of theory and algorithms, but most of the work we did together has found its way into GLL essays that illuminate in startling new ways material I thought I understood thoroughly. Our paper on the nature of proof that now appears in Harry Lewis’s <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/ideas-created-future">collection</a> of 46 of the most important (in his view) papers in computer science made its first <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/02/16/proofs-and-elevator-rides/">appearance</a> on the blog in 2009 and has been a recurring character in the “GLL universe” ever since. Our probabilistic <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/11/30/the-curious-history-of-the-schwartz-zippel-lemma/">algorithm</a> for polynomial zero testing also entered GLL in 2009. For years I harbored vague resentment that Jack Schwartz was often cited in the Schwartz-Zippel Lemma for a result that Dick and I had published two years before in 1979, but the <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/11/30/the-curious-history-of-the-schwartz-zippel-lemma/">exposition</a> in GLL, Ken’s subsequent <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/11/30/the-curious-history-of-the-schwartz-zippel-lemma/#comment-1993">commentary</a>, and <em>years later</em>, a reader’s <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2009/11/30/the-curious-history-of-the-schwartz-zippel-lemma/#comment-64661">comment</a> showing that Daniel Erickson’s 1974 Caltech dissertation had scooped us all, laid that to rest. </p>
<p>
We both had a fascination with the idea of algorithm correctness—incorrectness, actually—that turned into entire fields in software engineering and cryptography. Those were documented in an “Un-Birthday” <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2021/01/29/happy-un-birthday-rich/">post</a> a year ago:</p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Rich and I started our work together over four decades ago. A central theme of our work was correctness. We were concerned That programs might not work as planned. At the time it was not obvious that this was a major theme of our joint work. But looking back now I can see that it was. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Also recently, I managed to coax Dick into the fraught waters of election security. I stood back to watch how flustered researchers would respond to his (brilliant but unworkable) <a href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/2019/05/10/making-elections-safe/">reconstructions</a> of what it means to vote in a public election. </p>
<p>
I have been delaying my plans to remove myself from day-to-day management duties to found a new department of cybersecurity at Georgia Tech, and I have missed Dick at my side since his retirement. There was always the possibility when Dick was in the room that someone’s long-held (but wrong) assumption would fall apart under a trademarked but understated Lipton assault. Michael Rabin (who also contributed to the Lipton-60 symposium) was fond of telling Dick on such occasions, “You are a very dangerous person.” </p>
<p>
With this intimate gathering on January 17 to commemorate GLL 1,000 and Dick Lipton’s 75th Birthday, Ken Regan has slyly kept alive the tradition of meetings that take place months after the anniversary of Dick’s birth. Times are different. Virtual meetings have replaced the casual travel and camaraderie of 2008. I cannot attend in any form on January 17 since I am at present on a ship bound for the Drake Passage and Patagonia, and I will lose Internet connectivity soon. I hope that explanation excuses this longer-than-asked-for expression of affection and admiration for Dick, my friend and collaborator for nearly 50 years. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
A meta open-problem: Which was the most <em>pliable</em> problem at the time this blog was founded? The Unique Games <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unique_games_conjecture">conjecture</a> strikes us as a perfect example, but you readers may have other examples from then and now.</p>
<p>
[fixed product 11*13*17, added more greetings and speakers, removed workshop link afterward]</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-14T21:14:32Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-14T21:14:32Z</published>
    <category term="All Posts"/>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="News"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="1000th post"/>
    <category term="anniversary"/>
    <category term="birthday"/>
    <category term="GLL blog"/>
    <category term="Richard Lipton"/>
    <author>
      <name>RJLipton+KWRegan</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/webclip.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wpcomstaging.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel's Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:36Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/14/empire-innovation-professor-quantum-information-science-and-engineering-at-stony-brook-university-apply-by-june-30-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/14/empire-innovation-professor-quantum-information-science-and-engineering-at-stony-brook-university-apply-by-june-30-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Empire Innovation Professor – Quantum Information Science and Engineering at Stony Brook University (apply by  June 30, 2022)</title>
    <summary>The Computer Science (CS) Department and the Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) Department at Stony Brook University invite applications for a tenure-track/tenured faculty position in Quantum Information Science and Engineering with an expected start date of Fall 2022. Exceptionally qualified candidates at any rank are invited to apply. Website: https://www.cs.stonybrook.edu/about-us/career/empire Email: recruit@cs.stonybrook.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Computer Science (CS) Department and the Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) Department at Stony Brook University invite applications for a tenure-track/tenured faculty position in Quantum Information Science and Engineering with an expected start date of Fall 2022. Exceptionally qualified candidates at any rank are invited to apply.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.cs.stonybrook.edu/about-us/career/empire">https://www.cs.stonybrook.edu/about-us/career/empire</a><br/>
Email: recruit@cs.stonybrook.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-14T16:36:58Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-14T16:36:58Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/008</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/008" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-008 |  Approximating Large Powers of Stochastic Matrices in Small Space | 

	Gil Cohen, 

	Dean Doron, 

	Ori Sberlo</title>
    <summary>We give a deterministic space-efficient algorithm for approximating powers of stochastic matrices. On input a $w \times w$ stochastic matrix $A$, our algorithm approximates $A^{n}$ in space $\widetilde{O}(\log n + \sqrt{\log n}\cdot \log w)$ to within high accuracy. This improves upon the seminal work by Saks and Zhou (FOCS'95), that requires $O(\log^{3/2}n + \sqrt{\log n} \cdot \log w)$ space, in the regime $n \gg w$.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-14T09:34:37Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-14T09:34:37Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/007</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/007" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-007 |  A Simpler Proof of the Worst-Case to Average-Case Reduction for Polynomial Hierarchy via Symmetry of Information | 

	Valentine Kabanets, 

	Halley Goldberg</title>
    <summary>We give a simplified proof of Hirahara's STOC'21 result showing that $DistPH \subseteq AvgP$ would imply $PH \subseteq DTIME[2^{O(n/\log n)}]$. The argument relies on a proof of the new result: Symmetry of Information for time-bounded Kolmogorov complexity under the assumption that $NP$ is easy on average, which is interesting in its own right and generalizes the ``weak'' Symmetry of Information theorem from the original paper by Hirahara.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-14T02:52:14Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-14T02:52:14Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/13/faculty-positions-in-quantum-science-and-information-at-university-of-maryland-apply-by-february-1-2022/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2022/01/13/faculty-positions-in-quantum-science-and-information-at-university-of-maryland-apply-by-february-1-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty Positions in Quantum Science and Information at University of Maryland (apply by February 1, 2022)</title>
    <summary>UMD invites applications for faculty positions in quantum science and information. Areas to be considered include quantum computation, quantum simulation, quantum information processing, quantum sensing, and quantum networking. Research can be experimental, theoretical or computational in nature. Successful applicants will be expected to maintain active research programs and teach. Website: https://ejobs.umd.edu/postings/91259 Email: gene@umd.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>UMD invites applications for faculty positions in quantum science and information. Areas to be considered include quantum computation, quantum simulation, quantum information processing, quantum sensing, and quantum networking. Research can be experimental, theoretical or computational in nature. Successful applicants will be expected to maintain active research programs and teach.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://ejobs.umd.edu/postings/91259">https://ejobs.umd.edu/postings/91259</a><br/>
Email: gene@umd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-13T20:29:53Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-13T20:29:53Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:38Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=8286</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/01/13/call-for-godel-prize-nominations-guest-post-by-david-zuckerman-and-samson-abramsky/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Call for Gödel prize nominations (guest post by David Zuckerman and Samson Abramsky)</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We’d like to encourage everyone to nominate outstanding papers in any area of theoretical computer science for the 2022 Gödel Prize. In short, papers that first appeared since 2009 (in any form) and appeared in a refereed journal by 2021 are eligible. If you wish to nominate a paper, or might wish to do so, or … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2022/01/13/call-for-godel-prize-nominations-guest-post-by-david-zuckerman-and-samson-abramsky/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Call for Gödel prize nominations (guest post by David Zuckerman and Samson Abramsky)</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>We’d like to encourage everyone to nominate outstanding papers in any area of theoretical computer science for the 2022 Gödel Prize. </p>



<p>In short, papers that first appeared since 2009 (in any form) and appeared in a refereed journal by 2021 are eligible. If you wish to nominate a paper, or might wish to do so, or if you want to suggest a paper informally, please contact the award committee chair, Samson Abramsky (<a href="mailto:s.abramsky@ucl.ac.uk" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">s.abramsky@ucl.ac.uk</a>). The deadline is February 28, 2022, but please contact the chair well in advance to coordinate efforts. For details, see <a href="https://sigact.org/prizes/g%C3%B6del.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">https://sigact.org/prizes/g%C3%B6del.html</a></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-13T18:33:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-13T18:33:00Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:51Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/006</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2022/006" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR22-006 |  Secret Sharing, Slice Formulas, and Monotone Real Circuits | 

	Benny Applebaum, 

	Amos Beimel, 

	Oded Nir, 

	Naty Peter, 

	Toniann Pitassi</title>
    <summary>A secret-sharing scheme allows to distribute a secret $s$ among $n$ parties such that only some predefined ``authorized'' sets of parties can reconstruct the secret, and all other ``unauthorized'' sets learn nothing about $s$. For over 30 years, it was known that any (monotone) collection of authorized sets can be realized by a secret-sharing scheme whose shares are of size $2^{n-o(n)}$ and until recently no better scheme was known. In a recent breakthrough, Liu and Vaikuntanathan (STOC 2018) have reduced the share size to $2^{0.994n+o(n)}$, and this was further improved by several follow-ups accumulating in an upper bound of $1.5^{n+o(n)}$ (Applebaum and Nir, CRYPTO 2021). Following these advances, it is natural to ask whether these new approaches can lead to a truly sub-exponential upper-bound of $2^{n^{1-\epsilon}}$ for some constant $\epsilon&gt;0$, or even all the way down to polynomial upper-bounds.

In this paper, we relate this question to the complexity of computing monotone Boolean functions by monotone real circuits (MRCs)  -- a computational model that was introduced by Pudl\'{a}k  (J. Symb. Log., 1997) in the context of proof complexity. We introduce a new notion of ``separable'' MRCs that lies between monotone real circuits and monotone real formulas (MRFs). As our main results, we show that recent constructions of general secret-sharing schemes implicitly give rise to separable MRCs for general monotone functions of similar complexity, and that some monotone functions (in monotone NP) cannot be computed by sub-exponential size separable MRCs. Interestingly, it seems that proving similar lower-bounds for general MRCs is beyond the reach of current techniques.

We use this connection to obtain lower-bounds against a natural family of secret-sharing schemes, as well as new non-trivial upper-bounds for MRCs. Specifically, we conclude that recent approaches for secret-sharing schemes cannot achieve sub-exponential share size and that every monotone function can be realized by an MRC (or even MRF) of complexity $1.5^{n+o(n)}$. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first improvement over the trivial $2^{n-o(n)}$ upper-bound. Along the way, we show that the recent constructions of general secret-sharing schemes implicitly give rise to Boolean formulas over slice functions and prove that such formulas can be simulated by separable MRCs of similar size. On a conceptual level, our paper continues the rich line of study that relates the share size of secret-sharing schemes to monotone complexity measures.</summary>
    <updated>2022-01-12T15:39:53Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-12T15:39:53Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T10:37:24Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-7334971011736548221</id>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/7334971011736548221/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/on-california-math-framework.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7334971011736548221" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/7334971011736548221" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2022/01/on-california-math-framework.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>On the California Math Framework</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><i>Guest post by Boaz Barak
and Jelani Nelson</i></p><p class="MsoNormal"/>

<p class="MsoNormal">In a <a href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2021/12/defending-status-quo.html">recent
post</a>, Lance Fortnow critiqued our <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/k12mathmatters/home">open letter</a> on the
proposed revisions for the <a href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ma/cf/">California Mathematics Framework</a> (CMF). We disagree
with Lance’s critique, and he has kindly allowed us to post our rebuttal here
(thank you Lance!).</p><p class="MsoNormal">First, let us point out the aspects where we agree with both
Lance and the authors of the CMF. Inequality in mathematical education, and in
particular the obstacles faced by low-income students and students of color, is
a huge problem in the US at large and California in particular. As a Black
mathematician, this portion of the CMF’s <a href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ma/cf/documents/mathfwchapter1.docx">introduction</a> particularly resonated
with me (Jelani):</p><blockquote><p class="MsoNormal">Girls and Black and Brown children, notably, represent
groups that more often receive messages that they are not capable of high-level
mathematics, compared to their White and male counterparts (Shah &amp;
Leonardo, 2017). As early as preschool and kindergarten, research and policy
documents use deficit-oriented labels to describe Black and Latinx and
low-income children’s mathematical learning and position them as already behind
their white and middle-class peers (NCSM &amp; TODOS, 2016).</p></blockquote><p class="MsoNormal"/>

<p class="MsoNormal">We agree with the observation that bias in the public
education system can have a negative impact on students from underrepresented
groups. Where we strongly oppose the CMF though is regarding their conclusions
on how to address this concern. </p><p class="MsoNormal"/>

<p class="MsoNormal">The CMF may state that they are motivated by increasing
equity in mathematics. However, if we read past the introduction to the actual
details of the CMF revisions, then we see they suffer from fundamental flaws,
which we believe if implemented, would <b>exacerbate</b> educational gaps, and
in particular make it <b>harder</b> for low-income students and students of
color to reach and be successful in college STEM.</p><p class="MsoNormal"/>

<p class="MsoNormal">You can read our <a href="https://gdoc.pub/doc/e/2PACX-1vQvuzlJ8MWthsqOhRLxQc5akGS0JkgThz3umqO3K-WQiXFhWiq9qw-9iYdTyC652Ftjvv5nHvgGYTEv">detailed
critique</a> of the CMF, but the revisions we take issue with are:</p><p class="MsoNormal"/>

<ol start="1" style="margin-top: 0in;" type="1"><li class="MsoNormal">Recommendation
     to drop the option of Algebra I in the 8th grade<br/>
     <!--[endif]--></li><li class="MsoNormal">Recommendation
     to offer (and in fact push and elevate above others) a “data science”
     pathway for high school education as an alternative to the traditional
     Algebra and Geometry curriculum. While data science can be a deep and
     important field, teaching it for students without a math background will
     be necessarily shallow. Indeed, the proposed data science courses focus on
     tools such as using spreadsheets etc., and do not provide mathematical
     foundations.</li>
</ol>

<p class="MsoNormal">1 and 2 make it all but impossible for students that follow
the recommended path to reach calculus (perhaps even pre-calculus)  in the
12th grade.  This means that such students will be at a disadvantage if
they want to pursue STEM majors in college. And who will be these students?
Since the CMF is only recommended, wealthier school districts are free to
reject it, and some already <a href="https://calmatters.org/education/k-12-education/2021/11/california-math/">signalled
that they will do so</a>. Within districts that do adopt the recommendations,
students with means are likely to take private Algebra I courses outside the
curriculum (as <a href="https://calmatters.org/education/k-12-education/2021/12/san-francisco-math/">already
</a><a href="https://edsource.org/2021/one-districts-faulty-data-shouldnt-drive-californias-math-policy/663374">happened</a>
in San Francisco), and reject the calculus-free “data science” pathway. Hence
this pathway will amount to a lower-tier track by another name, and worse than
now, students will be tracked based on whether their family has the financial
means to supplement the child’s public education with private coursework.</p><p class="MsoNormal">Notably, though the CMF aims to elevate data science, we’ve
had several data science faculty at the university level express disapproval of
the proposal by signing our opposition letter, including a founding faculty
member of the Data Science Institute at UCSD, and several others who are
directors of various undergraduate programs at their respective universities,
including four who direct their universities' undergraduate data science
programs (at Indiana University, Loyola University in Chicago, MIT, and the
University of Wisconsin)! </p>

<p class="MsoNormal">One could say that while the framework may hurt low-income
or students of color who want to pursue STEM in college, it might help other
students who are not interested in STEM. However, interest in STEM majors is <a href="https://www.ppic.org/blog/more-students-are-earning-stem-degrees/">rapidly
rising</a>, and with good reasons: employment in math occupations is projected
to <a href="https://www.bls.gov/ooh/math/mobile/home.htm">grow much faster </a>than
other occupations. With the increasing centrality of technology and STEM to our
society, we urgently need reforms that will diversify these professions rather
than the other way around.</p><p class="MsoNormal">As a final note, Lance claimed that by rejecting the CMF, we
are “defending the status quo”. This is not true. The CMF revisions are far
from the “only game in town” for improving the status quo in mathematics
education. In fact, unlike these largely untested proposals, there is a history
of approaches that do work for teaching mathematics for under-served
populations. We do not need to change the math itself, just invest in more
support (including extracurricular support) for students from under-resourced
communities. For example, Bob Moses’ <a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/codeswitch/2013/08/02/206813091/to-60s-civil-rights-hero-math-is-kids-formula-for-success">Algebra
Project</a> has time and again taken the least successful students according to
standardized exams, and turned them into a cohort that <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/07/education/algebra-project-bob-moses-empowers-students.html">outperformed</a>
state averages in math. One of our letter’s contact people is Adrian Mims, an
educator with 27 years of experience, whose dissertation was on 
"Improving African American Achievement in Geometry Honors" and who
went on to found <a href="https://thecalculusproject.org/">The Calculus
Project</a>, a non-profit organization creating a pathway for low-income
students and students of color to succeed in advanced mathematics. </p><p class="MsoNormal">To close, a critique of the proposed CMF revision is not a
defense of the status quo. Even if change is needed, not all change is good
change, and our letter does make some recommendations on the front, one of
which is a matter of process: if a goal is to best prepare Californian youth
for majors in data science and STEM more broadly, and ultimately careers in
these spaces, then involve college-level STEM educators and STEM professionals
in the <a href="https://www.cde.ca.gov/ci/ma/cf/mathcfccapplicants.asp">Curriculum
Framework and Evaluation Criteria Committee</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2022-01-12T15:32:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-01-12T15:32:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2022-01-29T09:42:41Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
