<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:planet="http://planet.intertwingly.net/" xmlns:indexing="urn:atom-extension:indexing" indexing:index="no"><access:restriction xmlns:access="http://www.bloglines.com/about/specs/fac-1.0" relationship="deny"/>
  <title>Theory of Computing Blog Aggregator</title>
  <updated>2020-11-24T02:38:48Z</updated>
  <generator uri="http://intertwingly.net/code/venus/">Venus</generator>
  <author>
    <name>Arnab Bhattacharyya, Suresh Venkatasubramanian</name>
    <email>arbhat+cstheoryfeed@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <id>http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml</id>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="http://www.cstheory-feed.org/" rel="alternate"/>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5106</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5106" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5106#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5106" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Huck Finn and the gaslighting of America</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">For the past month, I’ve been reading The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn to my 7-year-old daughter Lily. Is she too young for it? Is there a danger that she’ll slip up and say the n-word in school? I guess so, maybe. But I found it worthwhile just for the understanding that lit up her face […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>For the past month, I’ve been reading <em>The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn</em> to my 7-year-old daughter Lily.  Is she too young for it?  Is there a danger that she’ll slip up and say the n-word in school?  I guess so, maybe.  But I found it worthwhile just for the understanding that lit up her face when she realized what it meant that Huck would help Jim escape slavery even though Huck really, genuinely believed that he’d burn in hell for it.</p>



<p><em>Huck Finn</em> has been one of my favorite books since I was just slightly older than Lily.  It’s the greatest statement by one of history’s greatest writers about human stupidity and gullibility and evil and greed, but also about the power of seeing what’s right in front of your nose to counteract those forces.  (It’s also a go-to source for details of 19<sup>th</sup>-century river navigation.)  It rocks.</p>



<p>The other day, after we finished a chapter, I asked Lily whether she thought that injustice against Black people in America ended with the abolition of slavery.  No, she replied.  I asked: how much longer did it continue for?  She said she didn’t know.  So I said: if I told you that once, people in charge of an American election tried to throw away millions of votes that came from places where Black people lived—supposedly because some numbers didn’t exactly add up, except they didn’t care about similar numbers not adding up in places where White people lived—how long ago would she guess that happened?  100 years ago?  50 years?  She didn’t know.  So I showed her the news from the last hour.</p>



<p>These past few weeks, my comment queue has filled with missives, most of which I’ve declined to publish, about the giant conspiracy involving George Soros and Venezuela and dead people, which fabricated the overwhelmingly Democratic votes from overwhelmingly Democratic cities like Philadelphia and Milwaukee and Detroit (though for some reason, they weren’t <em>quite</em> as overwhelmingly Democratic as in other recent elections), while for some reason declining to help Democrats in downballot races.  Always, these commenters confidently insist, <em>I’m</em> the Pravda-reading brainwashed dupe, <em>I’m</em> the unreasonable one, if I don’t accept this.</p>



<p>This is the literal meaning of “gaslighting”: the intentional construction of an alternate reality so insistently as to make the sane doubt their sanity.  It occurred to me: <em>Huck Finn</em> could be read as an extended fable about gaslighting.  The Grangerfords make their deadly feud with the Shepherdsons seem normal and natural.  The fraudulent King and Duke make Huck salute them as royalty.  Tom convinces Huck that the former’s harebrained schemes for freeing Jim are just the way it’s done, and Huck is an idiot for preferring the simplistic approach of just freeing him.  And of course, the entire culture gaslights Huck that good is evil and evil is good.  Huck doesn’t fight the gaslighting as hard as we’d like him to, but he develops as a character to the extent he does.</p>



<p>Today, the Confederacy—which, as we’ve learned the past five years, never died, and is as alive and angry now as it was in Twain’s time—is trying to win by gaslighting what it couldn’t win at Antietam and Gettysburg and Vicksburg.  It’s betting that if it just insists, adamantly enough, that someone who lost an election by hundreds of thousands of votes spread across multiple states actually won the election, then it can bend the universe to its will.</p>



<p>Glued to the news, listening to Giuliani and McEnany and so on, reading the Trump campaign’s legal briefs, I keep asking myself one question: <em>do they actually believe this shit?</em>  Some of the only insight I got about that question came from a <a href="https://graymirror.substack.com/p/reflections-on-the-late-election">long piece</a> by Curtis Yarvin a.k.a. Mencius Moldbug, who’s been called one of the leading thinkers of neoreaction and who sometimes responds to this blog.  Esoterically, Yarvin says that he actually <em>prefers</em> a Biden victory, but only because Trump has proven himself unworthy by submitting himself to nerdy electoral rules rather than simply seizing power.  (If that’s not <em>quite</em> what Yarvin meant—well, I’m about as competent to render his irony-soaked meanings in plain language as I’d be to render Heidegger or Judith Butler!)</p>



<p>As for whether the election was “fraudulent,” here’s Yarvin’s key passage:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>The fundamental purpose of a democratic election is to test the strength of the sides in a civil conflict, without anyone actually getting hurt. The majority wins because the strongest side would win … But this guess is much better if it actually measures humans who are both willing and able to walk down the street and show up. Anyone who cannot show up at the booth is unlikely to show up for the civil war. This is one of many reasons that an in-person election is a more <em>accurate</em> election. (If voters could be qualified by <em>physique</em>, it would be even more accurate) … My sense is that in many urban communities, voting by proxy in some sense is the norm. The people whose names are on the ballots really exist; and almost all of them actually did support China Joe. Or at least, preferred him. The extent to which they perform any tangible political action, including physically going to the booth, is very low; so is their engagement with the political system. They do not watch much CNN. The demand for records of their engagement is very high, because each such datum cancels out some huge, heavily-armed redneck with a bass boat. This is why, in the data, these cities look politics-obsessed, but photos of the polling places look empty. Most votes from these communities are in some sense “organized” … Whether or not such a design constitutes “fraud” is the judge’s <em>de gustibus</em>.</p></blockquote>



<p>Did you catch that?  Somehow, Yarvin manages to insinuate that votes for Biden are plausibly fraudulent and plausibly shouldn’t count—at least <em>if</em> they were cast by mail, in “many urban communities” (which ones?), during a pandemic—even as Yarvin glaincingly acknowledges that the votes in question actually exist and are actually associated with Biden-preferring legal voters.  This is gaslighting in pure, abstract form, unalloyed with the laughable claims about Hugo Chávez or Dominion Voting Systems.</p>



<p>What I find terrifying about gaslighting is that it’s so <em>effective</em>.  In response to this post, I’ll again get long, erudite comments making the case that up is down, turkeys are mammals, and Trump won in a landslide.  And simply to <em>read</em> and <em>understand</em> those comments, some part of me will need to entertain the idea that they might be right.  Much like with Bigfoot theories, this will be purely a function of the effort the writers put in, not of any merit to the thesis.</p>



<p>And there’s a second thing I find terrifying about gaslighting.  Namely:<strong> it turns me into an ally of the SneerClubbers.</strong>  Like them, I feel barely any space left for rational discussion or argument.  Like them, I find it difficult to think of an appropriate response to Trumpian conspiracy theorists except to ridicule them, shame them as racists, and try to mute their influence.  Notably, public shaming (“[t]he Trump stain, the stain of racism that you, William Hartmann and Monica Palmer, have covered yourself in, is going to follow you throughout history”) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ebGOe2zHbLc">seems to have actually worked last week</a> to get the Wayne County Board of Canvassers to back down and certify the votes from Detroit.  So why not try more of it?</p>



<p>Of course, even if I agree with the wokeists that there’s a line beyond which rational discussion can’t reach, I radically disagree with them about the line’s <em>whereabouts</em>.  Here, for example, I try to draw mine generously enough to include any Republicans willing to stand up, however feebly, against the Trump cult, whereas the wokeists draw their line so narrowly as to exclude most <em>Democrats</em> (!).</p>



<p>There’s a more fundamental difference as well: the wokeists define their worldview in opposition to the patriarchy, the white male power structure, or whatever else is preventing utopia.  I, taking inspiration from Huck, define my moral worldview in opposition to gaslighting itself, whatever its source, and in favor of acknowledging obvious realities (<em>especially</em> realities about any harm we might be causing others).  Thus, it’s not just that I see no tension between opposing the excesses of the woke and opposing Trump’s attempted <em>putsch</em>—rather, it’s that my opposition to both comes from exactly the same source.  It’s a source that, at least in me, often runs dry of courage, but I’ve found <em>Huck Finn</em> to be helpful in replenishing it, and for that I’m grateful.</p>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Endnote:</span></strong> There are, of course, many <em>actual</em> security problems with the way we vote in the US, and there are computer scientists who’ve studied those problems for decades, rather than suddenly getting selectively interested in November 2020.  If you’re interested, see <a href="https://josephhall.org/papers/Experts-Statement-on-the-US-2020-General-Election-16NOV2020-1057.pdf">this letter</a> (“Scientists say no credible evidence of computer fraud in the 2020 election outcome, but policymakers must work with experts to improve confidence”), which was signed by 59 of the leading figures in computer security, including Ron Rivest, Bruce Schneier, Hovav Shacham, Dan Wallach, Ed Felten, David Dill, and my childhood best friend Alex Halderman.</p>



<p><strong><span class="has-inline-color has-vivid-red-color">Update:</span></strong> I just noticed <a href="https://twitter.com/seanmcarroll/status/1330573317627998208">this Twitter thread</a> by friend-of-the-blog Sean Carroll, which says a lot of what I was trying to say here.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-23T19:43:23Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-23T19:43:23Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Rage Against Doofosity"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="The Fate of Humanity"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T19:57:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/23/assistant-professor-at-university-of-warwick-apply-by-november-30-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/23/assistant-professor-at-university-of-warwick-apply-by-november-30-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor at University of Warwick (apply by November 30, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at the University of Warwick, UK, invites applications for multiple tenure-track positions at the Assistant Professor level. The call is open to candidates working in all areas of Computer Science. Website: https://atsv7.wcn.co.uk/search_engine/jobs.cgi?SID=amNvZGU9MTg3Mjk1MiZ2dF90ZW1wbGF0ZT0xNDU3Jm93bmVyPTUwNjI0NTImb3duZXJ0eXBlPWZhaXImYnJhbmRfaWQ9MCZ2YWNfeHRyYTUwNjI0NTIuNTJfNTA2MjQ1Mj0yMzk5MjEmcG9zdGluZ19jb2RlPTYzNQ== Email: tom.gur@warwick.ac.uk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at the University of Warwick, UK, invites applications for multiple tenure-track positions at the Assistant Professor level. The call is open to candidates working in all areas of Computer Science.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://atsv7.wcn.co.uk/search_engine/jobs.cgi?SID=amNvZGU9MTg3Mjk1MiZ2dF90ZW1wbGF0ZT0xNDU3Jm93bmVyPTUwNjI0NTImb3duZXJ0eXBlPWZhaXImYnJhbmRfaWQ9MCZ2YWNfeHRyYTUwNjI0NTIuNTJfNTA2MjQ1Mj0yMzk5MjEmcG9zdGluZ19jb2RlPTYzNQ==">https://atsv7.wcn.co.uk/search_engine/jobs.cgi?SID=amNvZGU9MTg3Mjk1MiZ2dF90ZW1wbGF0ZT0xNDU3Jm93bmVyPTUwNjI0NTImb3duZXJ0eXBlPWZhaXImYnJhbmRfaWQ9MCZ2YWNfeHRyYTUwNjI0NTIuNTJfNTA2MjQ1Mj0yMzk5MjEmcG9zdGluZ19jb2RlPTYzNQ==</a><br/>
Email: tom.gur@warwick.ac.uk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-23T18:58:06Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-23T18:58:06Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10528</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10528" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Space Lower Bounds for Graph Stream Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606089600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/v/Verma:Paritosh.html">Paritosh Verma</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.10528">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>This work concerns with proving space lower bounds for graph problems in the
streaming model. It is known that computing the length of shortest path between
two nodes in the streaming model requires $\Omega(n)$ space, where $n$ is the
number of nodes in the graph. We study the problem of finding the depth of a
given node in a rooted tree in the streaming model. For this problem we prove a
tight single pass space lower bound and a multipass space lower bound. As this
is a special case of computing shortest paths on graphs, the above lower bounds
also apply to the shortest path problem in the streaming model. The results are
obtained by using known communication complexity lower bounds or by
constructing hard instances for the problem. Additionally, we apply the
techniques used in proving the above lower bound results to prove space lower
bounds (single and multipass) for other graph problems like finding min $s-t$
cut, detecting negative weight cycle and finding whether two nodes lie in the
same strongly connected component.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-23T22:37:28Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Complexity"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CC" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Complexity (cs.CC) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CC updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10508</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10508" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Planning Folding Motion with Simulation in the Loop Using Laser Forming Origami and Thermal Behaviors as an Example</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606089600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hao:Yue.html">Yue Hao</a>, Weilin Guan, Edwin A Peraza Hernandez, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lien:Jyh=Ming.html">Jyh-Ming Lien</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.10508">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Designing a robot or structure that can fold itself into a target shape is a
process that involves challenges originated from multiple sources. For example,
the designer of rigid self-folding robots must consider foldability from
geometric and kinematic aspects to avoid self-intersection and undesired
deformations. Recent works have shown success in estimating foldability of a
design using robot motion planners. However, many foldable structures are
actuated using physically coupled reactions (i.e., folding originated from
thermal, chemical, or electromagnetic loads). Therefore, a reliable foldability
analysis must consider additional constraints that resulted from these critical
phenomena. This work investigates the idea of efficiently incorporating
computationally expensive physics simulation within the folding motion planner
to provide a better estimation of the foldability. In this paper, we will use
laser forming origami as an example to demonstrate the benefits of considering
the properties beyond geometry. We show that the design produced by the
proposed method can be folded more efficiently.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-23T22:48:35Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10450</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10450" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Graph Tikhonov Regularization and Interpolation via Random Spanning Forests</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606089600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Yusuf Pilavci, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/a/Amblard:Pierre=Olivier.html">Pierre-Olivier Amblard</a>, Simon Barthelme, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Tremblay:Nicolas.html">Nicolas Tremblay</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.10450">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Novel Monte Carlo estimators are proposed to solve both the Tikhonov
regularization (TR) and the interpolation problems on graphs. These estimators
are based on random spanning forests (RSF), the theoretical properties of which
enable to analyze the estimators' theoretical mean and variance. We also show
how to perform hyperparameter tuning for these RSF-based estimators. Finally,
TR or interpolation being a building block of several algorithms, we show how
the proposed estimators can be easily adapted to avoid expensive intermediate
steps in well-known algorithms such as generalized semi-supervised learning,
label propagation, Newton's method and iteratively reweighted least square. In
the experiments, we illustrate the proposed methods on several problems and
provide observations on their run time, which are comparable with the
state-of-the-art.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-23T22:47:45Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10446</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10446" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hop-Constrained Oblivious Routing</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606089600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/g/Ghaffari:Mohsen.html">Mohsen Ghaffari</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Haeupler:Bernhard.html">Bernhard Haeupler</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Zuzic:Goran.html">Goran Zuzic</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.10446">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We prove the existence of an oblivious routing scheme that is
$\mathrm{poly}(\log n)$-competitive in terms of $(congestion + dilation)$, thus
resolving a well-known question in oblivious routing.
</p>
<p>Concretely, consider an undirected network and a set of packets each with its
own source and destination. The objective is to choose a path for each packet,
from its source to its destination, so as to minimize $(congestion +
dilation)$, defined as follows: The dilation is the maximum path hop-length,
and the congestion is the maximum number of paths that include any single edge.
The routing scheme obliviously and randomly selects a path for each packet
independent of (the existence of) the other packets. Despite this
obliviousness, the selected paths have $(congestion + dilation)$ within a
$\mathrm{poly}(\log n)$ factor of the best possible value. More precisely, for
any integer hop-bound $h$, this oblivious routing scheme selects paths of
length at most $h \cdot \mathrm{poly}(\log n)$ and is $\mathrm{poly}(\log
n)$-competitive in terms of $congestion$ in comparison to the best possible
$congestion$ achievable via paths of length at most $h$ hops. These paths can
be sampled in polynomial time.
</p>
<p>This result can be viewed as an analogue of the celebrated oblivious routing
results of R\"{a}cke [FOCS 2002, STOC 2008], which are $O(\log n)$-competitive
in terms of $congestion$, but are not competitive in terms of $dilation$.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-23T22:46:05Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10400</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10400" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Modeling and Engineering Constrained Shortest Path Algorithms for Battery Electric Vehicles</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606089600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/b/Baum:Moritz.html">Moritz Baum</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/d/Dibbelt:Julian.html">Julian Dibbelt</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/w/Wagner:Dorothea.html">Dorothea Wagner</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/z/Z=uuml=ndorf:Tobias.html">Tobias Zündorf</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.10400">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>We study the problem of computing constrained shortest paths for battery
electric vehicles. Since battery capacities are limited, fastest routes are
often infeasible. Instead, users are interested in fast routes on which the
energy consumption does not exceed the battery capacity. For that, drivers can
deliberately reduce speed to save energy. Hence, route planning should provide
both path and speed recommendations. To tackle the resulting NP-hard
optimization problem, previous work trades correctness or accuracy of the
underlying model for practical running times. We present a novel framework to
compute optimal constrained shortest paths (without charging stops) for
electric vehicles that uses more realistic physical models, while taking speed
adaptation into account. Careful algorithm engineering makes the approach
practical even on large, realistic road networks: We compute optimal solutions
in less than a second for typical battery capacities, matching the performance
of previous inexact methods. For even faster query times, the approach can
easily be extended with heuristics that provide high quality solutions within
milliseconds.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-23T22:40:34Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10385</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10385" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fixed-Parameter Algorithms for Graph Constraint Logic</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606089600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hatanaka:Tatsuhiko.html">Tatsuhiko Hatanaka</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/h/Hommelsheim:Felix.html">Felix Hommelsheim</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Ito:Takehiro.html">Takehiro Ito</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/k/Kobayashi:Yusuke.html">Yusuke Kobayashi</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/m/M=uuml=hlenthaler:Moritz.html">Moritz Mühlenthaler</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/s/Suzuki:Akira.html">Akira Suzuki</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.10385">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Non-deterministic constraint logic (NCL) is a simple model of computation
based on orientations of a constraint graph with edge weights and vertex
demands. NCL captures \PSPACE\xspace and has been a useful tool for proving
algorithmic hardness of many puzzles, games, and reconfiguration problems. In
particular, its usefulness stems from the fact that it remains \PSPACE-complete
even under severe restrictions of the weights (e.g., only edge-weights one and
two are needed) and the structure of the constraint graph (e.g., planar
\textsc{and/or}\xspace graphs of bounded bandwidth). While such restrictions on
the structure of constraint graphs do not seem to limit the expressiveness of
NCL, the building blocks of the constraint graphs cannot be limited without
losing expressiveness: We consider as parameters the number of weight-one edges
and the number of weight-two edges of a constraint graph, as well as the number
of \textsc{and}\xspace or \textsc{or}\xspace vertices of an
\textsc{and/or}\xspace constraint graph. We show that NCL is fixed-parameter
tractable (FPT) for any of these parameters. In particular, for NCL
parameterized by the number of weight-one edges or the number of
\textsc{and}\xspace vertices, we obtain a linear kernel. It follows that, in a
sense, NCL as introduced by Hearn and Demaine is defined in the most economical
way for the purpose of capturing \PSPACE.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-23T22:38:16Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10355</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10355" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>HyperLogLog (HLL) Security: Inflating Cardinality Estimates</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606089600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/r/Reviriego:Pedro.html">Pedro Reviriego</a>, Pablo Adell, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/t/Ting:Daniel.html">Daniel Ting</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.10355">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Counting the number of distinct elements on a set is needed in many
applications, for example to track the number of unique users in Internet
services or the number of distinct flows on a network. In many cases, an
estimate rather than the exact value is sufficient and thus many algorithms for
cardinality estimation that significantly reduce the memory and computation
requirements have been proposed. Among them, Hyperloglog has been widely
adopted in both software and hardware implementations. The security of
Hyperloglog has been recently studied showing that an attacker can create a set
of elements that produces a cardinality estimate that is much smaller than the
real cardinality of the set. This set can be used for example to evade
detection systems that use Hyperloglog. In this paper, the security of
Hyperloglog is considered from the opposite angle: the attacker wants to create
a small set that when inserted on the Hyperloglog produces a large cardinality
estimate. This set can be used to trigger false alarms in detection systems
that use Hyperloglog but more interestingly, it can be potentially used to
inflate the visits to websites or the number of hits of online advertisements.
Our analysis shows that an attacker can create a set with a number of elements
equal to the number of registers used in the Hyperloglog implementation that
produces any arbitrary cardinality estimate. This has been validated in two
commercial implementations of Hyperloglog: Presto and Redis. Based on those
results, we also consider the protection of Hyperloglog against such an attack.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-23T22:44:51Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10175</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10175" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Escherization with Generalized Distance Functions Focusing on Local Structural Similarity</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606089600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b><a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/n/Nagata:Yuichi.html">Yuichi Nagata</a>, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/i/Imahori:Shinji.html">Shinji Imahori</a> <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.10175">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>The Escherization problem involves finding a closed figure that tiles the
plane that is most similar to a given goal figure. In Koizumi and Sugihara's
formulation of the Escherization problem, the tile and goal figures are
represented as $n$-point polygons where the similarity between them is measured
based on the difference in the positions between the corresponding points. This
paper presents alternative similarity measures (distance functions) suitable
for this problem. The proposed distance functions focus on the similarity of
local structures in several different manners. The designed distance functions
are incorporated into a recently developed framework of the exhaustive search
of the templates for the Escherization problem. Efficient exhaustive and
incomplete search algorithms for the formulated problems are also developed to
obtain results within a reasonable computation time. Experimental results
showed that the proposed algorithms found satisfactory tile shapes for fairly
complicated goal figures in a reasonable computation time.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-23T22:48:16Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Computational Geometry"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CG" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Computational Geometry (cs.CG) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.CG updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10124</id>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2011.10124" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Best of Many Worlds: Dual Mirror Descent for Online Allocation Problems</title>
    <feedworld_mtime>1606089600</feedworld_mtime>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><b>Authors: </b>Santiago Balseiro, <a href="http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/indices/a-tree/l/Lu:Haihao.html">Haihao Lu</a>, Vahab Mirrokni <br/><b>Download:</b> <a href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/2011.10124">PDF</a><br/><b>Abstract: </b>Online allocation problems with resource constraints are central problems in
revenue management and online advertising. In these problems, requests arrive
sequentially during a finite horizon and, for each request, a decision maker
needs to choose an action that consumes a certain amount of resources and
generates reward. The objective is to maximize cumulative rewards subject to a
constraint on the total consumption of resources. In this paper, we consider a
data-driven setting in which the reward and resource consumption of each
request are generated using an input model that is unknown to the decision
maker.
</p>
<p>We design a general class of algorithms that attain good performance in
various inputs models without knowing which type of input they are facing. In
particular, our algorithms are asymptotically optimal under stochastic i.i.d.
input model as well as various non-stationary stochastic input models, and they
attain an asymptotically optimal fixed competitive ratio when the input is
adversarial. Our algorithms operate in the Lagrangian dual space: they maintain
a dual multiplier for each resource that is updated using online mirror
descent. By choosing the reference function accordingly, we recover dual
sub-gradient descent and dual exponential weights algorithm. The resulting
algorithms are simple, fast, and have minimal requirements on the reward
functions, consumption functions and the action space, in contrast to existing
methods for online allocation problems. We discuss applications to network
revenue management, online bidding in repeated auctions with budget
constraints, online proportional matching with high entropy, and personalized
assortment optimization with limited inventories.
</p></div>
    </summary>
    <updated>2020-11-23T22:37:37Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name/>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>http://arxiv.org/</id>
      <category term="Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms"/>
      <link href="http://arxiv.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://export.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rdf+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computer Science -- Data Structures and Algorithms (cs.DS) updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive</subtitle>
      <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T01:30:00Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-876463840143291851</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/876463840143291851/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/fun-with-birthdays-inspired-by-nov-20.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/876463840143291851" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/876463840143291851" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/fun-with-birthdays-inspired-by-nov-20.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Fun with birthdays, inspired by Nov 20</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p> On Nov 20, 2020  the Google Doodle was of Benoit Mandelbrot for his 96th birthday. Why have a Doodle on his 96th bday? Anyway, the Doodle is <a href="https://www.google.com/doodles/benoit-mandelbrots-96th-birthday">here</a>.  </p><p>On Nov 20, 2020 I read that Joe Biden turned 78. Why no Google Doodle of him? Maybe when he's 96. </p><p>This got me thinking of who else might have a Nov 20 birthday. I found the following (`found' is not quite right as I will explain later).</p><p>In order of age. </p><p>Benoit Mandelbrot: Dead at 85, would have been 96</p><p>Bobby Kennedy: Dead at 43, would have been 95.</p><p>Sergei Novikov: 82 years old. (Won Fields Medal in 1970 and did work on Solitons)</p><p>Dick Smothers: 80 years old (Tommy Smothers is not his twin, Tommy  is 3 years older) </p><p>Joe Biden, 78 years old (in most crowds he would be an old-timer, but in this crowd he is the baby of the bunch- though there is a reason for that as you will see later)</p><p>There are more Nov 20 famous people (famous to someone- I have not heard of most of them) <a href="https://www.famousbirthdays.com/november20.html">here</a></p><p>Some thoughts on all of this trivia</p><p>1) I keep a list of famous (to me) people over 80 (though if I look someone up who is not quite 80 I may put him on the list anyway, as is the case for Biden and Trump) so if they die I won't be one of those people saying `<i>I thought they were already dead</i>'.  I then began putting people on it who were  already dead so I could find matching bdays. Hence it was easy to find Nov 20 birthdays of people over 80, and one under. </p><p>2) Mandelbrot is more famous than Novikov since Mandelbrot has those pretty pictures. This is not a criticism of his work. Is it possible to make people who do hard and abstract math more in the public eye? Probably not. </p><p>3) There is an awesome song about the Mandelbrot set (though some of the comments on the you tube video say its the Julia Set, but HEY- if they have math in a song, I am happy and don't get too fussy about how accurate it is- though I would understand if Julia fans are annoyed). The song is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lIlwFpz9s_I">here</a>. It has 464 likes and 41 dislikes. That always puzzled me- why does it have <i>any</i> dislikes? I've seen really awesome songs still have some dislikes. Well, as Rick Nelson sings in Garden Party (see <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uAHR7_VZdRw">here</a>) ,<i>you</i> <i>can't please everyone, so you got to please yourself.</i> He got 25,000 likes and 702 dislikes. An awesome ratio, but why are there any dislikes? </p><p>4) I don't think Novikov will have a song about his work anytime soon.</p><p>5) Joe Biden has had some novelty songs about him in the past, and will do have more in the future once he is the Whitehouse. (Is the statement `Joe Biden is the president-elect' biased?)</p><p>6) I like the variety of the Nov 20 birthdays: two math, two politics, one entertainment. </p><p>7) I originally thought Nov 20 is NOT special and that most days would have around 5 bdays in my files. but actually no- I did a spot check of Nov 21,22,23,24,25,26,27,28,29,30 and they are all either 0,1, or 2 bdays. Prob not significant since this is just my small file. OR people avoid having babies close to thanksgiving (not sure of that one, but people DO avoid Feb 29 and Dec 25). </p><p>8) Of more interest are people born the same DAY and YEAR. I have a few of those, but I will point out one relevant to our field:</p><p>Albert Meyer and Art Garfunkel are same DAY and same YEAR.</p><p>Most famous SAME DAY and SAME YEAR of all time? I would guess</p><p>Abe Lincoln and Charles Darwin. <br/><br/></p><p>Second place</p><p> Margaret Thatcher and Lenny Bruce.</p><p> (I really doubt that's second place) </p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-22T21:19:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-22T21:19:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T00:54:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://mycqstate.wordpress.com/?p=1271</id>
    <link href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/2020/11/22/what-it-is-that-we-do/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>What it is that we do</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post is a follow-up on some somewhat off-hand comments that I made earlier regarding the notion of truth in a “proof-based” discipline such as pure mathematics or theoretical computer science. Since the former is easier to circumscribe and also … <a href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/2020/11/22/what-it-is-that-we-do/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>This post is a follow-up on some somewhat off-hand comments that I made <a href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/2020/09/29/it-happens-to-everyonebut-its-not-fun/">earlier</a> regarding the notion of truth in a “proof-based” discipline such as pure mathematics or theoretical computer science. Since the former is easier to circumscribe and also has a larger literature available on it, for the purposes of the post I will discuss my emerging take on truth in mathematics; what I say applies to TCS as well. (I wasn’t able to find satisfactory writings on the practice of computer science, even more broadly interpreted than just “theory”; any pointers on this are very welcome.) I obviously don’t claim any originality here; I suspect that to some the points I make might be interesting while to others they could feel passé–in the latter case, please help me make progress in the comments!</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><a href="https://mycqstate.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/circle.jpg"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1273" height="272" src="https://mycqstate.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/circle.jpg?w=762" width="261"/></a>A <em>circle</em> is a plane figure contained by one line such that all the straight lines falling upon it from one point among those lying within the figure equal one another. (Euclid, Elements, Book I, Definition 15.)</figure></div>



<p>The question is more interesting than it may seem. First, let’s set aside the Platonician answer that mathematics is about proving statements that apply to abstract objects. None of this makes sense: there is no such thing as an abstract object (What is an “abstract circle?” Euclid’s <em>definition</em> of an abstract circle exists, but that definition has nothing abstract; it is plain English—or well, Greek, which is no better). Neither is there anything fundamentally “true” about the statements that mathematicians make about these objects. This last point is made clear in Voevodsky’s retelling of the story that brought him to start his research program on univalent foundations: see in particular the paragraph starting with “The primary challenge that needed to be addressed” <a href="https://www.ias.edu/ideas/2014/voevodsky-origins">here</a>. While a subset of mathematicians has been carefully examining the logical foundations of mathematics and pursuing a program of formalizing these foundations with the goal of automating verification, two facts are historically evident: (1) this formalization has always come <em>after</em> the fact, i.e. first the theorem is proven, and second only is there some attempt at modifying the format of the “proof” so as to reach some abstract “higher standard”; (2) what the higher standard exactly is is a moving target. In other words, mathematicians do whatever it is that they do <em>first</em>, and only <em>after</em> that does some subset of them look back on what has been done and make an attempt to reformulate it in a way that seems more “rigorous” by the standards of the day. And even once this process has been completed (or rather, iterated over a few times), no absolute truth has been obtained; merely, one has gained higher confidence that some set of formal rules can be applied in a certain order to derive one statement for another. In summary, the logical answer “I define as true any statement that can be derived by said rules starting from said axioms” will not satisfy us. (My point is not to criticize this enterprise; only to point that this is not what mathematics is about. I don’t expect any mathematician would disagree.)</p>



<p>Once this point has been cleared we have opened up the possibility for a much richer interpretation of what mathematics is about, what it is that mathematicians do, and what is so special about the role played by the notion of truth in this enterprise.</p>



<h2>The Greeks</h2>



<p>Mathematicians have been around since Greek antiquity. I highly recommend the wonderful book <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511543296">The Shaping of Deduction in Greek Mathematics</a> by Reviel Netz, a historian at Stanford. The book provides a fantastic historical introduction to the birth of modern mathematics, as practiced in the Western world. In this book Netz gives a detailed account of the practice of Greek mathematics that is based on a sometimes almost comical literal reading of the original texts. Netz is not a mathematician, and he takes the Greek writings at face value, without preconceptions as to any deeper meaning, mathematical or otherwise. To see how fantastic an enterprise this might be I highly recommend taking the time to read through a few paragraphs of Euclid’s elements, see e.g. <a href="https://www.claymath.org/library/historical/euclid/index.html">here</a>. (I wasn’t able to find an online version that has clear figures; Netz’ book contains many reproductions and he spends a great deal of time examining their significance as a companion to the text.) Wait, and they called this a <em>proof</em>? </p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><a href="https://mycqstate.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/phil-2017-0007_05.jpg"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1276" height="241" src="https://mycqstate.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/phil-2017-0007_05.jpg?w=1024" width="320"/></a>Netz places a particular emphasis on the role of lettered diagrams such as this one in Greek mathematicians’ proofs. This one is taken from Apollonius, as reproduced in <a href="https://doi.org/10.1515/phil-2017-0007">this book</a>.</figure></div>



<p>What I find most amazing about Netz’ work is that his book makes it absolutely clear that what Greek mathematics did is invent a very special world, with its own set of rules and specifications as to how things should be presented, what counts as valid and what does not, etc; most importantly this set of rules and specifications is absolutely <em>arbitrary</em>. There is nothing <em>universally</em> true about any of the statements made in Euclid’s book ; what there is however, and which is just as important, is a form of <em>self-consistent</em>, <em>self-perpetuating</em> consistency. This is the Greek mathematician’s most important discovery, and most enduring legacy: a system of thought, based on the use of formal rules, such that users of that system of thought can easily and unequivocally agree on the same statements. Netz contrasts this with the political discourse that the Greeks were so famously fond of; while in rhetoric endless arguments can be made in favor or against any given statement, in mathematics once an argument has been made there is no discussing it; either the argument is correct and accepted by all or it is flawed and all will agree on the presence of a flaw. By saying that mathematics does not establish universal truths we do not take away any of the strength of its evident success as a system of thought. </p>



<p>I insist that in the previous sentence by “mathematics” I mean “Greek mathematics.” There is nothing universal about the formal “proof system” used by the Greeks, and in fact that system is arguably quite different from the one used today (contrast a proof in Euclid’s Elements from one in e.g. Kerodon (see figure below); clearly either school would reject the other’s papers!). There is nothing absolutely perfect or even fool-proof about it either; when I write that “either the argument is correct or it is flawed” I do not dismiss the existence of a substantial grey zone in which there might be, and generally is, discussion. (Netz in his presentation makes it plainly obvious that Greek proofs had many “gaps” and that completely arbitrary choices are made as to what is valid and what is not.) The point is that this grey zone is by orders of magnitude smaller than in other disciplines, and this is what makes mathematics special.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><a href="https://mycqstate.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/diagram.jpg"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1278" height="118" src="https://mycqstate.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/diagram.jpg?w=943" width="470"/></a>A lettered diagram taken from the proof of Lemma 3.5.3.11 in <a href="https://kerodon.net/">Kerodon</a>.</figure></div>



<p>Greek mathematics has its limitations. In particular, it seems like they were not able to expand their explorations much beyond geometry; possibly because they did not have a formal way of re-using proofs. Indeed, only propositions from Euclid’s elements were part of the general corpus of “truths” that could be used without justification; any other proof could only appeal to either a statement from the Elements or a statement proved within the same text (as opposed to a statement made by another mathematician). The current system has a much higher level of re-usability, allowing it to much deeper. It is possible that current attempt at formalization will provide yet another layer to this by enabling re-using statements without the mathematician herself even being cognizant of the statement that is being re-used (e.g. the proof assistant would figure out that there is some theorem somewhere that could be useful). </p>



<h2>The moderns</h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><a href="https://mycqstate.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/qkd.jpg"><img alt="" class="wp-image-1280" height="420" src="https://mycqstate.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/qkd.jpg?w=831" width="382"/></a>A lettered diagram taken from the proof of security of quantum key distribution in Renner’s <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0512258">Ph.D. thesis</a>.</figure></div>



<p>Once one has taken this somewhat distanced look at the practice of Greek mathematicians it becomes clear that there is no reason for contemporary practice to escape similar distanciation. As arbitrary as the rules that govern the former might seem now, just as arbitrary our own rules will seem later. The observation prompts us to re-evaluate the notion of proof and truth as follows: <em>The goal of the mathematical proof is to convince the mathematician; a statement is true whenever the mathematician is convinced.</em> I emphasize that the mathematician in this sentence is a human being, not a machine. <br/><br/>Propositions in Euclid’s elements are true because Euclid’s text convinced all other Greek mathematicians that they were true; the same hold of Voevodsky’s univalent foundations. To speak about my personal experience, the point was carried home vividly about a decade ago at the end of an entire afternoon spent sitting by the sea nearby Marseille in the South of France together with an illustrious French operator algebraist. For the whole afternoon I had been trying to explain, of all things, the Clause-Horne-Shimony-Holt inequality formulated as a nonlocal game—an elementary construction on which half of my research is based (see <a href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/2012/10/10/tsirelsons-bound/">this post</a> for example, although we  certainly didn’t get that far). To no avail! Alice, Bob, games, the mathematician would have none of it. How could it be so hard? The message I was trying to carry across is bread and butter to quantum information theorists; moreover the language of functional analysis was not foreign to me either and so I believed I ought to have more than it should take to make the explanations clear; in my mind I had a clear theorem, together with an airtight proof, to communicate. Not so: I ended the afternoon defeated, and the point hammered in: as much as we may think that our language is formal, our reasoning rational, our goals clear, as soon as we step out of our self-referential cocoon we have to face the evidence: not so; there is nothing clear, formal, self-evident, in the mathematical truths we take as such. (If you’re not convinced yet, look at the pictures.)</p>



<p>After having read through the viewpoint of a historian on Greek mathematics, it is interesting to come back to the present and read up on the modern mathematician’s own account of their practice. Having delighted in Hardy’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Mathematician%27s_Apology">A Mathematician’s Apology</a> in my student years I was naturally attracted to Harris’ explicitly referential book <a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691154237/mathematics-without-apologies">Mathematics Without Apologies</a>. The book aims to provide a personal answer to precisely the same question as Netz’ (“What do pure mathematicians do, and why do they do it?”—first line on back cover), with the essential difference that Harris’ book is written by a contemporary mathematician about the practice of modern mathematics. The perspective taken is thus very different: Harris does not waste a drop of ink to examine the material products of modern mathematics (e.g. printed articles), which naturally from his point of view do not have the least interest besides their mathematical significance; nor does he question the formal system that enables mathematics (he does discuss foundation issues, but these are themselves part of the formal system). </p>



<p>Harris delights in telling us stories about the practice of mathematics from the inside: the way one acquires prestige (he calls it “charisma”), how mathematicians perceive when a mathematical statement is interesting, what drives a mathematician to work on one problem or another, the influence of large research programs such as the Langlands program, etc. Just as Netz, Harris agrees that the proof itself, while an important product of the mathematician’s practice, is not a goal in itself. The goal is to introduce new objects, find relations between them, and build structures that support this exploration (Harris quotes extensively from Grothendieck, a builder of structures if there is any). Crucially the mathematician’s goal is not at all to find <em>truth</em>: her goal is to find <em>beauty</em>. Harris (un-apologetically!) defends the mathematician’s position as playing a privileged and essential role in our (Western) society: mathematics is the rare, if not unique, discipline where thought is valued <em>for itself</em>: not for its consequences or potential applications, nor even for some kind of universal validity or truth that it might reach — for itself, the sheer beauty of it. No apologies. While one might think that the arts are in a similar position, Harris points out that in contemporary discussions about art the notion of beauty has all but disappeared; instead, one talks of society, ecology, politics—all of this is good and important, but it is not about beauty. Mathematics is about exploring the beauty of human thought. This exploration is carried out within the very special, narrow and arbitrary corner that mathematical practice has delineated for itself since the Greeks got us started. And yet does not matter that it is narrow and arbitrary; what matters is that it is purely and uniquely human.</p>



<p>I don’t have a conclusion to give to this post. I suppose it is the kind of digression that one is naturally inclined to make while on <a href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/2020/09/20/announcing-a-short-course-in-paris/">sabbatical</a>. (I was delighted to see Harris reference his time at the Institut Henri Poincaré in Paris extensively and spend multiple pages gossiping about Ed Frenkel, then a holder of the same FSMP chair I am now occupying.) Certainly it helps to gain a sense of what it is that one is doing. While these explorations destroyed a number of simple comforting myths about what it is that I do every day, in the end I find the void that lies beneath the surface much more appealing; I feel privileged and comforted in my desire to make use of that privilege.</p>



<h2>Post-scriptum</h2>



<p>In addition to the two books referenced in the post there are a couple articles that I found helpful. I am listing them here because I found such writings non-trivial to come by, and so they might be helpful to anyone interested in the topic. I welcome additional references. </p>



<ul><li>Barton, <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11858-999-0009-7">Ethnomathematics and Philosophy</a>. This is Barton’s Ph.D. thesis, in which he studies the social emergence of mathematics not as inevitable, but as cultural, yet without negating what is so special about it. .</li><li>Wallet and Neuwirth, <a href="https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01943079/">Enquete sur les modes d’existence des etres mathematiques</a> (unfortunately in French only it seems). The authors build on Netz’ work and others to examine the notion of mathematical proof within Latour’s framework of “modes of existence,” which Latour mostly applied to experimental sciences. </li></ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-22T16:14:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-22T16:14:00Z</published>
    <category term="meta"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="meta-mathematics"/>
    <author>
      <name>Thomas</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://mycqstate.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://mycqstate.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>In superposition</subtitle>
      <title>MyCQstate</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:38:34Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?p=4419</id>
    <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/11/22/post-doc-opportunities-in-milan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Post-doc Opportunities in Milan</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[call for applications] [application form] I am recruiting two postdocs for two-year positions to work with me starting in Fall 2021 at Bocconi University. The positions have competitive salaries and are tax-free. If applicable, I will pay for relocation expenses, … <a href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/2020/11/22/post-doc-opportunities-in-milan/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>[<a href="https://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/dd6db99c-fac4-4971-a749-54a6ff58ea64/2ADR+CALL+BIDSA+01B1+16.12.20.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&amp;CVID=nlQcPwz">call for applications</a>] [<a href="https://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/667b728b-c2b2-42c3-a1c1-0dc34adf8418/Form+2ADR+01B1+BIDSA+16.12.20.docx?MOD=AJPERES&amp;CVID=nlQcVxf">application form]</a></p>



<p>I am recruiting two postdocs for two-year positions to work with me starting in Fall 2021 at Bocconi University. The positions have competitive salaries and are tax-free. If applicable, I will pay for relocation expenses, including the assistance of a relocation agency for help in finding a place to live and activate utilities, to complete immigration formalities, and to sign up for the national health care service.</p>



<p>Milan has been suffering as much or more than other European and American big cities for the effects of the Covid-19 pandemic. I have seen Milan in its normal condition for a few months from September 2019 to February 2020, and it is a beautiful cosmopolitan city, with an active cultural and social life, and with beautiful surroundings. Like San Francisco, it is smaller than one would expect it to be and very walkable (no hills!). Bocconi is situated in a semi-central area, about twenty minute walk from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan_Cathedral">Duomo</a>.</p>



<p>I have received a large European grant that, besides paying for these postdoc positions, has a budget for senior visitors and for organizing two workshops over the duration of the grant. In particular, I was planning a workshop to be held last May in a villa on Lake Como. All such plans have been on hold, but Fall 2021 should be around the time that the global pandemic emergency ends, and I am planning for a lot of exciting scientific activity at Bocconi in the academic year 2021-22 and beyond.</p>



<p>I am looking for candidates with an established body of work on topics related to my research agenda, such as pseudorandomness and combinatorial constructions; spectral graph theory; worst-case and average-case analysis of  semidefinite programming relaxation of combinatorial optimization problems.</p>



<p>Here are the <a href="https://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/dd6db99c-fac4-4971-a749-54a6ff58ea64/2ADR+CALL+BIDSA+01B1+16.12.20.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&amp;CVID=nlQcPwz">call for applications</a> and the <a href="https://www.unibocconi.eu/wps/wcm/connect/667b728b-c2b2-42c3-a1c1-0dc34adf8418/Form+2ADR+01B1+BIDSA+16.12.20.docx?MOD=AJPERES&amp;CVID=nlQcVxf">application form</a>.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-22T15:28:25Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-22T15:28:25Z</published>
    <category term="Milan"/>
    <category term="theory"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
    <category term="postdoc"/>
    <author>
      <name>luca</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://lucatrevisan.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>"Marge, I agree with you - in theory. In theory, communism works. In theory." -- Homer Simpson</subtitle>
      <title>in   theory</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:10Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?p=514</id>
    <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/2020/11/20/the-coin-problem-with-applications-to-data-streams/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>The Coin Problem with Applications to Data Streams</title>
    <summary>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, November 25th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). Sumegha Garg from Harvard University will speak about “The Coin Problem with Applications to Data Streams” (abstract below). You can reserve a spot as an individual or a […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The next TCS+ talk will take place this coming Wednesday, November 25th at 1:00 PM Eastern Time (10:00 AM Pacific Time, 19:00 Central European Time, 18:00 UTC). <strong>Sumegha Garg</strong> from Harvard University will speak about “<em>The Coin Problem with Applications to Data Streams</em>” (abstract below). </p>



<p>You can reserve a spot as an individual or a group to join us live by signing up on <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/livetalk/live-seat-reservation">the online form</a>. Due to security concerns, <em>registration is required</em> to attend the interactive talk. As usual, for more information about the TCS+ online seminar series and the upcoming talks, or to <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/suggest">suggest</a> a possible topic or speaker, please see <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/plustcs/">the website</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-quote">Abstract: Consider the problem of computing the majority of a stream of <img alt="n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=n&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="n"/> i.i.d. uniformly random bits. This problem, known as the coin problem, is central to a number of counting problems in different data stream models. We show that any streaming algorithm for solving this problem with large constant advantage (over the uniform distribution) must use <img alt="\Omega(\log n)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5COmega%28%5Clog+n%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\Omega(\log n)"/> bits of space. Previously, it was known that computing the majority on every input with a constant probability takes <img alt="\Omega(\log n)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5COmega%28%5Clog+n%29&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\Omega(\log n)"/> space. We extend our lower bound to proving tight lower bounds for solving multiple, randomly interleaved copies of the coin problem, as well as for solving the OR of multiple copies of a variant of the coin problem. Our proofs involve new measures of information complexity that are well-suited for data streams.<br/><br/>We use these lower bounds to obtain a number of new results for data streams. In each case there is an underlying <img alt="d" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="d"/>-dimensional vector <img alt="x" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=x&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="x"/> with additive updates to its coordinates given in a stream of length <img alt="m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="m"/>. The input streams arising from our coin lower bound have nice distributional properties, and consequently for many problems for which we only had lower bounds in general turnstile streams, we now obtain the same lower bounds in more natural models, such as the bounded deletion model, in which <img alt="\|x\|_2" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5C%7Cx%5C%7C_2&amp;bg=fff&amp;fg=444444&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\|x\|_2"/> never drops by a constant fraction of what it was earlier, or in the random order model, in which the updates are ordered randomly. <br/><br/>Based on joint work with Mark Braverman and David P. Woodruff.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-20T15:00:57Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-20T15:00:57Z</published>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
    <author>
      <name>plustcs</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://tcsplus.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://tcsplus.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A carbon-free dissemination of ideas across the globe.</subtitle>
      <title>TCS+</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:38:11Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=20419</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/20/peter-pal-pach-and-richard-palincza-a-glimpse-beyond-the-horizon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Péter Pál Pach and Richárd Palincza: a Glimpse Beyond the Horizon</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prologue Consider the following problems: P3: What is the maximum density of a set A in without a 3-term AP? (AP=arithmetic progression.) This is the celebrated Cap Set problem and we reported here in 2016 the breakthrough results by … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/20/peter-pal-pach-and-richard-palincza-a-glimpse-beyond-the-horizon/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><h2><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/peter-pach.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-20448" height="150" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/peter-pach.jpg?w=132&amp;h=150" width="132"/></a> <a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/palincza.jpg"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-thumbnail wp-image-20449" height="150" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/palincza.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150" width="150"/></a></h2>
<h2>Prologue</h2>
<p>Consider the following problems:</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>P3:</strong></span> What is the maximum density of a set A in <img alt="(\mathbb Z/3\mathbb Z)^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28%5Cmathbb+Z%2F3%5Cmathbb+Z%29%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="(\mathbb Z/3\mathbb Z)^n"/> without a 3-term AP? (AP=arithmetic progression.)</p>
<p>This is the celebrated Cap Set problem and we <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2016/05/15/mind-boggling-following-the-work-of-croot-lev-and-pach-jordan-ellenberg-settled-the-cap-set-problem/">reported here</a> in 2016 the breakthrough results by Croot-Lev-Pach-Ellenberg-Gijswijt (CLPEG) asserting that <img alt="|A| \le 2.755..^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7CA%7C+%5Cle+2.755..%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="|A| \le 2.755..^n"/>.</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">P4:</span></strong> What is the maximum density of a set A in  <img alt="(\mathbb Z/4\mathbb Z)^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28%5Cmathbb+Z%2F4%5Cmathbb+Z%29%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="(\mathbb Z/4\mathbb Z)^n"/> without a 4-term AP?</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>P5:</strong></span> What is the maximum density of a set A in  <img alt="(\mathbb Z/5\mathbb Z)^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28%5Cmathbb+Z%2F5%5Cmathbb+Z%29%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="(\mathbb Z/5\mathbb Z)^n"/> without a 5-term AP?</p>
<p>Moving from 3 term AP to 4 term AP represents a major leap for such problems. In some cases moving from 4 to 5 also represents a major leap. Usually the techniques that work for <img alt="k=5" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k%3D5&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k=5"/> continue to work for <img alt="k&gt;5" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k%3E5&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k&gt;5"/>, that is, I am not aware of cases where moving from 5 to 6 also represent a major leap. In other words, we do not have reasons to think, so far,  that progress on P6 (below) will be considerably harder than progress on P5.</p>
<p><strong><span style="color: #0000ff;">P6:</span></strong> What is the maximum density of a set A in <img alt="(\mathbb Z/6\mathbb Z)^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%28%5Cmathbb+Z%2F6%5Cmathbb+Z%29%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="(\mathbb Z/6\mathbb Z)^n"/> without a 6-term AP?</p>
<p>And, of course, we can move on to <span style="color: #0000ff;"><strong>P7, P8, P9,….</strong> </span>,</p>
<p>It is known that the density of a set <img alt="A \subset (\mathbb Z_m)^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A+%5Csubset+%28%5Cmathbb+Z_m%29%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="A \subset (\mathbb Z_m)^n"/> without <img alt="m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="m"/>-term AP for  every fixed m goes to zero with n. This was proved by  Furstenberg and Katznelson using ergodic theoretical tools. Following the CLPEG breakthrough we can certainly believe that the density that guarantees m-term AP in <img alt="\mathbb Z_m^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z_m%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb Z_m^n"/> for every fixed m is exponentially small in n. I vaguely remember that the best known bounds for P4 are polylogarithmically small with n and were achieved by Green and Tao using tools from Gowers’ work on 4AP-free sets over the integers.</p>
<h3>A little more before we move on</h3>
<p>To have some general notation let <img alt="r_k(\mathbb Z_m^n)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=r_k%28%5Cmathbb+Z_m%5En%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="r_k(\mathbb Z_m^n)"/> denote the maximal size of a set <img alt="A \subset \mathbb Z_m^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=A+%5Csubset+%5Cmathbb+Z_m%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="A \subset \mathbb Z_m^n"/> with no <em>k</em> distinct elements in arithmetic progression. It is reasonable to believe that <img alt="r_m(\mathbb Z_m^n) \le \delta_m^n m^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=r_m%28%5Cmathbb+Z_m%5En%29+%5Cle+%5Cdelta_m%5En+m%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="r_m(\mathbb Z_m^n) \le \delta_m^n m^n"/> for some <img alt="\delta_m &lt; 1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdelta_m+%3C+1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\delta_m &lt; 1"/>, that is that sets in <img alt="\mathbb Z_m^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z_m%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb Z_m^n"/> avoiding <img alt="m" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=m&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="m"/> terms AP are exponentially small. To be more precise let</p>
<p><img alt="\delta_m= \frac {1}{m} \lim r_k(\mathbb Z_m^n)^{1/n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdelta_m%3D+%5Cfrac+%7B1%7D%7Bm%7D+%5Clim+r_k%28%5Cmathbb+Z_m%5En%29%5E%7B1%2Fn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\delta_m= \frac {1}{m} \lim r_k(\mathbb Z_m^n)^{1/n}"/></p>
<p>We can believe that the limits exist,  that <img alt="\delta_m&lt;1" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdelta_m%3C1&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\delta_m&lt;1"/>, and we may also guess (wildly but safely) that they satisfy <img alt="{\delta_3} &lt; {\delta_4} &lt; {\delta_5} \cdots&#xA0; " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdelta_3%7D+%3C+%7B%5Cdelta_4%7D+%3C+%7B%5Cdelta_5%7D+%5Ccdots%C2%A0+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\delta_3} &lt; {\delta_4} &lt; {\delta_5} \cdots&#xA0; "/>.</p>
<p>These problems, as well as the analogous problems over the integers, (Roth’s and Szemeredi’s theorems and later developments), and the related density Hales Jewett problem,  form a  holy grail of additive combinatorics and they attracted a lot of attention also on this blog.</p>
<p>Here is a partial list of posts: <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2008/07/10/pushing-behrend-around/">2008</a> Pushing the Behrend bound; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2009/02/07/frankl-rodls-theorem-and-variations-on-the-cap-set-problem-a-recent-research-project-with-roy-meshulam-a/">2009A</a>, <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2009/05/11/around-the-cap-set-problem-b/">2009B</a> <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2009/05/18/the-cap-set-problem-and-frankl-rodl-theorem-c/">2009C</a> Attempts to relate the problem to the Frankl-Wilson Theorem (and the polynomial method) and to Frankl-Rodl theorem and also to find counterexamples;  <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2009/03/11/polymath1-probable-success/">2009D</a> polymath1;  <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2009/03/25/an-open-discussion-and-polls-around-roths-theorem/">2009P</a> public opinion poll about the true behavior;  <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2010/11/24/roths-theorem-sanders-reaches-the-logarithmic-barrier/">2010</a> The logarithmic bound for Roth is reached; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2011/12/09/cup-sets-sunflowers-and-matrix-multiplication/">2011</a> cap sets and matrix multiplications; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2016/05/15/mind-boggling-following-the-work-of-croot-lev-and-pach-jordan-ellenberg-settled-the-cap-set-problem/">2016a</a>, <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2016/05/10/math-from-facebook/">2016b</a> The CLPEG breakthrough; <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2016/12/21/polynomial-method-workshop/">2016W</a> A polynomial method workshop;  <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/07/08/to-cheer-you-up-in-difficult-times-7-bloom-and-sisask-just-broke-the-logarithm-barrier-for-roths-theorem/">2020</a> The logarithmic bound for Roth is broken.</p>
<p>Let’s move on to the new result by Péter Pál Pach and Richárd Palincza</p>
<h2><span style="color: #0000ff;">The</span> <span style="color: #ffffff;">absolutely stunning</span> <span style="color: #0000ff;">result by Péter Pál Pach and Richárd Palincza</span></h2>
<p><span id="more-20419"/></p>
<p>As we already mentioned, so far we do not have reasons to expect that proving density results for 6-terms AP in <img alt="\mathbb Z_6^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z_6%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb Z_6^n"/> (or <img alt="\mathbb Z" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb Z"/>) will be much harder than the question over <img alt="\mathbb Z_5^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z_5%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb Z_5^n"/>. <strong>However</strong>, what Pach and Palincza proved is as follows:</p>
<p><strong>Theorem</strong>:  sets avoiding 6-term arithmetic progressions in <img alt="\mathbb Z_6^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z_6%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb Z_6^n"/> have size at most <img alt="5.709^n" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=5.709%5En&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="5.709^n"/>.</p>
<p>The big surprise is that the problem P6 over integers modulo six is <strong>much easier</strong> than P4 and P5. The proof is based on a simple combinatorial reasoning showing that</p>
<p><img alt="r_6(\mathbb Z_6^n) \le 2^{n+1} \sqrt {3^nr_3(\mathbb Z_3^n).}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=r_6%28%5Cmathbb+Z_6%5En%29+%5Cle+2%5E%7Bn%2B1%7D+%5Csqrt+%7B3%5Enr_3%28%5Cmathbb+Z_3%5En%29.%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="r_6(\mathbb Z_6^n) \le 2^{n+1} \sqrt {3^nr_3(\mathbb Z_3^n).}"/></p>
<p>The paper arXived on September 2020 is</p>
<p><a href="https://arxiv.org/search/math?searchtype=author&amp;query=Pach%2C+P+P">Péter Pál Pach and</a> <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/math?searchtype=author&amp;query=Palincza%2C+R">Richárd Palincza</a>: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.11897">Sets avoiding six-term arithmetic progressions in <img alt="\mathbb Z^n_6" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathbb+Z%5En_6&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathbb Z^n_6"/> are exponentially small</a></p>
<p>Click and enjoy this beautiful, stunning and <strong>very simple</strong> proof.<span style="color: #ff0000;"><br/>
</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Congratulations to Péter and Richárd!</span></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-20T09:16:40Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-20T09:16:40Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Geometry"/>
    <category term="Number theory"/>
    <category term="Open problems"/>
    <category term="P&#xE9;ter P&#xE1;l Pach"/>
    <category term="Rich&#xE1;rd Palincza"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-11-19-bft-protocol-forensics/</id>
    <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/2020-11-19-bft-protocol-forensics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>BFT Protocol Forensics</title>
    <summary>An important property satisfied by any Byzantine fault tolerant consensus protocol is agreement, which requires non-faulty replicas to not decide on conflicting values. Depending on the network model, typical consensus protocols tolerate only a fraction of Byzantine replicas. In particular, under partial synchrony or asynchrony, no consensus protocol with $n$...</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-20T01:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-20T01:00:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io</id>
      <author>
        <name>Decentralized Thoughts</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://decentralizedthoughts.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Decentralized thoughts about decentralization</subtitle>
      <title>Decentralized Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T22:51:05Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-6939903186223741314</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/6939903186223741314/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/vaughan-jones-and-kaikoura.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6939903186223741314" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/6939903186223741314" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/vaughan-jones-and-kaikoura.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Vaughan Jones and Kaikoura</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaughan_Jones">Vaughan Jones</a>, one of the greatest mathematicians from New Zealand, passed away on September 6 at 67. Jones is an expert in knot theory among other areas and received the Fields Medal in 1990.</p><p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jones_polynomial">Jones polynomial</a> captures information about knots. Vaughan Jones himself co-authored a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/0511096">paper</a> on a polynomial-time quantum algorithm for approximating the Jones polynomial, one of the few natural problems outside of factoring that has an exponential improvement with a quantum algorithm. </p><p>From his Vanderbilt <a href="https://news.vanderbilt.edu/2020/09/09/vaughan-jones-preeminent-vanderbilt-mathematician-has-died/">obituary</a></p><blockquote><p>One way he worked to improve the field of mathematics in his native country was to organize a “summer school” in January each year and attract leading mathematicians from around the world to give lectures and interact with local students and professional mathematicians at a variety of beautiful locations around New Zealand. Out of this activity grew the New Zealand Mathematics Research Institute, which he co-founded and then led from the mid-1990s to this year.</p></blockquote><p>I had the pleasure of teaching in one of those summer schools in January 2000 in Kaikoura on the South Island. In between the whale watching, mountain hiking, <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2008/09/jogging-on-trips.html">jogging</a>, gorging on mussels, and Maori ceremonies, the NZMRI summer school <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Aspects_of_Complexity/XlB_JTR0sV8C">Aspects of Complexity</a> had short courses to a mix of students and researchers in complexity and logic. I gave some <a href="https://lance.fortnow.com/papers/files/kaikoura.pdf">lectures</a> on Kolmogorov complexity that preceded a study of algorithmic randomness in the logic community. Other speakers included Eric Allender on basic complexity, Felipe Cucker on real computation, Mike Fellows on parameterized complexity, and Dominic Welsh on counting complexity. </p><p>It took me 36 hours door-to-door to get to Kaikoura but definitely worth it. Thanks to Vaughan Jones, for his research, his polynomial and creating a summer school that gave me that one perfect week in New Zealand.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-19T16:56:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-19T16:56:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T00:54:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7906</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/11/19/updated-research-masters-programs-database-by-aviad-rubinstein-and-matt-weinberg/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Updated Research Masters programs database by Aviad Rubinstein and Matt Weinberg</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Guest post by Aviad Rubinstein and Matt Weinberg As explained in Boaz’s previous posts [1] [2], the PhD admission process can be challenging for students who discover their passion for Theory of Computer Science late in their undergraduate studies. Discovering TCS earlier is especially challenging for students who aren’t exposed to CS in high school, … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/11/19/updated-research-masters-programs-database-by-aviad-rubinstein-and-matt-weinberg/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Updated Research Masters programs database by Aviad Rubinstein and Matt Weinberg</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Guest post by <a href="https://cs.stanford.edu/~aviad/">Aviad Rubinstein</a> and <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~smattw/">Matt Weinberg</a></p>



<p>As explained in Boaz’s previous posts <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2018/02/20/research-masters/">[1]</a> <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/07/02/crowdsourcing-masters-program/">[2]</a>, the PhD admission process can be challenging for students who discover their passion for Theory of Computer Science late in their undergraduate studies. Discovering TCS earlier is especially challenging for students who aren’t exposed to CS in high school, and this bias aggravates the diversity issues we have in our community. Masters programs are one way to mitigate this issue.<br/>On a personal note, one of us (Aviad), worked half-time during undergraduate and would not have been in academia today -let alone TCS of all subjects- if it weren’t for the awesome TCS masters program at Tel-Aviv University.</p>



<p><br/>But where would you go (or send your students) to do a masters in TCS?A little over a year ago, we were discussing how useful it would be to have a unified resource that can help students choose. We decided that we should create one! Months passed, and right before we ran out of excuses to procrastinate, Boaz made this <a href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/07/02/crowdsourcing-masters-program/">post</a> crowdsourcing information on TCS masters programs.<br/>After some more procrastination, we eventually did send a lot of emails and tried to clean and organize the information to the best of our ability. Thanks to everyone who contributed! You can find the latest version <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~smattw/masters/masters.html">here</a>. (Short url: <a href="http://tiny.cc/tcsmasters">http://tiny.cc/tcsmasters</a>)</p>



<p>Now you should share it with your brightest students!</p>



<p><br/>This is also meant to be a live project. Please email aviad [at] <a href="http://cs.stanford.edu/" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">cs.stanford.edu</a> if you have more new information or find any inaccuracies.</p>



<p>Thanks!</p>



<p>-Aviad and Matt</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-19T14:40:09Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-19T14:40:09Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:59Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/19/assistant-professor-at-london-school-of-economics-and-political-science-apply-by-january-11-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/19/assistant-professor-at-london-school-of-economics-and-political-science-apply-by-january-11-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Assistant Professor at London School of Economics and Political Science (apply by January 11, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Mathematics at LSE seeks to appoint an Assistant Professor with expertise in a subject area related to the Mathematics of Game Theory. Website: https://tinyurl.com/MathJobLSE2020 Email: j.van-den-heuvel@lse.ac.uk</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Mathematics at LSE seeks to appoint an Assistant Professor with expertise in a subject area related to the Mathematics of Game Theory.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://tinyurl.com/MathJobLSE2020">https://tinyurl.com/MathJobLSE2020</a><br/>
Email: j.van-den-heuvel@lse.ac.uk</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-19T10:12:32Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-19T10:12:32Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?p=17791</id>
    <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/19/traveling-salesman-problem-meets-complexity-theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Traveling Salesman Problem Meets Complexity Theory</title>
    <summary>Crazy ideas meet crazed audience Merrill Flood was a mathematician who publicized the Traveling salesman problem TSP back in the 1940s. He says that he found the problem while: I was struggling with the problem in connecting with a school-bus routing study in New Jersey. Today I thought we might look at the TSP from […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>
<font color="#0044cc"><br/>
<em>Crazy ideas meet crazed audience</em><br/>
<font color="#000000"/></font></p><font color="#0044cc"><font color="#000000">
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/19/traveling-salesman-problem-meets-complexity-theory/flood/" rel="attachment wp-att-17793"><img alt="" class="alignright  wp-image-17751" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/flood.jpg?w=144" width="144"/></a></p>
<p>
Merrill Flood was a mathematician who publicized the Traveling salesman problem <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merrill_M._Flood">TSP</a> back in the 1940s.  </p>
<p>He says that he found the problem while: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> <img alt="{\dots}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cdots%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\dots}"/> I was struggling with the problem in connecting with a school-bus routing study in New Jersey. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
Today I thought we might look at the TSP from a viewpoint of complexity theory.</p>
<p>
First, we note that the origins of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travelling_salesman_problem">TSP</a> are unclear. In 1832 it was mentioned in a handbook for traveling salesmen in Germany and Switzerland. William Hamilton talked about the related problem later named for him: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> On finding a circuit through all points of graph. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Karl Menger, in the 1930s, defined the TSP, and considered the obvious brute-force algorithm, and observed the non-optimality of the nearest neighbor heuristic. We have annotated Wikipedia’s optimal-tour example to show (in blue) one case where a node is not connected to either of its two nearest neighbors in the tour and another where a mutual nearest-neighbor edge is not used in the optimal tour (the latter is a slight fib as-is but can be nudged, we believe): </p>
<p><a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/11/19/traveling-salesman-problem-meets-complexity-theory/tspwikimod/" rel="attachment wp-att-17815"><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-17815" height="287" src="https://rjlipton.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/tspwikimod-1.png?w=300&amp;h=287" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Modern Times–Practice </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The TSP is now well known to be NP-complete thanks to Dick Karp’s brilliant work in the 1970s. Flood would be happy to hear—we believe—that there is now a computer program <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concorde_TSP_Solver">Concorde</a> that can solve TSP with many cites and get a nearly optimal solution. The authors of this program are: David Applegate, Robert Bixby, Vasek Chvatal, and William Cook. </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Concorde has been applied to problems of gene mapping, protein function prediction, vehicle routing, conversion of bitmap images to continuous line drawings, scheduling ship movements for seismic surveys, and in studying the scaling properties of combinatorial optimization problems. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Modern Times–Theory </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
Concorde’s solutions are guaranteed to be within 2-3% of optimal and have worked for problems with tens of thousand cities or more. A lot more than Flood considered. </p>
<p>
So why are we interested in the TSP still? A good question. </p>
<p>
The answer is not simple. In spite of the problem’s NP-completeness and widespread belief that P<img alt="{&lt;}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%3C%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{&lt;}"/>NP we still do not know for sure. Could there be an algorithm that always solves TSP in polynomial time? We do not know. </p>
<p>
We also as complexity theorists want provable algorithms, want exact algorithms, or at least approximate algorithms with provable bounds. These are lacking. This is why we were excited by the <a href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/2020/10/26/a-vast-and-tiny-breakthrough/">recent</a> result of a tiny improvement to the <img alt="{1.5}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1.5%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{1.5}"/> bound on TSP by Anna Karlin, Nathan Klein, and Shayan Oveis Gharan. </p>
<p>
Maybe we are crazy to be excited over a microscopic shaving off from <img alt="{1.5}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1.5%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{1.5}"/>.  But their result comes with new ideas, and since we don’t believe that <img alt="{1.5 - \epsilon}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B1.5+-+%5Cepsilon%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{1.5 - \epsilon}"/> is Nature’s final answer, those ideas should yield further advances.  What we are really crazy over is new ideas, and that prompts us to attempt to find another in the rest of this post.  What complexity theorists do have more of than when Ken and I started is receptacles for new ideas, and we try for one in resource-bounded communication complexity.</p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Alice and Bob </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
In this spirit of craziness let’s take a complexity viewpoint of TSP. Let’s visit Alice and Bob. By the way I always have thought the invention of them by Ron Rivest, Adi Shamir, and Leonard Adleman in their 1978 RSA <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_and_Bob">paper</a> was important. This idea has probably helped improve exposition more than any other single idea. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> They Meet the TSP </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
So suppose that Alice and Bob are presented with a <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> city TSP. Further suppose that Alice can solve the TSP, but Bob like the rest of us cannot. An issue is: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Can Alice send a succinct message to Bob that allows him to find an optimal tour in polynomial time? </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Without the word “succinct” there would be the simple answer of sending Bob her optimal tour. We will discuss a modest improvement: she can send half as many bits to Bob as it takes to describe the optimal tour. We suspect the following is known, but it suggests a possible interesting direction.</p>
<blockquote><p><b>Theorem 1 (Main)</b> <em> Alice can send Bob a message of <img alt="{\frac{n}{2} \lceil \log_{2}n \rceil}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bn%7D%7B2%7D+%5Clceil+%5Clog_%7B2%7Dn+%5Crceil%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\frac{n}{2} \lceil \log_{2}n \rceil}"/> bits, so that he can get an optimal TSP tour in polynomial time. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p/><p>
This theorem holds for general TSP: it can be asymmetric and need not satisfy the triangle inequality. </p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> The Proof </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
<em>Proof:</em>  Let’s assume that <img alt="{n=2m}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%3D2m%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n=2m}"/>; the argument is the essentially same if <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> is odd. </p>
<p>
Alice will first solve the TSP exactly. Assume she finds an optimal tour that visits the cities in order 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{2}, \dots, x_{n}, x_{1}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x_%7B1%7D%2C+x_%7B2%7D%2C+%5Cdots%2C+x_%7Bn%7D%2C+x_%7B1%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{2}, \dots, x_{n}, x_{1}. "/></p>
<p>To simply the notation let <img alt="{d(i,j)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bd%28i%2Cj%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{d(i,j)}"/> be the distance from <img alt="{x_{i}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_%7Bi%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{x_{i}}"/> to <img alt="{x_{j}}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bx_%7Bj%7D%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{x_{j}}"/>. Then let Alice send Bob the odd cities in order 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{3}, \dots, x_{2m-1}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x_%7B1%7D%2C+x_%7B3%7D%2C+%5Cdots%2C+x_%7B2m-1%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{3}, \dots, x_{2m-1}. "/></p>
<p>This message has the right length in bits of <img alt="{\frac{n}{2} \lceil \log_{2}n \rceil}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cfrac%7Bn%7D%7B2%7D+%5Clceil+%5Clog_%7B2%7Dn+%5Crceil%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\frac{n}{2} \lceil \log_{2}n \rceil}"/>.</p>
<p>
Bob receives this message and creates the following bipartite graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/>: The left vertices are the cities 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x_{2}, x_{4}, \dots, x_{2m}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x_%7B2%7D%2C+x_%7B4%7D%2C+%5Cdots%2C+x_%7B2m%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x_{2}, x_{4}, \dots, x_{2m}. "/></p>
<p>The right vertices are 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{3}, \dots, x_{2m-1}. " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x_%7B1%7D%2C+x_%7B3%7D%2C+%5Cdots%2C+x_%7B2m-1%7D.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x_{1}, x_{3}, \dots, x_{2m-1}. "/></p>
<p>
<img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> has edges connecting every left vertex to every right vertex; i.e., <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> is the complete bipartite graph.</p>
<p>
The first idea is that any perfect matching in <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> extends uniquely to a tour, because Bob knows the order of the odd vertices in Alice’s tour.  That is, if <img alt="{(2k+1,2l)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%282k%2B1%2C2l%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{(2k+1,2l)}"/> is an edge in the tour, then Bob knows that the next edge goes to node <img alt="{2k+3}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2k%2B3%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{2k+3}"/> (modulo <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/>).</p>
<p>
The second idea—which is a caveat—is that an optimal matching under the graph’s original distance function might not produce Alice’s tour.  For this to be true, it would need to be the case that for every optimal tour, either one of the two perfect matchings it induces would need to be an optimal matching for the tour’s odd and even vertices.  An example where this fails is shown at lower left in our diagram above: The green edge is part of the optimal odd-even matching but is not in Alice’s optimal tour.</p>
<p>
The trick is to change the distance function to include the edge that Bob must add to the tour.  That is, we give the edge <img alt="{(2k+1,2l)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%282k%2B1%2C2l%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{(2k+1,2l)}"/> the cost 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  d(2k+1,2l) + d(2l,2k+3). " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++d%282k%2B1%2C2l%29+%2B+d%282l%2C2k%2B3%29.+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  d(2k+1,2l) + d(2l,2k+3). "/></p>
<p>Note<img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> has edges connecting every left vertex to every right vertex; i.e., <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> is the complete bipartite graph.</p>
<p>
Bob then finds a minimum cost matching for the graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/>. This can be done in polynomial time. We claim the following: </p>
<ol>
<li>
The matching 		<p/>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  x_{2k+2} \rightarrow x_{2k+1}, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++x_%7B2k%2B2%7D+%5Crightarrow+x_%7B2k%2B1%7D%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  x_{2k+2} \rightarrow x_{2k+1}, "/></p>
<p>has the cost of the original TSP tour. </p>
</li><li>
Every minimum complete matching of <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> yields a tour for the original TSP with the same cost as the matching.
</li></ol>
<p>These claims imply that Bob can solve the TSP in polynomial time.</p>
<p>
We note that (1) follows from the definition of the graph <img alt="{G}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7BG%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{G}"/> and its costs. In order to see (2) let <img alt="{2\pi(k)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2%5Cpi%28k%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{2\pi(k)}"/> match to <img alt="{2k+1}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B2k%2B1%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{2k+1}"/>. This means that there are edges 	</p>
<p align="center"><img alt="\displaystyle  2k+1 \rightarrow 2\pi(k) \rightarrow 2k+3, " class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cdisplaystyle++2k%2B1+%5Crightarrow+2%5Cpi%28k%29+%5Crightarrow+2k%2B3%2C+&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\displaystyle  2k+1 \rightarrow 2\pi(k) \rightarrow 2k+3, "/></p>
<p>for all <img alt="{k}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bk%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{k}"/>. This is clearly a tour, since <img alt="{\pi(k)}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7B%5Cpi%28k%29%7D&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{\pi(k)}"/> is a permutation by the definition of matching. 	 <img alt="\Box" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5CBox&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\Box"/></p>
<p>
</p><p/><h2> Open Problems </h2><p/>
<p/><p>
The fact that Alice can send only half of the tour to Bob suggests: can we avoid having Alice solve the TSP in order to compute her message? This is the direction we are interested in. If she could do that it would improve some known complexity bounds on TSP. A possible idea is: </p>
<blockquote><p><b> </b> <em> Replace having Alice solve the <img alt="{n}" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%7Bn%7D&amp;bg=e8e8e8&amp;fg=000000&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="{n}"/> city TSP exactly. Instead have her solve some randomly selected subproblem exactly, and then use the above method to add in the remaining cities. </em>
</p></blockquote>
<p>Can this work?</p>
<p>
We have not found something like this when searching on TSP and communication complexity, but would not be surprised if the matching idea, caveat, and trick have been noticed and remarked on before.</p></font></font></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-19T05:08:54Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-19T05:08:54Z</published>
    <category term="History"/>
    <category term="Ideas"/>
    <category term="Oldies"/>
    <category term="Open Problems"/>
    <category term="People"/>
    <category term="Proofs"/>
    <category term="Results"/>
    <category term="Alice and Bob"/>
    <category term="communication complexity"/>
    <category term="complexity"/>
    <category term="complexity theory"/>
    <category term="Merrill Flood"/>
    <category term="TSP"/>
    <author>
      <name>rjlipton</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://rjlipton.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://rjlipton.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>a personal view of the theory of computation</subtitle>
      <title>Gödel’s Lost Letter and P=NP</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:40Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-US">
    <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5101</id>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5101" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5101#comments" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom&amp;p=5101" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <title xml:lang="en-US">Annual post: Come join UT Austin’s Quantum Information Center!</title>
    <summary xml:lang="en-US">Hook ’em Hadamards! If you’re a prospective PhD student: Apply here for the CS department (the deadline this year is December 15th), here for the physics department (the deadline is December 1st), or here for the ECE department (the deadline is 15th). GREs are not required this year because of covid. If you apply to […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml" xml:lang="en-US"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~qic/">Hook ’em Hadamards!</a></p>



<p><strong>If you’re a prospective PhD student:</strong> Apply <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/graduate/prospective-students/apply">here</a> for the CS department (the deadline this year is December 15th), <a href="https://ph.utexas.edu/prospective-graduate-students/admissions">here</a> for the physics department (the deadline is December 1st), or <a href="https://www.ece.utexas.edu/academics/graduate/admissions">here</a> for the ECE department (the deadline is 15th).  GREs are not required this year because of covid.  If you apply to CS and specify that you want to work with me, I’ll be sure to see your application.  If you apply to physics or ECE, I <em>won’t</em> see your application, but once you arrive, I can sometimes supervise or co-supervise PhD students in other departments (or, of course, serve on their committees).  In any case, everyone in the UT community is extremely welcome at our quantum information group meetings (which are now on Zoom, naturally, but depending on vaccine distribution, hopefully won’t be by the time you arrive!).  Emailing me won’t make a difference.  Admissions are very competitive, so apply broadly to maximize your chances.</p>



<p><strong>If you’re a prospective postdoctoral fellow:</strong> By January 1, 2021, please email me a cover letter, your CV, and two or three of your best papers (links or attachments).  Please also ask two recommenders to email me their letters by January 1.  While my own work tends toward computational complexity, I’m open to all parts of theoretical quantum computing and information.</p>



<p><strong>If you’re a prospective faculty member:</strong> Yes, faculty searches are still happening despite covid!  Go <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/faculty/recruiting">here</a> to apply for an opening in the CS department (which, in quantum computing, currently includes me and <a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4512">MIP*=RE</a> superstar <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~wright/">John Wright</a>), or <a href="https://faculty.utexas.edu/career/66111">here</a> to apply to the physics department (which, in quantum computing, currently includes <a href="https://cns.utexas.edu/directory/item/18-physics/2826-potter-andrew?Itemid=349">Drew Potter</a>, along with a world-class condensed matter group).</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-19T01:50:07Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-19T01:50:07Z</published>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Announcements"/>
    <category scheme="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" term="Quantum"/>
    <author>
      <name>Scott</name>
      <uri>http://www.scottaaronson.com</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog</id>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?feed=atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle xml:lang="en-US">The Blog of Scott Aaronson</subtitle>
      <title xml:lang="en-US">Shtetl-Optimized</title>
      <updated>2020-11-23T19:57:37Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/postdoc-at-princeton-university-apply-by-december-10-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/postdoc-at-princeton-university-apply-by-december-10-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at Princeton University (apply by December 10, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Positions are for one year anticipated to start in September 2021 with the possibility of renewal contingent upon satisfactory performance and continued funding. Candidates must have a PhD in Computer Science or a related field. For full consideration, we recommend that candidates apply by December 10, 2020 11:59pm, EST, though we will continue to review […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Positions are for one year anticipated to start in September 2021 with the possibility of renewal contingent upon satisfactory performance and continued funding. Candidates must have a PhD in Computer Science or a related field.</p>
<p>For full consideration, we recommend that candidates apply by December 10, 2020 11:59pm, EST, though we will continue to review applications past that date.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://puwebp.princeton.edu/AcadHire/apply/application.xhtml?listingId=18501">https://puwebp.princeton.edu/AcadHire/apply/application.xhtml?listingId=18501</a><br/>
Email: smweinberg@princeton.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-18T23:20:35Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-18T23:20:35Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/174</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/174" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-174 |  Isoperimetric Inequalities for Real-Valued Functions with Applications to Monotonicity Testing | 

	Hadley Black, 

	Iden Kalemaj, 

	Sofya Raskhodnikova</title>
    <summary>We generalize the celebrated isoperimetric inequality of Khot, Minzer, and Safra (SICOMP 2018) for Boolean functions to the case of real-valued functions $f \colon \{0,1\}^d\to\mathbb{R}$. Our main tool in the proof of the generalized inequality is a new Boolean decomposition that represents every real-valued function $f$ over an arbitrary partially ordered domain as a collection of Boolean functions over the same domain, roughly capturing the distance of $f$ to monotonicity and the structure of violations of $f$ to monotonicity.

We apply our generalized isoperimetric inequality to improve algorithms for testing monotonicity and approximating the distance to monotonicity for real-valued functions. Our tester for monotonicity has query complexity $\widetilde{O}(\min(r \sqrt{d},d))$, where $r$ is the size of the image of the input function. (The best previously known tester, by Chakrabarty and Seshadhri (STOC 2013), makes $O(d)$ queries.) Our tester is nonadaptive and has 1-sided error. We show a matching lower bound for nonadaptive, 1-sided error testers for monotonicity. We also show that the distance to monotonicity of real-valued functions that are $\alpha$-far from monotone can be approximated nonadaptively within a factor of $O(\sqrt{d\log d})$ with query complexity polynomial in  $1/\alpha$ and the dimension $d$. This query complexity is known to be nearly optimal for nonadaptive algorithms even for the special case of Boolean functions. (The best previously known distance approximation algorithm for real-valued functions, by Fattal and Ron (TALG 2010) achieves $O(d\log r)$-approximation.)</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T19:33:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-18T19:33:00Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/faculty-at-idaho-state-university-apply-by-december-15-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/faculty-at-idaho-state-university-apply-by-december-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty at Idaho State University  (apply by December 15, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Be part of a great team! Idaho State University’s College of Science and Engineering is seeking an Assistant Professor of Computer Science for our Idaho Falls campus. For complete job description, requirements, and application instructions visit jobs.isu.edu. For priority consideration, apply by November 22, 2020. Website: https://isu.csod.com/ats/careersite/JobDetails.aspx?id=1124&amp;site=1 Email: burkstep@isu.edul</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Be part of a great team! Idaho State University’s College of Science and Engineering is seeking an Assistant Professor of Computer Science for our Idaho Falls campus. For complete job description, requirements, and application instructions visit jobs.isu.edu. For priority consideration, apply by November 22, 2020.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://isu.csod.com/ats/careersite/JobDetails.aspx?id=1124&amp;site=1">https://isu.csod.com/ats/careersite/JobDetails.aspx?id=1124&amp;site=1</a><br/>
Email: burkstep@isu.edul</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-18T17:24:32Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-18T17:24:32Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en-us">
    <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/173</id>
    <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/report/2020/173" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>TR20-173 |  Block Rigidity: Strong Multiplayer Parallel Repetition implies Super-Linear Lower Bounds for Turing Machines | 

	Kunal Mittal, 

	Ran Raz</title>
    <summary>We prove that a sufficiently strong parallel repetition theorem for a special case of multiplayer (multiprover) games implies super-linear lower bounds for multi-tape Turing machines with advice. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first connection between parallel repetition and lower bounds for time complexity and the first major potential implication of a parallel repetition theorem with more than two players.

Along the way to proving this result, we define and initiate a study of block rigidity, extending Valiant's notion of rigidity [Val77]. While rigidity was originally defined for matrices, or, equivalently, for (multi-output) linear functions, we extend and study both rigidity and block rigidity for general (multi-output) functions. Using techniques of Paul, Pippenger, Szemer{\'{e}}di and Trotter [PPST83], we show that a block-rigid function cannot be computed by multi-tape Turing machines that run in linear (or slightly super-linear) time, even in the non-uniform setting, where the machine gets an arbitrary advice tape.

We then describe a class of multiplayer games, such that, a sufficiently strong parallel repetition theorem for that class of games implies an explicit block-rigid function. The games in that class have the following property that may be of independent interest: for every random string for the verifier (which, in particular, determines the vector of queries to the players), there is a unique correct answer for each of the players, and the verifier accepts if and only if all answers are correct. We refer to such games as independent games. The theorem that we need is that parallel repetition reduces the value of games in this class from $v$ to $v^{\Omega(n)}$, where $n$ is the number of repetitions.

As another application of block rigidity, we show conditional size-depth tradeoffs for boolean circuits, where the gates compute arbitrary functions over large sets.</summary>
    <updated>2020-11-18T05:19:58Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-18T05:19:58Z</published>
    <source>
      <id>https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/</id>
      <author>
        <name>ECCC papers</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://example.com/feeds/reports/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Latest Reports published at https://eccc.weizmann.ac.il</subtitle>
      <title>ECCC - Reports</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:32Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/faculty-positions-in-quantum-computing-and-theoretical-computer-science-at-stony-brook-university-apply-by-january-5-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/18/faculty-positions-in-quantum-computing-and-theoretical-computer-science-at-stony-brook-university-apply-by-january-5-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty Positions in Quantum Computing and Theoretical Computer Science at Stony Brook University (apply by January 5, 2021)</title>
    <summary>Stony Brook University’s Department of Computer Science invites applicants for *two* tenure-track/tenured faculty positions in theoretical computer science starting Fall 2021. Areas of interest are 1) quantum computing/information science; (2) algorithms and complexity theory; and 3) theory of machine learning. Website: https://apptrkr.com/2039466 Email: skiena@cs.stonybrook.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Stony Brook University’s Department of Computer Science invites applicants for *two* tenure-track/tenured faculty positions in theoretical computer science starting Fall 2021. Areas of interest are 1) quantum computing/information science; (2) algorithms and complexity theory; and 3) theory of machine learning.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://apptrkr.com/2039466">https://apptrkr.com/2039466</a><br/>
Email: skiena@cs.stonybrook.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-18T01:23:26Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-18T01:23:26Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://windowsontheory.org/?p=7895</id>
    <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/11/17/election-insecurity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Election insecurity</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Election security has been studied for many years by computer scientists, but it is not as often that it attracts so much mainstream attention. I would never have expected to see my former Princeton colleague Andrew Appel on a Sean Hannity segment tweeted by President Trump. It may seem that even if it has partisan … <a class="more-link" href="https://windowsontheory.org/2020/11/17/election-insecurity/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Election insecurity</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Election security has been studied for many years by <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/rsa-cryptographer-ronald-rivest-seeks-secure-elections-20200312/">computer scientists</a>, but it is not as often that it attracts so much mainstream attention. I would never have expected to see my former Princeton colleague <a href="https://www.cs.princeton.edu/~appel/">Andrew Appel</a> on a Sean Hannity segment tweeted by President Trump.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/image.png"><img alt="" class="wp-image-7899" src="https://windowsontheory.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/image.png?w=1024"/></a></figure>



<p/>



<p>It may seem that even if it has partisan motivations, the recent GOP interest in election security is overall a positive thing. Who wouldn’t want elections to be more secure? Who wouldn’t want less fraud? However, in a very precise sense, the definition of “election security” used by the GOP these days corresponds to <strong>election insecurity</strong>.</p>



<p>To understand this claim, consider what it means for an election to be secure. (Let’s focus just on the correctness aspect of the count, since it is at the heart of the current issues, and not on the very interesting privacy aspect.) Computer scientists use <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1605.08554">the technical terms</a> “<strong>cast as intended</strong>“, “<strong>recorded as cast</strong>“, and “<strong>tallied as recorded</strong>“. In other words: if a voter X intends to cast vote for candidate Y,  then this vote should be recorded and tallied, and only such votes should be tallied.</p>



<p>With mail-in voting, there are several potential points of failure on the path between voter intent and the final tally:</p>



<ol><li>Mail can be lost or delayed too much, leading to the vote not counting.</li><li>A third party could intercept the ballot and impersonate the voter.</li><li>A ballot may not be formatted properly in some way, leading to it being disqualified.</li><li>There can be errors or hacks in the tallying process.</li></ol>



<p>Election security is about combatting points 1-4 (of which the last 3 are also applicable to in-person voting) , ideally in a way that is <em>verifiable</em> to the individual voters. Achieving verifiability while maintaining secrecy and not requiring the voter to trust complex technology is a challenging task, but there have been some proposed solutions (see above links).<br/><br/>The Hannity segment and much of the “Dominion” non story focused on point 4. This is an important point, but as <a href="https://freedom-to-tinker.com/2020/11/13/did-sean-hannity-misquote-me/">Appel himself notes</a>, paper ballots, which are mostly used in the US, serve as a way to audit counting. Re-counting is important, and is commonly done, but such recounts often change the total counts by relatively little (and the changes mostly cancel out). For example, here is the list of ballots changed and reasons from the Wisconsin 2016 count (taken from <a href="https://t.co/AUagggIp6j?amp=1">this paper</a>)</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img alt="Image" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/Emk1EJaU4AAtAJm?format=jpg&amp;name=4096x4096"/></figure>



<p>In contrast, many of the legal cases by the Trump campaign focused on signature verification and other ballot irregularities. There are two main reasons why a signature would not match between a ballot and driver’s license or other records:</p>



<ol><li>The signature may have been forged by someone trying to impersonate the voter.<br/></li><li>The voter’s signature might not very consistent, or maybe they have more than one signature (for example, I sometimes sign in Hebrew and sometimes in English) .</li></ol>



<p>Empirically, reason 2 is much more common than reason 1. If a ballot is tossed out because of the second reason it corresponds to a <strong>break between the voter intent and the final tally</strong>, and hence it is a case of <em>election insecurity</em>. For this reason, making more stringent signature checks could make elections less secure!</p>



<p>While President Trump might claim on Twitter that the election was stolen by a massive conspiracy involving forging of tens of thousands of ballots, this is not the actual content of the court cases (especially after some <a href="https://lawandcrime.com/2020-election/lawyers-pan-significant-shrinkage-of-trump-campaigns-pennsylvania-lawsuit-only-addresses-a-handful-of-ballots/">recent</a> <a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/484456818/Redline-Trump-Complaint">amendments</a>). For example, at the heart of the PA case is the process of “<a href="https://www.factcheck.org/2020/11/ballot-curing-in-pennsylvania/">curing a ballot</a>“. This is when a ballot is disqualified due to some technical issue, and a voter has a chance to fix it. Curing a ballot ensures that the voters intent is captured, and hence makes elections more secure. </p>



<p>In PA, the decision of whether to notify voters in such cases was left to the counties, and apparently Democrat-controlled counties were more likely to do so Republican-controlled counties. This is a shame, and had the Trump campaign asked to extend the deadline for curing  ballots, then I would think it makes perfect sense. However, this is not what their lawsuit is about. To quote their complaint: <em>“plaintiffs seek a permanent injunction requiring the County Election Boards to invalidate ballots cast by voters who were notified and given an opportunity to cure their invalidly cast mail-in ballot.”</em> This are ballots where there is no question of the eligibility of the voter, nor of the accuracy of their intent, yet the Trump campaign seeks to prevent them from counting. I call this election insecurity.</p>



<p/>



<p>p.s. See <a href="https://twitter.com/KlasfeldReports">Adam Klasfeld’s feed</a> for more about the various Trump campaign cases</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-twitter wp-block-embed-twitter"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-twitter"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p dir="ltr" lang="en">The DNC's lawyer Uzoma Nkwonta, from Perkins Coie, is up. <br/><br/>He reiterates a point made earlier by the counties that Trump's co-plaintiffs sued the wrong counties.<br/><br/>They're from Trump-backing Fayette and Lancaster Counties. <br/><br/>They sued seven blue counties, alleging vote denial.</p>— Adam Klasfeld (@KlasfeldReports) <a href="https://twitter.com/KlasfeldReports/status/1328823948319076355?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 17, 2020</a></blockquote></div>
</div></figure></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T22:31:11Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T22:31:11Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Boaz Barak</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://windowsontheory.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://windowsontheory.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>A Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Windows On Theory</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/tenure-track-assistant-professor-position-at-university-of-british-columbia-apply-by-december-20-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/tenure-track-assistant-professor-position-at-university-of-british-columbia-apply-by-december-20-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Tenure-track assistant professor position at University of British Columbia (apply by December 20, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Department of Computer Science at the University of British Columbia (Vancouver campus) is inviting applications for one position at the rank of Assistant Professor. We invite applications from candidates of outstanding scientific talent in all areas of computer science. Website: https://www.cs.ubc.ca/our-department/employment/tenure-track-assistant-professor-department-computer-science-ubc-research Email: research-recruiting-chair@cs.ubc.ca</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Department of Computer Science at the University of British Columbia (Vancouver campus) is inviting applications for one position at the rank of Assistant Professor. We invite applications from candidates of outstanding scientific talent in all areas of computer science.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.cs.ubc.ca/our-department/employment/tenure-track-assistant-professor-department-computer-science-ubc-research">https://www.cs.ubc.ca/our-department/employment/tenure-track-assistant-professor-department-computer-science-ubc-research</a><br/>
Email: research-recruiting-chair@cs.ubc.ca</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T19:33:56Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T19:33:56Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/3-tenure-track-professors-w2-at-saarland-university-saarbrucken-germany-apply-by-december-11-2020-2/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/3-tenure-track-professors-w2-at-saarland-university-saarbrucken-germany-apply-by-december-11-2020-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>3 Tenure Track Professors (W2) at Saarland University, Saarbrücken, Germany (apply by December 11, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Saarland University is seeking to hire up to 3 Tenure Track Professors (W2) in computer science and related areas with six-year tenure track to a permanent professorship (W3). Areas of interest include: * Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning * Data Science, Big Data * Computational Logic and Verification * Theory and Algorithms * Quantum Computing Website: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Saarland University is seeking to hire up to 3 Tenure Track Professors (W2)<br/>
in computer science and related areas with six-year tenure track to a permanent professorship (W3). Areas of interest include:</p>
<p>* Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning<br/>
* Data Science, Big Data<br/>
* Computational Logic and Verification<br/>
* Theory and Algorithms<br/>
* Quantum Computing</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.uni-saarland.de/fileadmin/user_upload/verwaltung/stellen/wissenschaftler/W1786_W2TT-Informatik_Ausschreibung_final.pdf">https://www.uni-saarland.de/fileadmin/user_upload/verwaltung/stellen/wissenschaftler/W1786_W2TT-Informatik_Ausschreibung_final.pdf</a><br/>
Email: apply@saarland-informatics-campus.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T16:19:45Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T16:19:45Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/3-tenure-track-professors-w2-at-saarland-university-saarbrucken-germany-apply-by-december-11-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/3-tenure-track-professors-w2-at-saarland-university-saarbrucken-germany-apply-by-december-11-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>3 Tenure Track Professors (W2) at Saarland University, Saarbrücken, Germany (apply by December 11, 2020)</title>
    <summary>Saarland University is seeking to hire up to 3 Tenure Track Professors (W2) in computer science and related areas with six-year tenure track to a permanent professorship (W3). Areas of interest include: * Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning * Data Science, Big Data * Computational Logic and Verification * Theory and Algorithms * Quantum Computing Website: […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Saarland University is seeking to hire up to 3 Tenure Track Professors (W2)<br/>
in computer science and related areas with six-year tenure track to a permanent professorship (W3). Areas of interest include:</p>
<p>* Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning<br/>
* Data Science, Big Data<br/>
* Computational Logic and Verification<br/>
* Theory and Algorithms<br/>
* Quantum Computing</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://www.uni-saarland.de/fileadmin/user_upload/verwaltung/stellen/wissenschaftler/W1786_W2TT-Informatik_Ausschreibung_final.pdf">https://www.uni-saarland.de/fileadmin/user_upload/verwaltung/stellen/wissenschaftler/W1786_W2TT-Informatik_Ausschreibung_final.pdf</a><br/>
Email: apply@saarland-informatics-campus.de</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T16:19:39Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T16:19:39Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661.post-2955644832205049973</id>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/2955644832205049973/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/comment.g?blogID=27705661&amp;postID=2955644832205049973" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/2955644832205049973" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default/2955644832205049973" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/2020/11/faculty-positions-at-department-of.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Faculty positions at the Department of Computer Science, Reykjavik University</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The <a href="https://en.ru.is/st/dcs/">Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University</a> is hiring and invites applications for faculty positions at any rank. </p><p>We are looking for energetic, highly qualified academics with a proven international research record.  We particularly welcome applications from researchers who have a strong network of research collaborators, can strengthen internal collaborations within the department, and generally have potential to flourish in our setting. </p><p>We have just posted three separate calls for applications. <br/></p><ul style="text-align: left;"><li>If you are interested in applying for one of the faculty positions in the fields of Data Science, Machine Learning, Software Engineering, and Computer Security, please follow <a href="https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/is/5933" target="_blank">this link</a> for more information on the positions and on how to apply. </li><li>If you are interested in applying for the faculty position in Game Design and Development, see <a href="https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/is/5938" target="_blank">here</a> for more information on the position and on how to apply. <br/></li><li>We also have a call for faculty positions in any area of Computer Science. You can find further information on those positions <a href="https://jobs.50skills.com/ru/is/5937" target="_blank">here</a>. </li></ul><p><b>Addendum dated 19 November 2020: </b>Scientists coming to Iceland from abroad for work can apply for a tax relief for the first <i>three</i> years of their employment. If the application is successful, 25% of their salary is tax free. </p><p><b>Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University </b><br/></p><p>The Department of Computer Science at Reykjavik University has about 650 full-time-equivalent students and 22 faculty members. It provides an excellent working environment that encourages and supports independence in academic endeavors, and in which a motivated academic can have impact at all levels. The department offers undergraduate and graduate programs in computer science and software engineering, as well as a combined undergraduate program in discrete mathematics and computer science.  The department is home to several research centers producing high-quality collaborative research in areas such as artificial intelligence, financial technology, language technology, software systems, and theoretical computer science, among others; for more information on those research centers, see <a href="https://en.ru.is/research/units/">https://en.ru.is/research/units/</a>.</p><p> <b>Reykjavík University </b></p><p>On the Times Higher Education rankings for 2021, Reykjavík University is ranked in first place along with eight other universities for the average number of citations per faculty. Overall, RU is ranked among the 350 best universities world-wide, 59th of all universities established fewer than 50 years ago, and first among Icelandic universities.  Reykjavík University has around 3.700 students and 250 faculty and employees in addition to numerous adjunct faculty in two schools: Technology and Social Sciences. We offer a welcoming and stimulating environment in which to work and live. The University is centrally located in Reykjavík, the capital city of Iceland.  The role of Reykjavik University is to create and disseminate knowledge to enhance the competitiveness and quality of life for individuals and society, guided by good ethics, sustainability and responsibility. Education and research at RU are based on strong ties with industry and society. We emphasize interdisciplinary collaboration, international relations and entrepreneurship. </p><p><b>Iceland</b> </p><p>Iceland is well known for breathtaking natural beauty, with volcanoes, hot springs, lava fields and glaciers offering a dramatic landscape. It consistently ranks as one of the best places in the world to live. It offers a high quality of life, is one of the safest places in the world, has high gender equality, and strong health-care and social-support systems. It is in fourth position in the 2020 UN World Happiness Report, which correlates with various life factors.  </p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T15:15:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T15:15:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>Luca Aceto</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-27705661</id>
      <author>
        <name>Luca Aceto</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/01092671728833265127</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="http://processalgebra.blogspot.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/27705661/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Papers I find interesting---mostly, but not solely, in Process Algebra---, and some fun stuff in Mathematics and Computer Science at large and on general issues related to research, teaching and academic life.</subtitle>
      <title>Process Algebra Diary</title>
      <updated>2020-11-19T10:22:26Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/postdoc-at-hdsi-simons-institute-at-halicioglu-data-science-institute-ucsd-apply-by-february-15-2021/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/postdoc-at-hdsi-simons-institute-at-halicioglu-data-science-institute-ucsd-apply-by-february-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at HDSI/Simons Institute at Halıcıoğlu Data Science Institute, UCSD (apply by February 15, 2021)</title>
    <summary>The Halıcıoğlu Data Science Institute (HDSI) and the UC Berkeley Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing have created a joint two-year postdoctoral fellowship opening aimed at preparing outstanding researchers for academic and leadership careers in the theoretical aspects of Data Science. Website: https://datascience.ucsd.edu/jobs/hdsi-post-doctoral/ Email: esnee@ucsd.edu</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Halıcıoğlu Data Science Institute (HDSI) and the UC Berkeley Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing have created a joint two-year postdoctoral fellowship opening aimed at preparing outstanding researchers for academic and leadership careers in the theoretical aspects of Data Science.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://datascience.ucsd.edu/jobs/hdsi-post-doctoral/">https://datascience.ucsd.edu/jobs/hdsi-post-doctoral/</a><br/>
Email: esnee@ucsd.edu</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T04:55:39Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T04:55:39Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/postdoc-at-university-of-waterloo-apply-by-december-31-2020/</id>
    <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/2020/11/17/postdoc-at-university-of-waterloo-apply-by-december-31-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Postdoc at University of Waterloo (apply by December 31, 2020)</title>
    <summary>The Algorithms &amp; Complexity group at the University of Waterloo is offering postdoctoral positions starting in the Fall of 2021. We seek candidates from all areas of theoretical computer science. Interested applicants should have their CV, research statement, and three recommendation letters emailed to theory.waterloo@gmail.com. Applications are due December 31st. Website: https://algcomp.uwaterloo.ca/positions/ Email: theory.waterloo@gmail.com</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The Algorithms &amp; Complexity group at the University of Waterloo is offering postdoctoral positions starting in the Fall of 2021. We seek candidates from all areas of theoretical computer science.<br/>
Interested applicants should have their CV, research statement, and three recommendation letters emailed to theory.waterloo@gmail.com. Applications are due December 31st.</p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://algcomp.uwaterloo.ca/positions/">https://algcomp.uwaterloo.ca/positions/</a><br/>
Email: theory.waterloo@gmail.com</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-17T02:38:26Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-17T02:38:26Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>shacharlovett</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://cstheory-jobs.org</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://cstheory-jobs.org/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <title>Theoretical Computer Science Jobs</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:43Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?p=20411</id>
    <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/17/to-cheer-you-up-14-hong-liu-and-richard-montgomery-solved-the-erdos-and-hajnals-odd-cycle-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>To cheer you up 14: Hong Liu and Richard Montgomery solved the Erdős and Hajnal’s odd cycle problem</title>
    <summary type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The news: In 1981, Paul Erdős and András Hajnal asked whether the sum of the reciprocals of the odd cycle lengths in a graph with infinite chromatic number is necessarily infinite. Hong Liu and Richard Montgomery have just proved that … <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2020/11/17/to-cheer-you-up-14-hong-liu-and-richard-montgomery-solved-the-erdos-and-hajnals-odd-cycle-problem/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">→</span></a></div>
    </summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/solvers.png"><img alt="" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-20426" height="359" src="https://gilkalai.files.wordpress.com/2020/11/solvers.png?w=640&amp;h=359" width="640"/></a></p>
<p>The news: In 1981, Paul Erdős and András Hajnal asked whether the sum of the reciprocals of the odd cycle lengths in a graph with infinite chromatic number is necessarily infinite. Hong Liu and Richard Montgomery <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.15802">have just proved</a> that the answer is positive!  They also proved a variety of other old standing conjectures. This is remarkable. Congratulations!</p>
<p><span style="color: #0000ff;">Before going on let me pose an even stronger conjecture</span></p>
<p><strong>Conjecture:</strong> The sum of the reciprocals of the odd<strong> induced</strong> cycle lengths in a <em>triangle-free</em> graph with no triangles and infinite chromatic number is necessarily infinite.</p>
<p>The same conclusion should apply to graphs with bounded clique numbers; it is related to the general area of <img alt="\chi" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cchi&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\chi"/>-boundedness, see <a href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/2014/12/19/when-a-few-colors-suffice/">this post</a> and this <a href="https://web.math.princeton.edu/~pds/papers/chibounded/paper.pdf">recent survey</a> by Alex Scott and Paul Seymour.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Returning to Liu and Montgomery’s breakthrough</span>, let me mention two other conjectures that Hong and Richard proved in the same paper:</p>
<p>A) (Conjecture by Erdős from 1984) There is a constant <em>d</em> such that any graph with average degree <em>d</em> has a cycle whose length is a power of 2.</p>
<p>B) (Conjecture by Carsten Thomassen from 1984) for every <em><span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-11-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-84"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-85"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-86">k</span></span></span></span></em>, there is some <em><span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-12-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-87"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-88"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-89">d</span></span></span></span></em> so that every graph with average degree at least <em><span class="MathJax" id="MathJax-Element-13-Frame"><span class="math" id="MathJax-Span-90"><span class="mrow" id="MathJax-Span-91"><span class="mi" id="MathJax-Span-92">d</span></span></span></span></em> has a subdivision of the complete graph <img alt="K_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=K_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="K_k"/> in which each edge is subdivided the same number of times.</p>
<p>I am thankful to Benny Sudakov for telling me about the new result.</p>
<p>A key ingredient of the proof is the study of expanders that you can always find in graphs. Komlós and Szemerédi showed in 1996 that every graph <em>G</em> contains an expander with comparable average degree to <em>G </em>and since their work, with greater and greater sophistication, finding expanders in general graphs has become an important tool for a large number of extremal problems.</p>
<h2 class="title mathjax">Hong Liu, Richard Montgomery: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.15802">A solution to Erdős and Hajnal’s odd cycle problem</a> (click for the arXive.)</h2>
<p><strong>Abstract:</strong></p>
<p>In 1981, Erdős and Hajnal asked whether the sum of the reciprocals of the odd cycle lengths in a graph with infinite chromatic number is necessarily infinite. Let <img alt="\mathcal{C}(G)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathcal%7BC%7D%28G%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathcal{C}(G)"/> be the set of cycle lengths in a graph <img alt="G" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G"/> and let <img alt="\mathcal{C}_\text{odd}(G)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathcal%7BC%7D_%5Ctext%7Bodd%7D%28G%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathcal{C}_\text{odd}(G)"/> be the set of odd numbers in <img alt="\mathcal{C}(G)" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Cmathcal%7BC%7D%28G%29&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\mathcal{C}(G)"/>. We prove that, if <img alt="G" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=G&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="G"/> has chromatic number <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/>, then <img alt="\sum_{\ell\in  \mathcal{C}_\text{odd}(G)}1/\ell\geq (1/2-o_k(1))\log k." class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=%5Csum_%7B%5Cell%5Cin++%5Cmathcal%7BC%7D_%5Ctext%7Bodd%7D%28G%29%7D1%2F%5Cell%5Cgeq+%281%2F2-o_k%281%29%29%5Clog+k.&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="\sum_{\ell\in  \mathcal{C}_\text{odd}(G)}1/\ell\geq (1/2-o_k(1))\log k."/> This solves Erdős and Hajnal’s odd cycle problem, and, furthermore, this bound is asymptotically optimal.<br/>
In 1984, Erdős asked whether there is some d such that each graph with chromatic number at least d (or perhaps even only average degree at least <img alt="d" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="d"/>) has a cycle whose length is a power of 2. We show that an average degree condition is sufficient for this problem, solving it with methods that apply to a wide range of sequences in addition to the powers of 2.<br/>
Finally, we use our methods to show that, for every <img alt="k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="k"/>, there is some <img alt="d" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=d&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="d"/> so that every graph with average degree at least d has a subdivision of the complete graph <img alt="K_k" class="latex" src="https://s0.wp.com/latex.php?latex=K_k&amp;bg=ffffff&amp;fg=333333&amp;s=0&amp;c=20201002" title="K_k"/> in which each edge is subdivided the same number of times. This confirms a conjecture of Thomassen from 1984.</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-16T22:56:06Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-16T22:56:06Z</published>
    <category term="Combinatorics"/>
    <category term="Andr&#xE1;s Hajnal"/>
    <category term="Carsten Thomassen"/>
    <category term="Hong Liu"/>
    <category term="Paul Erdos"/>
    <category term="Richard Montgomry"/>
    <author>
      <name>Gil Kalai</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://gilkalai.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://gilkalai.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Gil Kalai's blog</subtitle>
      <title>Combinatorics and more</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:37:35Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://theorydish.blog/?p=1802</id>
    <link href="https://theorydish.blog/2020/11/16/hiring-postdocs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Hiring Postdocs</title>
    <summary>I am looking to hire postdocs in the coming years on topics of algorithmic fairness with relation to a Simons Collaboration and on the meaning of individual probabilities with relation to a Sloan Foundation project. Please contact me (reingold@stanford.edu) for details and please forward to any relevant individual. Some comments: The Simons Collaboration will offer additional postdoc opportunities across the participating institutions. To be advertised soon. The perspective taken in both these projects is of TOC but the research will gain from collaborations with other fields within and outside of CS (Statistics, Economics, Philosophy, Law, Social Sciences at large). I will therefore be open to postdocs with various backgrounds (and would consider co-hosting with colleagues in other fields). Candidates from under-represented populations are encouraged to apply and I promise to give those applications my close attention.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>I am looking to hire postdocs in the coming years on topics of algorithmic fairness with relation to a <a href="https://www.simonsfoundation.org/2020/06/18/foundation-announces-simons-collaboration-on-the-theory-of-algorithmic-fairness/">Simons Collaboration</a> and on the meaning of individual probabilities with relation to a <a href="https://sloan.org/">Sloan Foundation</a> project. Please contact me (reingold@stanford.edu) for details and please forward to any relevant individual. Some comments:</p>



<ol type="1"><li>The Simons Collaboration will offer additional postdoc opportunities across the participating institutions. To be advertised soon.</li></ol>



<ul><li>The perspective taken in both these projects is of TOC but the research will gain from collaborations with other fields within and outside of CS (Statistics, Economics, Philosophy, Law, Social Sciences at large). I will therefore be open to postdocs with various backgrounds (and would consider co-hosting with colleagues in other fields).</li></ul>



<ul><li>Candidates from under-represented populations are encouraged to apply and I promise to give those applications my close attention.</li></ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-16T17:39:07Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-16T17:39:07Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <author>
      <name>Omer Reingold</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://theorydish.blog</id>
      <logo>https://theorydish.files.wordpress.com/2017/03/cropped-nightdish1.jpg?w=32</logo>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://theorydish.blog/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Stanford's CS Theory Research Blog</subtitle>
      <title>Theory Dish</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:38:17Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/15/linkage</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/15/linkage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Linkage</title>
    <summary>The early history of continued fractions (\(\mathbb{M}\)). Includes the equivalences of infinitude with irrationality and periodicity with quadraticness, and the work of Euler and Gauss on continued fractions for values with nice series expansions.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://golem.ph.utexas.edu/category/2020/09/five_levels_of_continued_fract.html">The early history of continued fractions</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105139147272940535">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Includes the equivalences of infinitude with irrationality and periodicity with quadraticness, and the work of Euler and Gauss on continued fractions for values with nice series expansions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>According to <a href="http://cams.ehess.fr/">EHESS</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Rosenstiehl">Pierre Rosenstiehl</a> has died (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105147747900598849">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). I don’t think I met or interacted with Rosenstiehl, but I definitely interacted with his works: he was one of the founders of the International Symposium on Graph Drawing and co-editor in chief of the European Journal of Combinatorics, with important publications in topological and algorithmic graph theory on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bipolar_orientation">bipolar orientations</a> and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Left-right_planarity_test">left-right planarity test</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.aerialphotoawards.com/aerial-photos-of-the-year-2020-man-made-category">Aerial photos of the year, 2020</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105155256595043126">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://www.metafilter.com/189287/A-Different-Perspective">via</a>). The link shows only the “man-made” category; be sure to click on all the others as well.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.slac.stanford.edu/~kaehler/homepage/visualizations/dark-matter.html">Simulation and visualization of the large-scale structure of the universe</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105161855079392754">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap201025.html">via</a>), including webs of dark matter and the transition from an opaque early universe to its present mostly-transparent state.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2007.06838">The cocked hat</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105167862476053808">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). This interestingly-titled recent preprint by Bárány, Steiger, and Toledo concerns locating yourself by measuring angles to three landmarks. Usually, random error causes rays from the landmarks to form a triangle rather than meeting at a point. Supposedly this triangle contains your position with probability 1/4, but the preprint shows that this can be proven only for distributions that force the rays to form a triangle. See also Toledo’s new book, <em><a href="http://www.cs.tau.ac.il/~stoledo/LocationEstimationFromTheGroundUp/">Location Estimation from the Ground Up</a></em>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:DMacks&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=987454393">MDPI is asking its authors to spam Wikipedia with their work</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105176559718608713">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>), and <a href="https://www.elsevier.com/__data/assets/pdf_file/0013/201325/Get-Noticed_Brochure_2018.pdf">so is Elsevier</a>. I’m not surprised by MDPI doing this but, despite my low opinion of them, I thought Elsevier were better than that.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://drawingmachines.org/">Drawing machines</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105181738042763529">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25033793">via</a>). An archive of optical/mechanical/automated drawing machines/devices/aids.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LdnvxN4UUfs">Origami Fibonacci torus and knotted torus</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105184956163150834">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). I have the impression that the Fibonacci part just gives it a nice organic look, <a href="http://www.starcage.org/englishindex.html">visible in much of Akio Hizume’s other architecture</a>, but what interests me is the way it rotates smoothly. That’s not something unfolded paper can do, because the inner parts of a torus have negative curvature, the outer parts are positive, and unfolded paper can’t change curvature.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The floorplan below is of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K%C3%B6lntriangle">KölnTriangle</a>, a building in Cologne which has been claimed to be a Reuleaux triangle in cross-section (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105195769927037078">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Obviously it’s not. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torre_de_Collserola">Torre de Collserola in Barcelona</a> looks <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Barcelona_Torre_de_Collserola_Planol_Evacuacio.jpg">much more promising</a> but a published description of its specific architecture would help make that more clear.</p>

    <p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="K&#xF6;lntriangle floor plan from CC-BY-SA image https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Fluchtwegeplan_K%C3%B6ln_Trangle.JPG by Bin im Garten, with overlaid Reuleaux triangle" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/KoelnTriangle-not-Reuleaux.jpg"/></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=5094">The <em>Complexity Zoo</em> needs a new home</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105199077818825073">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Scott Aaronson’s collection of complexity classes and their relations had been at the U. Waterloo Institute for Quantum Computing, but their bureaucrats have decided that they cannot accept the liability of it possibly being out of compliance with accessibility rules, without allowing him to fix any issues or even tell him what issues it might have. As Scott writes, “Do you find it ironic that a central effect of these accessibility policies seems to be to make free academic content less accessible than before?”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Two more recent deaths in discrete mathematics and theoretical computer science (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105205573414576460">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>): <a href="http://emps.exeter.ac.uk/mathematics/news-events/news/articles/robinchapmanobituary.html">Robin J. Chapman, problem-solver extraordinaire</a> (and scarily almost exactly the same age as me), and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chung_Laung_Liu">Dave (C. L.) Liu</a>, early researcher in scheduling algorithms and VLSI layout and later president of National Tsing Hua University (<a href="https://news.ltn.com.tw/amp/news/life/breakingnews/3346060">Chinese-language obituary</a>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://www.the-sandpit.com/contortions/contort.htm">Contortion engineering</a> (<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105217523608810155">\(\mathbb{M}\)</a>). Engineering-style drawings of Escher-like impossible objects. An old link from my old Geometry Junkyard site — its old earthlink url went dead some time after 2016, when archive.org last captured it, but now it has a new home.</p>
  </li>
</ul></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-15T21:05:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-15T21:05:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T22:25:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry xml:lang="en">
    <id>http://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?p=797</id>
    <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/2020/11/15/marijuana-brings-good-to-your-community/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Marijuana brings good to your community</title>
    <summary>Subsequence of official communication from Newton: […] recently reviewed applications from […] marijuana retailers who have submitted proposals […]. […] has a diverse management team with experience in the cannabis industry, equity, community relations and public health. […] certified by the Cannabis Control Commission as an Economic Empowerment Applicant, signifying that the applicant demonstrates experience […]</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Subsequence of official communication from Newton:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td><br/>[…] recently reviewed applications from […] marijuana retailers who have submitted proposals […].<br/><br/>[…] has a diverse management team with experience in the cannabis industry, equity, community relations and public health. […] certified by the Cannabis Control Commission as an Economic Empowerment Applicant, signifying that the applicant demonstrates experience in or business practices that promote economic empowerment in disproportionately impacted communities. Their plan involves […] additional parking on-site.<br/><br/>[…] also signing […] is a family owned and operated business. The company is certified by the Massachusetts Supplier Diversity Office as both a Minority Business and a Women Business Enterprise. […] will renovate the building and create surface parking. It has indicated it is willing to make transportation infrastructure improvements to the intersection […].<br/><br/>I am also signing […]. […] brings experience in the cannabis industry along with commitments to equity, public health, and community relations. […] will be constructing a new building and parking on what is currently a vacant parcel. <br/><br/>[…] with a revised plan to […] include more parking.<br/><br/></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td>Et cetera.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p/></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-15T12:40:43Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-15T12:40:43Z</published>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
    <category term="marijuana"/>
    <author>
      <name>Manu</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com</id>
      <logo>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</logo>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/osd.xml" rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml"/>
      <link href="https://emanueleviola.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>by Manu</subtitle>
      <title>Thoughts</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T02:38:06Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233.post-3746629932537659579</id>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/3746629932537659579/comments/default" rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/alex-trebekwhat-is-todays-post-about.html#comment-form" rel="replies" type="text/html"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3746629932537659579" rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default/3746629932537659579" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2020/11/alex-trebekwhat-is-todays-post-about.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Alex Trebek/What is today's post about?</title>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>(ADDED on Nov 23: Ken Jennings will be an interim host for Jeopardy, see <a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/jeopardy-will-resume-with-ken-jennings-as-interim-guest-host?ref=home">here</a>.)</p><p><br/></p><p> Alex Trebek, long time host of the TV show Jeopardy! (the exclamation point is part of the name, though I will omit it for the rest of the post), passed away in November of 2020 at the age of 80. He announced he had pancreatic cancer in March 2019.</p><p>0) <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/search?q=Jeopardy">Here</a> is a pointer to a page that has all of our posts with the word <i>Jeopardy </i>in them. Some are about the show and others mention the show in passing. All of the posts relate to the TV show. That is because Lance and I lead fairly safe lives.</p><p>1) On April Fools day of 1997 Pat Sajak hosted <i>Jeopardy</i> and Alex Trebek hosted <i>Wheel of Fortune</i>. Both are on You tube: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dtIT-jr1hmQ">Trebek hosts wheel</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LwVNmYjClXE">Pat hosts Jeopardy</a> Alex's hosting was more fun because- well, you can see for yourself. </p><p>2) Aside from that one day, Alex Trebek hosted <i>Jeopardy</i> every night since he began in 1984. </p><p>3) My favorite pangram (sentence that has all 26 letters) is</p><p>Watch <i>Jeopardy!</i>, Alex Trebek's fun TV quiz game show. </p><p>(See my post on natural pangrams <a href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/2017/11/can-you-measure-which-panagrams-are.html">here</a> for... more natural pangrams and a discussion of what natural means.) </p><p>It's my favorite since I can really imagine someone saying it. The show should have used it for its tagline. And now they can't :-(</p><p>4) From Alex's comments he seems to like high scoring games that are not run-a-ways. He also likes when people bet big on the daily doubles and on<i> final Jeopardy</i>.  I think he liked having long win streaks like Ken Jenning's  and James Holzhauer, but see point 7 below.  I think he didn't like it when people go for the high scoring questions first (perhaps looking for the Daily Double) since sometimes the category name is not quite clear (e.g., <i>Country Groups</i> could be things like<i> NATO </i>or things like <i>The Charlie Daniels Band</i>) so you want to do a cheap question to get your feet wet, and also easier for the audience to see what the category means.  IMHO they should really make the Daily Double Uniformly distributed on all the squares instead of having it tend to be the bigger-money questions. </p><p>5) When the final <i>Jeopardy</i> category is  revealed he sometimes says <i>that's a  good category!</i> or <i>that sounds hard. </i> Makes me wonder that if he makes no comment he is thinking<i> that's a stupid categor</i>y  or <i>Gee that's easy.</i></p><p>6) Because of the pandemic they could not, for a while, make new shows. Hence  they aired old shows including the  first ever Alex-Trebek-<i>Jeopardy</i> (the show had been hosted by Art Fleming and the Trebek-version was really a reboot). From that show I found out WHY it's called<i> Jeopardy</i> (a question I had never thought about). It's because if you get an answer WRONG you can LOSE money- that's the Jeopardy. Not really a good name, but by now everyone knows the show by that name.</p><p>7) Art Fleming also died of pancreatic cancer, back in 1995 (he was 70). Coincidence? Well, yes, though two game show hosts of the same show dying of the same disease 25 years apart could be the premise of a really bad murder mystery. </p><p>8) Alex makes some small talk with the contestants  (though some is edited for time). Things like <i>I hear you have a book on muffins that is not a cookbook-- what's that all about?</i>' I wonder if during Ken Jenning's 74-long winning streak, towards the end,  Alex ran out of things to ask him. I can imagine <i>I hear you're pretty good at Jeopardy.</i></p><p>9) I wonder how good Alex would be playing <i>Jeopardy</i>. When he hosted <i>Wheel of Fortune</i> he said in passing that he would NEVER go on <i>Jeopardy</i> as a contestant, so he doesn't think he would do well. He could be wrong about that since over time they ask questions that are not quite repeats but draw on the same knowledge- and he's heard all of them. However, it could be that he is too busy concentrating on other things to really absorb all of this knowledge. </p><p>10) The <i>we give the answers you give the questions </i>is a bit odd. However, in my classes I  sometimes say  <i>We'll Trebek this - we know what the answer is, we have to find the question</i>.</p><p>11) <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A7UgxCayfV0">This</a> youtube video is of a contestant singing WORDS to the <i>Jeopardy</i> theme song that he wrote.The contestant  refers to Jon Stewart as having also written words to the <i>Jeopardy</i> theme, but I can't find that anywhere- if you can, let me know. </p><p>12) Weird Al did a novelty song about <i>Jeopardy</i> using Art Fleming in the video (see  <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BvUZijEuNDQ">here</a>)  I always hoped he would update it and use Alex Trebek. He never did and now he can't :-( OR-with todays technology maybe he can. Here's hoping!</p><p>13) Alex Trebek was in a category by himself!</p><p><br/></p><p><br/></p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-14T20:26:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-14T20:26:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>gasarch</name>
      <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/03004932739846901628</uri>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-3722233</id>
      <category term="typecast"/>
      <category term="focs metacomments"/>
      <author>
        <name>Lance Fortnow</name>
        <email>noreply@blogger.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06752030912874378610</uri>
      </author>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/feeds/posts/default" rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://blog.computationalcomplexity.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/" rel="hub" type="text/html"/>
      <link href="https://www.blogger.com/feeds/3722233/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25" rel="next" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <subtitle>Computational Complexity and other fun stuff in math and computer science from Lance Fortnow and Bill Gasarch</subtitle>
      <title>Computational Complexity</title>
      <updated>2020-11-24T00:54:58Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/14/pathbreaking-for-intervals</id>
    <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/14/pathbreaking-for-intervals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <title>Pathbreaking for intervals</title>
    <summary>The use of Nash’s Hex lemma in my previous post, according to which any 2-coloring of a triangular grid has a long monochromatic path, naturally raises the question: for which graphs other than the triangular grid is this true? In that post I mentioned that it is also true for certain outerplanar graphs, but false for bipartite graphs and for subcubic graphs. Here’s another class of graphs for which it is false: the graphs of bounded pathwidth. These graphs can always be 2-colored in a way that breaks up all long paths, leaving the remaining monochromatic paths of bounded size.</summary>
    <content type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The use of Nash’s Hex lemma in <a href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/2020/11/10/hex-books-queues.html">my previous post</a>, according to which any 2-coloring of a triangular grid has a long monochromatic path, naturally raises the question: for which graphs other than the triangular grid is this true? In that post I mentioned that it is also true for certain outerplanar graphs, but false for bipartite graphs and for subcubic graphs. Here’s another class of graphs for which it is false: the graphs of bounded <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pathwidth">pathwidth</a>. These graphs can always be 2-colored in a way that breaks up all long paths, leaving the remaining monochromatic paths of bounded size.</p>

<p>Rather than dealing with pathwidth directly, I want to formulate it geometrically in terms of interval graphs. Every graph can be completed (by adding extra edges) to form an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interval_graph">interval graph</a> of the same pathwidth; an interval graph has one-dimensional closed intervals as its vertices, connected by an edge whenever they intersect. The pathwidth of an interval graph is always one less than the maximum number of intervals that overlap at the same point (their ply). So rather than looking at graphs of bounded pathwidth I’ll be considering sets of intervals of bounded ply. For example in the illustration below which I drew a few years ago for Wikipedia, the intervals shown have ply 3, and their interval graph has pathwidth 2.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="A set of intervals and their associated interval graph" src="https://11011110.github.io/blog/assets/2020/interval-graph.svg"/></p>

<p>Intervals with low ply that are all either nested or disjoint can have no long paths in their intersection graph regardless of coloring. In any set of intervals forming a path, the path can pass through the outermost level of nesting at most once, subdividing it into two smaller paths with lower ply. It follows by induction the number of intervals in the path can be at most \(2^{\operatorname{ply}}-1\). (This is the standard argument behind an equivalence in graphs between longest path length and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tree-depth">tree-depth</a>.) So if we could partition an arbitrary set of intervals into two subsets within which all intervals are nested or disjoint, we’d be done. For instance, in the example above, the partition into \(\{A,B,F\}\) and \(\{C,D,E,G\}\) works. Not every set of intervals can be partitioned in this way, but I’ll show below that it’s always possible to lengthen some intervals, keeping the ply small, so that the lengthened intervals can be partitioned (colored) into two nested subsets.</p>

<p>As a subroutine in the construction, let’s find a set of points with the following properties:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Each interval lies strictly between the leftmost and rightmost selected points.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>No interval covers more than one selected point.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The union of the intervals that cover selected points equals the union of all the intervals.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>This can be done by a greedy algorithm that repeatedly selects an uncovered interval endpoint until the intervals that cover selected points also cover all other interval endpoints. Finish by selecting any two points to the left and right of all the intervals, and then number the selected points as \(x_0,x_1,\dots\) in left-to-right order. For example, one possible choice for our example would have \(x_0\) to the left of the intervals, \(x_1\) at the left endpoint of \(D\), \(x_2\) at the left endpoint of \(F\), and \(x_3\) to the right of the intervals. For this choice, \(B\) and \(E\) do not cover any selected points, but that’s not a problem. It’s not necessary to optimize how many points are selected.</p>

<p>Call an interval “odd” if it covers an odd-numbered point \(x_i\) and “even” if it covers an even-numbered point. In our example, \(A\), \(C\), and \(D\) are odd, and \(F\), and \(G\) are even, but \(B\) and \(E\) are neither odd nor even. We will color the odd intervals blue and the even intervals red. Because they are different colors, we don’t have to worry about nesting between odd and even intervals. However, the intervals that contain any single point \(x_i\) will have the same color and need to be lengthened to nesting intervals. To do so, we extend all these intervals to a single longer interval, from just after \(x_{i-1}\) to just before \(x_{i+1}\). Because of the way the points \(x_i\) were chosen, this does not create new intersections between intervals of the same color, and it makes all colored intervals nest with all uncolored ones (not just with each other). However, it can also increase the ply. If the ply was \(p\) previously, it can increase by as much as \(2p-1\), when a point that was previously covered by only one odd or even interval becomes covered by \(2p-1\) more of them.</p>

<p>Finally, we apply the same coloring and lengthening process recursively, to the remaining subsets of uncolored intervals between each pair of selected points.
To make sure the intervals stay nested after lengthening, we take care in each recursive subproblem to select its first and last points to be inside all intervals of the outer problem that contain the subproblem. Because every point in an interval of a recursive subproblem is also in at least one of the outer colored intervals, the recursive subproblem has smaller ply than the initial ply of the outer problem. The recursion stops at ply 2; for this ply the intersection graph is a tree (more precisely a caterpillar) and it is possible to 2-color the intervals without any lengthening so that no two intervals of the same color intersect, by 2-coloring the tree.</p>

<p>So if we start with intervals of ply 2, we produce a lengthened, 2-colored, and monochromatically nested set of intervals of ply 2 again (no change to the ply). If we start with intervals of ply 3, we produce a lengthened, 2-colored, and monochromatically nested set of intervals of ply at most 8, because the ply-3 interval-lengthening process added at most 5 to the existing ply. More generally for any starting ply \(p\) the new ply will be at most \(p^2+p-4\). And since the interval graph for the lengthened intervals has no monochromatic path with more than \(2^{p^2+p-4}-1\) intervals in it, neither does the interval graph for the original intervals, with the same 2-coloring.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@11011110/105211974100055236">Discuss on Mastodon</a>)</p></div>
    </content>
    <updated>2020-11-14T17:59:00Z</updated>
    <published>2020-11-14T17:59:00Z</published>
    <author>
      <name>David Eppstein</name>
    </author>
    <source>
      <id>https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml</id>
      <author>
        <name>David Eppstein</name>
      </author>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
      <link href="https://11011110.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
      <subtitle>Geometry, graphs, algorithms, and more</subtitle>
      <title>11011110</title>
      <updated>2020-11-18T22:25:28Z</updated>
    </source>
  </entry>
</feed>
